<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title>Theory of Computing Report</title>
  <link rel="self" href=""/>
  <link href=""/>
  <id></id>
  <updated></updated>
  <generator uri="http://feedreader.github.io/">Pluto 1.6.2 on Ruby 3.0.5 (2022-11-24) [x86_64-linux]</generator>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: An approach to robust ICP initialization</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05332"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05332</id>
    <updated>2022-12-13T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kolpakov_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Alexander Kolpakov&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Werman_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Michael Werman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this note, we propose an approach for initializing the Iterative Closest
Point (ICP) algorithm that allows us to apply ICP to unlabelled point clouds
that are related by rigid transformations. We also give bounds on the
robustness of our approach to noise. Numerical experiments confirm our
theoretical findings.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Isometric deformable cones and cylinders carrying planar curves</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05484"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05484</id>
    <updated>2022-12-13T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nawratil_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Georg Nawratil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study cones and cylinders with a 1-parametric isometric deformation
carrying at least two planar curves, which remain planar during this continuous
flexion and are located in non-parallel planes. We investigate this
geometric/kinematic problem in the smooth and the discrete setting, as it is
the base for a generalized construction of so-called T-hedral zipper tubes. In
contrast to the cylindrical case, which can be solved easily, the conical one
is more tricky, but we succeed to give a closed form solution for the discrete
case, which is used to prove that these cones correspond to caps of Bricard
octahedra of the plane-symmetric type. For the smooth case we are able to
reduce the problem by means of symbolic computation to an ordinary differential
equation, but its solution remains an open problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Transcoding Unicode Characters with AVX-512 Instructions</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05098"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05098</id>
    <updated>2022-12-13T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Clausecker_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Robert Clausecker&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lemire_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Daniel Lemire&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Intel includes on its recent processors a powerful set of instructions
capable of processing 512-bit registers with a single instruction (AVX-512).
Some of these instructions have no equivalent in earlier instruction sets. We
leverage these instructions to efficiently transcode strings between the most
common formats: UTF-8 and UTF-16. With our novel algorithms, we are often twice
as fast as the previous best solutions. For example, we transcode Chinese text
from UTF-8 to UTF-16 at more than 5 GiB/s using fewer than 2 CPU instructions
per character. To ensure reproducibility, we make our software freely available
as an open source library.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Efficient and Generic Algorithms for Quantitative Attack Tree Analysis</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05358"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05358</id>
    <updated>2022-12-13T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lopuhaa_Zwakenberg_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Milan Lopuha&amp;#xe4;-Zwakenberg&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Budde_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Carlos E. Budde&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Stoelinga_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mari&amp;#xeb;lle Stoelinga&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Numerous analysis methods for quantitative attack tree analysis have been
proposed. These algorithms compute relevant security metrics, i.e. performance
indicators that quantify how good the security of a system is; typical metrics
being the most likely attack, the cheapest, or the most damaging one. However,
existing methods are only geared towards specific metrics or do not work on
general attack trees. This paper classifies attack trees in two dimensions:
proper trees vs. directed acyclic graphs (i.e. with shared subtrees); and
static vs. dynamic gates. For three out of these four classes, we propose novel
algorithms that work over a generic attribute domain, encompassing a large
number of concrete security metrics defined on the attack tree semantics;
dynamic attack trees with directed acyclic graph structure are left as an open
problem. We also analyse the computational complexity of our methods.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Beyond circular-arc graphs -- recognizing lollipop graphs and medusa graphs</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05433"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05433</id>
    <updated>2022-12-13T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Cagirici_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Deniz A&amp;#x11f;ao&amp;#x11f;lu &amp;#xc7;a&amp;#x11f;&amp;#x131;r&amp;#x131;c&amp;#x131;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Cagirici_O/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Onur &amp;#xc7;a&amp;#x11f;&amp;#x131;r&amp;#x131;c&amp;#x131;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Derbisz_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jan Derbisz&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hartmann_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tim A. Hartmann&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hlineny_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Petr Hlin&amp;#x11b;n&amp;#xfd;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kratochvil_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jan Kratochv&amp;#xed;l&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Krawczyk_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tomasz Krawczyk&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zeman_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Peter Zeman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1992 Bir\&#39;{o}, Hujter and Tuza introduced, for every fixed connected graph
$H$, the class of $H$-graphs, defined as the intersection graphs of connected
subgraphs of some subdivision of $H$. Recently, quite a lot of research has
been devoted to understanding the tractability border for various computational
problems, such as recognition or isomorphism testing, in classes of $H$-graphs
for different graphs $H$. In this work we undertake this research topic,
focusing on the recognition problem. Chaplick, T\&quot;{o}pfer, Voborn\&#39;{\i}k, and
Zeman showed, for every fixed tree $T$, a polynomial-time algorithm recognizing
$T$-graphs. Tucker showed a polynomial time algorithm recognizing $K_3$-graphs
(circular-arc graphs). On the other hand, Chaplick at al. showed that
recognition of $H$-graphs is $NP$-hard if $H$ contains two different cycles
sharing an edge.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main two results of this work narrow the gap between the $NP$-hard and
$P$ cases of $H$-graphs recognition. First, we show that recognition of
$H$-graphs is $NP$-hard when $H$ contains two different cycles. On the other
hand, we show a polynomial-time algorithm recognizing $L$-graphs, where $L$ is
a graph containing a cycle and an edge attached to it ($L$-graphs are called
lollipop graphs). Our work leaves open the recognition problems of $M$-graphs
for every unicyclic graph $M$ different from a cycle and a lollipop. Other
results of this work, which shed some light on the cases that remain open, are
as follows. Firstly, the recognition of $M$-graphs, where $M$ is a fixed
unicyclic graph, admits a polynomial time algorithm if we restrict the input to
graphs containing particular holes (hence recognition of $M$-graphs is probably
most difficult for chordal graphs). Secondly, the recognition of medusa graphs,
which are defined as the union of $M$-graphs, where $M$ runs over all unicyclic
graphs, is $NP$-complete.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Algorithms approaching the threshold for semi-random planted clique</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05619"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05619</id>
    <updated>2022-12-13T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Buhai_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Rares-Darius Buhai&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kothari_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Pravesh K. Kothari&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Steurer_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;David Steurer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We design new polynomial-time algorithms for recovering planted cliques in
the semi-random graph model introduced by Feige and Kilian~\cite{FK01}. The
previous best algorithms for this model succeed if the planted clique has size
at least \(n^{2/3}\) in a graph with \(n\) vertices (Mehta, Mckenzie, Trevisan,
2019 and Charikar, Steinhardt, Valiant 2017). Our algorithms work for
planted-clique sizes approaching \(n^{1/2}\) -- the information-theoretic
threshold in the semi-random model~\cite{steinhardt2017does} and a conjectured
computational threshold even in the easier fully-random model. This result
comes close to resolving open questions by Feige and Steinhardt.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our algorithms are based on higher constant degree sum-of-squares relaxation
and rely on a new conceptual connection that translates certificates of upper
bounds on biclique numbers in \emph{unbalanced} bipartite Erd\H{o}s--R\&#39;enyi
random graphs into algorithms for semi-random planted clique. The use of a
higher-constant degree sum-of-squares is essential in our setting: we prove a
lower bound on the basic SDP for certifying bicliques that shows that the basic
SDP cannot succeed for planted cliques of size $k =o(n^{2/3})$. We also provide
some evidence that the information-computation trade-off of our current
algorithms may be inherent by proving an average-case lower bound for
unbalanced bicliques in the low-degree-polynomials model.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Binary Error-Correcting Codes with Minimal Noiseless Feedback</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05673"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05673</id>
    <updated>2022-12-13T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gupta_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Meghal Gupta&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Guruswami_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Venkatesan Guruswami&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zhang_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Rachel Yun Zhang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the setting of error-correcting codes with feedback, Alice wishes to
communicate a $k$-bit message $x$ to Bob by sending a sequence of bits over a
channel while noiselessly receiving feedback from Bob. It has been long known
(Berlekamp, 1964) that in this model, Bob can still correctly determine $x$
even if $\approx \frac13$ of Alice&#39;s bits are flipped adversarially. This
improves upon the classical setting without feedback, where recovery is not
possible for error fractions exceeding $\frac14$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original feedback setting assumes that after transmitting each bit, Alice
knows (via feedback) what bit Bob received. In this work, our focus in on the
limited feedback model, where Bob is only allowed to send a few bits at a small
number of pre-designated points in the protocol. For any desired $\epsilon &amp;gt;
0$, we construct a coding scheme that tolerates a fraction $ 1/3-\epsilon$ of
bit flips relying only on $O_\epsilon(\log k)$ bits of feedback from Bob sent
in a fixed $O_\epsilon(1)$ number of rounds. We complement this with a matching
lower bound showing that $\Omega(\log k)$ bits of feedback are necessary to
recover from an error fraction exceeding $1/4$ (the threshold without any
feedback), and for schemes resilient to a fraction $1/3-\epsilon$ of bit flips,
the number of rounds must grow as $\epsilon \to 0$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also study (and resolve) the question for the simpler model of erasures.
We show that $O_\epsilon(\log k)$ bits of feedback spread over $O_\epsilon(1)$
rounds suffice to tolerate a fraction $(1-\epsilon)$ of erasures. Likewise, our
$\Omega(\log k)$ lower bound applies for erasure fractions exceeding $1/2$, and
an increasing number of rounds are required as the erasure fraction approaches
$1$.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Minimum-weight partitioning of a set with associated subsets</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05823"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05823</id>
    <updated>2022-12-13T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zinder_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yakov Zinder&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lin_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Bertrand M.T. Lin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Berlinska_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Joanna Berli&amp;#x144;ska&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The paper presents complexity results and performance guaranties for a family
of approximation algorithms for an optimisation problem arising in software
testing and manufacturing. The problem is formulated as a partitioning of a set
where each element has an associated subset in another set, but can also be
viewed as a scheduling problem with infinitely large communication delay,
precedence constraints in the form of a bipartite graph, and duplication.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">CCI: jobs: Assistant Professor in Computer Science at HSE University (apply by January 15, 2023)</title>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/12/12/assistant-professor-in-computer-science-at-hse-university-apply-by-january-15-2023/"/>
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/12/12/assistant-professor-in-computer-science-at-hse-university-apply-by-january-15-2023/</id>
    <updated>2022-12-12T11:11:39+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;The Faculty of Computer Science, HSE University invites applications for positions of assistant [professor in all areas of computer science including theoretical CS.&lt;br /&gt;
Candidates must hold a recent PhD in computer science, mathematics or related fields, posess teaching experience and speak fluent English.&lt;br /&gt;
Tenure track positions are only available on a full-time, residential basis in Moscow, Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://iri.hse.ru/ru/TTCS2223&quot;&gt;https://iri.hse.ru/ru/TTCS2223&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: iri@hse.ru&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>CCI: jobs</name>
      <uri>https://cstheory-jobs.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Decentralized Thoughts: What about Validity?</title>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2022-12-12-what-about-validity/"/>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2022-12-12-what-about-validity/</id>
    <updated>2022-12-12T09:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    Perhaps the architipical trilemma is consensus - it requires three properties: agreement, liveness, and validity. Getting any two is easy, but all three together is what makes consensus such a facinating problem that continues to create new challenges even after 40 years of research. A lot of research focuses on...
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Decentralized Thoughts</name>
      <uri>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Computational Complexity: Commercials are not logical.  FTX edition.</title>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/12/commercials-are-not-logical-ftx-edition.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-1729382940974134289</id>
    <updated>2022-12-12T04:03:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;Some people asked me to comment on FTX since I teach Crypto. My insights are no better than anyone else; however, I have wanted to do a blog post about the illogic of commercials, so I will do that with FTX as an example.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ALL conversations in the post are fictional.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;------------------------------------&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alice: Bob,&amp;nbsp; why did you invest $1,000,000 with FTX?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bob: Because Tom Brady endorsed it. (See&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nypost.com/2022/11/22/tom-brady-stephen-curry-larry-david-probed-over-ftx-endorsements/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alice: But Tom Brady is a football player, not a finance person.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bob: Well... I know that now.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The people in commercials are&amp;nbsp; paid to hawk the product.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;a) Are they experts? In the above case about about FTX&amp;nbsp; NO, they are not. So this should not work.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;b) There are commercials where the people ARE experts. For example, a basketball player endorsing Sneaker brand (not quite an expert, but they DO use the product). But even this should not work since the viewers KNOW that the person is being PAID to tell us it&#39;s a good product.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;c) Commercial spokesman (Geico-Gecko, Progressive-Flo, Dos&amp;nbsp; XX- the worlds most interesting man, see his commercial&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n5HX7y1yDi4&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;and a Ramsey Meme based on it&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.umd.edu/users/gasarch/BLOGPAPERS/idont.jpg&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) are even stranger- they are fictional characters who are urging me to buy something.&amp;nbsp; So the question &lt;i&gt;are they experts? &lt;/i&gt;doesn&#39;t even make sense. Someone pretending to be someone they are not is pretending to like a product they do not use.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;d) Some commercials pretend to be&amp;nbsp; informative but are not. For example, the Insurance Companies seem to brag about something that ALL of the insurance companies do (bundling, not-paying-for-what-you-don&#39;t-need).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;e) A truly new product may have an informative commercial, just to tell me that its out there. For example. &lt;i&gt;Stephen Colbert&#39;s Americone Dream Ice Cream&lt;/i&gt; which is awesome. (My spellchecker thinks &lt;i&gt;Americone&lt;/i&gt; is not a word. This time they are probably right.)&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;f) SO, if I did a commercial for &lt;i&gt;Stephen Colbert&#39;s Americone Dream Ice Cream&lt;/i&gt; would you try it? Lets say I wasn&#39;t being paid and I truly did it for my love of that ice cream. STILL doesn&#39;t make sense- my tastes and yours may differ. However, you can try it and decide, and&amp;nbsp; it costs far less than $1,000,000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;---------------------------------------&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So what are we left with? The only commercials that make logical sense would be those where&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;a) the person is an expert&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;b) the person is not being paid&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;c) the person is telling you something about the product that distinguishes it from its competitors OR p its a new product&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;d) Its not a matter of taste- there is an absolute standard that is easily understood.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do you know of ANY commercials like that? Influencers who are NOT paid by the people whose product they are hawking (are there such influencers?) might begin to qualify.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;------------------------------------------------------&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So LOGICALLY commercials should not work. So why do they?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;a) They don&#39;t. Its possible they just are not that effective. See&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://insight.kellogg.northwestern.edu/article/tv-advertising-is-usually-not-worth-it&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;for DON&quot;T WORK and&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/financial-edge/1111/8-of-the-most-successful-ad-campaigns-of-all-time.aspx&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;for 8 times when it did work. I think&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=you+tube+soup+commercial+stan+freberg&amp;amp;rlz=1C1EJFC_enUS884US884&amp;amp;ei=gaiWY7iVAqae5NoPgum46Ac&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwj42avlmfP7AhUmD1kFHYI0Dn0Q4dUDCA8&amp;amp;uact=5&amp;amp;oq=you+tube+soup+commercial+stan+freberg&amp;amp;gs_lcp=Cgxnd3Mtd2l6LXNlcnAQAzIFCCEQqwI6CggAEEcQ1gQQsAM6BggAEBYQHjoFCAAQhgM6BwghEKABEAo6CAghEBYQHhAdSgQIQRgASgQIRhgAUNkDWOoWYOgXaAFwAXgAgAFyiAH7CJIBBDEwLjOYAQCgAQHIAQi4AQPAAQE&amp;amp;sclient=gws-wiz-serp#fpstate=ive&amp;amp;vld=cid:cf8fea70,vid:lZN86IOv79k&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;is a great commercial (watch it to the end) but it does not make me want to out and buy soup. (Stan Freberg wrote some GREAT commercials. They are on You Tube and I recommend them highly for entertainment. He also has several great novelty-song albums.)&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;b) Indirectly. They build brand awareness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;c) Because people are stupid. This is not an interesting answer since I still want to know what their reasoning is, whether or not its faulty.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;d) Because you are part of a movement. Drink the Uncola (7UP) to be rebellious! Or the 1984-Apple commercial (see&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zIE-5hg7FoA&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). These are both odd since drinking 7UP or having an Apple Computer seem to me to be the opposite of rebellious.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;e) Buying the product to express your philosophy:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ted: Carol, why did you invest in $1,000,000 in FTX?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carol: Because I believe in effective altruism.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ted: Do you still?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carol: This might need a rethink. But for now I&#39;ll&amp;nbsp; invest by getting a Freedom Unlimited credit card that gets cash back since Kevin Hart says I should (see&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=you+tube+kevin+hart+credit+card&amp;amp;rlz=1C1EJFC_enUS884US884&amp;amp;oq=you+tube+kevin+hart+credit+card&amp;amp;aqs=chrome..69i57j69i64.12160j1j4&amp;amp;sourceid=chrome&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8#fpstate=ive&amp;amp;vld=cid:e977cbbb,vid:m3TSpuaQvDo&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By gasarch&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Implementing Neural Network-Based Equalizers in a Coherent Optical Transmission System Using Field-Programmable Gate Arrays</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04703"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04703</id>
    <updated>2022-12-12T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/eess/1/au:+Freire_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Pedro J. Freire&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/eess/1/au:+Srivallapanondh_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sasipim Srivallapanondh&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/eess/1/au:+Anderson_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Michael Anderson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/eess/1/au:+Spinnler_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Bernhard Spinnler&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/eess/1/au:+Bex_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Thomas Bex&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/eess/1/au:+Eriksson_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tobias A. Eriksson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/eess/1/au:+Napoli_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Antonio Napoli&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/eess/1/au:+Schairer_W/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Wolfgang Schairer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/eess/1/au:+Costa_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nelson Costa&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/eess/1/au:+Blott_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Michaela Blott&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/eess/1/au:+Turitsyn_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sergei K. Turitsyn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/eess/1/au:+Prilepsky_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jaroslaw E. Prilepsky&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this work, we demonstrate the offline FPGA realization of both recurrent
and feedforward neural network (NN)-based equalizers for nonlinearity
compensation in coherent optical transmission systems. First, we present a
realization pipeline showing the conversion of the models from Python libraries
to the FPGA chip synthesis and implementation. Then, we review the main
alternatives for the hardware implementation of nonlinear activation functions.
The main results are divided into three parts: a performance comparison, an
analysis of how activation functions are implemented, and a report on the
complexity of the hardware. The performance in Q-factor is presented for the
cases of bidirectional long-short-term memory coupled with convolutional NN
(biLSTM + CNN) equalizer, CNN equalizer, and standard 1-StpS digital
back-propagation (DBP) for the simulation and experiment propagation of a
single channel dual-polarization (SC-DP) 16QAM at 34 GBd along 17x70km of LEAF.
The biLSTM+CNN equalizer provides a similar result to DBP and a 1.7 dB Q-factor
gain compared with the chromatic dispersion compensation baseline in the
experimental dataset. After that, we assess the Q-factor and the impact of
hardware utilization when approximating the activation functions of NN using
Taylor series, piecewise linear, and look-up table (LUT) approximations. We
also show how to mitigate the approximation errors with extra training and
provide some insights into possible gradient problems in the LUT approximation.
Finally, to evaluate the complexity of hardware implementation to achieve 400G
throughput, fixed-point NN-based equalizers with approximated activation
functions are developed and implemented in an FPGA.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Controllability of complex networks: input node placement restricting the longest control chain</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04718"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04718</id>
    <updated>2022-12-12T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Alizadeh_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Samie Alizadeh&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Posfai_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;M&amp;#xe1;rton P&amp;#xf3;sfai&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ghasemi_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Abdorasoul Ghasemi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The minimum number of inputs needed to control a network is frequently used
to quantify its controllability. Control of linear dynamics through a minimum
set of inputs, however, often has prohibitively large energy requirements and
there is an inherent trade-off between minimizing the number of inputs and
control energy. To better understand this trade-off, we study the problem of
identifying a minimum set of input nodes such that controllabililty is ensured
while restricting the length of the longest control chain. The longest control
chain is the maximum distance from input nodes to any network node, and recent
work found that reducing its length significantly reduces control energy. We
map the longest control chain-constraint minimum input problem to finding a
joint maximum matching and minimum dominating set. We show that this graph
combinatorial problem is NP-complete, and we introduce and validate a heuristic
approximation. Applying this algorithm to a collection of real and model
networks, we investigate how network structure affects the minimum number of
inputs, revealing, for example, that for many real networks reducing the
longest control chain requires only few or no additional inputs, only the
rearrangement of the input nodes.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: A refinement on the structure of vertex-critical ($P_5$, gem)-free graphs</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04659"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04659</id>
    <updated>2022-12-12T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Cameron_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ben Cameron&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Hoang_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ch&amp;#xed;nh T. Ho&amp;#xe0;ng&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We give a new, stronger proof that there are only finitely many
$k$-vertex-critical ($P_5$,~gem)-free graphs for all $k$. Our proof further
refines the structure of these graphs and allows for the implementation of a
simple exhaustive computer search to completely list all $6$- and
$7$-vertex-critical $(P_5$, gem)-free graphs. Our results imply the existence
of polynomial-time certifying algorithms to decide the $k$-colourability of
$(P_5$, gem)-free graphs for all $k$ where the certificate is either a
$k$-colouring or a $(k+1)$-vertex-critical induced subgraph. Our complete lists
for $k\le 7$ allow for the implementation of these algorithms for all $k\le 6$.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Breaking the Barrier $2^k$ for Subset Feedback Vertex Set in Chordal Graphs</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04726"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04726</id>
    <updated>2022-12-12T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Bai_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tian Bai&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Xiao_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mingyu Xiao&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Subset Feedback Vertex Set problem (SFVS), to delete $k$ vertices from a
given graph such that any vertex in a vertex subset (called a terminal set) is
not in a cycle in the remaining graph, generalizes the famous Feedback Vertex
Set problem and Multiway Cut problem. SFVS remains $\mathrm{NP}$-hard even in
split and chordal graphs, and SFVS in Chordal Graphs can be considered as a
special case of the 3-Hitting Set problem. However, it is not easy to solve
SFVS in Chordal Graphs faster than 3-Hitting Set. In 2019, Philip, Rajan,
Saurabh, and Tale (Algorithmica 2019) proved that SFVS in Chordal Graphs can be
solved in $2^k n^{\mathcal{O}(1)}$, slightly improving the best result $2.076^k
n^{\mathcal{O}(1)}$ for 3-Hitting Set. In this paper, we break the
&quot;$2^k$-barrier&quot; for SFVS in Chordal Graphs by giving a $1.619^k
n^{\mathcal{O}(1)}$-time algorithm. Our algorithm uses reduction and branching
rules based on the Dulmage-Mendelsohn decomposition and a divide-and-conquer
method.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: A Polynomial-Time Algorithm for MCS Partial Search Order on Chordal Graphs</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04880"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04880</id>
    <updated>2022-12-12T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rong_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Guozhen Rong&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Yang_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yongjie Yang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Li_W/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Wenjun Li&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the partial search order problem (PSOP) proposed recently by
Scheffler [WG 2022]. Given a graph $G$ together with a partial order over the
vertices of $G$, this problem determines if there is an $\mathcal{S}$-ordering
that is consistent with the given partial order, where $\mathcal{S}$ is a graph
search paradigm like BFS, DFS, etc. This problem naturally generalizes the
end-vertex problem which has received much attention over the past few years.
It also generalizes the so-called ${\mathcal{F}}$-tree recognition problem
which has just been studied in the literature recently. Our main contribution
is a polynomial-time dynamic programming algorithm for the PSOP on chordal
graphs with respect to the maximum cardinality search (MCS). This resolves one
of the most intriguing open questions left in the work of Sheffler [WG 2022].
To obtain our result, we propose the notion of layer structure and study
numerous related structural properties which might be of independent interest.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Robustness Implies Privacy in Statistical Estimation</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05015"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05015</id>
    <updated>2022-12-12T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hopkins_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Samuel B. Hopkins&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kamath_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Gautam Kamath&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Majid_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mahbod Majid&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Narayanan_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Shyam Narayanan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the relationship between adversarial robustness and differential
privacy in high-dimensional algorithmic statistics. We give the first black-box
reduction from privacy to robustness which can produce private estimators with
optimal tradeoffs among sample complexity, accuracy, and privacy for a wide
range of fundamental high-dimensional parameter estimation problems, including
mean and covariance estimation. We show that this reduction can be implemented
in polynomial time in some important special cases. In particular, using
nearly-optimal polynomial-time robust estimators for the mean and covariance of
high-dimensional Gaussians which are based on the Sum-of-Squares method, we
design the first polynomial-time private estimators for these problems with
nearly-optimal samples-accuracy-privacy tradeoffs. Our algorithms are also
robust to a constant fraction of adversarially-corrupted samples.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">CCI: jobs: Postdocs in TCS at University of Copenhagen (apply by January 10, 2023)</title>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/12/11/postdocs-in-tcs-at-university-of-copenhagen-apply-by-january-10-2023/"/>
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/12/11/postdocs-in-tcs-at-university-of-copenhagen-apply-by-january-10-2023/</id>
    <updated>2022-12-11T01:24:45+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;The CS department at the University of Copenhagen invites applications for postdocs in TCS. The application deadline is January 10, 2023. See &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jakobnordstrom.se/openings/Postdoc-UCPH-230110.html&quot;&gt;http://www.jakobnordstrom.se/openings/Postdoc-UCPH-230110.html&lt;/a&gt; for more information and instructions how to apply. Informal enquiries are welcome to Mikkel Abrahamsen (miab@di.ku.dk), Jakob Nordstrom (jn@di.ku.dk), or Rasmus Pagh (pagh@di.ku.dk).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jakobnordstrom.se/openings/Postdoc-UCPH-230110.html&quot;&gt;http://www.jakobnordstrom.se/openings/Postdoc-UCPH-230110.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: jn@di.ku.dk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>CCI: jobs</name>
      <uri>https://cstheory-jobs.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">CCI: jobs: PhD position at U of Rochester (apply by December 15, 2022)</title>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/12/10/phd-position-at-u-of-rochester-apply-by-december-15-2022/"/>
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/12/10/phd-position-at-u-of-rochester-apply-by-december-15-2022/</id>
    <updated>2022-12-10T16:47:48+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;We invite Ph.D. applicants in theoretical computer science. There is no application fee. Late applications will be considered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several open positions in many areas such as:&lt;br /&gt;
computational complexity, approximation and randomized algorithms, pseudorandomness, theoretical machine learning, combinatorics and additive combinatorics, game theory and economics, and computational social choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.rochester.edu/research/theory/&quot;&gt;https://www.cs.rochester.edu/research/theory/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: robin.clark@rochester.edu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>CCI: jobs</name>
      <uri>https://cstheory-jobs.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Foundation of Data Science - Virtual Talk Series: Wednesday, Dec 14th, 2022 — Omri Ben-Eliezer from MIT</title>
    <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/2022/12/10/wednesday-dec-14th-2022-omri-ben-eliezer-from-mit/"/>
    <id>http://dstheory.wordpress.com/?p=142</id>
    <updated>2022-12-10T04:13:32+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;has-text-align-justify&quot;&gt;The next &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot; href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/dstheory/home&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Foundations of Data Science&lt;/a&gt; virtual talk series on recent advances in &lt;em&gt;adversarially robust streaming&lt;/em&gt; will take place on &lt;strong&gt;Wednesday, December 14th&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;strong&gt;1:00 PM Pacific Time&lt;/strong&gt; (16:00 Eastern Time, 22:00 Central European Time, 20:00 UTC). &lt;strong&gt;Omri Ben-Eliezer&lt;/strong&gt; from&lt;strong&gt; MIT&lt;/strong&gt; will talk about &lt;em&gt;“Robust sampling and online learning”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/dstheory&quot;&gt;Details of the talk (Zoom link) are available here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;has-text-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;:  Random sampling is a fundamental primitive in modern algorithms, statistics and machine learning, used as a generic method to obtain a small yet “representative” subset of the data. In this talk we shall explore to what extent random sampling is robust to adaptive inputs in a streaming setting, proposing and studying a model for sampling against a white-box adaptive adversary (where future inputs generated by the adversary are allowed to depend on the current internal state of the sampler). I will demonstrate scenarios where the adaptive sample complexity can be much larger than in the static world, but argue that these scenarios are not entirely realistic. I will then reveal a deep connection between our setting and online learning. As it turns out, the sample complexity in our sampling setting is captured by a sequential version of Rademacher complexity, a notion that is also known to capture the regret in online classification problems. Leveraging this connection, one can bound the sample complexity using the Littlestone dimension of the relevant concept class. The obtained bounds are tight in many regimes, and lead us to resolve a classical open problem on optimal regret bounds in online learning.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Based on joint works with Noga Alon, Yuval Dagan, Shay Moran, Moni Naor, and Eylon Yogev.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;The series is supported by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1934846&amp;amp;HistoricalAwards=false&quot;&gt;NSF HDR TRIPODS Grant 1934846&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By dstheory&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Foundation of Data Science - Virtual Talk Series</name>
      <uri>https://dstheory.wordpress.com</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Richard Lipton: Thanks</title>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/09/thanks-2/"/>
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=20558</id>
    <updated>2022-12-09T23:25:51+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks to you all. I must explain why I have not been active in the last six months. I have had several illnesses. I had a broken hip that needed surgery&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/09/thanks-2/bed-4/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-20604&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;20604&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/09/thanks-2/bed-4/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/bed-1-rotated.jpeg?fit=480%2C640&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;480,640&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;bed&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/bed-1-rotated.jpeg?fit=225%2C300&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/bed-1-rotated.jpeg?fit=480%2C640&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/bed-1-rotated.jpeg?resize=300%2C400&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter wp-image-20604&quot; srcset=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/bed-1-rotated.jpeg?w=480&amp;amp;ssl=1 480w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/bed-1-rotated.jpeg?resize=225%2C300&amp;amp;ssl=1 225w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/bed-1-rotated.jpeg?resize=300%2C400&amp;amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/bed-1-rotated.jpeg?resize=150%2C200&amp;amp;ssl=1 150w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I also had several COVID related illnesses, and some terrible GI issues. I am trying to get better. Thanks to my dear wife Kathryn Farley I have finally started to get better. I cannot ever thank her enough.  Kenneth Regan and Rich DeMillo and many others have also helped me. Thanks to you all. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/09/thanks-2/kkrr/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-20607&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;20607&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/09/thanks-2/kkrr/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/KKRR.png?fit=739%2C299&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;739,299&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;KKRR&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/KKRR.png?fit=300%2C121&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/KKRR.png?fit=600%2C243&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/KKRR.png?resize=550%2C223&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;550&quot; height=&quot;223&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter wp-image-20607&quot; srcset=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/KKRR.png?w=739&amp;amp;ssl=1 739w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/KKRR.png?resize=300%2C121&amp;amp;ssl=1 300w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I have dodged emails and phone calls in the interim. I feel often that I am overcome with my illnesses. I am finally making some progress and I hope that I will be able to respond to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also plan on working more on the blog and hope you all will enjoy reading it again. Thanks for your support in the past and hope you enjoy it again.  I have been able to get out more in the past six weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/09/thanks-2/coney2/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-20612&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;20612&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/09/thanks-2/coney2/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Coney2.png?fit=1260%2C427&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1260,427&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;Coney2&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Coney2.png?fit=300%2C102&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Coney2.png?fit=600%2C203&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Coney2.png?resize=600%2C203&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;203&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-large wp-image-20612&quot; srcset=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Coney2.png?resize=1024%2C347&amp;amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Coney2.png?resize=300%2C102&amp;amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Coney2.png?resize=768%2C260&amp;amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Coney2.png?resize=1200%2C407&amp;amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Coney2.png?w=1260&amp;amp;ssl=1 1260w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Thanks to all your your support over the many years. It means the world to me. Happy holidays to all and a wonderful fruitful 2023 to everyone. (2023 is not a prime by the way.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally thanks to Kathryn once again. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/09/thanks-2/card2/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-20610&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;20610&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/09/thanks-2/card2/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/card2.jpeg?fit=640%2C427&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;640,427&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;card2&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/card2.jpeg?fit=300%2C200&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/card2.jpeg?fit=600%2C400&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/card2.jpeg?resize=400%2C267&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; height=&quot;267&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter wp-image-20610&quot; srcset=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/card2.jpeg?w=640&amp;amp;ssl=1 640w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/card2.jpeg?resize=300%2C200&amp;amp;ssl=1 300w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By rjlipton&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Lipton</name>
      <uri>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">CCI: jobs: Faculty at University of Southern California (apply by January 6, 2023)</title>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/12/09/faculty-at-university-of-southern-california-apply-by-january-6-2023/"/>
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/12/09/faculty-at-university-of-southern-california-apply-by-january-6-2023/</id>
    <updated>2022-12-09T18:27:16+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;The Computer Science Department of the University of Southern California invites applications for multiple positions for tenure-track positions at all ranks. The department is looking for exceptional candidates in all areas of computer science. One or two positions will prioritize candidates in security, privacy, and cryptography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://usccareers.usc.edu/job/los-angeles/open-rank-assistant-associate-full-professor-of-computer-science/1209/36964536288&quot;&gt;https://usccareers.usc.edu/job/los-angeles/open-rank-assistant-associate-full-professor-of-computer-science/1209/36964536288&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: jiapengz@usc.edu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>CCI: jobs</name>
      <uri>https://cstheory-jobs.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Luca Aceto: Report on the formative research evaluation of the Department of Computer Science at Reykjavik University</title>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2022/12/report-on-formative-research-evaluation.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-617398418692917975</id>
    <updated>2022-12-09T10:17:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I am pleased to share with you the &lt;a href=&quot;http://icetcs.ru.is/DCS-Reykjavik-Formative-Research-Review-November2022.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; I received yesterday from the panel that carried out a formative research evaluation review for the Department of Computer Science at Reykjavik University last month. (See below for some excerpts from the report.) The (IMHO, stellar) review panel consisted of &lt;a href=&quot;http://igw.tuwien.ac.at/hci/people/gfitzpatrick&quot;&gt;Geraldine Fitzpatrick&lt;/a&gt; (TU Wien, Austria),  &lt;a href=&quot;https://homes.cs.aau.dk/~kgl/&quot;&gt;Kim Guldstrand Larsen&lt;/a&gt; (Aalborg University, Denmark) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/michael.wooldridge/&quot;&gt;Michael Wooldridge&lt;/a&gt; (University of Oxford, United Kingdom). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our evaluators have given us a lot of food for thought, have identified several challenges for the department and have given us many recommendations we might follow to improve our research environment and work, as well as its impact. I trust that some of those remarks will be useful for the university as a whole.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our next task as a department will be to do justice to the work of the review panel and build on it to improve our research environment and output.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I thank all my colleagues at the department, including postdocs and PhD students of course, whose creativity, drive, enthusiasm and research work have contributed to building a research environment that, in my admittedly very biassed opinion, punches well above its weight. I am very proud of their work.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, we have to keep our feet on the ground and realise that, as the challenges identified by the review panel indicate, we are just starting our journey.&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Excerpts from the formative review report&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;margin-left: 40px; text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&quot;Overall we were pleased and impressed to find that a department which is very young in international terms has succeeded in establishing itself as an internationally competitive hub for Computer Science research. This is a noteworthy achievement by any measure, but is particularly impressive when considering the highly competitive culture of international computer science research, where world-class researchers are very highly-sought after and are able to demand highly lucrative packages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;margin-left: 40px; text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We repeatedly heard that the department is a highly collegial environment, and has largely avoided the curse of factionalism that taints so many university departments.&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;margin-left: 40px; text-align: left;&quot;&gt;We were impressed by the international links that the department has been able to establish, with many visitors who clearly contribute to the research culture of the department at all levels. We saw evidence that directly experiencing this culture has been instrumental in a number of hires and in attracting PhD students.&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;margin-left: 40px; text-align: left;&quot;&gt;The self-evaluation report we were provided with gave a number of key performance indicators, such as volume of publications in internationally competitive journal and conference venues, research awards such as best-paper prizes, and the acquisition of research funding. We were pleased to note that, modulo some expected minor year-on-year variations, all of these measures seem to be on a positive upward trajectory.&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;margin-left: 40px; text-align: left;&quot;&gt;We noted that much of the Department’s research portfolio is strongly interdisciplinary, and addresses key societal challenges with demonstrable national impact.&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;margin-left: 40px; text-align: left;&quot;&gt;Finally, we noted that the Department does well in terms of diversity at faculty level, with an increased number of female staff. Other aspects of diversity are less clear, though this perhaps represents Iceland’s racial demographic.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.icetcs.ru.is/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ICE-TCS&lt;/a&gt; glasses on, I was delighted to read the panel&#39;s opinion on our centre:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;margin-left: 40px; text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&quot;We were truly impressed by ICE-TCS that in a short span of time (inaugurated in 2005) has established itself as a world-class center within Theoretical Computer Science (TCS). In particular, we find that the center has been extremely successful combining Track A and Track B of TCS with notable research contributions within and recognitions from the sub-fields of Concurrency Theory, Logic, Programming Languages, Combinatorics and Algorithms.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a centre, we will strive to improve following the panel&#39;s recommendations and to develop a crisp, overarching research vision for the coming few years, which may help us keep spreading the TCS gospel in Iceland and attract talent to the country. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Luca Aceto&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      <uri>http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">CCI: jobs: Faculty at Georgia Tech (apply by December 31, 2022)</title>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/12/09/faculty-at-georgia-tech-apply-by-december-31-2022/"/>
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/12/09/faculty-at-georgia-tech-apply-by-december-31-2022/</id>
    <updated>2022-12-09T08:23:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;Faculty Position at Georgia Tech SCS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/23304&quot;&gt;https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/23304&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: ssingla@gatech.edu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>CCI: jobs</name>
      <uri>https://cstheory-jobs.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: On the strong metric dimension of composed graphs</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04166"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04166</id>
    <updated>2022-12-09T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wagner_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Marcel Wagner&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Schmitz_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yannick Schmitz&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wanke_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Egon Wanke&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two vertices $u$ and $v$ of an undirected graph $G$ are strongly resolved by
a vertex $w$ if there is a shortest path between $w$ and $u$ containing $v$ or
a shortest path between $w$ and $v$ containing $u$. A vertex set $R$ is a
strong resolving set for $G$ if for each pair of vertices there is a vertex in
$R$ that strongly resolves them. The strong metric dimension of $G$ is the size
of a minimum strong resolving set for $G$. We show that a minimum strong
resolving set for an undirected graph $G$ can be computed efficiently if and
only if a minimum strong resolving set for each biconnected component of $G$
can be computed efficiently.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Gap Preserving Reductions between Reconfiguration Problems</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04207"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04207</id>
    <updated>2022-12-09T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ohsaka_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Naoto Ohsaka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Combinatorial reconfiguration is a growing research field studying problems
on the transformability between a pair of solutions of a search problem. We
consider the approximability of optimization variants of reconfiguration
problems; e.g., for a Boolean formula $\varphi$ and two satisfying truth
assignments $\sigma_{\sf s}$ and $\sigma_{\sf t}$ for $\varphi$, Maxmin SAT
Reconfiguration requires to maximize the minimum fraction of satisfied clauses
of $\varphi$ during transformation from $\sigma_{\sf s}$ to $\sigma_{\sf t}$.
Solving such optimization variants approximately, we may obtain a
reconfiguration sequence comprising almost-satisfying truth assignments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this study, we prove a series of gap-preserving reductions to give
evidence that a host of reconfiguration problems are PSPACE-hard to
approximate, under some plausible assumption. Our starting point is a new
working hypothesis called the Reconfiguration Inapproximability Hypothesis
(RIH), which asserts that a gap version of Maxmin CSP Reconfiguration is
PSPACE-hard. This hypothesis may be thought of as a reconfiguration analogue of
the PCP theorem. Our main result is PSPACE-hardness of approximating Maxmin
$3$-SAT Reconfiguration of bounded occurrence under RIH. The crux of its proof
is a gap-preserving reduction from Maxmin Binary CSP Reconfiguration to itself
of bounded degree. Because a simple application of the degree reduction
technique using expander graphs due to Papadimitriou and Yannakakis does not
preserve the perfect completeness, we modify the alphabet as if each vertex
could take a pair of values simultaneously. To accomplish the soundness
requirement, we further apply an explicit family of near-Ramanujan graphs and
the expander mixing lemma. As an application of the main result, we demonstrate
that under RIH, optimization variants of popular reconfiguration problems are
PSPACE-hard to approximate.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Coloring Inside the Lines: The Jagged Legacy of the HOLC Neighborhood Risk Maps</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04117"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04117</id>
    <updated>2022-12-09T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/stat/1/au:+Gupta_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Arunav Gupta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There has been a large body of work exploring the discriminatory nature of
the home mortgage risk maps produced by the Home Owners&#39; Loan Corporation in
the late 1930s. However, little attention has been paid to the question of
whether these maps are still descriptive of racial residential boundaries in
their cities 80 years after their creation. To address this gap, Markov Chain
Monte Carlo, previously unutilized in the relevant literature, is employed to
randomly generate many plausible alternative mortgage security maps. Then, the
racial evenness of the HOLC maps and the generated maps is compared using
Shannon&#39;s entropy. These findings indicate that the HOLC maps are significantly
descriptive of the precise racial residential boundaries prevalent across
eleven US cities in 2010. The methodology used here is highly modular and
reproducible, allowing for future work measuring different outcome statistics,
locations, and time periods.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Quantum Lower Bounds for Finding Stationary Points of Nonconvex Functions</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03906"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03906</id>
    <updated>2022-12-09T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Zhang_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Chenyi Zhang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Li_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tongyang Li&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Quantum algorithms for optimization problems are of general interest. Despite
recent progress in classical lower bounds for nonconvex optimization under
different settings and quantum lower bounds for convex optimization, quantum
lower bounds for nonconvex optimization are still widely open. In this paper,
we conduct a systematic study of quantum query lower bounds on finding
$\epsilon$-approximate stationary points of nonconvex functions, and we
consider the following two important settings: 1) having access to $p$-th order
derivatives; or 2) having access to stochastic gradients. The classical query
lower bounds is $\Omega\big(\epsilon^{-\frac{1+p}{p}}\big)$ regarding the first
setting, and $\Omega(\epsilon^{-4})$ regarding the second setting (or
$\Omega(\epsilon^{-3})$ if the stochastic gradient function is mean-squared
smooth). In this paper, we extend all these classical lower bounds to the
quantum setting. They match the classical algorithmic results respectively,
demonstrating that there is no quantum speedup for finding
$\epsilon$-stationary points of nonconvex functions with $p$-th order
derivative inputs or stochastic gradient inputs, whether with or without the
mean-squared smoothness assumption. Technically, our quantum lower bounds are
obtained by showing that the sequential nature of classical hard instances in
all these settings also applies to quantum queries, preventing any quantum
speedup other than revealing information of the stationary points sequentially.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Fast and Practical DAG Decomposition with Reachability Applications</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03945"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03945</id>
    <updated>2022-12-09T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kritikakis_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Giorgos Kritikakis&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Tollis_I/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ioannis G. Tollis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present practical linear and almost linear-time algorithms to compute a
chain decomposition of a directed acyclic graph (DAG), $G=(V,E)$. The number of
vertex-disjoint chains computed is very close to the minimum. The time
complexity of our algorithm is $O(|E|+c*l)$, where $c$ is the number of path
concatenations and $l$ is the length of a longest path of the graph. We give a
comprehensive explanation on factors $c$ and $l$ in the following sections. Our
techniques have important applications in many areas, including the design of
faster practical transitive closure algorithms. We observe that $|E_{red}|\leq
width*|V|$ ($E_{red}$: non-transitive edges) and show how to find a
substantially large subset of $E_{tr}$ (transitive edges) using a chain
decomposition in linear time, without calculating the transitive closure. Our
extensive experimental results show the interplay between the width, $E_{red}$,
$E_{tr}$ in various models of graphs. We show how to compute a reachability
indexing scheme in $O(k_c*|E_{red}|)$ time, where $k_c$ is the number of chains
and $|E_{red}|$ is the number of non-transitive edges. This scheme can answer
reachabilitiy queries in constant time. The space complexity of the scheme is
$O(k_c*|V|)$. The experimental results reveal that our methods are even better
in practice than the theoretical bounds imply, indicating how fast chain
decomposition algorithms can be applied to the transitive closure problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: DeMEtRIS: Counting (near)-Cliques by Crawling</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03957"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03957</id>
    <updated>2022-12-09T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Bera_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Suman K.Bera&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Choudhari_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jayesh Choudhari&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Haddadan_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Shahrzad Haddadan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ahmadian_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sara Ahmadian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the problem of approximately counting cliques and near cliques in a
graph, where the access to the graph is only available through crawling its
vertices; thus typically seeing only a small portion of it. This model, known
as the random walk model or the neighborhood query model has been introduced
recently and captures real-life scenarios in which the entire graph is too
massive to be stored as a whole or be scanned entirely and sampling vertices
independently is non-trivial in it. We introduce DeMEtRIS: Dense Motif
Estimation through Random Incident Sampling. This method provides a scalable
algorithm for clique and near clique counting in the random walk model. We
prove the correctness of our algorithm through rigorous mathematical analysis
and extensive experiments. Both our theoretical results and our experiments
show that DeMEtRIS obtains a high precision estimation by only crawling a
sub-linear portion on vertices, thus we demonstrate a significant improvement
over previously known results.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Property Testing Review: News for November 2022</title>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/2022/12/news-for-october-2022-2/"/>
    <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1784</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T18:22:31+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;All the best to everyone for a Happy 2023. The holiday season is ripe with lots of papers to engage our readers. So, we have nine papers and we hope some of those will catch your fancy. As a new year treat, we also feature Gilmer&amp;#8217;s constant lower bound on the union-closed sets problem of Frankl. On we go.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sublinear Time Algorithms and Complexity of Approximate Maximum Matching&lt;/strong&gt; by Soheil Behnezhad, Mohammad Roghani, Aviad Rubinstein (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.15843&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;) This paper makes significantly advances our understanding of the maximum matching problem in the sublinear regime. Your goal is to estimate the size of the maximum matching and you may assume that you have query access to the adjacency list of your graph. Our posts from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ptreview.sublinear.info/2021/12/&quot;&gt;Dec 2021&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ptreview.sublinear.info/2022/07/news-for-june-2022/&quot;&gt;June 2022&lt;/a&gt; reported some impressive progress on this problem. The upshot from these works essentially said that you can beat greedy matching and obtain a \(\frac{1}{2} + \Omega(1)\) approximate maximum matching in sublinear time. Let me first go over the algorithmic results from the current paper. The paper shows the following two algorithmic results:&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;(1) An algorithm that runs in time \(n^{2 &amp;#8211; \Omega_{\varepsilon}(1)}\) and returns a \(2/3 &amp;#8211; \varepsilon\) approximation to maximum matching in general graphs, and &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;(2) An algorithm that runs in time \(n^{2 &amp;#8211; \Omega_{\varepsilon}(1)}\) and returns a \(2/3 + \varepsilon\) approximation to maximum matching size in &lt;em&gt;bipartite&lt;/em&gt; graphs. &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The question remained &amp;#8212; can we show a lower bound that grows superlinearly with \(n\). The current work achieves this and shows that &lt;em&gt;even on bipartite graphs&lt;/em&gt;, you must make at least \(n^{1.2 &amp;#8211; o(1)}\) &lt;em&gt;queries &lt;/em&gt;to the adjacency list to get a better than \(2/3 + \Omega(1)\) approximation.  Thus, you cannot shoot for a bonafide quadratic lower bound on the number of queries to beat a two-thirds approximation to the maximum matching size.  (An aside: A concurrent work by &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.00189&quot;&gt;Bhattacharya-Kiss-Saranurak&lt;/a&gt; from December also obtains similar algorithmic results for approximating the maximum matching size in general graphs). &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Directed Isoperimetric Theorems for Boolean Functions on the Hypergrid and an \(\widetilde{O}(n \sqrt d)\) Monotonicity Tester&lt;/strong&gt; by Hadley Black, Deeparnab Chakrabarty, C. Seshadhri (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05281&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;) Boolean Monotonicity testing is as classic as classic gets in property testing. Encouraged by the success of isoperimetric theorems over the hypercube domain and the monotonicity testers powered by these isoperimetries (over the hypercube), one may wish to obtain efficient monotonicity testers for the hypergrid \([n]^d\). Indeed, the same gang of authors as above showed in a previous work that a Margulis style directed isoperimetry can be extended from the lowly hypercube to the hypergrid. This resulted in a tester with \(\widetilde{O}(d^{5/6})\) queries. The more intricate task of proving a directed Talagrand style isoperimetry that underlies the Khot-Minzer-Safra breakthrough was a challenge. Was. The featured work extends this isoperimetry from the hypercube to the hypergrid and this gives a tester with query complexity \(\widetilde{O}(n \sqrt d)\) which is an improvement over the \(d^{5/6}\) bound for domains where \(n\) is (say) some small constant. But as they say, when it rains, it pours. This brings us to a concurrent paper with the same result.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improved Monotonicity Testers via Hypercube Embeddings&lt;/strong&gt; by Mark Braverman, Subhash Khot, Guy Kindler, Dor Minzer (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.09229&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;) Similar to the paper above, this paper also obtains monotonicity testers over the hypergrid domain, \([n]^d\), with \(\widetilde{O}(n^3 \sqrt d)\) queries. This paper also presents monotonicity testers over the standard hypercube domain &amp;#8212; \(\{0,1\}^d\) in the \(p\)-biased setting. In particular, their tester issues \(\widetilde{O}(\sqrt d)\) queries to successfully test monotonicity on the \(p\)-biased cube. Coolly enough, this paper also proves directed Talagrand style isoperimetric inequalities both over the hypergrid and the \(p\)-biased hypercube domains.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Toeplitz Low-Rank Approximation with Sublinear Query Complexity&lt;/strong&gt; by Michael Kapralov, Hannah Lawrence, Mikhail Makarov, Cameron Musco, Kshiteej Sheth (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.11328&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;) Another intriguing paper for the holiday month. So, take a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toeplitz_matrix&quot;&gt;Toeplitz matrix&lt;/a&gt;. Did you know that any &lt;em&gt;psd&lt;/em&gt; Toeplitz matrix admits a (near-optimal in the Frobenius norm) low-rank approximation which is itself Toeplitz? This is a remarkable statement. The featured paper proves this result and uses it to get more algorithmic mileage. In particular, suppose you are given a \(d \times d\) Toeplitz matrix \(T\). Armed with the techniques from the paper you get algorithms that return a Toeplitz matrix \(\widetilde{T}\) with rank slightly bigger than \(rank(T)\) which is a very good approximation to \(T\) in the Frobenius norm. Moreover, the algorithm only issues a number of queries sublinear in the size of \(T\).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sampling an Edge in Sublinear Time Exactly and Optimally&lt;/strong&gt; by Talya Eden, Shyam Narayanan and Jakub Tětek (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.04981&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;) Regular readers of PTReview are no strangers to the fundamental task of sampling a random edge from a graph which you can access via query access to its vertices. Of course, you don&amp;#8217;t have direct access to the edges of this graph. This paper considers the task of sampling a truly uniform edge from the graph \(G = (V,E)\) with \(|V| = n, |E| = m\). In STOC 22, Tětek and Thorup presented an algorithm for a relaxation of this problem where you want an \(\varepsilon\)-approximately unifrom edge. This algorithm runs in time \(O\left(\frac{n}{\sqrt{m}} \cdot \log(1/\varepsilon) \right)\). The featured paper presents an algorithm that samples an honest to goodness uniform edge in expected time \(O(n/\sqrt{m})\). This closes the problem as we already know a matching lower bound. Indeed, just consider a graph with \(O(\sqrt m)\) vertices which induce a clique and all the remaining components are singletons. You need to sample at least \(\Omega(n/\sqrt m)\) vertices before you see any edge.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Support Size Estimation: The Power of Conditioning&lt;/strong&gt; by Diptarka Chakraborty, Gunjan Kumar, Kuldeep S. Meel (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.11967&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;) This work considers the classic problem of support size estimation with a slight twist. You are given access to a stronger (conditioning based) sampling oracle. Let me highlight one of the results from this paper. So, you are given a distribution \(D\) where \(supp(D) \subseteq [n]\). You want to obtain an estimate to \(supp(D)\) that lies within \(supp(D) \pm \varepsilon n\) with high probability. Suppose you are also given access to the following sampling oracle. You may choose any subset \(S \subseteq [n]\) and you may request a sample \(x \sim D\vert_S\). An element \(x \in S\) is returned with probability \(D\vert_S(x) = D(x)/D(S)\) (for simplicity of this post, let us assume \(D(S) &amp;gt; 0\)). In addition, this oracle also reveals for you the value \(D(x)\). The paper shows that the algorithmic task of obtaining a high probability estimate to the support size (to within \(\pm \varepsilon n\)) with this sampling oracle admits a lower bound of \(\Omega(\log (\log n)\) calls to the sampling oracle.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Computing (1+epsilon)-Approximate Degeneracy in Sublinear Time&lt;/strong&gt; by Valerie King, Alex Thomo, Quinton Yong (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.04627&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;) Degeneracy is one of the important graph parameters which is relevant to several problems in algorithmic graph theory. A graph \(G = (V,E)\) is \(\delta\)-degenerate if all induced subgraphs of \(G\) contain a vertex with degree at most \(\delta\). The featured paper presents algorithms for a \((1 + \varepsilon)\)-approximation to degeneracy of \(G\) where you are given access to \(G\) via its adjacency list. &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning and Testing Latent-Tree Ising Models Efficiently&lt;/strong&gt; by Davin Choo, Yuval Dagan, Constantinos Daskalakis, Anthimos Vardis Kandiros (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.13291&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;) Ising models are emerging as a rich and fertile frontier for Property Testing and Learning Theory researchers (at least to the uninitiated ones like me). This paper considers latent-tree ising models. These are ising models that can only be observed at their leaf nodes. One of the results in this paper gives an algorithm for testing whether the leaf distributions attached to two latent-tree ising models are close or far in the TV distance.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A constant lower bound for the union-closed sets conjecture&lt;/strong&gt; by Justin Gilmer (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.09055&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;) The union-closed sets conjecture of Frankl states that for any union closed set system \(\mathcal{F} \subseteq 2^{[n]}\), it holds that there is a mysterious element \(i \in [n]\) that shows up in at least \(c = 1/2\) of the sets in \(\mathcal{F}\). Gilmer took a first swipe on this problem and gave a constant lower bound of \(c = 0.01\). This has already been improved by at least four different groups to \(\frac{3-\sqrt{5}}{2}\), a bound which is the limit of Gilmer&amp;#8217;s method (which takes all of only 9 pages!). &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The key lemma Gilmer proves is the following. Suppose you sample two sets: \(A, B \sim \mathcal{D}_n\) &lt;em&gt;(iid)&lt;/em&gt; from some distribution \(\mathcal{D}_n\) over the subsets of \([n]\). Suppose for every index \(i \in [n]\), it holds that the probability that the element \(i\) shows up in the random set \(A\) is at most $0.01$. Then you have \(H(A \cup B) \geq 1.26 H(A)\). This is all you need to finish Gilmer&amp;#8217;s proof (of \(c = 0.01\)). The remaining argument is as follows. Suppose, by the way of contradiction, that no element shows up in at least \(0.01\) fraction of sets in the union closed family \(\mathcal{F}\). An application of the key lemma would then give \(H(A \cup B) &amp;gt; H(A)\) which is a contradiction if \(A,B\) are chosen uniformly from \(\mathcal{F}\). The proof of the key lemma is also fairly slick and uses pretty simple information theoretic tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Akash&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Property Testing Review</name>
      <uri>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Computational Complexity: Harry Lewis&#39;s talk  on The Birth of Binary on Dec 8 (Thats today!)</title>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/12/harry-lewiss-talk-on-birth-of-binary-on.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-8537518250187298951</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T15:38:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;More on the information on Harry Lewis&#39;s&amp;nbsp; talk is in his blog post about it:&lt;a href=&quot;http://harry-lewis.blogspot.com/2022/11/skolem-lecture-on-birth-of-binary-8.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1) On Dec 8, 2022 Harry Lewis is giving the annual Thoraf Skolem Memorial Lecture on&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;The Birth of binary&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Its in Oslo. BOO- I can&#39;t get there!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It will be on Zoom- YEAH I can see it! Here is the link:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://uio.zoom.us/j/63956167845&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;It will be at 7:15AM East Coast Time- BOO- I needs my sleep!&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;(Plus, I am posting this after its over)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;It will be recorded-YEAH I can see it later. CAVEAT- Will I?&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;(It will be linked to at the link in item 4 below.)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;2) Lloyd Strickland and Harry Lewis have a book on the subject:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262544344/leibniz-on-binary/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;titled&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;i&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;Leibniz on binary: The Invention of Computer Arithmetic.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;3) Questions like &lt;i&gt;who invented binary&amp;nbsp; &lt;/i&gt;or &lt;i&gt;who invented parallelism&lt;/i&gt; or&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;who first proved the dual-muffin theorem&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;can be hard to answer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;First&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp; is an ill defined term. In the current era we can see who published first, which is usually well defined, though might not get at the heart of the issue.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Which brings us to Leibniz on Binary.&amp;nbsp; He had lots of notes, not really intended for modern readers or even for readers in his own time. The notes lay out binary notation and some algorithms, but not in a modern way. Hence the book is quite valuable to tell a modern audience what Leibniz did. Leibniz published very little of it.&amp;nbsp; Even so, seeing what he did, the statement&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;i&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;Leibnitz invented binary&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt; is reasonable. Some of his notes dealt with what we would now call complexity, so I need to add him to my already-long list of people who had modern ideas about complexity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;4) For more on the Skolem Lecture, see&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hf.uio.no/ifikk/english/research/groups/logic/events/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By gasarch&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR22-178 |  A Strongly Polynomial Algorithm for Approximate Forster Transforms and its Application to Halfspace Learning | 

	Ilias Diakonikolas, 

	Christos Tzamos, 

	Daniel Kane</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/178"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/178</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T13:27:12+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    The Forster transform is a method of regularizing a dataset 
by placing it in {\em radial isotropic position}
while maintaining some of its essential properties.
Forster transforms have played a key role in a diverse range of settings
spanning computer science and functional analysis. Prior work had given
{\em weakly} polynomial time algorithms for computing Forster transforms, when they exist.
Our main result is the first {\em strongly polynomial time} algorithm to
compute an approximate Forster transform of a given dataset 
or certify that no such transformation exists. By leveraging our strongly polynomial Forster algorithm, 
we obtain the first strongly polynomial time algorithm for {\em distribution-free} PAC learning of halfspaces.
This learning result is surprising because {\em proper} PAC learning of halfspaces 
is {\em equivalent} to linear programming.
Our learning approach extends to give a strongly polynomial halfspace learner
in the presence of random classification noise and, more generally, Massart noise.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Partial gathering of mobile agents in dynamic rings</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03457"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03457</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Shibataa_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Masahiro Shibataa&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sudo_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yuichi Sudo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nakamura_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Junya Nakamura&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kim_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yonghwan Kim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we consider the partial gathering problem of mobile agents in
synchronous dynamic bidirectional ring networks. When k agents are distributed
in the network, the partial gathering problem requires, for a given positive
integer g (&amp;lt; k), that agents terminate in a configuration such that either at
least g agents or no agent exists at each node. So far, the partial gathering
problem has been considered in static graphs. In this paper, we start
considering partial gathering in dynamic graphs. As a first step, we consider
this problem in 1-interval connected rings, that is, one of the links in a ring
may be missing at each time step. In such networks, focusing on the
relationship between the values of k and g, we fully characterize the
solvability of the partial gathering problem and analyze the move complexity of
the proposed algorithms when the problem can be solved. First, we show that the
g-partial gathering problem is unsolvable when k &amp;lt;= 2g. Second, we show that
the problem can be solved with O(n log g) time and the total number of O(gn log
g) moves when 2g + 1 &amp;lt;= k &amp;lt;= 3g - 2. Third, we show that the problem can be
solved with O(n) time and the total number of O(kn) moves when 3g - 1 &amp;lt;= k &amp;lt;=
8g - 4. Notice that since k = O(g) holds when 3g - 1 &amp;lt;= k &amp;lt;= 8g - 4, the move
complexity O(kn) in this case can be represented also as O(gn). Finally, we
show that the problem can be solved with O(n) time and the total number of
O(gn) moves when k &amp;gt;= 8g - 3. These results mean that the partial gathering
problem can be solved also in dynamic rings when k &amp;gt;= 2g + 1. In addition,
agents require a total number of \Omega(gn) moves to solve the partial (resp.,
total) gathering problem. Thus, when k &amp;gt;= 3g - 1, agents can solve the partial
gathering problem with the asymptotically optimal total number of O(gn) moves.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Recognizing when a preference system is close to admitting a master list</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03521"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03521</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Schlotter_I/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ildik&amp;#xf3; Schlotter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A preference system $\mathcal{I}$ is an undirected graph where vertices have
preferences over their neighbors, and $\mathcal{I}$ admits a master list if all
preferences can be derived from a single ordering over all vertices. We study
the problem of deciding whether a given preference system~$\mathcal{I}$ is
close to admitting a master list based on three different distance measures. We
determine the computational complexity of the following questions: can
$\mathcal{I}$ be modified by (i) $k$ swaps in the preferences, (ii) $k$ edge
deletions, or (iii) $k$ vertex deletions so that the resulting instance admits
a master list? We investigate these problems in detail from the viewpoint of
parameterized complexity and of approximation. We also present two applications
related to stable and popular matchings.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Quantum Worst-Case to Average-Case Reductions for All Linear Problems</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03348"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03348</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Asadi_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vahid R. Asadi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Golovnev_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Alexander Golovnev&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Gur_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tom Gur&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Shinkar_I/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Igor Shinkar&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Subramanian_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sathyawageeswar Subramanian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the problem of designing worst-case to average-case reductions for
quantum algorithms. For all linear problems, we provide an explicit and
efficient transformation of quantum algorithms that are only correct on a small
(even sub-constant) fraction of their inputs into ones that are correct on all
inputs. This stands in contrast to the classical setting, where such results
are only known for a small number of specific problems or restricted
computational models. En route, we obtain a tight $\Omega(n^2)$ lower bound on
the average-case quantum query complexity of the Matrix-Vector Multiplication
problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our techniques strengthen and generalise the recently introduced additive
combinatorics framework for classical worst-case to average-case reductions
(STOC 2022) to the quantum setting. We rely on quantum singular value
transformations to construct quantum algorithms for linear verification in
superposition and learning Bogolyubov subspaces from noisy quantum oracles. We
use these tools to prove a quantum local correction lemma, which lies at the
heart of our reductions, based on a noise-robust probabilistic generalisation
of Bogolyubov&#39;s lemma from additive combinatorics.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Extending Utility Functions on Arbitrary Sets</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03394"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03394</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Chebotarev_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Pavel Chebotarev&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We consider the problem of whether a function $f^{}_P$ defined on a subset
$P$ of an arbitrary set $X$ can be extended to $X$ monotonically with respect
to a preorder $\succcurlyeq$ defined on $X$. We prove that whenever
$\succcurlyeq$ has a utility representation, such an extension exists if and
only if $f^{}_P$ is gap-safe increasing. An explicit construction for a
monotone extension of this kind involving an arbitrary utility representation
of $\succcurlyeq$ is presented. The special case where $P$ is a Pareto subset
of $X$ is considered. The problem under study does not include continuity
constraints.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: A Decision Diagram Operation for Reachability</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03684"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03684</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Brand_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sebastiaan Brand&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Back_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Thomas B&amp;#xe4;ck&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Laarman_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Alfons Laarman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Saturation is considered the state-of-the-art method for computing fixpoints
with decision diagrams. We present a relatively simple decision diagram
operation called REACH that also computes fixpoints. In contrast to saturation,
it does not require a partitioning of the transition relation. We give
sequential algorithms implementing the new operation for both binary and
multi-valued decision diagrams, and moreover provide parallel counterparts. We
implement these algorithms and experimentally compare their performance against
saturation on 692 model checking benchmarks in different languages. The results
show that the REACH operation often outperforms saturation, especially on
transition relations with low locality. In a comparison between parallelized
versions of REACH and saturation we find that REACH obtains comparable speedups
up to 16 cores, although falls behind saturation at 64 cores. Finally, in a
comparison with the state-of-the-art model checking tool ITS-tools we find that
REACH outperforms ITS-tools on 29% of models, suggesting that REACH can be
useful as a complementary method in an ensemble tool.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Density Approximation for Kinetic Groups</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03685"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03685</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mulken_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Max van Mulken&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Speckmann_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Bettina Speckmann&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Verbeek_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Kevin Verbeek&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sets of moving entities can form groups which travel together for significant
amounts of time. Tracking such groups is an important analysis task in a
variety of areas, such as wildlife ecology, urban transport, or sports
analysis. Correspondingly, recent years have seen a multitude of algorithms to
identify and track meaningful groups in sets of moving entities. However, not
only the mere existence of one or more groups is an important fact to discover;
in many application areas the actual shape of the group carries meaning as
well. In this paper we initiate the algorithmic study of the shape of a moving
group. We use kernel density estimation to model the density within a group and
show how to efficiently maintain an approximation of this density description
over time. Furthermore, we track persistent maxima which give a meaningful
first idea of the time-varying shape of the group. By combining several
approximation techniques, we obtain a kinetic data structure that can
approximately track persistent maxima efficiently.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: An improved approximation guarantee for Prize-Collecting TSP</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03776"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03776</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Blauth_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jannis Blauth&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nagele_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Martin N&amp;#xe4;gele&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present a new approximation algorithm for the (metric) prize-collecting
traveling salesperson problem (PCTSP). In PCTSP, opposed to the classical
traveling salesperson problem (TSP), one may not include a vertex of the input
graph in the returned tour at the cost of a given vertex-dependent penalty, and
the objective is to balance the length of the tour and the incurred penalties
for omitted vertices by minimizing the sum of the two. We present an algorithm
that achieves an approximation guarantee of $1.774$ with respect to the natural
linear programming relaxation of the problem. This significantly reduces the
gap between the approximability of classical TSP and PCTSP, beating the
previously best known approximation factor of $1.915$. As a key ingredient of
our improvement, we present a refined decomposition technique for solutions of
the LP relaxation, and show how to leverage components of that decomposition as
building blocks for our tours.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Why the equivalence problem for unambiguous grammars has not been solved back in 1966?</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03786"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03786</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Makarov_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vladislav Makarov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1966, Semenov, by using a technique based on power series, suggested an
algorithm that tells apart the languages described by an unambiguous grammar
and a DFA. At the first glance, it may appear that the algorithm can be easily
modified to yield a full solution of the equivalence problem for unambiguous
grammars. This article shows why this hunch is, in fact, incorrect.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Computing linear sections of varieties: quantum entanglement, tensor decompositions and beyond</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03851"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03851</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Johnston_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nathaniel Johnston&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lovitz_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Benjamin Lovitz&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Vijayaraghavan_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Aravindan Vijayaraghavan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the problem of finding elements in the intersection of an arbitrary
conic variety in $\mathbb{F}^n$ with a given linear subspace (where
$\mathbb{F}$ can be the real or complex field). This problem captures a rich
family of algorithmic problems under different choices of the variety. The
special case of the variety consisting of rank-1 matrices already has strong
connections to central problems in different areas like quantum information
theory and tensor decompositions. This problem is known to be NP-hard in the
worst-case, even for the variety of rank-1 matrices.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, despite these hardness results we give efficient algorithms
that solve this problem for &quot;typical&quot; subspaces. Here, the subspace $U
\subseteq \mathbb{F}^n$ is chosen generically of a certain dimension,
potentially with some generic elements of the variety contained in it. Our main
algorithmic result is a polynomial time algorithm that recovers all the
elements of $U$ that lie in the variety, under some mild non-degeneracy
assumptions on the variety. As corollaries, we obtain the following results:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\bullet$ Uniqueness results and polynomial time algorithms for generic
instances of a broad class of low-rank decomposition problems that go beyond
tensor decompositions. Here, we recover a decomposition of the form
$\sum_{i=1}^R v_i \otimes w_i$, where the $v_i$ are elements of the given
variety $X$. This implies new algorithmic results even in the special case of
tensor decompositions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\bullet$ Polynomial time algorithms for several entangled subspaces problems
in quantum entanglement, including determining $r$-entanglement, complete
entanglement, and genuine entanglement of a subspace. While all of these
problems are NP-hard in the worst case, our algorithm solves them in polynomial
time for generic subspaces of dimension up to a constant multiple of the
maximum possible.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Cocke--Younger--Kasami--Schwartz--Zippel algorithm and relatives</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03861"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03861</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Makarov_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vladislav Makarov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The equivalence problem for unambiguous grammars is an important, but very
difficult open question in formal language theory. Consider the \emph{limited}
equivalence problem for unambiguous grammars -- for two unambiguous grammars
$G_1$ and $G_2$, tell whether or not they describe the same set of words of
length $n$. Obviously, the naive approach requires exponential time with
respect to $n$. By combining two classic algorithmic ideas, I introduce a
$O({\rm poly}(n, |G_1|, |G_2|))$ algorithm for this problem. Moreover, the
ideas behind the algorithm prove useful in various other scenarious.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Richard Lipton: Quantum Circuits in the New York Times</title>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/07/quantum-circuits-in-the-new-york-times/"/>
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=20531</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T19:16:32+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;
&lt;font color=&quot;#0044cc&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Can quantum circuits have something to do with wormholes?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;font color=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;image alignright&quot;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/07/quantum-circuits-in-the-new-york-times/ms-3/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-20534&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;20534&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/07/quantum-circuits-in-the-new-york-times/ms-3/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/ms.jpeg?fit=259%2C194&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;259,194&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;ms&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/ms.jpeg?fit=259%2C194&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/ms.jpeg?fit=259%2C194&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/ms.jpeg?resize=200%2C150&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; height=&quot;150&quot; class=&quot;alignright wp-image-20534&quot; srcset=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/ms.jpeg?w=259&amp;amp;ssl=1 259w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/ms.jpeg?resize=200%2C150&amp;amp;ssl=1 200w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;caption alignright&quot;&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;-2&quot;&gt;Wikipedia &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_Spiropulu&quot;&gt;src&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Maria Spiropulu, a physicist &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hep.caltech.edu/~smaria/&quot;&gt;at&lt;/a&gt; the California Institute of Technology, is featured in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2022/11/30/science/physics-wormhole-quantum-computer.html&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; in last week&amp;#8217;s Tuesday Science section of the New York Times about teleporting qubits through what might be described as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wormhole&quot;&gt;wormhole&lt;/a&gt;. The article says that physicists such as she&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;#038;bg=e8e8e8&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;dots}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; like to compare the teleportation process to two cups of tea. Drop a cube of sugar into one teacup, and it promptly dissolves&amp;#8212;then, after a tick of the quantum clock, the cube reappears intact in the other teacup. &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Today (yesterday? tomorrow? &lt;a href=&quot;https://chadorzel.substack.com/p/wormhole-to-2006&quot;&gt;years ago?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8212;with a quantum clock, does it &lt;a href=&quot;https://phys.org/news/2019-03-physicists-reverse-quantum.html&quot;&gt;matter&lt;/a&gt;?) we ask what the paper referenced in the NYT story might really be about. This is after trying to work through a lot of hype and pushback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first trouble is that we cannot tick a real quantum clock quite yet. But Spiropulu and her group were able to simulate a quantum clock via using a quantum computer. The group comprises: first author Daniel Jafferis, then Alexander Zlokapa, Joseph Lykken, David Kolchmeyer, Samantha Davis, Nikolai Lauk, Hartmut Neven, and then Spiropulu. Their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-022-05424-3&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; was just reported in &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt;. The whole buzz makes us recall an exchange that never took place:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; Albert Einstein: &amp;#8220;Reality is merely an illusion, albeit a persistent one.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Woody Allen: &amp;#8220;[If] everything is an illusion and nothing exists, [then] I definitely overpaid for my carpet.&amp;#8221; &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; The Quantum Experiment &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Spiropulu&amp;#8217;s group could not build a quantum experiment to directly test this kind of teleportation. At least it seemed like that would be impossible. But they cleverly used the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sycamore_processor&quot;&gt;Sycamore&lt;/a&gt; chip developed by Google in 2019. It uses a type of quantum computing called superconducting qubits, which send electric currents flowing through superconducting materials to store and process information. Google created the chip to study &amp;#8220;quantum supremacy&amp;#8221; as we &lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2019/10/27/quantum-supremacy-at-last/&quot;&gt;covered&lt;/a&gt; three years ago. A wonderful &lt;a href=&quot;https://jonathan-hui.medium.com/quantum-supremacy-google-sycamore-processor-6f30073a17fa&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;em&gt;Medium&lt;/em&gt; by Jonathan Hui runs helpful commentary around circuit diagrams of the processor from the Google team&amp;#8217;s original &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-019-1666-5&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;. Hui says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; Regardless of other claims, Google’s processor is a significant milestone because it demonstrates a problem with some real value. Whether classical computers will take 100,000 years or 2.5 days for the pseudo-random generator, this kind of speed improvement is rarely or never demonstrated with a general-purpose quantum computer. &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
What we find significant is that Google&amp;#8217;s processor is not limited to the pseudo-randomness application to demonstrate what we&amp;#8217;ll call &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ibm.com/blogs/research/tag/quantum-advantage/&quot;&gt;advantage&lt;/a&gt;. It has plug-and-play capabilities. Google may not have created Sycamore to study quantum teleportation. But it was possible to exploit its quantum ability to demonstrate teleportation. See their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-022-05424-3&quot;&gt;Nature&lt;/a&gt; paper for how. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; Wormholes and Their Duals &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The NYT story and an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantamagazine.org/physicists-create-a-wormhole-using-a-quantum-computer-20221130/&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; by Natalie Wolchover in &lt;em&gt;Quanta&lt;/em&gt; have some pithy quotes from people well-known to us:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
John Preskill, about &amp;#8216;the evolving system of qubits in the Sycamore chip&amp;#8217;: &amp;#8220;[It] has this really cool alternative description. You can think of the system in a very different language as being gravitational.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Leonard Susskind: &amp;#8220;The really interesting thing here is the possibility of analyzing purely quantum phenomena using general relativity, and who knows where that’s going to go.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Scott Aaronson: &amp;#8220;If this experiment has brought a wormhole into actual physical existence, then a strong case could be made that you, too, bring a wormhole into actual physical existence every time you sketch one with pen and paper.&amp;#8221; (See also Scott&amp;#8217;s post &lt;a href=&quot;https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6871&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
These quotes allude to a duality, both ends of which connect Einstein and the Israeli-American physicist Nathan Rosen. Their 1935 paper, abbreviated ER, showed how a wormhole could arise in the specific form of an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wormhole&quot;&gt;Einstein-Rosen bridge&lt;/a&gt; according to the equations of general relativity. They were joined that same year by Boris Podolsky in a paper that described quantum &lt;em&gt;entanglement&lt;/em&gt; via the so-called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EPR_paradox&quot;&gt;EPR paradox&lt;/a&gt;. In 2013, Juan Maldacena wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1306.0533&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; with Susskind claiming a correspondence between them. This was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev_model&quot;&gt;expanded&lt;/a&gt; by Alexei Kitaev following work by Subir Sachdev and Jinwu Ye. All this draws on Maldacena&amp;#8217;s work in the 1990s showing a duality between two cosmic models that have different dimensionalities, in the manner of a hologram. Maldacena and Susskind&amp;#8217;s claim is pithily expressed as the title of section 3 of their paper: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=center&gt;&lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cmathsf%7BER+%3D+EPR%7D+&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;#92;displaystyle  &amp;#92;mathsf{ER = EPR} &quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equality is enticing because this could effect the communion of relativity and quantum mechanics. This matter found its way into another New York Times &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2022/10/10/science/black-holes-cosmology-hologram.html&quot;&gt;story&lt;/a&gt; in October, where Susskind is quoted as saying in 2017:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; &amp;#8220;It may be too strong to say that gravity and quantum mechanics are exactly the same thing. But those of us who are paying attention may already sense that the two are inseparable, and that neither makes sense without the other.&amp;#8221; &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
That story centered the duality on black holes, but Will Kinney, a colleague of Ken&amp;#8217;s at Buffalo, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/WKCosmo/status/1600153143702016001&quot;&gt;observed&lt;/a&gt; that Maldacena and Susskind &amp;#8220;conjectured that ANY entangled particle pair is dual to a wormhole solution.&amp;#8221; Kinney also &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/WKCosmo/status/1598323058476982273&quot;&gt;quoted&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Quanta&lt;/em&gt; editor Thomas Lin as saying,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; &amp;#8220;In the context of the article, it should be clear that a quantum system was created that was dual to a holographic wormhole.&amp;#8221; &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
What fascinates us is that the quantum system had the form of direct simulation of quantum circuitry. In fact, Spiropulu&amp;#8217;s team used only 9 of 72 available qubits on a Sycamore chip. The NYT article has a big graphic on the role of ordinary quantum circuits, from which we snip this detail:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/07/quantum-circuits-in-the-new-york-times/nytcircuitdetail/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-20535&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;20535&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/07/quantum-circuits-in-the-new-york-times/nytcircuitdetail/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/NYTcircuitdetail.jpg?fit=794%2C466&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;794,466&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;KWRegan&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1670368563&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;NYTcircuitdetail&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/NYTcircuitdetail.jpg?fit=300%2C176&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/NYTcircuitdetail.jpg?fit=600%2C352&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/NYTcircuitdetail.jpg?resize=450%2C264&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;450&quot; height=&quot;264&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter wp-image-20535&quot; srcset=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/NYTcircuitdetail.jpg?w=794&amp;amp;ssl=1 794w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/NYTcircuitdetail.jpg?resize=300%2C176&amp;amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/NYTcircuitdetail.jpg?resize=768%2C451&amp;amp;ssl=1 768w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This leads us to some speculations of our own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; Dualling Quantum Circuits? &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Setting aside the question of wormholes or their duals, Spiropulu&amp;#8217;s team did observe behavior that could be forecasted only after running an exhaustive classical simulation tied to the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model on the 9-qubit scale. This is described in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uOJCS1W1uzgstarting&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Quanta&lt;/em&gt; about their work, starting about &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/uOJCS1W1uzg?t=660&quot;&gt;11:00&lt;/a&gt;. As Wolchover summarizes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; &amp;#8220;[A]n ineffable quantum phenomenon&amp;#8212;information teleporting between particles&amp;#8212;has a tangible interpretation as a particle receiving a kick of energy and moving at a calculable speed from A to B.&amp;#8221; &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Maybe there is no actual burst of energy, as Mateus Ara&amp;uacute;jo &lt;a href=&quot;https://mateusaraujo.info/2022/12/01/the-death-of-quanta-magazine/&quot;&gt;underscored&lt;/a&gt; while criticizing this segment of the video. But is the physical process in the circuit nevertheless subject to instability and noise? We reiterate a question that we &lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/11/01/quantum-trick-or-treat/&quot;&gt;posed&lt;/a&gt; a year ago after describing how small quantum circuits can embody quantum walks that are &lt;em&gt;chaotic&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; When a quantum circuit simulates an unstable physical process with full quantum advantage, what is the boundary between the simulation and the behavior being simulated?  Is potential bridging of this boundary a stumbling block to maintaining coherent operation while scaling up quantum hardware? &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
In the context of the November 2021 post, we noted that when one simulates chaotic physical systems in, say, FORTRAN or C++ or Python on a classical computer, one would not say the physical classical chips are themselves behaving chaotically. In the quantum case, we note Peter Shor&amp;#8217;s response to Wolchover&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nattyover/status/1598476586164035585&quot;&gt;referencing&lt;/a&gt; a 2017 lecture video on simulating physical systems. Shor retorts that a quantum computer simulating fusion doesn&amp;#8217;t shine like the sun, nor can quantum circuits both using and simulating superconductivity power the nation&amp;#8217;s electric grid. But our instances of chaotic quantum walks, and now possibly wormhole duality, strike us as more closely attached to the relation of physical behavior to computation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The new question we have is even more speculative, but may work as a counterpoint to the current discussion of the new paper. If ER=EPR is correct, then ordinary entanglements are dual to wormholes. That maximal entanglements are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monogamy_of_entanglement&quot;&gt;binary-only&lt;/a&gt; may correspond to the simplest wormholes going only from a point A to a point B. Entanglements are bread-and-butter to quantum circuits, so if this duality has any force, it should extend to the circuits themselves:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; If the team could possibly create a theoretical dual to a wormhole in a quantum circuit, then does the correspondence in the other direction yield &lt;b&gt;duals to quantum circuits&lt;/b&gt; that could house wormholes? Might the notion of such a circuit dual, expressed within general relativity, furnish an organizing principle about how the universe processes information to build structures on cosmic scales? &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
A 2018 &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1808.09072&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; by Tadashi Takayanagi titled &amp;#8220;Holographic Spacetimes as Quantum Circuits of Path-Integrations&amp;#8221; seems to open at least one direction of a cosmos-to-quantum-circuits correspondence.  A very recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.15601&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; by Scott with Jason Pollack, on how Maldacena&amp;#8217;s correspondence treats quantum states, draws on earlier work by Takayanagi, but seems to stop short of such duality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; Open Problems &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
What do you think of the questions raised by the new paper? As we highlighted at the start, it is couched in down-to-earth terms of quantum circuits. Setting aside the rampant controversy on the physics side&amp;#8212;there are more &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/?p=13181&quot;&gt;links&lt;/a&gt; collected by Peter Woit besides those we&amp;#8217;ve used&amp;#8212;what does this say about realizing the quantum circuit model?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[some slight word changes]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By RJLipton+KWRegan&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Lipton</name>
      <uri>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Emanuele Viola: |Northeastern – Simons Institute| &lt; 10, EXP, and PhD in complexity theory</title>
    <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2022/12/07/northeastern-simons-institute-10-exp-and-phd-in-complexity-theory/"/>
    <id>http://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?p=1101</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T13:32:01+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;Northeastern recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://mills.northeastern.edu/merger/&quot;&gt;merged with Mills College, in Oakland, California.  &lt;/a&gt;The massive campus is less than 10 miles from the Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing.  This is the n+1 growth in an amazing streak, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.northeastern.edu/graduate/our-campus-network/&quot;&gt;multiple campuses all over the world, &lt;/a&gt;naming &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bizjournals.com/boston/news/2018/12/17/northeastern-to-rename-computer-science-school.html&quot;&gt;gifts&lt;/a&gt;, and new buildings, including one named after a complexity class: &lt;a href=&quot;https://facilities.northeastern.edu/exp/&quot;&gt;EXP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;This expansion puts Northeastern at the center of the two main hubs for theory in the U.S., the Bay State and the Bay Area.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;If you want to work on theory apply to join our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.ccs.neu.edu/theory/&quot;&gt;theory group.&lt;/a&gt;  I always have room for strong students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Manu&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Emanuele Viola</name>
      <uri>https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Finite model theory for pseudovarieties and universal algebra: preservation, definability and complexity</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02653"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02653</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Ham_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Lucy Ham&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Jackson_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Marcel Jackson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We explore new interactions between finite model theory and a number of
classical streams of universal algebra and semigroup theory. After refocussing
some finite model theoretic tools in universal algebraic context, we present a
number of results. A key result is an example of a finite algebra whose variety
is not finitely axiomatisable in first order logic, but which has first order
definable finite membership problem. This algebra witnesses the simultaneous
failure of the {\L}os-Tarski Theorem, the SP-preservation theorem and
Birkhoff&#39;s HSP-preservation theorem at the finite level as well as providing a
negative solution to the first order formulation of the long-standing Eilenberg
Sch\&quot;utzenberger problem. The example also shows that a pseudovariety without
any finite pseudo-identity basis may be finitely axiomatisable in first order
logic. Other results include the undecidability of deciding first order
definability of the pseudovariety of a finite algebra and a mapping from any
fixed template constraint satisfaction problem to a first order equivalent
variety membership problem, thereby providing examples of variety membership
problems complete in each of the classes $\texttt{L}$, $\texttt{NL}$,
$\texttt{Mod}_p(\texttt{L})$, $\texttt{P}$ (provided they are nonempty), and
infinitely many others (depending on complexity-theoretic assumptions).
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: On the Size of Chromatic Delaunay Mosaics</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03121"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03121</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Biswas_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ranita Biswas&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Montesano_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sebastiano Cultrera di Montesano&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Draganov_O/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ond&amp;#x159;ej Draganov&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Edelsbrunner_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Herbert Edelsbrunner&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Saghafian_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Morteza Saghafian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given a locally finite set $A \subseteq \mathbb{R}^d$ and a coloring $\chi
\colon A \to \{0,1,\ldots,s\}$, we introduce the chromatic Delaunay mosaic of
$\chi$, which is a Delaunay mosaic in $\mathbb{R}^{s+d}$ that represents how
points of different colors mingle. Our main results are bounds on the size of
the chromatic Delaunay mosaic, in which we assume that $d$ and $s$ are
constants. For example, if $A$ is finite with $n = \#{A}$, and the coloring is
random, then the chromatic Delaunay mosaic has $O(n^{\lceil{d/2}\rceil})$ cells
in expectation. In contrast, for Delone sets and Poisson point processes in
$\mathbb{R}^d$, the expected number of cells within a closed ball is only a
constant times the number of points in this ball. Furthermore, in
$\mathbb{R}^2$ all colorings of a dense set of $n$ points have chromatic
Delaunay mosaics of size $O(n)$. This encourages the use of chromatic Delaunay
mosaics in applications.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Persistent Homology of Chromatic Alpha Complexes</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03128"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03128</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Montesano_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sebastiano Cultrera di Montesano&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Draganov_O/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ond&amp;#x159;ej Draganov&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Edelsbrunner_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Herbert Edelsbrunner&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Saghafian_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Morteza Saghafian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Motivated by applications in medical sciences, we study finite chromatic sets
in Euclidean space from a topological perspective. Based on persistent homology
for images, kernels and cokernels, we design provably stable homological
quantifiers that describe the geometric micro- and macro-structure of how the
color classes mingle. These can be efficiently computed using chromatic
variants of Delaunay mosaics and Alpha complexes.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Improved Approximation Schemes for (Un-)Bounded Subset-Sum and Partition</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02883"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02883</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wu_X/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Xiaoyu Wu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chen_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Lin Chen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We consider the SUBSET SUM problem and its important variants in this paper.
In the SUBSET SUM problem, a (multi-)set $X$ of $n$ positive numbers and a
target number $t$ are given, and the task is to find a subset of $X$ with the
maximal sum that does not exceed $t$. It is well known that this problem is
NP-hard and admits fully polynomial-time approximation schemes (FPTASs). In
recent years, it has been shown that there does not exist an FPTAS of running
time $\tilde\OO( 1/\epsilon^{2-\delta})$ for arbitrary small $\delta&amp;gt;0$
assuming ($\min$,+)-convolution conjecture~\cite{bringmann2021fine}. However,
the lower bound can be bypassed if we relax the constraint such that the task
is to find a subset of $X$ that can slightly exceed the threshold $t$ by
$\epsilon$ times, and the sum of numbers within the subset is at least
$1-\tilde\OO(\epsilon)$ times the optimal objective value that respects the
constraint. Approximation schemes that may violate the constraint are also
known as weak approximation schemes. For the SUBSET SUM problem, there is a
randomized weak approximation scheme running in time $\tilde\OO(n+
1/\epsilon^{5/3})$ [Mucha et al.&#39;19]. For the special case where the target $t$
is half of the summation of all input numbers, weak approximation schemes are
equivalent to approximation schemes that do not violate the constraint, and the
best-known algorithm runs in $\tilde\OO(n+1/\epsilon^{{3}/{2}})$ time
[Bringmann and Nakos&#39;21].
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: A Strongly Polynomial Algorithm for Approximate Forster Transforms and its Application to Halfspace Learning</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03008"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03008</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Diakonikolas_I/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ilias Diakonikolas&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Tzamos_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Christos Tzamos&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kane_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Daniel M. Kane&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Forster transform is a method of regularizing a dataset by placing it in
{\em radial isotropic position} while maintaining some of its essential
properties. Forster transforms have played a key role in a diverse range of
settings spanning computer science and functional analysis. Prior work had
given {\em weakly} polynomial time algorithms for computing Forster transforms,
when they exist. Our main result is the first {\em strongly polynomial time}
algorithm to compute an approximate Forster transform of a given dataset or
certify that no such transformation exists. By leveraging our strongly
polynomial Forster algorithm, we obtain the first strongly polynomial time
algorithm for {\em distribution-free} PAC learning of halfspaces. This learning
result is surprising because {\em proper} PAC learning of halfspaces is {\em
equivalent} to linear programming. Our learning approach extends to give a
strongly polynomial halfspace learner in the presence of random classification
noise and, more generally, Massart noise.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


</feed>
