<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title>Theory of Computing Report</title>
  <link rel="self" href=""/>
  <link href=""/>
  <id></id>
  <updated></updated>
  <generator uri="http://feedreader.github.io/">Pluto 1.6.2 on Ruby 3.0.6 (2023-03-30) [x86_64-linux]</generator>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Bell sampling from quantum circuits</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00083"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00083</id>
    <updated>2023-06-02T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Hangleiter_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Dominik Hangleiter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Gullans_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Michael J. Gullans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A central challenge in the verification of quantum computers is benchmarking
their performance as a whole and demonstrating their computational
capabilities. In this work, we find a model of quantum computation, Bell
sampling, that can be used for both of those tasks and thus provides an ideal
stepping stone towards fault-tolerance. In Bell sampling, we measure two copies
of a state prepared by a quantum circuit in the transversal Bell basis. We show
that the Bell samples are classically intractable to produce and at the same
time constitute what we call a circuit shadow: from the Bell samples we can
efficiently extract information about the quantum circuit preparing the state,
as well as diagnose circuit errors. In addition to known properties that can be
efficiently extracted from Bell samples, we give two new and efficient
protocols, a test for the depth of the circuit and an algorithm to estimate a
lower bound to the number of T gates in the circuit. With some additional
measurements, our algorithm learns a full description of states prepared by
circuits with low T -count.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Graph Colouring is Hard for Algorithms Based on Hilbert&#39;s Nullstellensatz and Gr\&quot;{o}bner Bases</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00125"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00125</id>
    <updated>2023-06-02T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lauria_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Massimo Lauria&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nordstrom_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jakob Nordstr&amp;#xf6;m&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We consider the graph $k$-colouring problem encoded as a set of polynomial
equations in the standard way over $0/1$-valued variables. We prove that there
are bounded-degree graphs that do not have legal $k$-colourings but for which
the polynomial calculus proof system defined in [Clegg et al &#39;96, Alekhnovich
et al &#39;02] requires linear degree, and hence exponential size, to establish
this fact. This implies a linear degree lower bound for any algorithms based on
Gr\&quot;{o}bner bases solving graph $k$-colouring using this encoding. The same
bound applies also for the algorithm studied in a sequence of papers [De Loera
et al &#39;08,&#39;09,&#39;11,&#39;15] based on Hilbert&#39;s Nullstellensatz proofs for a slightly
different encoding, thus resolving an open problem mentioned in [De Loera et al
&#39;08,&#39;09,&#39;11] and [Li &#39;16]. We obtain our results by combining the polynomial
calculus degree lower bound for functional pigeonhole principle (FPHP) formulas
over bounded-degree bipartite graphs in [Mik\v{s}a and Nordstr\&quot;{o}m &#39;15] with
a reduction from FPHP to $k$-colouring derivable by polynomial calculus in
constant degree.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Logics with probabilistic team semantics and the Boolean negation</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00420"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00420</id>
    <updated>2023-06-02T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hannula_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Miika Hannula&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hirvonen_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Minna Hirvonen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kontinen_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Juha Kontinen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mahmood_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yasir Mahmood&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Meier_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Arne Meier&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Virtema_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jonni Virtema&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the expressivity and the complexity of various logics in
probabilistic team semantics with the Boolean negation. In particular, we study
the extension of probabilistic independence logic with the Boolean negation,
and a recently introduced logic FOPT. We give a comprehensive picture of the
relative expressivity of these logics together with the most studied logics in
probabilistic team semantics setting, as well as relating their expressivity to
a numerical variant of second-order logic. In addition, we introduce novel
entropy atoms and show that the extension of first-order logic by entropy atoms
subsumes probabilistic independence logic. Finally, we obtain some results on
the complexity of model checking, validity, and satisfiability of our logics.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Robust Estimation of Surface Curvature Information from Point Cloud Data</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00299"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00299</id>
    <updated>2023-06-02T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Spang_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jared Spang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper surveys and evaluates some popular state of the art methods for
algorithmic curvature and normal estimation. In addition to surveying existing
methods we also propose a new method for robust curvature estimation and
evaluate it against existing methods thus demonstrating its superiority to
existing methods in the case of significant data noise. Throughout this paper
we are concerned with computation in low dimensional spaces (N &amp;lt; 10) and
primarily focus on the computation of the Weingarten map and quantities that
may be derived from this; however, the algorithms discussed are theoretically
applicable in any dimension. One thing that is common to all these methods is
their basis in an estimated graph structure. For any of these methods to work
the local geometry of the manifold must be exploited; however, in the case of
point cloud data it is often difficult to discover a robust manifold structure
underlying the data, even in simple cases, which can greatly influence the
results of these algorithms. We hope that in pushing these algorithms to their
limits we are able to discover, and perhaps resolve, many major pitfalls that
may affect potential users and future researchers hoping to improve these
methods
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: A polynomial-time iterative algorithm for random graph matching with non-vanishing correlation</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00266"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00266</id>
    <updated>2023-06-02T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ding_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jian Ding&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Li_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zhangsong Li&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose an efficient algorithm for matching two correlated
Erd\H{o}s--R\&#39;enyi graphs with $n$ vertices whose edges are correlated through
a latent vertex correspondence. When the edge density $q= n^{- \alpha+o(1)}$
for a constant $\alpha \in [0,1)$, we show that our algorithm has polynomial
running time and succeeds to recover the latent matching as long as the edge
correlation is non-vanishing. This is closely related to our previous work on a
polynomial-time algorithm that matches two Gaussian Wigner matrices with
non-vanishing correlation, and provides the first polynomial-time random graph
matching algorithm (regardless of the regime of $q$) when the edge correlation
is below the square root of the Otter&#39;s constant (which is $\approx 0.338$).
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Best $L_p$ Isotonic Regressions, $p \in \{0, 1, \infty\}$</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00269"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00269</id>
    <updated>2023-06-02T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Stout_Q/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Quentin F.Stout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given a real-valued weighted function $f$ on a finite dag, the $L_p$ isotonic
regression of $f$, $p \in [0,\infty]$, is unique except when $p \in [0,1] \cup
\{\infty\}$. We are interested in determining a ``best&#39;&#39; isotonic regression
for $p \in \{0, 1, \infty\}$, where by best we mean a regression satisfying
stronger properties than merely having minimal norm. One approach is to use
strict $L_p$ regression, which is the limit of the best $L_q$ approximation as
$q$ approaches $p$, and another is lex regression, which is based on lexical
ordering of regression errors. For $L_\infty$ the strict and lex regressions
are unique and the same. For $L_1$, strict $q \scriptstyle\searrow 1$ is
unique, but we show that $q \scriptstyle\nearrow 1$ may not be, and even when
it is unique the two limits may not be the same. For $L_0$, in general neither
of the strict and lex regressions are unique, nor do they always have the same
set of optimal regressions, but by expanding the objectives of $L_p$
optimization to $p &amp;lt; 0$ we show $p{ \scriptstyle \nearrow} 0$ is the same as
lex regression. We also give algorithms for computing the best $L_p$ isotonic
regression in certain situations.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Last Switch Dependent Bandits with Monotone Payoff Functions</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00338"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00338</id>
    <updated>2023-06-02T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Foussoul_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ayoub Foussoul&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Goyal_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vineet Goyal&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Papadigenopoulos_O/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Orestis Papadigenopoulos&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zeevi_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Assaf Zeevi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a recent work, Laforgue et al. introduce the model of last switch
dependent (LSD) bandits, in an attempt to capture nonstationary phenomena
induced by the interaction between the player and the environment. Examples
include satiation, where consecutive plays of the same action lead to decreased
performance, or deprivation, where the payoff of an action increases after an
interval of inactivity. In this work, we take a step towards understanding the
approximability of planning LSD bandits, namely, the (NP-hard) problem of
computing an optimal arm-pulling strategy under complete knowledge of the
model. In particular, we design the first efficient constant approximation
algorithm for the problem and show that, under a natural monotonicity
assumption on the payoffs, its approximation guarantee (almost) matches the
state-of-the-art for the special and well-studied class of recharging bandits
(also known as delay-dependent). In this attempt, we develop new tools and
insights for this class of problems, including a novel higher-dimensional
relaxation and the technique of mirroring the evolution of virtual states. We
believe that these novel elements could potentially be used for approaching
richer classes of action-induced nonstationary bandits (e.g., special instances
of restless bandits). In the case where the model parameters are initially
unknown, we develop an online learning adaptation of our algorithm for which we
provide sublinear regret guarantees against its full-information counterpart.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Time and Space Optimal Massively Parallel Algorithm for the 2-Ruling Set Problem</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00432"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00432</id>
    <updated>2023-06-02T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Cambus_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;M&amp;#xe9;lanie Cambus&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kuhn_F/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Fabian Kuhn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Pai_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Shreyas Pai&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Uitto_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jara Uitto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this work, we present a constant-round algorithm for the $2$-ruling set
problem in the Congested Clique model. As a direct consequence, we obtain a
constant round algorithm in the MPC model with linear space-per-machine and
optimal total space. Our results improve on the $O(\log \log \log n)$-round
algorithm by [HPS, DISC&#39;14] and the $O(\log \log \Delta)$-round algorithm by
[GGKMR, PODC&#39;18]. Our techniques can also be applied to the semi-streaming
model to obtain an $O(1)$-pass algorithm. Our main technical contribution is a
novel sampling procedure that returns a small subgraph such that almost all
nodes in the input graph are adjacent to the sampled subgraph. An MIS on the
sampled subgraph provides a $2$-ruling set for a large fraction of the input
graph. As a technical challenge, we must handle the remaining part of the
graph, which might still be relatively large. We overcome this challenge by
showing useful structural properties of the remaining graph and show that
running our process twice yields a $2$-ruling set of the original input graph
with high probability.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR23-082 |  Self-Improvement for Circuit-Analysis Problems | 

	Ryan Williams</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/082"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/082</id>
    <updated>2023-06-01T14:41:12+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    Many results in fine-grained complexity reveal intriguing consequences from solving various SAT problems even slightly faster than exhaustive search. We prove a ``self-improving&amp;#39;&amp;#39; (or ``bootstrapping&amp;#39;&amp;#39;) theorem for Circuit-SAT, $\#$Circuit-SAT, and its fully-quantified version: solving one of these problems faster for ``large&amp;#39;&amp;#39; circuit sizes implies a significant speed-up for ``smaller&amp;#39;&amp;#39; circuit sizes. Our general arguments work for a variety of models solving circuit-analysis problems, including non-uniform circuits and randomized models of computation.

We derive striking consequences for the complexities of these problems. For example, we show that certain fine-grained improvements on the runtime exponents of polynomial-time versions of Circuit-SAT would imply *subexponential-time* algorithms for Circuit-SAT on $2^{o(n)}$-size circuits, refuting the Exponential Time Hypothesis. We also show how slightly faster $\#$Circuit-SAT algorithms on large circuits can be used to prove lower bounds against uniform circuits with symmetric gates for functions in deterministic linear time. Our result suggests an ``algorithmic method&amp;#39;&amp;#39; approach for uniform circuit lower bounds, which trades non-uniformity for a substantial reduction in the complexity of the hard function.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR23-081 |  Constant-Round Arguments from One-Way Functions | 

	Noga Amit, 

	Guy Rothblum</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/081"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/081</id>
    <updated>2023-06-01T05:42:37+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    We study the following question: what cryptographic assumptions are needed for obtaining constant-round computationally-sound argument systems? We focus on argument systems with almost-linear verification time for subclasses of $\mathbf{P}$, such as depth-bounded computations.
Kilian&amp;#39;s celebrated work [STOC 1992] provides such 4-message arguments for $\mathbf{P}$ (actually, for $\mathbf{NP}$) using collision-resistant hash functions. 
We show that $one$-$way\ functions$ suffice for obtaining constant-round arguments of almost-linear verification time for languages in $\mathbf{P}$ that have log-space uniform circuits of linear depth and polynomial size. More generally, the complexity of the verifier scales with the circuit depth.  Furthermore, our argument systems (like Kilian&amp;#39;s) are doubly-efficient; that is, the honest prover strategy can be implemented in polynomial-time. 
Unconditionally sound interactive proofs for this class of computations do not rely on any cryptographic assumptions, but they require a linear number of rounds [Goldwasser, Kalai and Rothblum, STOC 2008]. Constant-round interactive proof systems of linear verification complexity are not known even for $\mathbf{NC}$ (indeed, even for $\mathbf{AC}^1$).
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Self-Replicating Hierarchical Structures Emerge in a Binary Cellular Automaton</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19504"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19504</id>
    <updated>2023-06-01T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/nlin/1/au:+Yang_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Bo Yang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have discovered a novel transition rule for binary cellular automata (CA)
that yields self-replicating structures across two spatial and temporal scales
from sparsely populated random initial conditions. Lower-level, shapeshifting
clusters frequently follow a transient attractor trajectory, generating new
clusters, some of which periodically self-duplicate. When the initial
distribution of live cells is sufficiently sparse, these clusters coalesce into
larger formations that also self-replicate. These formations may further form
the boundaries of an expanding complex on an even larger scale. This rule,
dubbed ``Outlier,&#39;&#39; is rotationally symmetric and applies to 2D Moore
neighborhoods. It was evolved through Genetic Programming during an extensive
automated search for rules that foster open-ended evolution in CA. While
self-replicating structures, both crafted and emergent, have been created in CA
with state sets intentionally designed for this purpose, the Outlier may be the
first known rule to facilitate emergent self-replication across two spatial
scales in simple binary CA.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: On the Shortest Lattice Vector vs. the Shortest Basis</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19777"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19777</id>
    <updated>2023-06-01T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Eisenberg_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yael Eisenberg&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Rot_I/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Itamar Rot&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Safra_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Muli Safra&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given an arbitrary basis for a mathematical lattice, to find a ``good&quot; basis
for it is one of the classic and important algorithmic problems. In this note,
we give a new and simpler proof of a theorem by Regavim (&lt;a href=&quot;/abs/0706.1234&quot;&gt;arXiv:0706.1234&lt;/a&gt;): we
construct a 18-dimensional lattice that does not have a basis that satisfies
the following two properties simultaneously: 1. The basis includes the shortest
non-zero lattice vector. 2. The basis is shortest, that is, minimizes the
longest basis vector (alternatively: the sum or the sum-of-squares of the basis
vectors). The vectors&#39; length can be measured in any $\ell^q$ norm, for $q\in
\mathbb{N}_+$ (albeit, via another lattice, of a somewhat larger dimension).
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: On the algebraic proof complexity of Tensor Isomorphism</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19320"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19320</id>
    <updated>2023-06-01T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Galesi_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nicola Galesi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Grochow_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Joshua A. Grochow&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Pitassi_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Toniann Pitassi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+She_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Adrian She&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Tensor Isomorphism problem (TI) has recently emerged as having
connections to multiple areas of research within complexity and beyond, but the
current best upper bound is essentially the brute force algorithm. Being an
algebraic problem, TI (or rather, proving that two tensors are non-isomorphic)
lends itself very naturally to algebraic and semi-algebraic proof systems, such
as the Polynomial Calculus (PC) and Sum of Squares (SoS). For its combinatorial
cousin Graph Isomorphism, essentially optimal lower bounds are known for
approaches based on PC and SoS (Berkholz &amp;amp; Grohe, SODA &#39;17). Our main results
are an $\Omega(n)$ lower bound on PC degree or SoS degree for Tensor
Isomorphism, and a nontrivial upper bound for testing isomorphism of tensors of
bounded rank.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also show that PC cannot perform basic linear algebra in sub-linear
degree, such as comparing the rank of two matrices, or deriving $BA=I$ from
$AB=I$. As linear algebra is a key tool for understanding tensors, we introduce
a strictly stronger proof system, PC+Inv, which allows as derivation rules all
substitution instances of the implication $AB=I \rightarrow BA=I$. We
conjecture that even PC+Inv cannot solve TI in polynomial time either, but
leave open getting lower bounds on PC+Inv for any system of equations, let
alone those for TI. We also highlight many other open questions about proof
complexity approaches to TI.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Concentrated Geo-Privacy</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19756"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19756</id>
    <updated>2023-06-01T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Liang_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yuting Liang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Yi_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ke Yi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper proposes concentrated geo-privacy (CGP), a privacy notion that can
be considered as the counterpart of concentrated differential privacy (CDP) for
geometric data. Compared with the previous notion of geo-privacy [ABCP13,
CABP13], which is the counterpart of standard differential privacy, CGP offers
many benefits including simplicity of the mechanism, lower noise scale in high
dimensions, and better composability known as advanced composition. The last
one is the most important, as it allows us to design complex mechanisms using
smaller building blocks while achieving better utilities. To complement this
result, we show that the previous notion of geo-privacy inherently does not
admit advanced composition even using its approximate version. Next, we study
three problems on private geometric data: the identity query, k nearest
neighbors, and convex hulls. While the first problem has been previously
studied, we give the first mechanisms for the latter two under geo-privacy. For
all three problems, composability is essential in obtaining good utility
guarantees on the privatized query answer.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Doubly Constrained Fair Clustering</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19475"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19475</id>
    <updated>2023-06-01T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Dickerson_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;John Dickerson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Esmaeili_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Seyed A. Esmaeili&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Morgenstern_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jamie Morgenstern&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zhang_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Claire Jie Zhang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The remarkable attention which fair clustering has received in the last few
years has resulted in a significant number of different notions of fairness.
Despite the fact that these notions are well-justified, they are often
motivated and studied in a disjoint manner where one fairness desideratum is
considered exclusively in isolation from the others. This leaves the
understanding of the relations between different fairness notions as an
important open problem in fair clustering. In this paper, we take the first
step in this direction. Specifically, we consider the two most prominent
demographic representation fairness notions in clustering: (1) Group Fairness
(GF), where the different demographic groups are supposed to have close to
population-level representation in each cluster and (2) Diversity in Center
Selection (DS), where the selected centers are supposed to have close to
population-level representation of each group. We show that given a constant
approximation algorithm for one constraint (GF or DS only) we can obtain a
constant approximation solution that satisfies both constraints simultaneously.
Interestingly, we prove that any given solution that satisfies the GF
constraint can always be post-processed at a bounded degradation to the
clustering cost to additionally satisfy the DS constraint while the reverse is
not true. Furthermore, we show that both GF and DS are incompatible (having an
empty feasibility set in the worst case) with a collection of other
distance-based fairness notions. Finally, we carry experiments to validate our
theoretical findings.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Active causal structure learning with advice</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19588"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19588</id>
    <updated>2023-06-01T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Choo_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Davin Choo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gouleakis_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Themis Gouleakis&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Bhattacharyya_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Arnab Bhattacharyya&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduce the problem of active causal structure learning with advice. In
the typical well-studied setting, the learning algorithm is given the essential
graph for the observational distribution and is asked to recover the underlying
causal directed acyclic graph (DAG) $G^*$ while minimizing the number of
interventions made. In our setting, we are additionally given side information
about $G^*$ as advice, e.g. a DAG $G$ purported to be $G^*$. We ask whether the
learning algorithm can benefit from the advice when it is close to being
correct, while still having worst-case guarantees even when the advice is
arbitrarily bad. Our work is in the same space as the growing body of research
on algorithms with predictions. When the advice is a DAG $G$, we design an
adaptive search algorithm to recover $G^*$ whose intervention cost is at most
$O(\max\{1, \log \psi\})$ times the cost for verifying $G^*$; here, $\psi$ is a
distance measure between $G$ and $G^*$ that is upper bounded by the number of
variables $n$, and is exactly 0 when $G=G^*$. Our approximation factor matches
the state-of-the-art for the advice-less setting.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Improving Expressivity of Graph Neural Networks using Localization</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19659"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19659</id>
    <updated>2023-06-01T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kumar_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Anant Kumar&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Das_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Shrutimoy Das&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Roy_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Shubhajit Roy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Maity_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Binita Maity&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Dasgupta_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Anirban Dasgupta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we propose localized versions of Weisfeiler-Leman (WL)
algorithms in an effort to both increase the expressivity, as well as decrease
the computational overhead. We focus on the specific problem of subgraph
counting and give localized versions of $k-$WL for any $k$. We analyze the
power of Local $k-$WL and prove that it is more expressive than $k-$WL and at
most as expressive as $(k+1)-$WL. We give a characterization of patterns whose
count as a subgraph and induced subgraph are invariant if two graphs are Local
$k-$WL equivalent. We also introduce two variants of $k-$WL: Layer $k-$WL and
recursive $k-$WL. These methods are more time and space efficient than applying
$k-$WL on the whole graph. We also propose a fragmentation technique that
guarantees the exact count of all induced subgraphs of size at most 4 using
just $1-$WL. The same idea can be extended further for larger patterns using
$k&amp;gt;1$. We also compare the expressive power of Local $k-$WL with other GNN
hierarchies and show that given a bound on the time-complexity, our methods are
more expressive than the ones mentioned in Papp and Wattenhofer[2022a].
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Efficient Algorithms for Exact Graph Matching on Correlated Stochastic Block Models with Constant Correlation</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19666"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19666</id>
    <updated>2023-06-01T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Yang_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Joonhyuk Yang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Shin_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Dongpil Shin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chung_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hye Won Chung&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We consider the problem of graph matching, or learning vertex correspondence,
between two correlated stochastic block models (SBMs). The graph matching
problem arises in various fields, including computer vision, natural language
processing and bioinformatics, and in particular, matching graphs with inherent
community structure has significance related to de-anonymization of correlated
social networks. Compared to the correlated Erdos-Renyi (ER) model, where
various efficient algorithms have been developed, among which a few algorithms
have been proven to achieve the exact matching with constant edge correlation,
no low-order polynomial algorithm has been known to achieve exact matching for
the correlated SBMs with constant correlation. In this work, we propose an
efficient algorithm for matching graphs with community structure, based on the
comparison between partition trees rooted from each vertex, by extending the
idea of Mao et al. (2021) to graphs with communities. The partition tree
divides the large neighborhoods of each vertex into disjoint subsets using
their edge statistics to different communities. Our algorithm is the first
low-order polynomial-time algorithm achieving exact matching between two
correlated SBMs with high probability in dense graphs.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Quantum Speedups for Bayesian Network Structure Learning</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19673"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19673</id>
    <updated>2023-06-01T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Harviainen_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Juha Harviainen&lt;/a&gt; (1), &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rychkova_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Kseniya Rychkova&lt;/a&gt; (2), &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Koivisto_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mikko Koivisto&lt;/a&gt; (1) ((1) University of Helsinki, (2) IQM)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Bayesian network structure learning (BNSL) problem asks for a directed
acyclic graph that maximizes a given score function. For networks with $n$
nodes, the fastest known algorithms run in time $O(2^n n^2)$ in the worst case,
with no improvement in the asymptotic bound for two decades. Inspired by recent
advances in quantum computing, we ask whether BNSL admits a polynomial quantum
speedup, that is, whether the problem can be solved by a quantum algorithm in
time $O(c^n)$ for some constant $c$ less than $2$. We answer the question in
the affirmative by giving two algorithms achieving $c \leq 1.817$ and $c \leq
1.982$ assuming the number of potential parent sets is, respectively,
subexponential and $O(1.453^n)$. Both algorithms assume the availability of a
quantum random access memory.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Optimal Decision Trees for Separable Objectives: Pushing the Limits of Dynamic Programming</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19706"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19706</id>
    <updated>2023-06-01T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Linden_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jacobus G. M. van der Linden&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Weerdt_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mathijs M. de Weerdt&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Demirovic_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Emir Demirovi&amp;#x107;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Global optimization of decision trees has shown to be promising in terms of
accuracy, size, and consequently human comprehensibility. However, many of the
methods used rely on general-purpose solvers for which scalability remains an
issue. Dynamic programming methods have been shown to scale much better because
they exploit the tree structure by solving subtrees as independent subproblems.
However, this only works when an objective can be optimized separately for
subtrees. We explore this relationship in detail and show necessary and
sufficient conditions for such separability and generalize previous dynamic
programming approaches into a framework that can optimize any combination of
separable objectives and constraints. Experiments on four application domains
show the general applicability of this framework, while outperforming the
scalability of general-purpose solvers by a large margin.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR23-080 |  Improved Learning from Kolmogorov Complexity | 

	Valentine Kabanets, 

	Halley Goldberg</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/080"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/080</id>
    <updated>2023-06-01T00:07:23+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    Carmosino, Impagliazzo, Kabanets, and Kolokolova (CCC, 2016) showed that the existence of natural properties in the sense of Razborov and Rudich (JCSS, 1997) implies PAC learning algorithms in the sense of Valiant (Comm. ACM, 1984), for boolean functions in $\P/\poly$, under the uniform distribution and with membership queries. It is still an open problem to get from natural properties learning algorithms that do not rely on membership queries but rather use randomly drawn labeled examples.  

        Natural properties may be understood as an average-case version of MCSP, the problem of deciding the minimum size of a circuit computing a given truth-table. Problems related to MCSP include those concerning time-bounded Kolmogorov complexity. MKTP, for example, asks for the KT-complexity of a given string. KT-complexity is a relaxation of circuit size, as it does away with the requirement that a short description of a string be interpreted as a boolean circuit.    
        In this work, under assumptions of MKTP and the related problem $\mktp$ being easy on average, we get  learning algorithms for boolean functions in $\P/\poly$ that       
        \begin{itemize}
            \item  work over any distribution $D$ samplable by a family of polynomial-size circuits (given explicitly in the case of $\MKTP$), 
            \item  only use randomly drawn labeled examples from $D$, and
            \item are agnostic (do not require the target function to belong to the hypothesis class). 
        \end{itemize}
        Our results build upon the recent work of Hirahara and Nanashima (FOCS, 2021) who showed similar learning consequences but under a stronger assumption that $\NP$ is easy on average.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR23-079 |  Mutual Empowerment between  Circuit Obfuscation and Circuit Minimization | 

	Russell Impagliazzo, 

	Valentine Kabanets, 

	Ilya Volkovich</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/079"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/079</id>
    <updated>2023-06-01T00:00:41+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    We study close connections between Indistinguishability Obfuscation ($IO$) and the Minimum Circuit Size Problem ($MCSP$), and argue that algorithms for one of $MCSP$ or $IO$ would empower the other one. Some of our main results are:

\begin{itemize}
    \item If there exists a perfect (imperfect) $IO$ that is computationally secure against nonuniform polynomial-size circuits, then for all $k \in \mathbb{N}$: $NP \cap ZPP^{MCSP} \not \subseteq SIZE[n^k]$ ($MA \cap ZPP^{MCSP} \not \subseteq SIZE[n^k]$). 
    
    \item  In addition, if there exists a perfect $IO$ that is computationally secure against nonuniform polynomial-size circuits, then $NEXP \cap ZPEXP^{MCSP} \not \subseteq P/poly.$
    
    \item If $MCSP \in BPP$, then statistical security and computational security for $IO$ are equivalent.
    
    \item If computationally-secure perfect $IO$ exists, then $MCSP \in BPP$ iff $NP = ZPP$.

    \item If computationally-secure perfect $IO$ exists, then $ZPEXP \neq BPP$.
    
\end{itemize}

To the best of our knowledge, this is the first consequence of strong circuit lower bounds from the existence of an $IO$. The results are obtained via a construction of an optimal \emph{universal distinguisher}, computable in randomized polynomial time with access to the $MCSP$ oracle, that will distinguish any two circuit-samplable distributions with the advantage that is the statistical distance between these two distributions minus some negligible error term. This is our main technical contribution. As another immediate application, we get a simple proof of the result by Allender and Das (Inf. Comput., 2017) that $SZK \subseteq BPP^{MCSP}$.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">David Eppstein: Linkage</title>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2023/05/31/linkage.html"/>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2023/05/31/linkage</id>
    <updated>2023-05-31T18:49:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@kisonecat/110372922533677135&quot;&gt;The state space of a \(2\times 2\times 2\) Rubik’s cube under half-turns&lt;/a&gt; turns out to be yet another way of describing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nauru_graph&quot;&gt;Nauru graph&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arstechnica.com/science/2023/05/french-painters-inspire-new-insights-into-the-physics-of-soap-bubbles/&quot;&gt;French painters inspire new insights into the physics of soap bubbles&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/110393699679704026&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/span&gt; Jennifer Ouelette in &lt;em&gt;Ars Technica&lt;/em&gt; on how blowing bubbles through a long narrow air tube affects their size, based on a preprint “&lt;a href=&quot;https://storage.pardot.com/640833/1683834035YRiFuKjN/FA10159_min.pdf&quot;&gt;Unstable growth of bubbles from a constriction&lt;/a&gt;” by Marc Grosjean and Elise Lorenceau.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Good news for teaching faculty in my department &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/110397234546657594&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/span&gt; my friend and colleague &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~mikes/&quot;&gt;Michael Shindler&lt;/a&gt; just got tenure, as an associate professor of teaching. Michael is local: he was an undergraduate here before getting a Ph.D. in theoretical computer science with Adam Meyerson at UCLA, and then taught at the University of Southern California before returning to us as an assistant professor of teaching. Whenever I see an exceptionally bright undergraduate asking to take my graduate data structures class, it’s almost always because they were encouraged along the way by Michael.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The “professor of teaching” series is relatively new for us, added about five years ago alongside our “Unit 18” lecturers (named for their union) and replacing our previous “lecturer with security of employment” series. Compared to other regular-rank faculty they have a higher teaching load and lower but nonzero research expectations, typically focusing on computer science education. They can also advise doctoral students (and Michael is doing so). Although we have hired some into the more senior ranks, Michael is the first to go through the tenure process. He says that when he recently went to SIGCSE, the question everyone wanted to ask him was: is it true that computer science education specialists can be senate faculty in your department? It is true, and they can get tenure for doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/dodecahedrons-roman-empire&quot;&gt;The mysterious dodecahedrons of the Roman empire&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/110405305127131102&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=35937540&quot;&gt;via&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_dodecahedron&quot;&gt;see also&lt;/a&gt;). One plausible theory: they are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spool_knitting&quot;&gt;spool knitting&lt;/a&gt; devices for making gloves.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thisiscolossal.com/2023/04/charles-brooks-architecture-music/&quot;&gt;Architecturally-styled photographs of the interior of musical instruments&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@colossal@mastodon.art/110356933574807837&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2023/05/21/science/math-puzzles-integer-sequences.html&quot;&gt;The &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt; has a profile by Siobhan Roberts on the Online Encyclopedia of Integer Sequences, celebrating its 50th anniversary&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/110411066621174831&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20230522005810/https://www.nytimes.com/2023/05/21/science/math-puzzles-integer-sequences.html&quot;&gt;archived&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 3d, every polyhedron has a combinatorially equivalent form with rational (or integer) coordinates, but in higher dimensions that isn’t true &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/110420402994075366&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; Daniel Bernstein in The Matroid Union examines &lt;a href=&quot;http://matroidunion.org/?p=4868&quot;&gt;connections between irrational polytope constructions and matroid theory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/076/&quot;&gt;A pseudodeterministic algorithm for finding primes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@fortnow@fediscience.org/110429540761716309&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2023/05/finding-primes-pseudodeterministically.html&quot;&gt;via&lt;/a&gt;), by Lijie Chen, Zhenjian Lu, Igor Carboni Oliveira, Hanlin Ren and Rahul Santhanam. More precisely, this is a randomized algorithm for finding an \(n\)-bit prime number that runs in time polynomial in \(n\) and, with high probability, for infinitely many \(n\), outputs the same prime whenever you run it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2023/6/273222-the-silent-revolution-of-sat/fulltext&quot;&gt;The silent (r)evolution of SAT&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@Jose_A_Alonso/110430153381835143&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; new survey in &lt;em&gt;CACM&lt;/em&gt; on SAT-solvers and their applications, by Johannes K. Fichte, Daniel Le Berre, Markus Hecher, and Stefan Szeider.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://torrentfreak.com/music-company-asks-google-to-delist-youtube-downloader-wikipedia-article-230528/&quot;&gt;Music industry requests Google to censor Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/110448051373386779&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=36106741&quot;&gt;via&lt;/a&gt;). The Wikipedia article in question: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comparison_of_YouTube_downloaders&quot;&gt;Comparison of YouTube downloaders&lt;/a&gt;. It’s not a great example of a high-quality Wikipedia article but the precedent of asking for censorship of any mention or discussion of content piracy (beyond going after the pirates themselves) is extremely troubling.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dailynous.com/2023/05/25/am-i-the-unethical-one-a-philosophy-professor-his-cheating-students/&quot;&gt;Ethics professor asks “Am I the unethical one?”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/110450109807128058&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insidehighered.com/news/quick-takes/2023/05/26/philosophy-professor-uses-fake-online-answers-catch-cheating&quot;&gt;via&lt;/a&gt;) after setting an online trap for cheating students and catching nearly half his class.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.17743&quot;&gt;A chiral aperiodic monotile&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@csk/110454792622698781&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@csk/110454664118770148&quot;&gt;see also&lt;/a&gt;), like the hat (actually, exactly like an equilateral hat) but with no flipping required. It’s called the spectre. New preprint by Smith, Myers, Kaplan, and Goodman-Strauss.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gantry.io/blog/papers-to-know-20230110/&quot;&gt;Supposedly practical application and deployment of cuckoo hashing in the TikTok recommendation system&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/110459570741633679&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Diff/1157764695&quot;&gt;via&lt;/a&gt;). For more, see “&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.07663&quot;&gt;Monolith: Real time recommendation system with
collisionless embedding table&lt;/a&gt;”, Liu et al. The cuckoo hashing is what makes this “collisionless”, and is used to map sparse feature data to something more dense.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interesting “near-miss” of two integer sequences &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@jsiehler/110429683229584306&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://oeis.org/A000240&quot;&gt;OEIS A000240&lt;/a&gt;, counting permutations with one fixed point, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://oeis.org/A182390&quot;&gt;OEIS A182390&lt;/a&gt;, generated by a recurrence involving XOR. The rencontres numbers (the first sequence) also have a similar recurrence, but with \(\pm\) in place of \(\oplus\), and some binary-representation coincidence causes them to be equal for surprisingly many terms.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By David Eppstein&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
      <uri>https://11011110.github.io/blog/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Gil Kalai: Questions and Concerns About Google’s Quantum Supremacy Claim</title>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/31/questions-and-concerns-about-googles-quantum-supremacy-claim/"/>
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=24142</id>
    <updated>2023-05-31T17:36:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;Yosi Rinott, Tomer Shoham, and I wrote our third paper regarding our statistical study of the Google 2019 supremacy experiment.&amp;nbsp; Our paper presents statistical analysis that may shed light on the quality and reliability of the data and the statistical methods of the Google experiment. Comments, corrections and discussion are most welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title of the Google 2019 paper was &amp;#8220;Quantum supremacy using a programmable superconducting processor&amp;#8221;. As the readers may remember, the supremacy claim has largely been refuted by several research groups; see &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2021/03/10/amazing-feng-pan-and-pan-zhang-announced-a-way-to-spoof-classically-simulate-the-googles-quantum-supremacy-circuit/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/08/06/ordinary-computers-can-beat-googles-quantum-computer-after-all/&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/10/25/remarkable-limitations-of-linear-cross-entropy-as-a-measure-for-quantum-advantage-by-xun-gao-marcin-kalinowski-chi-ning-chou-mikhail-d-lukin-boaz-barak-and-soonwon-choi/&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;. The calibration process of the Google experiment weakens the claim of a “programmable processor”, and some of our findings from the second paper as well as a few of the findings from the new paper further weaken this claim (see below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.01064&quot;&gt;Questions and Concerns About Google’s Quantum Supremacy Claim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;In October 2019,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;Nature&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;published a paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-019-1666-5&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt; describing an ex&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;perimental work that was performed at Google.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;The paper claims &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;to demonstrate quantum (computational) supremacy on a 53-qubit &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;quantum computer. Since then we have been involved in a long-term &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;project to study various statistical aspects of the Google experiment.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/sts836.pdf&quot;&gt;[32]&lt;/a&gt; we studied Google’s statistical framework that we found to be &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;very sound and offered some technical improvements. This document &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;describes three main concerns (based on statistical analysis) about &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;the Google 2019 experiment.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;The first concern is that the data do &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;not agree with Google’s noise model (or any other specific model). &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;The second concern is that a crucial formula for a priori estimation of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;the fidelity is surprisingly simple and seems to involve an unexpected &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;independence assumption, and yet it gives very accurate predictions. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;The third concern is about surprising statistical properties of the cal&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;ibration process&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Some findings of this paper&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. There is a large gap between the samples of the Google experiment and the Google noise mode, and any other specific noise model. The gap between the empirical distribution and the model is asymmetric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. There are large fluctuations of the empirical behavior which are not understood. Consequently, there is evidence that the distance between the Google noise model and uniform distribution is smaller (when the number of qubits is n &amp;gt; 16) than the distance between the experimental samples and the Google noise model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. The empirical behavior of the samples is not stationary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4. While the empirical distribution is not stationary the XEB fidelity is stable along the samples. Moreover, “high energy events” that lead to abrupt increase in errors that are reported for later experiments with the Sycamore quantum computer cannot be detected in the 2019 quantum supremacy experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5. The predictive power of Formula (77) for the XEB fidelity estimates is statistically surprising: the subsumed independence between components of systems such as quantum computers, which are known to be sensitive to noise and errors caused by interactions with their environment, is striking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6. The systematic bias of the predictions of Formula (77) for patch circuits seems statistically surprising, and the Google explanation is not convincing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7. The behavior of the fidelities of the two patches for patch circuits is very different; This appears to be in tension with Formula (77). ( We were not yet provided with the data needed to check this matter.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8. The success of the experiments fully depends on the very large effect of the calibration adjustments. There are large differences between the effects of the calibration adjustments for different 2-gates, and even for different appearances of the same 2-gate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9. The calibration adjustments are surprisingly effective, especially given the stated local nature of the calibration. Mathematically speaking, we witness a local optimization process reaching a critical point of a function depending on hundreds of parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #0000ff&quot;&gt;A few problems of general interest&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scrutinizing a scientific work necessarily involves punctiliousness and nitpicking, but there are several issues that we find of general interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #0000ff&quot;&gt;(a) What is the statistical methodology for analyzing samples obtained from noisy quantum computers and for finding appropriate models to describe the empirical data?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #0000ff&quot;&gt;(b) We suggest that the statistical independence assumption in a certain predictive model is very surprising. What could be the scientific framework and methodology to study this matter?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #0000ff&quot;&gt;(c) We find it surprising that a local optimization process (namely, a process that separately optimizes each variable) of a function of many variables, reaches a critical point. What could be further tools to study this matter?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #0000ff&quot;&gt;(d) What are the tools to study if an empirical behavior is non-stationary and perhaps even inherently unpredictable?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #0000ff&quot;&gt;(e) What is the appropriate methodology and ethics for scrutinizing major scientific works, and how is it possible to bridge the gap between theoreticians (like us) and experimentalists?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What&amp;#8217;s next&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are in the process of&amp;nbsp; writing a paper on readout errors, gate errors, and Fourier expansion. On the theoretical side, we will study the effect of gate errors on the Fourier expansion, which is of interest in and of itself and could serve as some sanity test for various aspects of the Google 2019 experiment. (The effect of readout errors is well understood &amp;#8211; it is essentially the noise operator that I have been studying extensively since the mid-1980s.) On the technical side, this will be our first work where we use simulators for noisy quantum circuits, and we currently use both the Google and the IBM simulators. Then, we may apply some of our statistical tools at other NISQ experiments, and will even try to reproduce, using an IBM quantum computer, a certain random circuit experiment with 6 qubits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pictorial Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Concern I&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a large gap between the samples of the Google quantum supremacy experiments and the Google noise model. In fact, the samples are far away from any noise model we are aware of. There is evidence that the distance between the Google noise model and uniform distribution is smaller (when&lt;br /&gt;
the number of qubits is n &amp;gt; 16) than the distance between the experimental samples and the Google noise model. We studied other properties of the empirical distribution like its behavior in different scales, its non-stationary nature, and its Fourier behavior, and there is more to be done mainly for data coming from other NISQ experiments and data from simulators of noisy circuits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig2-kts2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;24445&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/31/questions-and-concerns-about-googles-quantum-supremacy-claim/fig2-kts2/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig2-kts2.jpg&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1367,599&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;Fig2-KTS2&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig2-kts2.jpg?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig2-kts2.jpg?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-24445&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig2-kts2.jpg?w=640&quot; alt=&quot;Fig2-KTS2&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig2-kts2.jpg?w=640 640w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig2-kts2.jpg?w=1278 1278w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig2-kts2.jpg?w=150 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig2-kts2.jpg?w=300 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig2-kts2.jpg?w=768 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig2-kts2.jpg?w=1024 1024w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px&quot;  &gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000&quot;&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;The left-hand side scatterplots display theoretical vs.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;empirical &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;frequencies of the Google sample (file 0) with&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;= 12. The right-hand side &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;scatterplots display theoretical vs.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;our simulated empirical frequencies ac&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;cording to Google’s noise model (1) with&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;φ&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;= 0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;3701.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Concern II&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remarkable predictive power of Formula (77) is statistically surprising: the subsumed independence between components of the quantum computer, is striking. The close agreement of the experimental XEB fidelities between the patch circuits and full circuits shows an unexplained systematic deviation from the predictions of Formula (77). On the other hand, confirmations [13, 23] and replications [33, 35] lend support to the claims in the Google paper. There are various matters that remain to be explored. For example, (i) using simulations of noisy circuits, the magnitude of the difference between the two sides of Formula (77) (Gao et al. [11]) could be estimated, and (ii) the individual values in Formula (77) could be used to study the different XEB fidelities of the two patches in patch circuits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig9-krs.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;24447&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/31/questions-and-concerns-about-googles-quantum-supremacy-claim/fig9-krs/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig9-krs.jpg&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1696,835&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;FIG9-KRS&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig9-krs.jpg?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig9-krs.jpg?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-24447&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig9-krs.jpg?w=640&quot; alt=&quot;FIG9-KRS&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig9-krs.jpg?w=640 640w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig9-krs.jpg?w=1280 1280w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig9-krs.jpg?w=150 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig9-krs.jpg?w=300 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig9-krs.jpg?w=768 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig9-krs.jpg?w=1024 1024w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px&quot;  &gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000&quot;&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The striking prediction power of Formula (77):&lt;/strong&gt; Comparison between average XEB fidelity for full, elided, and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;patch circuits with (77).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Concern III&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The calibration process accounts for systematic errors for 2-gates and applies certain adjustments to the definition of the circuits. These adjustments are local, namely the adjustments for a 2-gate involving qubits x and y primarily depend on outcomes for 1- and 2-circuits on these qubits. Some statistical findings regarding the calibration process are: (i) The effects of the calibration is large even for a single 2-gate; (ii) there is a large difference between the effect for different 2-gates and even different appearances of the same 2-gate, and; (iii) the effectiveness of the 2-gate calibrations is remarkable. We note that these findings enhance the tension between the calibration process and Google’s claim for a “programmable quantum computer.” The effectiveness of the calibration process is especially surprising in view of the local nature of the calibration: mathematically speaking, we witness a local optimization process reaching a critical point of a function depending on hundreds of parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/caliba.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;24164&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/31/questions-and-concerns-about-googles-quantum-supremacy-claim/caliba/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/caliba.png&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1842,712&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;calibA&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/caliba.png?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/caliba.png?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-24164&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/caliba.png?w=640&quot; alt=&quot;calibA&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/caliba.png?w=640 640w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/caliba.png?w=1278 1278w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/caliba.png?w=150 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/caliba.png?w=300 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/caliba.png?w=768 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/caliba.png?w=1024 1024w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px&quot;  &gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The remarkable effectiveness of the calibration.&lt;/strong&gt; The effect of removing the calibration for the kth 2-gate of a circuit for the first Google file (file 0) with n = 12. Note that the same 2-gate occurs periodically along the circuit, indicated by the vertical black dashed lines. Here we remove all ingredients of the calibration: both the 1-gate rotations and 2-gate adjustments.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/calibb.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/calibb.png?w=640&quot; alt=&quot;calibB&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The remarkable effectiveness of the calibration II.&lt;/strong&gt; The effect of removing the 2-gate adjustments involving the kth 2-gate of a circuit. (The same 2-gate occurs periodically along the circuit.) The 2-gate involving the qubits (3,3) and (3,4) has consistently large effect.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #0000ff&quot;&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;To make matters clear, the calibration is not about tightening the screws &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;in Sycamore; rather, it is about change in the program. We can think about &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;the calibration process as a change in the model that would greatly reduce &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;certain systematic forms of noise. For example, if we discovered that a certain &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;1-gate that is supposed to apply a 90-degree rotation systematically performs &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;an 80-degree rotation, rather than changing the engineering of the 1-gate, we &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;would change the definition of the circuit.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;(no) Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #000000&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;We laid the dry facts and findings, and we let the readers make their own interpretation, or rather take note of our concerns and wait for more experimental data from future experiments.&amp;#8221;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Was the Google experiment a &amp;#8220;Programmable quantum computer?&amp;#8221;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title of the Google 2019 paper was &amp;#8220;Quantum supremacy using a programmable superconducting processor&amp;#8221;. As we mentioned, the supremacy claim has largely (but not fully) been refuted. There are also doubts regarding the claim that the Sycamore 2019 experiment represents a &amp;#8220;programmable processor&amp;#8221; as the calibration process and other matters weaken this. (This was pointed out in a comment from October 2019 by &lt;a href=&quot;https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=4372#comment-1822373&quot;&gt;Craig Gidney&lt;/a&gt; from the Google team and also a few months later by a commentator &lt;a href=&quot;https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=5159#comment-1869118&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;Till&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt; . Till&amp;#8217;s comment led to interesting discussion regarding the nature of the calibration, which was earlier believed by many to represent physical changes in the device.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some findings of our papers further weaken the Google claim for &amp;#8220;programmable device&amp;#8221;. The Google paper describes about 1000 experiments on various circuits but, as it turns out, all these experiments depend on the random choices made for the largest ten circuits, and this fact is also in contrast with the &amp;#8220;programmable&amp;#8221; claim.&amp;nbsp; (It was quite possible to choose a different random circuit in every case.) A related concern is that improvements of the calibration process were interlaced with the experiment, and that the last minute calibration procedure for the EFGH circuits represented a substantial improvement.&amp;nbsp; We note that while the general principles of the calibration process are publicly available, the precise details are a commercial secret. Of course, concerns regarding the Google calibration process may reflect on other Sycamore experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Our earlier papers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wrote two earlier papers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Y. Rinott, T. Shoham, and G. Kalai, &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/sts836.pdf&quot;&gt;Statistical Aspects of the Quantum Supremacy Demonstration,&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;Statistical Science&amp;nbsp; (2022)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: initial&quot;&gt;G. Kalai, Y. Rinott and T. Shoham, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/10/cc22a19.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;Google’s 2019 “Quantum Supremacy” Claims:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;Data, Documentation, &amp;amp; Discussion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp; (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/10/07/the-google-supremacy-experiment-data-information-discussions-and-three-questions/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question of appropriate methodology,&amp;nbsp; ethics, and culture for scrutinizing major scientific works is related to the replication crisis that we mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/30/physics-related-news-israel-joining-cern-pugwash-and-global-zero-the-replication-crisis-and-max-the-damon/&quot;&gt;an earlier post&lt;/a&gt;. There we described our policy regarding data requests. Our experience was overall rather positive. (Things went rather slowly but we were slow as well.) We still did not get the individual terms of Formula (77) (namely, the error rate for individual 1-gates and 2-gates) but the Google team promised to try to push toward getting this information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;(From our paper:) &amp;#8220;A few months after the publication of the Google paper we initiated what has &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;become a long-term project to study various statistical aspects of the Google &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;experiment and to scrutinize the Google paper.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;This is a good place to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;mention that Google’s quantum supremacy claim appeared to refute Kalai’s &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;theory regarding quantum computation ([15, 16, 18]) and Kalai’s specific pre&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;diction that NISQ systems cannot demonstrate `quantum supremacy.&amp;#8217; This &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: initial&quot;&gt;fact influenced and may have biased Kalai’s assessment of Google’s quan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;tum supremacy claim.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;(Recent improved classical algorithms have largely &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;refuted Google’s quantum supremacy claim and therefore the Google results &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;no longer refute Kalai’s theory.)&amp;#8221;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my argument see &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/12/29/the-argument-against-quantum-computers-a-very-short-introduction/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/11/05/inaugural-address-at-the-hungarian-academy-of-science-the-quantum-computer-a-miracle-or-mirage/&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A few more figures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig5-kts2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;24453&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/31/questions-and-concerns-about-googles-quantum-supremacy-claim/fig5-kts2/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig5-kts2.jpg&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1722,642&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;Fig5-KTS2&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig5-kts2.jpg?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig5-kts2.jpg?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-24453&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig5-kts2.jpg?w=640&quot; alt=&quot;Fig5-KTS2&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig5-kts2.jpg?w=640 640w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig5-kts2.jpg?w=1280 1280w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig5-kts2.jpg?w=150 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig5-kts2.jpg?w=300 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig5-kts2.jpg?w=768 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig5-kts2.jpg?w=1024 1024w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px&quot;  &gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zooming in on the empirical frequency of bitstrings with amplitudes between the median and the 0.55 quantile. The left plot is the empirical occurrences of the bitstrings in Google file 0, n=12. The right plot is based on a simulation with φ = 0.3862. The red line describes the expected number of bitstrings of the Google noise model, and the blue dashed line is 3 standard deviations from the expectation. (We plan to test if these fluctuations are present in samples from IBM quantum computers.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig6-krs.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;24454&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/31/questions-and-concerns-about-googles-quantum-supremacy-claim/fig6-krs/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig6-krs.jpg&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1639,628&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;FIG6-KRS&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig6-krs.jpg?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig6-krs.jpg?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-24454&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig6-krs.jpg?w=640&quot; alt=&quot;FIG6-KRS&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig6-krs.jpg?w=640 640w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig6-krs.jpg?w=1280 1280w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig6-krs.jpg?w=150 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig6-krs.jpg?w=300 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig6-krs.jpg?w=768 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig6-krs.jpg?w=1024 1024w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px&quot;  &gt;&lt;/a&gt; Comparing the two halves of the Google samples: the black vertical lines are the ℓ1 distance of the occurrences of bitstrings when we partition the samples into two halves according to the sampling order. The histograms give the ℓ1 distances between the occurrences of bitstrings for random partitions of the bitstrings into two halves.&amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig7-krs.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;24455&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/31/questions-and-concerns-about-googles-quantum-supremacy-claim/fig7-krs/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig7-krs.jpg&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1691,638&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;FIG7-KRS&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig7-krs.jpg?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig7-krs.jpg?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-24455&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig7-krs.jpg?w=640&quot; alt=&quot;FIG7-KRS&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig7-krs.jpg?w=640 640w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig7-krs.jpg?w=1278 1278w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig7-krs.jpg?w=150 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig7-krs.jpg?w=300 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig7-krs.jpg?w=768 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig7-krs.jpg?w=1024 1024w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px&quot;  &gt;&lt;/a&gt; Drifts in the fractions of ones. We divided the 500,000 bitstrings into 250 groups of 2,000 bitstrings each, according to the sampling order. For each group calculated the fraction of bitstring having a “1” bit in some place in the bitstring. The Figure shows the fractions of ones in locations 11 and 12 for one circuit (file 0) with n = 12. (The red lines are linear regression fits to the data points.) The trend is consistent along the different circuits and is different for different locations in the bitstrings. &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig8-krs.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;24457&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/31/questions-and-concerns-about-googles-quantum-supremacy-claim/fig8-krs/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig8-krs.jpg&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1703,819&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;FIG8-KRS&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig8-krs.jpg?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig8-krs.jpg?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-24457&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig8-krs.jpg?w=640&quot; alt=&quot;FIG8-KRS&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig8-krs.jpg?w=640 640w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig8-krs.jpg?w=1280 1280w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig8-krs.jpg?w=150 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig8-krs.jpg?w=300 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig8-krs.jpg?w=768 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/fig8-krs.jpg?w=1024 1024w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px&quot;  &gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A histogram of differences between the empirical distribution and the values given by the Google noise model, n = 12, Google file 0, φ = 0.3701. What can explain the apparent asymmetry in the gaps between the empirical distribution and the model? Is an explanation at all necessary?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/table3-krs.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;24458&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/31/questions-and-concerns-about-googles-quantum-supremacy-claim/table3-krs/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/table3-krs.jpg&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1395,897&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;Table3-KRS&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/table3-krs.jpg?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/table3-krs.jpg?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-24458&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/table3-krs.jpg?w=640&quot; alt=&quot;Table3-KRS&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/table3-krs.jpg?w=640 640w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/table3-krs.jpg?w=1280 1280w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/table3-krs.jpg?w=150 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/table3-krs.jpg?w=300 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/table3-krs.jpg?w=768 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/table3-krs.jpg?w=1024 1024w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px&quot;  &gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Gil Kalai&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
      <uri>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">CCI: jobs: Postdoc at Warwick (apply by June 25, 2023) at University of Warwick (apply by June 25, 2023)</title>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/05/31/postdoc-at-warwick-apply-by-june-25-2023-at-university-of-warwick-apply-by-june-25-2023/"/>
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/05/31/postdoc-at-warwick-apply-by-june-25-2023-at-university-of-warwick-apply-by-june-25-2023/</id>
    <updated>2023-05-31T11:12:58+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;A postdoc position in algebraic/geometric complexity theory at the University of Warwick, under the supervision of Christian Ikenmeyer, is available. Listed as &amp;#8220;Research Fellow (107507-0523)&amp;#8221; on Warwick&amp;#8217;s website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://atsv7.wcn.co.uk/search_engine/jobs.cgi?SID=amNvZGU9MTg5MTIyMCZ2dF90ZW1wbGF0ZT0xNDU3Jm93bmVyPTUwNjI0NTImb3duZXJ0eXBlPWZhaXImYnJhbmRfaWQ9MCZ2YWNfeHRyYTUwNjI0NTIuNTJfNTA2MjQ1Mj0yMzk5MjEmcG9zdGluZ19jb2RlPTYzNQ==&quot;&gt;https://atsv7.wcn.co.uk/search_engine/jobs.cgi?SID=amNvZGU9MTg5MTIyMCZ2dF90ZW1wbGF0ZT0xNDU3Jm93bmVyPTUwNjI0NTImb3duZXJ0eXBlPWZhaXImYnJhbmRfaWQ9MCZ2YWNfeHRyYTUwNjI0NTIuNTJfNTA2MjQ1Mj0yMzk5MjEmcG9zdGluZ19jb2RlPTYzNQ==&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: christian.ikenmeyer@warwick.ac.uk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>CCI: jobs</name>
      <uri>https://cstheory-jobs.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Polynomial-time classical sampling of high-temperature quantum Gibbs states</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.18514"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.18514</id>
    <updated>2023-05-31T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Yin_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Chao Yin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Lucas_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Andrew Lucas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The computational complexity of simulating quantum many-body systems
generally scales exponentially with the number of particles. This enormous
computational cost prohibits first principles simulations of many important
problems throughout science, ranging from simulating quantum chemistry to
discovering the thermodynamic phase diagram of quantum materials or
high-density neutron stars. We present a classical algorithm that samples from
a high-temperature quantum Gibbs state in a computational (product state)
basis. The runtime grows polynomially with the number of particles, while error
vanishes polynomially. This algorithm provides an alternative strategy to
existing quantum Monte Carlo methods for overcoming the sign problem. Our
result implies that measurement-based quantum computation on a Gibbs state can
provide exponential speed up only at sufficiently low temperature, and further
constrains what tasks can be exponentially faster on quantum computers.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: RT-kNNS Unbound: Using RT Cores to Accelerate Unrestricted Neighbor Search</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.18356"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.18356</id>
    <updated>2023-05-31T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nagarajan_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vani Nagarajan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mandarapu_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Durga Mandarapu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kulkarni_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Milind Kulkarni&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The problem of identifying the k-Nearest Neighbors (kNNS) of a point has
proven to be very useful both as a standalone application and as a subroutine
in larger applications. Given its far-reaching applicability in areas such as
machine learning and point clouds, extensive research has gone into leveraging
GPU acceleration to solve this problem. Recent work has shown that using Ray
Tracing cores in recent GPUs to accelerate kNNS is much more efficient compared
to traditional acceleration using shader cores. However, the existing
translation of kNNS to a ray tracing problem imposes a constraint on the search
space for neighbors. Due to this, we can only use RT cores to accelerate
fixed-radius kNNS, which requires the user to set a search radius a priori and
hence can miss neighbors. In this work, we propose TrueKNN, the first unbounded
RT-accelerated neighbor search. TrueKNN adopts an iterative approach where we
incrementally grow the search space until all points have found their k
neighbors. We show that our approach is orders of magnitude faster than
existing approaches and can even be used to accelerate fixed-radius neighbor
searches.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Quantum chi-squared tomography and mutual information testing</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.18519"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.18519</id>
    <updated>2023-05-31T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Flammia_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Steven T. Flammia&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+ODonnell_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ryan O&amp;#x27;Donnell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For quantum state tomography on rank-$r$ dimension-$d$ states, we show that
$\widetilde{O}(r^{.5}d^{1.5}/\epsilon) \leq \widetilde{O}(d^2/\epsilon)$ copies
suffice for accuracy $\epsilon$ with respect to (Bures) $\chi^2$-divergence,
and $\widetilde{O}(rd/\epsilon)$ copies suffice for accuracy $\epsilon$ with
respect to quantum relative entropy. The best previous bound was
$\widetilde{O}(rd/\epsilon) \leq \widetilde{O}(d^2/\epsilon)$ with respect to
infidelity; our results are an improvement since \[ \text{infidelity} \leq
\text{relative entropy} \leq \text{$\chi^2$-divergence}.\] For algorithms that
are required to use single-copy measurements, we show that
$\widetilde{O}(r^{1.5} d^{1.5}/\epsilon) \leq \widetilde{O}(d^3/\epsilon)$
copies suffice for $\chi^2$-divergence, and $\widetilde{O}(r^{2} d/\epsilon)$
suffice for relative entropy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using this tomography algorithm, we show that
$\widetilde{O}(d^{2.5}/\epsilon)$ copies of a $d\times d$-dimensional bipartite
state suffice to test if it has quantum mutual information 0 or at least
$\epsilon$. As a corollary, we also improve the best known sample complexity
for the classical version of mutual information testing to
$\widetilde{O}(d/\epsilon)$.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR23-078 |  Toward Better Depth Lower Bounds: A KRW-like theorem for Strong Composition | 

	Or Meir</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/078"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/078</id>
    <updated>2023-05-30T15:41:38+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    One of the major open problems in complexity theory is proving super-logarithmic lower bounds on the depth of circuits (i.e., $\mathbf{P}\not\subseteq \mathbf{NC}^{1}$). Karchmer, Raz, and Wigderson (Computational Complexity 5(3/4), 1995) suggested to approach this problem by proving that depth complexity of a composition of functions $f \diamond g$ is roughly the sum of the depth complexities of $f$ and $g$. They showed that the validity of this conjecture would imply that $\mathbf{P}\not\subseteq\mathbf{NC}^{1}$.

The intuition that underlies the KRW conjecture is that the composition $f \diamond g$ should behave like a &amp;quot;direct-sum problem&amp;quot;, in a certain sense, and therefore the depth complexity of $f \diamond g$ should be the sum of the individual depth complexities. Nevertheless, there are two obstacles toward turning this intuition into a proof: first, we do not know how to prove that $f \diamond g$ must behave like a direct-sum problem; second, we do not know how to prove that the complexity of the latter direct-sum problem is indeed the sum of the individual complexities.

In this work, we focus on the second obstacle. To this end, we study a notion called ``strong composition&amp;#39;&amp;#39;, which is the same as $f \diamond g$ except that it is forced to behave like a direct-sum problem. We prove a variant of the KRW conjecture for strong composition, thus overcoming the above second obstacle. This result demonstrates that the first obstacle above is the crucial barrier toward resolving the KRW conjecture. Along the way, we develop some general techniques that might be of independent interest.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">CCI: jobs: Ph.D. position at King’s College London (apply by July 14, 2023)</title>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/05/30/ph-d-position-at-kings-college-london-apply-by-july-14-2023/"/>
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/05/30/ph-d-position-at-kings-college-london-apply-by-july-14-2023/</id>
    <updated>2023-05-30T14:44:06+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;A funded Ph.D. position in theoretical computer science is available at King’s College London. The successful candidate will be advised by Hubie Chen and will work on mutually agreeable topics in theoretical computer science. The primary criterion for this position is an undergraduate degree in mathematics with strong performance, or an equivalent experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://hubie-chen.github.io/may2023ad.html&quot;&gt;https://hubie-chen.github.io/may2023ad.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: hubie.chen@kcl.ac.uk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>CCI: jobs</name>
      <uri>https://cstheory-jobs.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">CCI: jobs: Postdoc position at King’s College London (apply by July 9, 2023)</title>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/05/30/postdoc-position-at-kings-college-london-apply-by-july-9-2023/"/>
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/05/30/postdoc-position-at-kings-college-london-apply-by-july-9-2023/</id>
    <updated>2023-05-30T14:42:41+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;A postdoctoral research position in theoretical computer science is available at King’s College London. The successful candidate will be hosted by Hubie Chen and will be expected to work on topics related to the themes of complexity, database theory, structural decomposition methods, and logic. The position is offered for 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://hubie-chen.github.io/may2023ad.html&quot;&gt;https://hubie-chen.github.io/may2023ad.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: hubie.chen@kcl.ac.uk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>CCI: jobs</name>
      <uri>https://cstheory-jobs.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Gil Kalai: Physics Related News: Israel Joining CERN, Pugwash and Global Zero, The Replication Crisis, and MAX the Damon.</title>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/30/physics-related-news-israel-joining-cern-pugwash-and-global-zero-the-replication-crisis-and-max-the-damon/"/>
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=23932</id>
    <updated>2023-05-30T05:38:33+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/poster.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; data-attachment-id=&quot;24346&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/30/physics-related-news-israel-joining-cern-pugwash-and-global-zero-the-replication-crisis-and-max-the-damon/poster-2/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/poster.png&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;796,1043&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;poster&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/poster.png?w=229&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/poster.png?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone  wp-image-24346&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/poster.png?w=337&amp;#038;h=442&quot; alt=&quot;poster&quot; width=&quot;337&quot; height=&quot;442&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/poster.png?w=337&amp;amp;h=442 337w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/poster.png?w=674&amp;amp;h=884 674w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/poster.png?w=114&amp;amp;h=150 114w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/poster.png?w=229&amp;amp;h=300 229w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 337px) 100vw, 337px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Click to enlarge.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #0000ff&quot;&gt;Plan for this post:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prologue: &amp;#8220;Can we sleep soundly at night?&amp;#8221; Meeting &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Efraim_Halevy&quot;&gt;Ephraim Halevi&lt;/a&gt; (former head of the Israeli Mossad) in 2007.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Israel and CERN, an evening in honor of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eliezer_Rabinovici&quot;&gt;Eliezer Rabinovici&lt;/a&gt;: The story of how Israel joined CERN is an intriguing  story that involves science, academic politics, real politics, money, and diplomacy of various kinds.  The evening was quite fascinating with interesting lectures by physicists and diplomats. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/live/mg3gy4Et_xY?feature=share&quot;&gt;Click for the video;&lt;/a&gt;  some of it was over my head.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ephraim Halevi&amp;#8217;s lecture on Israel, CERN, and more. Test your knowledge: did you ever hear about the organizations Pugwash and Global Zero?  And do you know who Joseph Rotblat and Frank von Hippel are?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reproducibility Crisis zoom conference organized by Sergey Frolov&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giving quantum talks at the German Israeli quantum academy, and at physics colloquia at PI and Rutgers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://maxthedemon.com/&quot;&gt;Max the Demon&lt;/a&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;physics comics&lt;/strong&gt; by Assa Auerbach and Richard Codor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Epilogue: &amp;#8220;Can we sleep soundly at night?&amp;#8221; Ephraim Halevi&amp;#8217;s 2023 answer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; data-attachment-id=&quot;24175&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/30/physics-related-news-israel-joining-cern-pugwash-and-global-zero-the-replication-crisis-and-max-the-damon/sbha/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sbha.png&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1148,592&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;SBHA&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sbha.png?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sbha.png?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone  wp-image-24175&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sbha.png?w=593&amp;#038;h=306&quot; alt=&quot;SBHA&quot; width=&quot;593&quot; height=&quot;306&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sbha.png?w=593&amp;amp;h=306 593w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sbha.png?w=150&amp;amp;h=77 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sbha.png?w=300&amp;amp;h=155 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sbha.png?w=768&amp;amp;h=396 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sbha.png?w=1024&amp;amp;h=528 1024w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sbha.png 1148w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 593px) 100vw, 593px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000&quot;&gt;Two speakers at the evening celebrating Israel&amp;#8217;s admission to CERN:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en-exact-sciences.tau.ac.il/profile/halina&quot;&gt;Halina Abramowicz&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.weizmann.ac.il/particle/Bressler/group-members&quot;&gt;Shikma Bressler&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;embed-youtube&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe title=&quot;ערב עיון לכבוד פרופ&amp;#039; אליעזר רבינוביץ | סיפור כניסת ישראל ל- CERN&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mg3gy4Et_xY?feature=oembed&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is about things around physics where the main topic is an evening at the Israeli Academy of Science honoring my friend Eliezer Rabinovici who is now the president of CERN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Prologue: Meeting Ephraim Halevi, the former head of the Mossad in 2007&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2007 we had a special semester at the (Israeli) Institute for Advanced Studies, and one evening the director, Eliezer Rabinovici, hosted the director of the sister IAS at Princeton, Peter Goddard (whose nickname, as we were told, was “God” &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/wp-content/mu-plugins/wpcom-smileys/twemoji/2/72x72/1f642.png&quot; alt=&quot;🙂&quot; class=&quot;wp-smiley&quot; style=&quot;height: 1em; max-height: 1em;&quot; /&gt; ) to a party. I was hanging with Imre Barany and a few minutes after we were introduced to Goddard, we saw him again in the crowd:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How do you enjoy your stay in Israel” I asked Goddard&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I like it” was the answer “but I am an Israeli!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking more carefully at the man we were talking to, I realized my mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Imre,” I said with enthusiasm “please meet the former head of the Mossad (&amp;#8220;Mossad&amp;#8221; is the national intelligence agency of Israel) and the current VP of the Hebrew University: Ephraim Halevi! And this is Professor Imre Barany from the Hungarian Academy of Science!” (&amp;#8220;actually the question &amp;#8216;how do you enjoy your stay in Israel` is quite appropriate for a Mossad guy as well,&amp;#8221; I thought.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imre and I were both very excited,  engaged in a small humorous chat with Halevi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end I asked&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So, can we sleep soundly at night?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yes you can,” Halevi answered, “There are people who make sure of it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I met Halevi at the &amp;#8220;Israel joining CERN&amp;#8221; evening. He gave an interesting lecture that I will mention shortly and I asked him again if we can sleep soundly at night. You can find his answer at the end of this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; data-attachment-id=&quot;24172&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/30/physics-related-news-israel-joining-cern-pugwash-and-global-zero-the-replication-crisis-and-max-the-damon/ghb/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/ghb.png&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;631,283&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;GHB&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/ghb.png?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/ghb.png?w=631&quot; class=&quot;alignnone  wp-image-24172&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/ghb.png?w=517&amp;#038;h=232&quot; alt=&quot;GHB&quot; width=&quot;517&quot; height=&quot;232&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/ghb.png?w=517&amp;amp;h=232 517w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/ghb.png?w=150&amp;amp;h=67 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/ghb.png?w=300&amp;amp;h=135 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/ghb.png 631w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 517px) 100vw, 517px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000&quot;&gt;Ephraim Halevi, Petter Goddard, and Imre Barany&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Israel entering CERN&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the evening at the Israeli Academy of Science and Humanities was to honor Eliezer Rabinovici, an old friend of mine who was replaced by Mark Karliner as the representative of Israel in CERN. Rabinovici is still connected to CERN as the president of CERN. The lectures were interesting, although some of them required knowledge of the Israeli physics community or of physics that I don&amp;#8217;t have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;24180&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/30/physics-related-news-israel-joining-cern-pugwash-and-global-zero-the-replication-crisis-and-max-the-damon/cernx2/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/cernx2.png&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1656,1085&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;cernx2&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/cernx2.png?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/cernx2.png?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-24180&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/cernx2.png?w=640&quot; alt=&quot;cernx2&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/cernx2.png?w=640 640w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/cernx2.png?w=1280 1280w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/cernx2.png?w=150 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/cernx2.png?w=300 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/cernx2.png?w=768 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/cernx2.png?w=1024 1024w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px&quot;   /&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000&quot;&gt;Five more speakers at  the evening celebrating Israel and CERN: Eliezer Rabinovici, Peter Jenni, Rafi Barak, Giora Mikenberg, and Mark Karliner&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Halevi&amp;#8217;s lecture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;24189&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/30/physics-related-news-israel-joining-cern-pugwash-and-global-zero-the-replication-crisis-and-max-the-damon/uefvheh/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/uefvheh.jpg&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;533,209&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;2.2&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;SM-G986B&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1681664955&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;2.2&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;80&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0.02&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;UEFvHEH&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/uefvheh.jpg?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/uefvheh.jpg?w=533&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-24189&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/uefvheh.jpg?w=640&quot; alt=&quot;UEFvHEH&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/uefvheh.jpg 533w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/uefvheh.jpg?w=150 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/uefvheh.jpg?w=300 300w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 533px) 100vw, 533px&quot;   /&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ephraim Halevi served in the Israeli Mossad for many years and was the head of the organization between 1998 and 2002. The lecture&amp;#8217;s title was &amp;#8220;&lt;span class=&quot;Y2IQFc&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;Track two and track three in the toolbox over the years.&amp;#8221; I still don&amp;#8217;t understand what &amp;#8220;track two&amp;#8221; and track three&amp;#8221; refer to :).  &lt;/span&gt;Halevi talked a little about the diplomacy (and his own part) behind Israel joining CERN, and about SESAME, but large parts of Halevi’s lecture were about one of his main activities since he retired from civil service: acting against nuclear weapon proliferation. Halevi mentioned two notable (and noble!) organizations against proliferation: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pugwash_Conferences_on_Science_and_World_Affairs&quot;&gt;Pugwash&lt;/a&gt; (founded in 1957 by &lt;a title=&quot;&quot; href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_Rotblat&quot;&gt;Joseph Rotblat&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_Zero_(campaign)&quot;&gt;Global Zero&lt;/a&gt; (founded in 2008) and he talked about the very interesting history of these organizations. As it turned out, these types of organizations served as platforms for building informal relations between Israel and other countries (like the Soviet Union). Halevi told  two little stories, one from a 2014 Global Zero meeting where he and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uzi_Eilam&quot;&gt;Uzi Eilam&lt;/a&gt; were the Israeli delegates and they had to deal with a detailed program of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank_N._von_Hippel&quot;&gt;Frank von Hippel&lt;/a&gt; regarding middle-east disarmament. (The picture above are portrays of these three personalities.) To make an exciting short story even shorter, at the end, the program was not adopted. The second story was about a Pugwash meeting in 2015 where Halevi indirectly posed a question to the Iranian Foreign minister. Ephraim Halevi also briefly mentioned the recent war in Ukraine and his hopes that nuclear weapons will not be applied there, and the question regarding the location of next-generation accelerators and his hopes regarding where it will be built. I found Halevi&amp;#8217;s (Hebrew) lecture quite exciting and it is very much recommended. I also greatly enjoyed the lecture of another diplomat, Rafi Barak who was the general manager of our Foreign Office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Eliezer&amp;#8217;s and Shikma&amp;#8217;s Lectures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eliezer&amp;#8217;s lecture (also in Hebrew) told the story of Israel and CERN from his own angle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/israel-cern.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; data-attachment-id=&quot;24290&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/30/physics-related-news-israel-joining-cern-pugwash-and-global-zero-the-replication-crisis-and-max-the-damon/israel-cern/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/israel-cern.png&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1103,968&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;Israel-CERN&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/israel-cern.png?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/israel-cern.png?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone  wp-image-24290&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/israel-cern.png?w=387&amp;#038;h=340&quot; alt=&quot;Israel-CERN&quot; width=&quot;387&quot; height=&quot;340&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/israel-cern.png?w=387&amp;amp;h=340 387w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/israel-cern.png?w=774&amp;amp;h=680 774w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/israel-cern.png?w=150&amp;amp;h=132 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/israel-cern.png?w=300&amp;amp;h=263 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/israel-cern.png?w=768&amp;amp;h=674 768w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 387px) 100vw, 387px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000&quot;&gt;Two critical moments (click to enlarge): Israel&amp;#8217;s request to join CERN (above); The decision to admit Israel (below); A crucial parameter (in my view): we see in the bottom right picture two women out of ten participants which is rather poor representation of women. (But sadly not surprising for physics/math.)  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shikma Bressler gave a very interesting lecture (click to enlarge the picture) on the role of Israeli scientists for ATLAS detectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/cern22.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; data-attachment-id=&quot;24370&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/30/physics-related-news-israel-joining-cern-pugwash-and-global-zero-the-replication-crisis-and-max-the-damon/cern22/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/cern22.jpg&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1568,760&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;CERN22&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/cern22.jpg?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/cern22.jpg?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone  wp-image-24370&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/cern22.jpg?w=472&amp;#038;h=229&quot; alt=&quot;CERN22&quot; width=&quot;472&quot; height=&quot;229&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/cern22.jpg?w=472&amp;amp;h=229 472w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/cern22.jpg?w=944&amp;amp;h=458 944w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/cern22.jpg?w=150&amp;amp;h=73 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/cern22.jpg?w=300&amp;amp;h=145 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/cern22.jpg?w=768&amp;amp;h=372 768w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 472px) 100vw, 472px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000&quot;&gt;The replication &lt;strong&gt;crisis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; data-attachment-id=&quot;24182&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/30/physics-related-news-israel-joining-cern-pugwash-and-global-zero-the-replication-crisis-and-max-the-damon/sfvm/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sfvm.png&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1184,466&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;SFVM&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sfvm.png?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sfvm.png?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone  wp-image-24182&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sfvm.png?w=546&amp;#038;h=215&quot; alt=&quot;SFVM&quot; width=&quot;546&quot; height=&quot;215&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sfvm.png?w=546&amp;amp;h=215 546w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sfvm.png?w=1092&amp;amp;h=430 1092w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sfvm.png?w=150&amp;amp;h=59 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sfvm.png?w=300&amp;amp;h=118 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sfvm.png?w=768&amp;amp;h=302 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/sfvm.png?w=1024&amp;amp;h=403 1024w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 546px) 100vw, 546px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000&quot;&gt;Sergey Frolov and Vincent Mourik&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I participated in a short zoom workshop organized by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.physicsandastronomy.pitt.edu/people/sergey-frolov&quot;&gt;Sergey Frolov&lt;/a&gt; about the reproduction crisis, and more precisely about the question &amp;#8220;Does condensed matter physics need to worry about a replication crisis?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe class=&quot;youtube-player&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/uVQpRPSZYN4?version=3&amp;#038;rel=1&amp;#038;showsearch=0&amp;#038;showinfo=1&amp;#038;iv_load_policy=1&amp;#038;fs=1&amp;#038;hl=en&amp;#038;autohide=2&amp;#038;wmode=transparent&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; style=&quot;border:0;&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;I think that a central problem is: &amp;#8220;What are the appropriate methodology and ethics for scrutinizing &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;major scientific works,&amp;#8221; and this problem is relevant to some of my own scientific endeavors over the years.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;Sergey Frolov and Vincent Mourik themselves &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-00954-8&quot;&gt;put under the microscope&lt;/a&gt; several works regarding &amp;#8220;Majorana zero modes&amp;#8221;, which are important steps toward topological quantum computers.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One issue that speakers elaborated on in the seminar was on getting data from authors, which is something I encountered on several occasions (and overall, had positive experiences).  In the last three years, with Yosi Rinot and Tomer Shoham, we have been putting Google&amp;#8217;s 2019 &amp;#8220;quantum supremacy&amp;#8221; paper under the microscope, and naturally, needed some data.  Our policy regarding data was: (a) We always &amp;#8220;asked&amp;#8221; and never &amp;#8220;demanded&amp;#8221; data; (b) In cases where the answer was negative we did not ask again; (c) Sometimes, when the answer was positive we did send reminders (trying not to be &amp;#8220;pushy&amp;#8221;) and so we did when we got no answer at all (which is ok).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;German-Israeli quantum academy and other quantum events.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I gave a talk at an Israeli-German &amp;#8220;Quantum Future academy Workshop&amp;#8221; for young students. &lt;span class=&quot;x193iq5w xeuugli x13faqbe x1vvkbs x1xmvt09 x1lliihq x1s928wv xhkezso x1gmr53x x1cpjm7i x1fgarty x1943h6x xudqn12 x3x7a5m x6prxxf xvq8zen xo1l8bm xzsf02u&quot; dir=&quot;auto&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;My lecture was about &amp;#8220;Limits of Computations, Noise and Quantum Computers&amp;#8221;. At the end, I talked mainly about how quantum computing is related to computational complexity and how quantum computers may give computational advantage and left only little time to discuss my own take on why a noisy quantum computer may not give computational advantage after all.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/gpt7.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; data-attachment-id=&quot;24184&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/30/physics-related-news-israel-joining-cern-pugwash-and-global-zero-the-replication-crisis-and-max-the-damon/gpt7/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/gpt7.jpg&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;2100,2100&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;gpt7&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/gpt7.jpg?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/gpt7.jpg?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone  wp-image-24184&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/gpt7.jpg?w=335&amp;#038;h=335&quot; alt=&quot;gpt7&quot; width=&quot;335&quot; height=&quot;335&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/gpt7.jpg?w=335&amp;amp;h=335 335w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/gpt7.jpg?w=670&amp;amp;h=670 670w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/gpt7.jpg?w=150&amp;amp;h=150 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/gpt7.jpg?w=300&amp;amp;h=300 300w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 335px) 100vw, 335px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000&quot;&gt;Alef&amp;#8217;s humorous futuristic view of me asking GPT7 whether quantum computers will ever achieve&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000&quot;&gt;advantage.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gave two (zoom) physics colloquium talks at Rutgers University and at the Perimeter Institute about my argument against quantum computers, and I felt that both talks went very well with very nice discussions afterwards. Thanks to my hosts Daniel Friedan at Rutgers and Latham Boyle at PI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PI talk was in direct &lt;span class=&quot;x193iq5w xeuugli x13faqbe x1vvkbs x1xmvt09 x1lliihq x1s928wv xhkezso x1gmr53x x1cpjm7i x1fgarty x1943h6x xudqn12 x3x7a5m x6prxxf xvq8zen xo1l8bm xzsf02u x1yc453h&quot; dir=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;competition with the World Cup France vs. Morocco football match, and it &lt;/span&gt;was recorded (&lt;a href=&quot;https://pirsa.org/22120066&quot;&gt;Video is here&lt;/a&gt;). It was very nice to meet face-to-face (in the zoom sense) Lee Smolin, Debbie Leung, Ray Lafflamme, and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Slides: &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/q-academy-1.pptx&quot;&gt;Israeli-German academy&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/qc-rutgers.pptx&quot;&gt;Rutgers&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/qc-perimeter.pptx&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/friedan-boyle.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; data-attachment-id=&quot;24319&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/30/physics-related-news-israel-joining-cern-pugwash-and-global-zero-the-replication-crisis-and-max-the-damon/friedan-boyle/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/friedan-boyle.png&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1153,970&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;Friedan-Boyle&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/friedan-boyle.png?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/friedan-boyle.png?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone  wp-image-24319&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/friedan-boyle.png?w=360&amp;#038;h=303&quot; alt=&quot;Friedan-Boyle&quot; width=&quot;360&quot; height=&quot;303&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/friedan-boyle.png?w=360&amp;amp;h=303 360w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/friedan-boyle.png?w=720&amp;amp;h=606 720w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/friedan-boyle.png?w=150&amp;amp;h=126 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/05/friedan-boyle.png?w=300&amp;amp;h=252 300w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 360px) 100vw, 360px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Max the Demon!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://maxthedemon.com/&quot;&gt;Max the Demon&lt;/a&gt; is a wonderful comics book about thermodynamics written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://phsites.technion.ac.il/assa/&quot;&gt;Assa Auerbach&lt;/a&gt; (a famous physicist) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://cartoonmovement.com/cartoonist/1041&quot;&gt;Richard Codor&lt;/a&gt; (a famous artist, among the writers of the legendary book &lt;a href=&quot;https://he.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zoo_%D7%90%D7%A8%D7%A5_zoo%3F&quot;&gt;Zoo Aretz Zoo&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; data-attachment-id=&quot;24185&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/05/30/physics-related-news-israel-joining-cern-pugwash-and-global-zero-the-replication-crisis-and-max-the-damon/maxdemon/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/maxdemon.jpg&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1355,1870&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;2.2&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;SM-G986B&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1681664955&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;2.2&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;80&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0.02&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;maxdemon&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/maxdemon.jpg?w=217&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/maxdemon.jpg?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone  wp-image-24185&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/maxdemon.jpg?w=482&amp;#038;h=665&quot; alt=&quot;maxdemon&quot; width=&quot;482&quot; height=&quot;665&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/maxdemon.jpg?w=482&amp;amp;h=665 482w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/maxdemon.jpg?w=964&amp;amp;h=1330 964w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/maxdemon.jpg?w=109&amp;amp;h=150 109w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/maxdemon.jpg?w=217&amp;amp;h=300 217w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/maxdemon.jpg?w=768&amp;amp;h=1060 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/maxdemon.jpg?w=742&amp;amp;h=1024 742w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 482px) 100vw, 482px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Epilogue: can we have a sound night sleep now?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the &amp;#8220;Israel joining CERN event&amp;#8221;, I had a little chat with Halevi. I told him about his answer to my 2007 question and asked him if these days we can also sleep soundly at night. Ephraim Halevi&amp;#8217;s response was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #0000ff&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;I haven&amp;#8217;t been sleeping soundly in recent weeks and I estimate that my sleep hours will be even shorter in the coming weeks. The days are gradually getting gloomier and the gates of reconciliation are closing.&amp;#8221;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This was in February, and I suppose that Halevi referred to the dispute regarding the judicial reforms in Israel. Indeed in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jpost.com/israel-news/politics-and-diplomacy/article-734532&quot;&gt;later&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.haaretz.com/israel-news/2023-03-15/ty-article/.premium/ex-mossad-head-reservists-have-every-grounds-for-refusal-over-netanyahu-judicial-overhaul/00000186-e683-d8a3-a9ae-e6a39f910000&quot;&gt;interviews&lt;/a&gt; he expressed his objection to these reforms.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Gil Kalai&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
      <uri>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Irreducibility of Recombination Markov Chains in the Triangular Lattice</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.17239"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.17239</id>
    <updated>2023-05-30T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Cannon_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sarah Cannon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the United States, regions are frequently divided into districts for the
purpose of electing representatives. How the districts are drawn can affect
who&#39;s elected, and drawing districts to give an advantage to a certain group is
known as gerrymandering. It can be surprisingly difficult to detect
gerrymandering, but one algorithmic method is to compare a current districting
plan to a large number of randomly sampled plans to see whether it is an
outlier. Recombination Markov chains are often used for this random sampling:
randomly choose two districts, consider their union, and split this union in a
new way. This works well in practice, but the theory behind it remains
underdeveloped. For example, it&#39;s not known if recombination Markov chains are
irreducible, that is, if recombination moves suffice to move from any
districting plan to any other.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Irreducibility of recombination Markov chains can be formulated as a graph
problem: for a graph $G$, is the space of all partitions of $G$ into $k$
connected subgraphs ($k$ districts) connected by recombination moves? We
consider three simply connected districts and district sizes $k_1\pm 1$
vertices, $k_2\pm 1$ vertices, and $k3\pm 1$ vertices. We prove for arbitrarily
large triangular regions in the triangular lattice, recombination Markov chains
are irreducible. This is the first proof of irreducibility under tight district
size constraints for recombination Markov chains beyond small or trivial
examples.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Differentially private low-dimensional representation of high-dimensional data</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.17148"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.17148</id>
    <updated>2023-05-30T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+He_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yiyun He&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Strohmer_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Thomas Strohmer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Vershynin_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Roman Vershynin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zhu_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yizhe Zhu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Differentially private synthetic data provide a powerful mechanism to enable
data analysis while protecting sensitive information about individuals.
However, when the data lie in a high-dimensional space, the accuracy of the
synthetic data suffers from the curse of dimensionality. In this paper, we
propose a differentially private algorithm to generate low-dimensional
synthetic data efficiently from a high-dimensional dataset with a utility
guarantee with respect to the Wasserstein distance. A key step of our algorithm
is a private principal component analysis (PCA) procedure with a near-optimal
accuracy bound that circumvents the curse of dimensionality. Different from the
standard perturbation analysis using the Davis-Kahan theorem, our analysis of
private PCA works without assuming the spectral gap for the sample covariance
matrix.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Clip-OGD: An Experimental Design for Adaptive Neyman Allocation in Sequential Experiments</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.17187"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.17187</id>
    <updated>2023-05-30T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/stat/1/au:+Dai_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jessica Dai&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/stat/1/au:+Gradu_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Paula Gradu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/stat/1/au:+Harshaw_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Christopher Harshaw&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From clinical development of cancer therapies to investigations into partisan
bias, adaptive sequential designs have become increasingly popular method for
causal inference, as they offer the possibility of improved precision over
their non-adaptive counterparts. However, even in simple settings (e.g. two
treatments) the extent to which adaptive designs can improve precision is not
sufficiently well understood. In this work, we study the problem of Adaptive
Neyman Allocation in a design-based potential outcomes framework, where the
experimenter seeks to construct an adaptive design which is nearly as efficient
as the optimal (but infeasible) non-adaptive Neyman design, which has access to
all potential outcomes. Motivated by connections to online optimization, we
propose Neyman Ratio and Neyman Regret as two (equivalent) performance measures
of adaptive designs for this problem. We present Clip-OGD, an adaptive design
which achieves $\widetilde{O}(\sqrt{T})$ expected Neyman regret and thereby
recovers the optimal Neyman variance in large samples. Finally, we construct a
conservative variance estimator which facilitates the development of
asymptotically valid confidence intervals. To complement our theoretical
results, we conduct simulations using data from a microeconomic experiment.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: DotHash: Estimating Set Similarity Metrics for Link Prediction and Document Deduplication</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.17310"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.17310</id>
    <updated>2023-05-30T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nunes_I/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Igor Nunes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Heddes_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mike Heddes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Verges_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Pere Verg&amp;#xe9;s&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Abraham_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Danny Abraham&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Veidenbaum_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Alexander Veidenbaum&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nicolau_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Alexandru Nicolau&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Givargis_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tony Givargis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Metrics for set similarity are a core aspect of several data mining tasks. To
remove duplicate results in a Web search, for example, a common approach looks
at the Jaccard index between all pairs of pages. In social network analysis, a
much-celebrated metric is the Adamic-Adar index, widely used to compare node
neighborhood sets in the important problem of predicting links. However, with
the increasing amount of data to be processed, calculating the exact similarity
between all pairs can be intractable. The challenge of working at this scale
has motivated research into efficient estimators for set similarity metrics.
The two most popular estimators, MinHash and SimHash, are indeed used in
applications such as document deduplication and recommender systems where large
volumes of data need to be processed. Given the importance of these tasks, the
demand for advancing estimators is evident. We propose DotHash, an unbiased
estimator for the intersection size of two sets. DotHash can be used to
estimate the Jaccard index and, to the best of our knowledge, is the first
method that can also estimate the Adamic-Adar index and a family of related
metrics. We formally define this family of metrics, provide theoretical bounds
on the probability of estimate errors, and analyze its empirical performance.
Our experimental results indicate that DotHash is more accurate than the other
estimators in link prediction and detecting duplicate documents with the same
complexity and similar comparison time.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Seeding with Differentially Private Network Information</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16590"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16590</id>
    <updated>2023-05-29T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rahimian_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;M. Amin Rahimian&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Yu_F/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Fang-Yi Yu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hurtado_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Carlos Hurtado&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When designing interventions in public health, development, and education,
decision makers rely on social network data to target a small number of people,
capitalizing on peer effects and social contagion to bring about the most
welfare benefits to the population. Developing new methods that are
privacy-preserving for network data collection and targeted interventions is
critical for designing sustainable public health and development interventions
on social networks. In a similar vein, social media platforms rely on network
data and information from past diffusions to organize their ad campaign and
improve the efficacy of targeted advertising. Ensuring that these network
operations do not violate users&#39; privacy is critical to the sustainability of
social media platforms and their ad economies. We study privacy guarantees for
influence maximization algorithms when the social network is unknown, and the
inputs are samples of prior influence cascades that are collected at random.
Building on recent results that address seeding with costly network
information, our privacy-preserving algorithms introduce randomization in the
collected data or the algorithm output, and can bound each node&#39;s (or group of
nodes&#39;) privacy loss in deciding whether or not their data should be included
in the algorithm input. We provide theoretical guarantees of the seeding
performance with a limited sample size subject to differential privacy budgets
in both central and local privacy regimes. Simulations on synthetic and
empirical network datasets reveal the diminishing value of network information
with decreasing privacy budget in both regimes.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: A Unified Approach for Maximizing Continuous DR-submodular Functions</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16671"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16671</id>
    <updated>2023-05-29T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Pedramfar_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mohammad Pedramfar&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Quinn_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Christopher John Quinn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Aggarwal_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vaneet Aggarwal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper presents a unified approach for maximizing continuous
DR-submodular functions that encompasses a range of settings and oracle access
types. Our approach includes a Frank-Wolfe type offline algorithm for both
monotone and non-monotone functions, with different restrictions on the general
convex set. We consider settings where the oracle provides access to either the
gradient of the function or only the function value, and where the oracle
access is either deterministic or stochastic. We determine the number of
required oracle accesses in all cases. Our approach gives new/improved results
for nine out of the sixteen considered cases, avoids computationally expensive
projections in two cases, with the proposed framework matching performance of
state-of-the-art approaches in the remaining five cases. Notably, our approach
for the stochastic function value-based oracle enables the first regret bounds
with bandit feedback for stochastic DR-submodular functions.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Polylogarithmic Approximation for Robust s-t Path</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16439"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16439</id>
    <updated>2023-05-29T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Li_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Shi Li&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Xu_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Chenyang Xu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zhang_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ruilong Zhang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The paper revisits the robust $s$-$t$ path problem, one of the most
fundamental problems in robust optimization. In the problem, we are given a
directed graph with $n$ vertices and $k$ distinct cost functions (scenarios)
defined over edges, and aim to choose an $s$-$t$ path such that the total cost
of the path is always provable no matter which scenario is realized. With the
view of each cost function being associated with an agent, our goal is to find
a common $s$-$t$ path minimizing the maximum objective among all agents, and
thus create a fair solution for them. The problem is hard to approximate within
$o(\log k)$ by any quasi-polynomial time algorithm unless $\mathrm{NP}
\subseteq \mathrm{DTIME}(n^{\mathrm{poly}\log n})$, and the best approximation
ratio known to date is $\widetilde{O}(\sqrt{n})$ which is based on the natural
flow linear program. A longstanding open question is whether we can achieve a
polylogarithmic approximation even when a quasi-polynomial running time is
allowed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We give the first polylogarithmic approximation for robust $s$-$t$ path since
the problem was proposed more than two decades ago. In particular, we introduce
a $O(\log n \log k)$-approximate algorithm running in quasi-polynomial time.
The algorithm is built on a novel linear program formulation for a
decision-tree-type structure which enables us to get rid of the
$\Omega(\max\{k,\sqrt{n}\})$ integrality gap of the natural flow LP. Further,
we also consider some well-known graph classes, e.g., graphs with bounded
treewidth, and show that the polylogarithmic approximation can be achieved
polynomially on these graphs. We hope the new proposed techniques in the paper
can offer new insights into the robust $s$-$t$ path problem and related
problems in robust optimization.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Sliding Window Sum Algorithms for Deep Neural Networks</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16513"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16513</id>
    <updated>2023-05-29T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Snytsar_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Roman Snytsar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sliding window sums are widely used for string indexing, hashing and time
series analysis. We have developed a family of the generic vectorized sliding
sum algorithms that provide speedup of O(P/w) for window size $w$ and number of
processors P. For a sum with a commutative operator the speedup is improved to
O(P/log(w)). Even more important, our algorithms exhibit efficient memory
access patterns. In this paper we study the application of the sliding sum
algorithms to the training and inference of the Deep Neural Networks. We
demonstrate how both pooling and convolution primitives could be expressed as
sliding sums and evaluated by the compute kernels with the shared structure. We
show that the sliding sum convolution kernels are more efficient than the
commonly used GEMM kernels on the CPU, and could even outperform their GPU
counterparts.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Efficient Computation of Quantiles over Joins</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16525"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16525</id>
    <updated>2023-05-29T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Tziavelis_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nikolaos Tziavelis&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Carmeli_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nofar Carmeli&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gatterbauer_W/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Wolfgang Gatterbauer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kimelfeld_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Benny Kimelfeld&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Riedewald_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mirek Riedewald&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present efficient algorithms for Quantile Join Queries, abbreviated as
%JQ. A %JQ asks for the answer at a specified relative position (e.g., 50% for
the median) under some ordering over the answers to a Join Query (JQ). Our goal
is to avoid materializing the set of all join answers, and to achieve
quasilinear time in the size of the database, regardless of the total number of
answers. A recent dichotomy result rules out the existence of such an algorithm
for a general family of queries and orders. Specifically, for acyclic JQs
without self-joins, the problem becomes intractable for ordering by sum
whenever we join more than two relations (and these joins are not trivial
intersections). Moreover, even for basic ranking functions beyond sum, such as
min or max over different attributes, so far it is not known whether there is
any nontrivial tractable %JQ. In this work, we develop a new approach to
solving %JQ. Our solution uses two subroutines: The first one needs to select
what we call a &quot;pivot answer&quot;. The second subroutine partitions the space of
query answers according to this pivot, and continues searching in one partition
that is represented as new %JQ over a new database. For pivot selection, we
develop an algorithm that works for a large class of ranking functions that are
appropriately monotone. The second subroutine requires a customized
construction for the specific ranking function at hand. We show the benefit and
generality of our approach by using it to establish several new complexity
results. First, we prove the tractability of min and max for all acyclic JQs,
thereby resolving the above question. Second, we extend the previous %JQ
dichotomy for sum to all partial sums. Third, we handle the intractable cases
of sum by devising a deterministic approximation scheme that applies to every
acyclic JQ.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: CARAMEL: A Succinct Read-Only Lookup Table via Compressed Static Functions</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16545"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16545</id>
    <updated>2023-05-29T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Coleman_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Benjamin Coleman&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ramos_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;David Torres Ramos&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lakshman_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vihan Lakshman&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Luo_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Chen Luo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Shrivastava_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Anshumali Shrivastava&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lookup tables are a fundamental structure in many data processing and systems
applications. Examples include tokenized text in NLP, quantized embedding
collections in recommendation systems, integer sketches for streaming data, and
hash-based string representations in genomics. With the increasing size of
web-scale data, such applications often require compression techniques that
support fast random $O(1)$ lookup of individual parameters directly on the
compressed data (i.e. without blockwise decompression in RAM). While the
community has proposd a number of succinct data structures that support queries
over compressed representations, these approaches do not fully leverage the
low-entropy structure prevalent in real-world workloads to reduce space.
Inspired by recent advances in static function construction techniques, we
propose a space-efficient representation of immutable key-value data, called
CARAMEL, specifically designed for the case where the values are multi-sets. By
carefully combining multiple compressed static functions, CARAMEL occupies
space proportional to the data entropy with low memory overheads and minimal
lookup costs. We demonstrate 1.25-16x compression on practical lookup tasks
drawn from real-world systems, improving upon established techniques, including
a production-grade read-only database widely used for development within
Amazon.com.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Sublinear-Space Streaming Algorithms for Estimating Graph Parameters on Sparse Graphs</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16815"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16815</id>
    <updated>2023-05-29T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chen_X/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Xiuge Chen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chitnis_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Rajesh Chitnis&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Eades_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Patrick Eades&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wirth_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Anthony Wirth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we design sub-linear space streaming algorithms for estimating
three fundamental parameters -- maximum independent set, minimum dominating set
and maximum matching -- on sparse graph classes, i.e., graphs which satisfy
$m=O(n)$ where $m,n$ is the number of edges, vertices respectively. Each of the
three graph parameters we consider can have size $\Omega(n)$ even on sparse
graph classes, and hence for sublinear-space algorithms we are restricted to
parameter estimation instead of attempting to find a solution.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Computational Complexity: On Nov 10, 2014 the TV show Scorpion mentions Software that is like ChatGPT for Music</title>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2023/05/on-nov-10-2014-tv-show-scorpion.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-7380998070167715843</id>
    <updated>2023-05-28T19:34:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Scorpion is a TV show that ran from 2014 to 2018. It involves a group of brilliant (to say the least) but socially awkward (to say the least) people who help the government battle threats and/or solve crimes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The episode &lt;i&gt;Risky Business &lt;/i&gt;aired on Nov 10, 2014 (episode 8).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the episode someone wrote a program that (in todays terminology) scrapes the web for all pop songs that were hits for the last 50 years and creates hits that share those properties and hence will be popular. And it works!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1) The episode says that if the fans of group X find out that they didn&#39;t create their own music, but its computer generated, then sales will drop. This may be true but I am not quite sure WHY its true. If I LIKE&amp;nbsp; listening to a song, I will still like it even if I know it was computer generated.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;2) While they didn&#39;t go into any detail about what the program does, it SOUNDS a lot like ChatGPT to me.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;3) Could ChatGPT do that now? Has it already? Lance happened to read an earlier version of this post and emailed me a link which says this is already happening to some extent. The link is&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2023/04/19/arts/music/ai-drake-the-weeknd-fake.html?unlocked_article_code=EAbzgrrnYPlWWP8bMw7TdZYabKqbPRK84bx8yi2YwEHpQL7iuKUpJ4Qz7F-3STJMP9li11P1y0MRNGBRdHwJJtYjQS1-vDsLZpn6mAbWoPQmcevIRg665mw3n_e_OyjFTK2Cfe928mnnK5RCGYm4giIv5zNMqz5vp8FA0s3jW2wuD7je4PnTDMRBBBo1VD4hISgqnGogiyyYYpBXE4rTebEjqyFvtakYxQ-lkjgNfAVShci0Q60FIgfnPk4oP-b8l1kXST71XbBsi2GjeJI1EVRv5HFcFz3IrKhHd5AJnehEXoAwCK-6ycaaWNwD1yxUcTT1kF_sXBrs8jfqFNFUsCHhv-U5&amp;amp;smid=url-share&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;but might be behind a paywall. (Note- My spellchecker DOES think paywall is a word. Yeah! It also thinks that spellchecker is a word. Yeah!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;4) Is it impressive that the shows writers predicted this kind of technology way back in 2014?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;5) In the real world would someone be murdered because they are going to reveal that group X&#39;s songs were not authentic? Either TV has far more murders than the real world OR on TV they just get caught more often. I would like to think that TV has far more murders (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2191990/Murder-capital-world-Quiet-seaside-town-Cabot-Cove-named-dangerous-place-Earth.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). It certainly has far more &lt;i&gt;interesting&lt;/i&gt; murders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By gasarch&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR23-077 |  Batch Proofs are Statistically Hiding | 

	Nir Bitansky, 

	Chethan Kamath, 

	Omer Paneth, 

	Ron Rothblum, 

	Prashant Nalini Vasudevan</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/077"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/077</id>
    <updated>2023-05-27T08:16:05+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    Batch proofs are proof systems that convince a verifier that $x_1,\dots, x_t \in  L$, for some $NP$ language $L$, with communication that is much shorter than sending the $t$ witnesses. In the case of statistical soundness (where the cheating prover is unbounded but honest prover is efficient), interactive batch proofs are known for $UP$, the class of unique witness $NP$ languages. In the case of computational soundness (aka arguments, where both honest and dishonest provers are efficient), non-interactive solutions are now known for all of $NP$, assuming standard cryptographic assumptions. We study the necessary conditions for the existence of batch proofs in these two settings. Our main results are as follows.

1. Statistical Soundness: the existence of a statistically-sound batch proof for $L$ implies that $L$ has a statistically witness indistinguishable ($SWI$) proof, with inverse polynomial $SWI$ error, and a non-uniform honest prover. The implication is unconditional for public-coin protocols and relies on one-way functions in the private-coin case.

This poses a barrier for achieving batch proofs beyond $UP$ (where witness indistinguishability is trivial). In particular, assuming that $NP$ does not have $SWI$ proofs, batch proofs for all of $NP$ do not exist. This motivates further study of the complexity class $SWI$, which, in contrast to the related class $SZK$, has been largely left unexplored.

2. Computational Soundness: the existence of batch arguments ($BARG$s) for $NP$, together with one-way functions, implies the existence of statistical zero-knowledge ($SZK$) arguments for $NP$ with roughly the same number of rounds, an inverse polynomial zero-knowledge error, and non-uniform honest prover.

    Thus, constant-round interactive $BARG$s from one-way functions would yield constant-round $SZK$ arguments from one-way functions. This would be surprising as $SZK$ arguments are currently only known assuming constant-round statistically-hiding commitments (which in turn are unlikely to follow from one-way functions).

3. Non-interactive: the existence of non-interactive $BARG$s for $NP$ and one-way functions, implies non-interactive statistical zero-knowledge arguments ($NISZKA$) for $NP$, with negligible soundness error, inverse polynomial zero-knowledge error, and non-uniform honest prover. Assuming also lossy public-key encryption, the statistical zero-knowledge error can be made negligible. We further show that $BARG$s satisfying a notion of honest somewhere extractability imply lossy public key encryption.

All of our results stem from a common framework showing how to transform a batch protocol for a language $L$ into an $SWI$ protocol for $L$.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">TCS+ Seminar Series: TCS+ talk: Wednesday, May 31 — Paul Gölz, Harvard University</title>
    <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2023/05/26/tcs-talk-wednesday-may-31-paul-golz-harvard-university/"/>
    <id>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=691</id>
    <updated>2023-05-26T06:40:08+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, May 31th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC). &lt;strong&gt;Paul Gölz&lt;/strong&gt; from Harvard University will speak about &amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;News from Algorithmic Democracy: Proportional Representation for Preferences and Demographics&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8221; (abstract below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to join us live by signing up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/next-tcs-talk&quot;&gt;the online form&lt;/a&gt;. Registration is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; required to attend the interactive talk, and the link will be posted on the website the day prior to the talk; however, by registering in the form, you will receive a reminder, along with the link. (The recorded talk will also be posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/past-talks&quot;&gt;on our website&lt;/a&gt; afterwards) As usual, for more information about the TCS+ online seminar series and the upcoming talks, or to &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/suggest-a-talk&quot;&gt;suggest&lt;/a&gt; a possible topic or speaker, please see &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/&quot;&gt;the website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abstract: How do you fill a knapsack with city projects to fund, in a way that aligns with voters’ preferences? And how do you choose a committee that represents the population’s makeup in terms of gender, age, etc.? Both questions are central to experiments with new forms of democracy in practice, and both have spurred an exploration for the right algorithms in computational social choice. In this talk, I will survey advances along these thrusts: proposed algorithms, guarantees offered and sought after, as well as technical challenges and connections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By plustcs&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>TCS+ Seminar Series</name>
      <uri>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: On the Weisfeiler-Leman dimension of permutation graphs</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.15861"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.15861</id>
    <updated>2023-05-26T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Guo_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jin Guo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Gavrilyuk_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Alexander L. Gavrilyuk&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Ponomarenko_I/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ilia Ponomarenko&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is proved that the Weisfeiler-Leman dimension of the class of permutation
graphs is at most 18. Previously it was only known that this dimension is
finite (Gru{\ss}ien, 2017).
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: A Fast Algorithm for Consistency Checking Partially Ordered Time</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.15917"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.15917</id>
    <updated>2023-05-26T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Eriksson_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Leif Eriksson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lagerkvist_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Victor Lagerkvist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Partially ordered models of time occur naturally in applications where agents
or processes cannot perfectly communicate with each other, and can be traced
back to the seminal work of Lamport. In this paper we consider the problem of
deciding if a (likely incomplete) description of a system of events is
consistent, the network consistency problem for the point algebra of partially
ordered time (POT). While the classical complexity of this problem has been
fully settled, comparably little is known of the fine-grained complexity of POT
except that it can be solved in $O^*((0.368n)^n)$ time by enumerating ordered
partitions. We construct a much faster algorithm with a run-time bounded by
$O^*((0.26n)^n)$. This is achieved by a sophisticated enumeration of structures
similar to total orders, which are then greedily expanded toward a solution.
While similar ideas have been explored earlier for related problems it turns
out that the analysis for POT is non-trivial and requires significant new
ideas.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Improved Algorithms for Allen&#39;s Interval Algebra by Dynamic Programming with Sublinear Partitioning</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.15950"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.15950</id>
    <updated>2023-05-26T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Eriksson_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Leif Eriksson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lagerkvist_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Victor Lagerkvist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Allen&#39;s interval algebra is one of the most well-known calculi in qualitative
temporal reasoning with numerous applications in artificial intelligence.
Recently, there has been a surge of improvements in the fine-grained complexity
of NP-hard reasoning tasks, improving the running time from the naive
$2^{O(n^2)}$ to $O^*((1.0615n)^{n})$, with even faster algorithms for unit
intervals a bounded number of overlapping intervals (the $O^*(\cdot)$ notation
suppresses polynomial factors). Despite these improvements the best known lower
bound is still only $2^{o(n)}$ (under the exponential-time hypothesis) and
major improvements in either direction seemingly require fundamental advances
in computational complexity. In this paper we propose a novel framework for
solving NP-hard qualitative reasoning problems which we refer to as dynamic
programming with sublinear partitioning. Using this technique we obtain a major
improvement of $O^*((\frac{cn}{\log{n}})^{n})$ for Allen&#39;s interval algebra. To
demonstrate that the technique is applicable to more domains we apply it to a
problem in qualitative spatial reasoning, the cardinal direction point algebra,
and solve it in $O^*((\frac{cn}{\log{n}})^{2n/3})$ time. Hence, not only do we
significantly advance the state-of-the-art for NP-hard qualitative reasoning
problems, but obtain a novel algorithmic technique that is likely applicable to
many problems where $2^{O(n)}$ time algorithms are unlikely.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: An exponential bound for simultaneous embeddings of planar graphs</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.15721"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.15721</id>
    <updated>2023-05-26T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Goenka_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ritesh Goenka&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Semnani_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Pardis Semnani&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Yip_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Chi Hoi Yip&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We show that there are $O(n \cdot 4^{n/11})$ planar graphs on $n$ vertices
which do not admit a simultaneous straight-line embedding on any $n$-point set
in the plane. In particular, this improves the best known bound $O(n!)$
significantly.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


</feed>
