<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title>Theory of Computing Report</title>
  <link rel="self" href=""/>
  <link href=""/>
  <id></id>
  <updated></updated>
  <generator uri="http://feedreader.github.io/">Pluto 1.6.2 on Ruby 3.0.4 (2022-04-12) [x86_64-linux]</generator>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Turing Machines with Two-level Memory: A Deep Look into the Input/Output Complexity</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09803"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09803</id>
    <updated>2022-08-23T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ma_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hengzhao Ma&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Li_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jianzhong Li&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gao_X/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Xiangyu Gao&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gao_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tianpeng Gao&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The input/output complexity, which is the complexity of data exchange between
the main memory and the external memory, has been elaborately studied by a lot
of former researchers. However, the existing works failed to consider the
input/output complexity in a computation model point of view. In this paper we
remedy this by proposing three variants of Turing machine that include external
memory and the mechanism of exchanging data between main memory and external
memory. Based on these new models, the input/output complexity is deeply
studied. We discussed the relationship between input/output complexity and the
other complexity measures such as time complexity and parameterized complexity,
which is not considered by former researchers. We also define the external
access trace complexity, which reflects the physical behavior of magnetic disks
and gives a theoretical evidence of IO-efficient algorithms.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Minimizing Visible Edges in Polyhedra</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09702"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09702</id>
    <updated>2022-08-23T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Toth_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Csaba D. T&amp;#xf3;th&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Urrutia_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jorge Urrutia&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Viglietta_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Giovanni Viglietta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We prove that, given a polyhedron $\mathcal P$ in $\mathbb{R}^3$, every point
in $\mathbb R^3$ that does not see any vertex of $\mathcal P$ must see eight or
more edges of $\mathcal P$; this bound is tight. More generally, this remains
true if $\mathcal P$ is any finite arrangement of internally disjoint polygons
in $\mathbb{R}^3$.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Area Coverage with Multiple Capacity-Constrained Robots</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09865"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09865</id>
    <updated>2022-08-23T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Agarwal_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Saurav Agarwal&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Akella_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Srinivas Akella&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The area coverage problem is the task of efficiently servicing a given
two-dimensional surface using sensors mounted on robots such as unmanned aerial
vehicles (UAVs) and unmanned ground vehicles (UGVs). We present a novel
formulation for generating coverage routes for multiple capacity-constrained
robots, where capacity can be specified in terms of battery life or flight
time. Traversing the environment incurs demands on the robot resources, which
have capacity limits. The central aspect of our approach is transforming the
area coverage problem into a line coverage problem (i.e., coverage of linear
features), and then generating routes that minimize the total cost of travel
while respecting the capacity constraints. We define two modes of travel: (1)
servicing and (2) deadheading, which correspond to whether a robot is
performing task-specific actions or not. Our formulation allows separate and
asymmetric travel costs and demands for the two modes. Furthermore, the cells
computed from cell decomposition, aimed at minimizing the number of turns, are
not required to be monotone polygons. We develop new procedures for cell
decomposition and generation of service tracks that can handle non-monotone
polygons with or without holes. We establish the efficacy of our algorithm on a
ground robot dataset with 25 indoor environments and an aerial robot dataset
with 300 outdoor environments. The algorithm generates solutions whose costs
are 10% lower on average than state-of-the-art methods. We additionally
demonstrate our algorithm in experiments with UAVs.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: On computing Ollivier-Ricci curvatures of graphs: fine-grained reductions and local algorithms</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09535"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09535</id>
    <updated>2022-08-23T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+DasGupta_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Bhaskar DasGupta&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Grigorescu_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Elena Grigorescu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mukherjee_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tamalika Mukherjee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Characterizing shapes of high-dimensional objects via Ricci curvatures plays
a critical role in many research areas in mathematics and physics. However,
even though several discretizations of Ricci curvatures for discrete
combinatorial objects such as networks have been proposed and studied by
mathematicians, the computational complexity aspects of these discretizations
have escaped the attention of theoretical computer scientists to a large
extent. In this paper, we study one such discretization, namely the
Ollivier-Ricci curvature, from the perspective of efficient computation by
fine-grained reductions and local query-based algorithms. Our main
contributions are the following.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(a) We relate our curvature computation problem to minimum weight perfect
matching problem on complete bipartite graphs via fine-grained reduction.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(b) We formalize the computational aspects of the curvature computation
problems in suitable frameworks so that they can be studied by researchers in
local algorithms.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(c) We provide the first known lower and upper bounds on queries for
query-based algorithms for the curvature computation problems in our local
algorithms framework.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We believe that our results bring forth an intriguing set of research
questions, motivated both in theory and practice, regarding designing efficient
algorithms for curvatures of objects.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Near-optimal fitting of ellipsoids to random points</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09493"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09493</id>
    <updated>2022-08-23T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Venkat_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Prayaag Venkat&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Turner_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Paxton Turner&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wein_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Alexander S. Wein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given independent standard Gaussian points $v_1, \ldots, v_n$ in dimension
$d$, for what values of $(n, d)$ does there exist with high probability an
origin-symmetric ellipsoid that simultaneously passes through all of the
points? This basic problem of fitting an ellipsoid to random points has
connections to low-rank matrix decompositions, independent component analysis,
and principal component analysis. Based on strong numerical evidence,
Saunderson, Parrilo, and Willsky [Proc. of Conference on Decision and Control,
pp. 6031-6036, 2013] conjecture that the ellipsoid fitting problem transitions
from feasible to infeasible as the number of points $n$ increases, with a sharp
threshold at $n \sim d^2/4$. We resolve this conjecture up to logarithmic
factors by constructing a fitting ellipsoid for some $n = \Omega( \,
d^2/\log^5(d) \,)$, improving prior work of Ghosh et al. [Proc. of Symposium on
Foundations of Computer Science, pp. 954-965, 2020] that requires $n =
o(d^{3/2})$. Our proof demonstrates feasibility of the least squares
construction of Saunderson et al. using a careful analysis of the eigenvectors
and eigenvalues of a certain non-standard random matrix.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Packet Forwarding with a Locally Bursty Adversary</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09522"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09522</id>
    <updated>2022-08-23T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rosenbaum_W/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Will Rosenbaum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We consider packet forwarding in the adversarial queueing theory (AQT) model
introduced by Borodin et al. We introduce a refinement of the AQT $(\rho,
\sigma)$-bounded adversary, which we call a \emph{locally bursty adversary}
(LBA) that parameterizes injection patterns jointly by edge utilization and
packet origin. For constant ($O(1)$) parameters, the LBA model is strictly more
permissive than the $(\rho, \sigma)$ model. For example, there are injection
patterns in the LBA model with constant parameters that can only be realized as
$(\rho, \sigma)$-bounded injection patterns with $\rho + \sigma = \Omega(n)$
(where $n$ is the network size). We show that the LBA model (unlike the $(\rho,
\sigma)$ model) is closed under packet bundling and discretization operations.
Thus, the LBA model allows one to reduce the study of general (uniform)
capacity networks and inhomogenous packet sizes to unit capacity networks with
homogeneous packets.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the algorithmic side, we focus on information gathering networks -- i.e.,
networks in which all packets share a common destination, and the union of
packet routes forms a tree. We show that the Odd-Even Downhill (OED) forwarding
protocol described independently by Dobrev et al.\ and Patt-Shamir and
Rosenbaum achieves buffer space usage of $O(\log n)$ against all LBAs with
constant parameters. OED is a local protocol, but we show that the upper bound
is tight even when compared to centralized protocols. Our lower bound for the
LBA model is in contrast to the $(\rho, \sigma)$-model, where centralized
protocols can achieve worst-case buffer space usage $O(1)$ for $\rho, \sigma =
O(1)$, while the $O(\log n)$ upper bound for OED is optimal only for local
protocols.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: An $O(k\log n)$ Time Fourier Set Query Algorithm</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09634"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09634</id>
    <updated>2022-08-23T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gao_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yeqi Gao&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Song_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zhao Song&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sun_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Baocheng Sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fourier transformation is an extensively studied problem in many research
fields. It has many applications in machine learning, signal processing,
compressed sensing, and so on. In many real-world applications, approximated
Fourier transformation is sufficient and we only need to do the Fourier
transform on a subset of coordinates. Given a vector $x \in \mathbb{C}^{n}$, an
approximation parameter $\epsilon$ and a query set $S \subset [n]$ of size $k$,
we propose an algorithm to compute an approximate Fourier transform result $x&#39;$
which uses $O(\epsilon^{-1} k \log(n/\delta))$ Fourier measurements, runs in
$O(\epsilon^{-1} k \log(n/\delta))$ time and outputs a vector $x&#39;$ such that
$\| ( x&#39; - \widehat{x} )_S \|_2^2 \leq \epsilon \| \widehat{x}_{\bar{S}} \|_2^2
+ \delta \| \widehat{x} \|_1^2 $ holds with probability of at least $9/10$.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: The computational complexity of some explainable clustering problems</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09643"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09643</id>
    <updated>2022-08-23T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Laber_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Eduardo Sany Laber&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the computational complexity of some explainable clustering problems
in the framework proposed by [Dasgupta et al., ICML 2020], where explainability
is achieved via axis-aligned decision trees. We consider the $k$-means,
$k$-medians, $k$-centers and the spacing cost functions. We prove that the
first three are hard to optimize while the latter can be optimized in
polynomial time.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Solving systems of linear equations through zero forcing set and application to lights out</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09731"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09731</id>
    <updated>2022-08-23T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wang_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jianbo Wang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Xu_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Chao Xu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zhou_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Siyun Zhou&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let $\mathbb{F}$ be any field, we consider solving $Ax=b$ repeatedly for a
matrix $A\in\mathbb{F}^{n\times n}$ of $m$ non-zero elements, and multiple
different $b\in\mathbb{F}^{n}$. If we are given a zero forcing set of $A$ of
size $k$, we can then build a data structure in $O(mk)$ time, such that each
instance of $Ax=b$ can be solved in $O(k^2+m)$ time. As an application, we show
how the lights out game in an $n\times n$ grid is solved in $O(n^3)$ time, and
then improve the running time to $O(n^\omega\log n)$ by exploiting the repeated
structure in grids.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: A Work-Efficient Parallel Algorithm for Longest Increasing Subsequence</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09809"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09809</id>
    <updated>2022-08-23T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gu_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yan Gu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Shen_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zheqi Shen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sun_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yihan Sun&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wan_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zijin Wan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper studies parallel algorithms for the longest increasing subsequence
(LIS) problem. Let $n$ be the input size and $k$ be the LIS length of the
input. Sequentially, LIS is a simple textbook problem that can be solved using
dynamic programming (DP) in $O(n\log n)$ work. However, parallelizing LIS is a
long-standing challenge. We are unaware of any parallel LIS algorithm that has
optimal $O(n\log n)$ work and non-trivial parallelism (i.e., $\tilde{O}(k)$ or
$o(n)$ span). Here, the work of a parallel algorithm is the total number of
operations, and the span is the longest dependent instructions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper proposes a parallel LIS algorithm that costs $O(n\log k)$ work,
$\tilde{O}(k)$ span, and $O(n)$ space, and is \emph{much simpler} than the
previous parallel LIS algorithms. We also generalize the algorithm to a
weighted version of LIS, which maximizes the weighted sum for all objects in an
increasing subsequence. Our weighted LIS algorithm has $O(n\log^2 n)$ work and
$\tilde{O}(k)$ span.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also implemented our parallel LIS algorithms. Due to simplicity, our
implementation is light-weighted, efficient, and scalable. On input size
$10^9$, our LIS algorithm outperforms a highly-optimized sequential algorithm
(with $O(n\log k)$ cost) on inputs with $k\le 3\times 10^5$. Our algorithm is
also much faster than the best existing parallel implementation by Shen et al.
on all input instances.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Teaching the Burrows-Wheeler Transform via the Positional Burrows-Wheeler Transform</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09840"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09840</id>
    <updated>2022-08-23T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gagie_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Travis Gagie&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Manzini_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Giovanni Manzini&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sciortino_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Marinella Sciortino&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Burrows-Wheeler Transform (BWT) is often taught in undergraduate courses
on algorithmic bioinformatics, because it underlies the FM-index and thus
important tools such as Bowtie and BWA. Its admirers consider the BWT a thing
of beauty but, despite thousands of pages being written about it over nearly
thirty years, to undergraduates seeing it for the first time it still often
seems like magic. Some who persevere are later shown the Positional BWT (PBWT),
which was published twenty years after the BWT. In this paper we argue that the
PBWT should be taught {\em before} the BWT.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We first use the PBWT&#39;s close relation to a right-to-left radix sort to
explain how to use it as a fast and space-efficient index for {\em positional
search} on a set of strings (that is, given a pattern and a position, quickly
list the strings containing that pattern starting in that position). We then
observe that {\em prefix search} (listing all the strings that start with the
pattern) is an easy special case of positional search, and that prefix search
on the suffixes of a single string is equivalent to {\em substring search} in
that string (listing all the starting positions of occurrences of the pattern
in the string).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Storing na\&quot;ively a PBWT of the suffixes of a string is space-{\em
inefficient} but, in even reasonably small examples, most of its columns are
nearly the same. It is not difficult to show that if we store a PBWT of the
cyclic shifts of the string, instead of its suffixes, then all the columns are
exactly the same -- and equal to the BWT of the string. Thus we can teach the
BWT and the FM-index via the PBWT.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Counting Cycles on Planar Graphs in Subexponential Time</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09948"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09948</id>
    <updated>2022-08-23T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Cai_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jin-Yi Cai&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Maran_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ashwin Maran&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the problem of counting all cycles or self-avoiding walks (SAWs) on
triangulated planar graphs. We present a subexponential $2^{O(\sqrt{n})}$ time
algorithm for this counting problem. Among the technical ingredients used in
this algorithm are the planar separator theorem and a delicate analysis using
pairs of Motzkin paths and Motzkin numbers. We can then adapt this algorithm to
uniformly sample SAWs, in subexponential time. Our work is motivated by the
problem of gerrymandered districting maps.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Bipartite Matchings with Group Fairness and Individual Fairness Constraints</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09951"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09951</id>
    <updated>2022-08-23T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Panda_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Atasi Panda&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Louis_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Anand Louis&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nibhorkar_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Prajakta Nibhorkar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We address group as well as individual fairness constraints in matchings in
the context of assigning items to platforms. Each item belongs to certain
groups and has a preference ordering over platforms. Each platform enforces
group fairness by specifying an upper and a lower bound on the number of items
that can be matched to it from each group. There could be multiple optimal
solutions that satisfy the group fairness constraints. To achieve individual
fairness, we introduce `probabilistic individual fairness&#39;, where the goal is
to compute a distribution over `group fair&#39; matchings such that every item has
a reasonable probability of being matched to a platform among its top choices.
In the case where each item belongs to exactly one group, we provide a
polynomial-time algorithm that computes a probabilistic individually fair
distribution over group fair matchings. When an item can belong to multiple
groups, and the group fairness constraints are specified as only upper bounds,
we rehash the same algorithm to achieve three different polynomial-time
approximation algorithms.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Locally Defined Independence Systems on Graphs</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.10003"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.10003</id>
    <updated>2022-08-23T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Amano_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yuki Amano&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The maximization for the independence systems defined on graphs is a
generalization of combinatorial optimization problems such as the maximum
$b$-matching, the unweighted MAX-SAT, the matchoid, and the maximum timed
matching problems. In this paper, we consider the problem under the local
oracle model to investigate the global approximability of the problem by using
the local approximability. We first analyze two simple algorithms FixedOrder
and Greedy for the maximization under the model, which shows that they have no
constant approximation ratio. Here algorithms FixedOrder and Greedy apply local
oracles with fixed and greedy orders of vertices, respectively. We then propose
two approximation algorithms for the $k$-degenerate graphs, whose approximation
ratios are $\alpha +2k -2$ and $\alpha k$, where $\alpha$ is the approximation
ratio of local oracles. The second one can be generalized to the hypergraph
setting. We also propose an $(\alpha + k)$-approximation algorithm for
bipartite graphs, in which the local independence systems in the one-side of
vertices are $k$-systems with independence oracles.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Simple and Optimal Stochastic Gradient Methods for Nonsmooth Nonconvex Optimization</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.10025"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.10025</id>
    <updated>2022-08-23T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Li_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zhize Li&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Li_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jian Li&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose and analyze several stochastic gradient algorithms for finding
stationary points or local minimum in nonconvex, possibly with nonsmooth
regularizer, finite-sum and online optimization problems. First, we propose a
simple proximal stochastic gradient algorithm based on variance reduction
called ProxSVRG+. We provide a clean and tight analysis of ProxSVRG+, which
shows that it outperforms the deterministic proximal gradient descent (ProxGD)
for a wide range of minibatch sizes, hence solves an open problem proposed in
Reddi et al. (2016b). Also, ProxSVRG+ uses much less proximal oracle calls than
ProxSVRG (Reddi et al., 2016b) and extends to the online setting by avoiding
full gradient computations. Then, we further propose an optimal algorithm,
called SSRGD, based on SARAH (Nguyen et al., 2017) and show that SSRGD further
improves the gradient complexity of ProxSVRG+ and achieves the optimal upper
bound, matching the known lower bound of (Fang et al., 2018; Li et al., 2021).
Moreover, we show that both ProxSVRG+ and SSRGD enjoy automatic adaptation with
local structure of the objective function such as the Polyak-\L{}ojasiewicz
(PL) condition for nonconvex functions in the finite-sum case, i.e., we prove
that both of them can automatically switch to faster global linear convergence
without any restart performed in prior work ProxSVRG (Reddi et al., 2016b).
Finally, we focus on the more challenging problem of finding an $(\epsilon,
\delta)$-local minimum instead of just finding an $\epsilon$-approximate
(first-order) stationary point (which may be some bad unstable saddle points).
We show that SSRGD can find an $(\epsilon, \delta)$-local minimum by simply
adding some random perturbations. Our algorithm is almost as simple as its
counterpart for finding stationary points, and achieves similar optimal rates.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Socially Fair Center-based and Linear Subspace Clustering</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.10095"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.10095</id>
    <updated>2022-08-23T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gorantla_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sruthi Gorantla&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gowda_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Kishen N. Gowda&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Deshpande_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Amit Deshpande&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Louis_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Anand Louis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Center-based clustering (e.g., $k$-means, $k$-medians) and clustering using
linear subspaces are two most popular techniques to partition real-world data
into smaller clusters. However, when the data consists of sensitive demographic
groups, significantly different clustering cost per point for different
sensitive groups can lead to fairness-related harms (e.g., different
quality-of-service). The goal of socially fair clustering is to minimize the
maximum cost of clustering per point over all groups. In this work, we propose
a unified framework to solve socially fair center-based clustering and linear
subspace clustering, and give practical, efficient approximation algorithms for
these problems. We do extensive experiments to show that on multiple benchmark
datasets our algorithms either closely match or outperform state-of-the-art
baselines.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: \~{O}ptimal Dual Vertex Failure Connectivity Labels</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.10168"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.10168</id>
    <updated>2022-08-23T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Parter_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Merav Parter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Petruschka_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Asaf Petruschka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this paper we present succinct labeling schemes for supporting
connectivity queries under vertex faults. For a given $n$-vertex graph $G$, an
$f$-VFT (resp., EFT) connectivity labeling scheme is a distributed data
structure that assigns each of the graph edges and vertices a short label, such
that given the labels of a vertex pair $u$ and $v$, and the labels of at most
$f$ failing vertices (resp., edges) $F$, one can determine if $u$ and $v$ are
connected in $G \setminus F$. The primary complexity measure is the length of
the individual labels. Since their introduction by [Courcelle, Twigg, STACS
&#39;07], FT labeling schemes have been devised only for a limited collection of
graph families. A recent work [Dory and Parter, PODC 2021] provided EFT
labeling schemes for general graphs under edge failures, leaving the vertex
failure case fairly open. We provide the first sublinear $f$-VFT labeling
schemes for $f \geq 2$ for any $n$-vertex graph. Our key result is $2$-VFT
connectivity labels with $O(\log^3 n)$ bits. Our constructions are based on
analyzing the structure of dual failure replacement paths on top of the
well-known heavy-light tree decomposition technique of [Sleator and Tarjan,
STOC 1981]. We also provide $f$-VFT labels with sub-linear length (in $|V|$)
for any $f=o(\log\log n)$, that are based on a reduction to the existing EFT
labels.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Deterministic Graph-Walking Program Mining</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.10290"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.10290</id>
    <updated>2022-08-23T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Belcak_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Peter Belcak&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wattenhofer_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Roger Wattenhofer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Owing to their versatility, graph structures admit representations of
intricate relationships between the separate entities comprising the data. We
formalise the notion of connection between two vertex sets in terms of edge and
vertex features by introducing graph-walking programs. We give two algorithms
for mining of deterministic graph-walking programs that yield programs in the
order of increasing length. These programs characterise linear long-distance
relationships between the given two vertex sets in the context of the whole
graph.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">David Eppstein: Permuted points of interest</title>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/08/22/permuted-points-interest.html"/>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/08/22/permuted-points-interest</id>
    <updated>2022-08-22T17:10:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;Suppose you have a map, with certain points of interest marked. To avoid cluttering the map with the labels of these points, you want to list the labels in a line down the side of the map, with each point of interest connected to its label by a line segment. Preferably, the line segments should not cross each other, as they did when I tried to match the sidebar to the points in this example from Google Maps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/2022/coffee-near-ryerson.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map of Toronto Metropolitan University (formerly Ryerson University) and its surrounding neighborhood, from Google Maps, with coffee shops marked and connected by line segments to the sidebar&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;max-width:720px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to find a non-crossing labeling (for points with distinct &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;\(y\)-coordinates)&lt;/span&gt; would be to make all of the line segments horizontal, and to sort the list of labels by the height of the points. However, that’s far from the only possibility. How many different permutations of the labels can a single set of points have?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The obvious bound is factorial, but the answer turns out to be much smaller than that. To see this, assume without loss of generality that the points are in general position (collinearities or equal coordinates can only reduce the number of labeling orders).  Consider any non-crossing labeling, and then adjust the right endpoint of each line segment (the one on the point of interest) to have the same &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;\(y\)-coordinate&lt;/span&gt; as its left endpoint, so that all of the line segments become straight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/2022/straighten-rake.svg&quot; alt=&quot;A vertical line connected to points of interest by line segments, and those same line segments straightened to horizontal by adjusting the y-coordinates of their right endpoints&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;max-width:720px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, connect the right endpoints of this diagram in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cartesian_tree&quot;&gt;Cartesian tree&lt;/a&gt;. This is a non-crossing binary tree, rooted at the rightmost endpoint, with two subtrees constructed recursively in the same way for the parts of the diagram above and below the root segment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/2022/cartesian-rake.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Cartesian tree on the endpoints of the horizontal line segments&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of possible binary trees is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catalan_number&quot;&gt;Catalan number&lt;/a&gt;, and each binary tree uniquely determines a labeling order. To reconstruct the labeling from the tree, count the number of segments that lie above the root segment in the tree, and draw a line segment connecting the corresponding point of interest to the sidebar line, splitting the remaining points of interest into the corresponding number of points above and below the segment. Combinatorially, there is only one way of making a split that subdivides the remaining points into subsets of the desired sizes. Then continue recursively in the same way within the two subtrees above and below the root segment. You may need to adjust the geometric positions of the left endpoints of some of the line segments to avoid crossings, and this adjustment may not be possible for some binary trees, but when it is possible there is only one permutation of the points that you can get for each tree. Therefore, there is at most a Catalan number of labeling orders!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same argument also works to count labelings with L-shaped connectors, horizontal from the label to the &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;\(x\)-coordinate&lt;/span&gt; of the point of interest and then vertical up or down to the point of interest. When the points of interest all have distinct coordinates, no adjustment of positions is ever necessary, and every binary tree produces a valid labeling order, so the number of labeling orders is exactly a Catalan number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some sets of points with straight line segment labelings, you can again get the maximum possible Catalan number of distinct labeling orders. This is true, for instance, when each point of interest is to the right of all of the lines through pairs of points to the left of it (including candidate left endpoints of connectors), because in this case the combinatorics of straight line connectors and &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;L-shaped&lt;/span&gt; connectors are the same. (For details of this equivalence, see my book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/forbidden/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Forbidden Configurations in Discrete Geometry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Chapter 14: “The Stretched Geometry of Permutations”.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/web/@11011110/108869453500480918&quot;&gt;(Discuss on Mastodon)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By David Eppstein&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
      <uri>https://11011110.github.io/blog/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Computational Complexity: 20 Years of the Computational Complexity Weblog</title>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/08/20-years-of-computational-complexity.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-5383207883567807338</id>
    <updated>2022-08-22T13:04:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEi6GDCODRrARsTAby27oCbx62tuXwL99PLAQoF3EAnHJ_VYJHxBeQBEW4WDsti4OYckqE0f6i3_pnSOpEoApn4H-Wxdn3XoZzhM5W-xjKtAdVcWE3-61i-McxSL6kosop34uFHoMflbs2O4lHftdkjoW0SCudrJf3pC3YtQY7J1nmhUnc9VBQ/s1024/DALL%C2%B7E%202022-08-22%2008.00.34%20-%20birthday%20cake%20with%20green%20frosting%20and%2020%20candles.png&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Birthday Cake&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; data-original-height=&quot;1024&quot; data-original-width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEi6GDCODRrARsTAby27oCbx62tuXwL99PLAQoF3EAnHJ_VYJHxBeQBEW4WDsti4OYckqE0f6i3_pnSOpEoApn4H-Wxdn3XoZzhM5W-xjKtAdVcWE3-61i-McxSL6kosop34uFHoMflbs2O4lHftdkjoW0SCudrJf3pC3YtQY7J1nmhUnc9VBQ/w200-h200/DALL%C2%B7E%202022-08-22%2008.00.34%20-%20birthday%20cake%20with%20green%20frosting%20and%2020%20candles.png&quot; title=&quot;Dall-E baked us a cake&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2002/08/this-is-my-complexity-web-log.html&quot;&gt;first posted&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;on&amp;nbsp;this blog twenty years ago today, still the oldest and longest running weblog in theoretical computer science, possibly in all of computer science. In those twenty years we&#39;ve had nearly 3000 posts and over 23,000 comments and 10,000,000 page views. Bill Gasarch &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2007/03/complexity-blog-lives.html&quot;&gt;joined me&lt;/a&gt; officially as a co-blogger over 15 years ago on March 30, 2007.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ve seen &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2014/12/favorite-theorems-recap.html&quot;&gt;major results in computational complexity&lt;/a&gt; but the biggest challenges remain, in particular major separations of complexity classes. We&#39;ve also had a front row seat to a computing revolution with&amp;nbsp; the growth of cloud and mobile computing, social networks connecting us for better or for worse, and incredible successes of machine learning. It&#39;s almost as though we&#39;ve been handed an oracle that gives us much of the goodness of P = NP while leaving cryptography intact.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What will the next twenty years bring? We&#39;ll be watching, posting and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/fortnow&quot;&gt;tweeting&lt;/a&gt;. Hope you keep reading and commenting.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Lance Fortnow&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Richard Lipton: A Theoretical Question About UAPs</title>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/08/20/a-theoretical-question-about-uaps/"/>
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=20310</id>
    <updated>2022-08-20T04:27:31+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;
&lt;font color=&quot;#0044cc&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;What should be the Bayesian prior for a new NASA study?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;font color=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;image alignright&quot;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/08/20/a-theoretical-question-about-uaps/spergelinterstellar/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-20313&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;20313&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/08/20/a-theoretical-question-about-uaps/spergelinterstellar/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/SpergelInterstellar.png?fit=206%2C261&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;206,261&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;SpergelInterstellar&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/SpergelInterstellar.png?fit=206%2C261&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/SpergelInterstellar.png?fit=206%2C261&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/SpergelInterstellar.png?resize=155%2C195&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;155&quot; height=&quot;195&quot; class=&quot;alignright wp-image-20313&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;caption alignright&quot;&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;-2&quot;&gt;Crop from &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8216;Interstellar&amp;#8217;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://paw.princeton.edu/article/paw-goes-movies-%E2%80%98interstellar-professor-david-spergel-82&quot;&gt;discussion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
David Spergel is a physics professor emeritus of Princeton University who now heads the James Simons Foundation. He shared the 2010 Shaw Prize and 2018 Breakthrough Prize with Charles Bennett of Johns Hopkins and others of the team on the Wilkinson Microwave Anisotropy Probe (&lt;a href=&quot;https://map.gsfc.nasa.gov/&quot;&gt;WMAP&lt;/a&gt;), whose mapping of fluctuations in the cosmic microwave background has channeled numerous physical theories. He has recently been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2022/06/09/nasa-ufo-uap-extraterrestrial-space/&quot;&gt;appointed&lt;/a&gt; to lead a new NASA &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/with-new-study-nasa-seeks-the-science-behind-ufos/&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; on unidentified aerial phenomena (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unidentified_flying_object&quot;&gt;UAP&lt;/a&gt;s, previously called UFOs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today we wish him &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auguri_professore&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;auguri&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on the project and pose a theoretical question on what its baseline should be. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I knew David both at Princeton and at Oxford. He was one class after me, 1982 to my 1981. At Oxford in 1983, he worked for a year under Professor James Binney, a Fellow of my college (Merton). David and I played squash at Oxford once or twice, also with a mutual friend. I don&amp;#8217;t remember what, if any, physics or mathematics we discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
David attracted my attention in 2014 when he was one of the first &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantamagazine.org/a-bold-critic-of-the-big-bangs-smoking-gun-20140703/&quot;&gt;critics&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/nature.2015.16830&quot;&gt;claim&lt;/a&gt; by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BICEP_and_Keck_Array#BICEP2&quot;&gt;BICEP2&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planck_(spacecraft)&quot;&gt;Planck&lt;/a&gt; probe teams to have proved the existence of gravitational waves with &amp;#8220;five sigma&amp;#8221; confidence. I was concerned because in myriad communications with the International Chess Federation (FIDE) I have cited &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B5%5Csigma%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{5&amp;#92;sigma}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; as the agreed scientific standard of statistical proof. Yet here was a case of a &amp;#8220;five-sigma&amp;#8221; claim being false for reasons of incorrect modeling, in this case overlooking effects of interstellar dust. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; UAPs and von Neumann Probes &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
David has on his Princeton &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.astro.princeton.edu/~dns/&quot;&gt;webpage&lt;/a&gt; a photo that is heartening for us to see:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/08/20/a-theoretical-question-about-uaps/spergeltheory/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-20314&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;20314&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/08/20/a-theoretical-question-about-uaps/spergeltheory/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/SpergelTheory.jpg?fit=640%2C480&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;640,480&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;4.9&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Canon PowerShot SD500&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1166654599&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;23.1&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0.04&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;SpergelTheory&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/SpergelTheory.jpg?fit=300%2C225&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/SpergelTheory.jpg?fit=600%2C450&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/SpergelTheory.jpg?resize=384%2C288&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;384&quot; height=&quot;288&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter wp-image-20314&quot; srcset=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/SpergelTheory.jpg?w=640&amp;amp;ssl=1 640w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/SpergelTheory.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/SpergelTheory.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/SpergelTheory.jpg?resize=200%2C150&amp;amp;ssl=1 200w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 384px) 100vw, 384px&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In this spirit, we pose a theoretical question about the UAP/UFO subject. I must confess that despite my long childhood interest in UFOs stemming from my father&amp;#8217;s amateur &lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2011/05/18/my-father-robert-james-regan/&quot;&gt;studies&lt;/a&gt;, I have been too busy these past two years to do more than follow the recent hearings about them at the level of indirect &lt;a href=&quot;https://marginalrevolution.com/?s=UAP&quot;&gt;coverage&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;em&gt;Marginal Revolution&lt;/em&gt; blog. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The center of gravity of the latest observations by pilots and other military personnel has not been &amp;#8220;close encounters&amp;#8221; or even viewings of formations of saucer-shaped large craft. Instead it has been visual and sensory recordings of relatively small objects moving &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livescience.com/ufo-hearing-metallic-hypersonic-flying-object&quot;&gt;over&lt;/a&gt; ocean waters at hypersonic speeds and also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.history.com/news/ufo-sightings-speed-appearance-movement&quot;&gt;under&lt;/a&gt; water at speeds gauged up to 70 knots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Before his terminal cancer in the 1950s, John von Neumann drafted a &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/theoryofselfrepr00vonn_0&quot;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Theory of Self-Reproducing Automata&lt;/em&gt;, which was completed in 1966 by William Burks. It described the physical representation of autonomous self-reproducing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-replicating_spacecraft#Von_Neumann_probes&quot;&gt;probes&lt;/a&gt; capable of interstellar travel. An avenue toward a working model was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rfreitas.com/Astro/ReproJBISJuly1980.htm&quot;&gt;detailed&lt;/a&gt; as long ago as 1980, and a long current study is discussed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.centauri-dreams.org/2022/07/12/probing-the-galaxy-self-reproduction-and-its-consequences/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
These probes avoid constraints on the duration of space travel by biological beings. Humanity has already sent un-crewed craft out into space. It is natural that we might aim probes toward exoplanets long before we can consider sending human travelers. We might achieve a radius of some tens of light years for such missions&amp;#8212;maybe minus the self-replicating part&amp;#8212;in the not too distant future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; Our Question &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Flipping this logic around leads straightaway to our question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; What should the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prior_probability&quot;&gt;Bayesian prior&lt;/a&gt; be for expectations about UAPs? Should it have highest weight on their being wholly terrestrial, or on their being un-crewed probes from other civilizations? &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
We note that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.space.com/nasa-unidentified-aerial-phenomena-science-panel&quot;&gt;initial&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnet.com/science/space/nasa-to-launch-scientific-study-of-ufos/&quot;&gt;communications&lt;/a&gt; from NASA were quick to say that `there is no evidence that the phenomena are extra-terrestrial in origin.&amp;#8217; But we are not talking about the stage of evidence. We are asking theoretically, in the same vein as longtime discussion of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnet.com/science/space/nasa-to-launch-scientific-study-of-ufos/&quot;&gt;Drake Equation&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fermi_paradox&quot;&gt;Fermi Paradox&lt;/a&gt;: What is the most likely status on &lt;em&gt;a-priori&lt;/em&gt; grounds, based on what we have learned about space and technology over the past century?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The baseline is also relevant to the drift of a companion &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/nasa-rsquo-s-ufo-study-isn-rsquo-t-really-looking-for-space-aliens/&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;em&gt;Scientific American&lt;/em&gt; titled, &amp;#8220;NASA’s UFO Study Isn’t Really Looking for Space Aliens.&amp;#8221; The search for terrestrial explanations of these phenomena is sharpened if it must bear some prior burden of proof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; Open Problems &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
What do you think of our question? There has been &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.effectivealtruism.org/posts/Y7hX9T6eA7kQQNaH5/an-ea-case-for-interest-in-uaps-ufos-and-an-idea-as-to-what&quot;&gt;some&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://theline.substack.com/p/robert-jago-if-aliens-have-really&quot;&gt;discussion&lt;/a&gt; of von Neumann probes as UAPs, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.universetoday.com/154949/why-would-an-alien-civilization-send-out-von-neumann-probes-lots-of-reasons-says-a-new-study/&quot;&gt;recently&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.cosmoquest.org/forum/science-and-space/life-in-space/77744-&quot;&gt;years ago&lt;/a&gt;, but they are absent from Robin Hanson&amp;#8217;s discussion of UAP priors &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.overcomingbias.com/2021/06/on-ufo-as-aliens-priors.html&quot;&gt;a year ago&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By KWRegan&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Lipton</name>
      <uri>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Gil Kalai: Alexander A. Gaifullin: Many  27-vertex Triangulations of Manifolds Like the Octonionic Projective Plane (Not Even One Was Known Before).</title>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/08/19/alexander-a-gaifullin-many-27-vertex-triangulations-of-manifolds-like-the-octonionic-projective-plane-not-even-one-was-known-before/"/>
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=23229</id>
    <updated>2022-08-19T11:37:49+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; data-attachment-id=&quot;23247&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/08/19/alexander-a-gaifullin-many-27-vertex-triangulations-of-manifolds-like-the-octonionic-projective-plane-not-even-one-was-known-before/ggkb/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/ggkb.png&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1920,1080&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;ggkb&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/ggkb.png?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/ggkb.png?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-23247&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/ggkb.png&quot; alt=&quot;ggkb&quot; width=&quot;1920&quot; height=&quot;1080&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/ggkb.png 1920w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/ggkb.png?w=150&amp;amp;h=84 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/ggkb.png?w=300&amp;amp;h=169 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/ggkb.png?w=768&amp;amp;h=432 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/ggkb.png?w=1024&amp;amp;h=576 1024w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;From top left clockwise: Alexander Gaifullin, Denis Gorodkov, Ulrich Brehm, Wolfgang Kühnel &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the paper:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alexander A. Gaifullin: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.08507&quot;&gt;634 vertex-transitive and more than 10¹⁰³ non-vertex-transitive 27-vertex triangulations of manifolds like the octonionic projective plane&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract with annotation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1987 Brehm and Kühnel showed that any combinatorial &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;d&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;-manifold with less than &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=3d%2F2%2B3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=3d%2F2%2B3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=3d%2F2%2B3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;3d/2+3&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; vertices is PL homeomorphic to the sphere and any combinatorial &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;d&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;-manifold with exactly &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=3d%2F2%2B3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=3d%2F2%2B3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=3d%2F2%2B3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;3d/2+3&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; vertices is PL homeomorphic to either the sphere or a manifold like a projective plane in the sense of Eells and Kuiper. The latter possibility may occur for &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d+%5Cin+%5C%7B2%2C4%2C8%2C16%5C%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d+%5Cin+%5C%7B2%2C4%2C8%2C16%5C%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d+%5Cin+%5C%7B2%2C4%2C8%2C16%5C%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;d &amp;#92;in &amp;#92;{2,4,8,16&amp;#92;}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;This is a lovely theorem and the proof is based on Morse theoretic ideas, The study was motivated by the theory of tight embeddings of manifolds in differential geometry.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There exist a unique 6-vertex triangulation of &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+RP%5E2&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+RP%5E2&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+RP%5E2&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;#92;mathbb RP^2&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;This is a wonderful object obtained by identifying opposite faces of an icosahedron.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a unique 9-vertex triangulation of &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+CP%5E2&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+CP%5E2&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+CP%5E2&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;#92;mathbb CP^2&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;This is an amazing mathematical construction by Kühnel and Lassman from 1983. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and at least three 15-vertex triangulations of &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+HP%5E2&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+HP%5E2&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+HP%5E2&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;#92;mathbb HP^2&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;. (We mentioned it &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/11/14/to-cheer-you-up-in-difficult-times-13-triangulating-real-projective-spaces-with-subexponentially-many-vertices/&quot;&gt;in this post&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;Those were constructed in 1992 by Brehm and Kühnel. Gorodkov proved in 2019 that the Brehm–Kühnel complexes are indeed PL homeomorphic to &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+HP%5E2&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+HP%5E2&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+HP%5E2&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;#92;mathbb HP^2&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;.   &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, until now, the question of whether there exists a 27-vertex triangulation of a manifold like the octonionic projective plane has remained open. We solve this problem by constructing a lot of examples of such triangulations. Namely, we construct 634 vertex-transitive 27-vertex combinatorial 16-manifolds like the octonionic projective plane. Four of them have symmetry group &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_3%5E3%5Crtimes+C_%7B13%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_3%5E3%5Crtimes+C_%7B13%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_3%5E3%5Crtimes+C_%7B13%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;C_3^3&amp;#92;rtimes C_{13}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; of order 351, and the other 630 have symmetry group &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_3%5E3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_3%5E3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_3%5E3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;C_3^3&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; of order 27. Further, we construct more than &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=10%5E%7B103%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=10%5E%7B103%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=10%5E%7B103%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;10^{103}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; non-vertex-transitive 27-vertex combinatorial 16-manifolds like the octonionic projective plane. Most of them have trivial symmetry group, but there are also symmetry groups &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;C_3&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;, &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_3%5E2&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_3%5E2&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_3%5E2&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;C_3^2&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;, and &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_%7B13%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_%7B13%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_%7B13%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;C_{13}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;. We conjecture that all the triangulations constructed are PL homeomorphic to the octonionic projective plane &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+O+P%5E2&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+O+P%5E2&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+O+P%5E2&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;#92;mathbb O P^2&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;. Nevertheless, we have no proof of this fact so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;(Actually one can even expect that in the Brehm-Kühnel theorems all triangulations of &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;d&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; manifolds with &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=3d%2F2%2B3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=3d%2F2%2B3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=3d%2F2%2B3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;3d/2+3&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; vertices are PL projective planes over the Reals, Quaternions or Octanions.) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#0000ff;&quot;&gt;I heard about the new result from Wolfgang Kühnel who wrote me: &amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;m quite surprised that an object with &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#0000ff;&quot;&gt;such a huge &lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;-vector can be constructed at all.&amp;#8221;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Diversion: Moore Graphs of girth five&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seek for a triangulation of a manifold like a projective plane with &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=3d%2F2%2B3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=3d%2F2%2B3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=3d%2F2%2B3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;3d/2+3&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; vertices (now completed by Gaifullin) reminded me of the situation of Moore graphs of girth five. A Moore graph is a regular &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;d&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;-graph with diameter &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;k&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;, and girth &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2k%2B1&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2k%2B1&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2k%2B1&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;2k+1&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;. (It must have &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=1%2Bd+%5Csum_%7Bk%3D0%7D%5E%7Bk-1%7D%28d-1%29%5Ek&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=1%2Bd+%5Csum_%7Bk%3D0%7D%5E%7Bk-1%7D%28d-1%29%5Ek&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=1%2Bd+%5Csum_%7Bk%3D0%7D%5E%7Bk-1%7D%28d-1%29%5Ek&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;1+d &amp;#92;sum_{k=0}^{k-1}(d-1)^k&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; vertices.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;b&gt;Hoffman–Singleton theorem&lt;/b&gt; states that any Moore graph with girth 5 must have degree 2, 3, 7, or 57.  There are known examples for degrees 2, 3 and 7, and the existence of a Moore graph of girth 5 and degree 57 is one of the great mysteries of mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Neighborly &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;2d&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;-manifolds&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can ask, more generally, about &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%28d%2B1%29&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%28d%2B1%29&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%28d%2B1%29&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;(d+1)&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;-neighborly triangulations of &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;2d&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; manifolds, namely triangulations for which every &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d%2B1&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d%2B1&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d%2B1&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;d+1&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; vertices form a face. (Triangulations of &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;2d&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;-manifolds with &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=3d%2B3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=3d%2B3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=3d%2B3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;3d+3&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; vertices must be &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%28d%2B1%29&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%28d%2B1%29&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%28d%2B1%29&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;(d+1)&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;-neighborly.) For &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d%3D1&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d%3D1&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d%3D1&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;d=1&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; this is essentially the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heawood_conjecture&quot;&gt;Heawood conjecture&lt;/a&gt;.  Ringel and Youngs showed, that 2-neighborly triangulation exists for all surfaces except for the Klein bottle. In dimensions greater than 2 only a small number of examples are known. Beside the triangulations that we talked about above, I am aware of two additional examples:  In dimension 4: 16-vertex K3 surface (Casella-Kühnel 2001);  In dimension 6: 13-vertex triangulations of  &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=S%5E3+%5Ctimes+S%5E3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=S%5E3+%5Ctimes+S%5E3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=S%5E3+%5Ctimes+S%5E3&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;S^3 &amp;#92;times S^3&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; (Frank H.Lutz).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neighborliness is related to upper bound conjectures (that comes in various strengths) proposed by Kühnel in 1993.  Here below is a lecture by Kuhnel in a birthday conference honoring the Indian mathematician Basudeb Datta. Kühnel&amp;#8217;s conjecture  for the maximum value of the Euler characteristic of a &lt;span id=&quot;MathJax-Element-1-Frame&quot; class=&quot;MathJax&quot;&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;MathJax-Span-1&quot; class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;MathJax-Span-2&quot; class=&quot;mrow&quot;&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;MathJax-Span-3&quot; class=&quot;mn&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;MathJax-Span-4&quot; class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;-dimensional simplicial manifold on $latex &lt;span id=&quot;MathJax-Element-2-Frame&quot; class=&quot;MathJax&quot;&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;MathJax-Span-5&quot; class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;MathJax-Span-6&quot; class=&quot;mrow&quot;&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;MathJax-Span-7&quot; class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;n$ vertices&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7Bn-k-2%7D+%5Cchoose+%7Bk%2B1%7D%7D+%5Cle+%28-1%29%5Ek+%7B%7B2k%2B1%7D+%5Cchoose+%7Bk%2B1%7D%7D+%28%5Cchi+%28M%29-2%29%2C&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7Bn-k-2%7D+%5Cchoose+%7Bk%2B1%7D%7D+%5Cle+%28-1%29%5Ek+%7B%7B2k%2B1%7D+%5Cchoose+%7Bk%2B1%7D%7D+%28%5Cchi+%28M%29-2%29%2C&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7Bn-k-2%7D+%5Cchoose+%7Bk%2B1%7D%7D+%5Cle+%28-1%29%5Ek+%7B%7B2k%2B1%7D+%5Cchoose+%7Bk%2B1%7D%7D+%28%5Cchi+%28M%29-2%29%2C&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;{{n-k-2} &amp;#92;choose {k+1}} &amp;#92;le (-1)^k {{2k+1} &amp;#92;choose {k+1}} (&amp;#92;chi (M)-2),&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/0711.0783&quot;&gt;was settled&lt;/a&gt; by Isabella Novik and Ed Swartz in 2009. Novik and Swartz (for the orientable case) and Satoshi Murai (for the general case) also proved some strong forms of Kühnel&amp;#8217;s conjecture conditioned on the Lefschetz property for the links; the Lefschetz property was proved by Karim Adiprasito in his &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=g&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=g&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=g&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;g&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;-conjecture&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1812.10454&quot;&gt; paper&lt;/a&gt;. (Things are moving along nicely in the &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=g&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=g&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=g&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;g&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;-conjecture front (for older posts see &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2021/01/21/amazing-simpler-and-more-general-proofs-for-the-g-theorem-by-stavros-argyrios-papadakis-and-vasiliki-petrotou-and-by-karim-adiprasito-stavros-argyrios-papadakis-and-vasiliki-petrotou/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2018/12/25/amazing-karim-adiprasito-proved-the-g-conjecture-for-spheres/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;); I hope to write about it soon and in the meanwhile, here are two posts (&lt;a href=&quot;https://adiprasito.wordpress.com/2022/07/10/sofia-and-the-holy-trinity/&quot;&gt;I&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;https://adiprasito.wordpress.com/2022/07/28/anisotropy-in-arbitrary-characteristic-lefschetz-beyond-positivity-moment-curves-and-lattice-polytopes-part-2/&quot;&gt;II&lt;/a&gt;) by Karim.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe class=&quot;youtube-player&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/gAb4091UNIE?version=3&amp;#038;rel=1&amp;#038;showsearch=0&amp;#038;showinfo=1&amp;#038;iv_load_policy=1&amp;#038;fs=1&amp;#038;hl=en&amp;#038;autohide=2&amp;#038;wmode=transparent&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; style=&quot;border:0;&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt; &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;For a wider view of upper bound theorems watch the following ICM22 lecture by Isabella Novik.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe class=&quot;youtube-player&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9Az0RM8qook?version=3&amp;#038;rel=1&amp;#038;showsearch=0&amp;#038;showinfo=1&amp;#038;iv_load_policy=1&amp;#038;fs=1&amp;#038;hl=en&amp;#038;autohide=2&amp;#038;wmode=transparent&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; style=&quot;border:0;&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Polyhedral and more general complexes: my conjecture.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also posed a related conjecture to the 1987 Brehm and Kühnel&amp;#8217;s theorem. (Related to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2021/01/10/open-problem-session-of-huji-combsem-problem-5-gil-kalai-the-3%e1%b5%88-problem/&quot; rel=&quot;bookmark&quot;&gt;3ᵈ problem&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conjecture:&lt;/strong&gt; A polyhedral &lt;img src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002 1x, https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=333333&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&amp;#038;zoom=4.5 4x&quot; alt=&quot;d&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;-manifold (more generally, a strongly regular CW manifold) in dimension &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt; which is not a sphere has at least &lt;img class=&quot;latex&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2%5E%7B%283d%2B4%29%2F2%7D&amp;amp;bg=ffffff&amp;amp;fg=333333&amp;amp;s=0&amp;amp;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;2^{(3d+4)/2}&quot; /&gt; faces. (Including the empty face.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can expect that extremal cases are only in dimensions 2, 4, 8, and 16 and are projective plane like or even genuinly PL projective planes over the reals, complex, quaternions or octonions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Gil Kalai&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
      <uri>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Computational Complexity: Conference Modality</title>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/08/conference-modality.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-483004697033875840</id>
    <updated>2022-08-18T14:47:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;We have had an almost normal summer conference season, for some sense of normal. At one of those conferences I participated in an hybrid conversation about whether the conference should be in-person, virtual or hybrid the following year. Here are some general thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;In-Person&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The traditional conference format. People travel from near and far to a hotel, conference center or campus location. Talks given in large rooms, often in parallel. A reception, some social activities, participants gathering in small groups to go out for meals.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Positives: In-person maximizes interaction between participants. Being physically away from your home means you can focus your time on the conference and your fellow participants. This was more true before the mobile devices/laptops/internet days, but still most participants will spend more time on-site than on-line.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Negatives: Expensive--with registration, hotel and air fare, even a domestic participant could have to pay $2000 or up, higher for those traveling internationally. Visas can be hard to get.&amp;nbsp;Some still feel unsafe in large groups. People often leave early, pity the last speakers. And don&#39;t forget the carbon footprint.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As countries declare war on other countries or states deny certain rights, there is a push against meetings in certain places. Note the disclaimer for next year&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://fcrc.acm.org/&quot;&gt;FCRC&lt;/a&gt;. You might upset some people if you have conferences at these locations (and others if you don&#39;t).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Virtual&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Virtual conferences would never in the past have been taken seriously but Covid forced our hands.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Talks are streamed or pre-recorded. Some interaction with chats in talks, zoom get togethers or though a systems like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.virtualchair.net/&quot;&gt;virtual chair&lt;/a&gt;. Even if we had a perfect &quot;metaverse&quot; experience where we could get together as though we were in person, not being there in person means we wouldn&#39;t make it a priority.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The big advantages are costs are low, it&#39;s easy to attend talks, and no danger of spreading disease. Still a virtual conference can feel too much like just a collection of streamed and recorded talks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hybrid&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So let&#39;s make the conference hybrid and have the best of both worlds. Alas, it doesn&#39;t work out that way. It&#39;s nearly impossible to have good interaction between in-person and virtual participants--basically you have to run two separate meetings. Do you allow virtual talks or require an author to show up in person.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;How do you set prices? Lower prices for virtual increases assess but decreases in-person attendance. Participants (or their advisors) might opt to save expenses and attend virtually instead of in-person, reducing the networking opportunities for everyone.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most conferences tend to take the hybrid route to avoid the complaints if one went fully in-person or virtual, but hybrid just pretty much guarantees a mediocre experience for all.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Opinion&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My suggestion is some years run the conference virtually and others in hybrid. We already have too many conferences, a byproduct of our field using conferences as the primary publication venue. I suggest following conferences like the International Congress of Mathematicians or the Game Theory World Congress, held every four years. If the main conference of a field is held every four years, researchers, particularly senior researchers, make a bigger effort to be there. You can have the virtual meetings the other years so researchers, particularly students, can continue to present their work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;No easy solutions and CS conferences have &lt;a href=&quot;https://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2009/8/34492-viewpoint-time-for-computer-science-to-grow-up/fulltext&quot;&gt;not worked well for years&lt;/a&gt;. Maybe the struggle to define future conferences will allow us to focus more on the connecting researchers than just &quot;journals that meet in a hotel&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Lance Fortnow&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR22-116 |  Constant-Depth Sorting Networks | 

	Natalia Dobrokhotova-Maikova, 

	Alexander Kozachinskiy, 

	Vladimir Podolskii</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/116"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/116</id>
    <updated>2022-08-17T17:04:17+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    In this paper, we address sorting networks that are constructed from comparators of arity $k &amp;gt; 2$. That is, in our setting the arity of the comparators -- or, in other words, the number of inputs that can be sorted at the unit cost --  is a parameter. We study its relationship with two other parameters -- $n$, the number of inputs, and $d$, the depth.

This model received considerable attention. Partly, its motivation is to better understand the structure of sorting networks. In particular, sorting networks with large arity are related to recursive constructions of ordinary sorting networks.
Additionally, studies of this model have natural correspondence with  a recent line of work on constructing circuits for majority functions from majority gates of lower fan-in. 



Motivated by these questions, we obtain the first lower bounds on the arity of constant-depth sorting networks.
More precisely, we consider sorting networks of depth $d$ up to 4, and determine the minimal $k$ for which there is such a network with comparators of arity $k$. For depths $d=1,2$ we observe that $k=n$. For $d=3$ we show that $k = \lceil \frac n2 \rceil$. For $d=4$ the minimal arity becomes sublinear: $k = \Theta(n^{2/3})$. This contrasts with the case of majority circuits, in which $k = O(n^{2/3})$ is achievable already for depth $d=3$.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR22-115 |  Polynomial Identity Testing via Evaluation of Rational Functions | 

	Dieter van Melkebeek, 

	Andrew Morgan</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/115"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/115</id>
    <updated>2022-08-17T14:04:37+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    We introduce a hitting set generator for Polynomial Identity Testing
based on evaluations of low-degree univariate rational functions at
abscissas associated with the variables. Despite the univariate
nature, we establish an equivalence up to rescaling with a generator
introduced by Shpilka and Volkovich, which has a similar structure but
uses multivariate polynomials in the abscissas. 

We study the power of the generator by characterizing its vanishing
ideal, i.e., the set of polynomials that it fails to hit. Capitalizing
on the univariate nature, we develop a small collection of polynomials
that jointly produce the vanishing ideal. As corollaries, we obtain
tight bounds on the minimum degree, sparseness, and partition class
size of set-multilinearity in the vanishing ideal. Inspired by an
alternating algebra representation, we develop a structured
deterministic membership test for the vanishing ideal. As a proof of
concept, we rederive known derandomization results based on the
generator by Shpilka and Volkovich and present a new application for
read-once oblivious algebraic branching programs.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Decentralized Thoughts: Polynomial Secret Sharing with crash failures</title>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2022-08-17-secret-sharing-with-crash/"/>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2022-08-17-secret-sharing-with-crash/</id>
    <updated>2022-08-17T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    We continue our series on polynomial secret sharing. In the previous post of this series we discussed secret sharing with a passive adversary. In this post we assume crash failures and in later posts we will extend to malicious failures. As before, we must assume parties have private channels: the...
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Decentralized Thoughts</name>
      <uri>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">CCI: jobs: Professorships in machine learning (including theory) at University of Copenhagen (apply by September 4, 2022)</title>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/08/17/professorships-in-machine-learning-including-theory-at-university-of-copenhagen-apply-by-september-4-2022/"/>
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/08/17/professorships-in-machine-learning-including-theory-at-university-of-copenhagen-apply-by-september-4-2022/</id>
    <updated>2022-08-17T10:20:03+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;The University of Copenhagen invites applications for assistant, associate, and full professorships in machine learning, including theoretical, mathematical, aspects. The application deadline is September 4. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://di.ku.dk/ominstituttet/ledige_stillinger/tenure-track-assisatant-professorassociate-professorfull-professor-in-machine-learning/&quot;&gt;https://di.ku.dk/ominstituttet/ledige_stillinger/tenure-track-assisatant-professorassociate-professorfull-professor-in-machine-learning/&lt;/a&gt; for the full announcement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://di.ku.dk/ominstituttet/ledige_stillinger/tenure-track-assisatant-professorassociate-professorfull-professor-in-machine-learning/&quot;&gt;https://di.ku.dk/ominstituttet/ledige_stillinger/tenure-track-assisatant-professorassociate-professorfull-professor-in-machine-learning/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: jn@di.ku.dk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>CCI: jobs</name>
      <uri>https://cstheory-jobs.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Direct Sum Theorems From Fortification</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07730"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07730</id>
    <updated>2022-08-17T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wu_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hao Wu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We revisit the direct sum theorems in communication complexity which askes
whether the resource to solve $n$ communication problems together is
(approximately) the sum of resources to solve these problems separately. Our
work starts with the observation that Meir and Dinur&#39;s fortification lemma for
protocol size over rectangles can be generalized to a general fortification
lemma for a sub-additive measure over set. By applying this lemma to the case
of cover number, we obtain a dual form of cover number, called
``$\delta$-fooling set&#39;&#39; which is a generalized fooling set. Given a
communication problem $S\subseteq (X\times Y) \times Z$, let $\Lambda \subseteq
X\times Y$ be a $\delta$-fooling set of $S$, then given any subset
$\tilde{\Lambda} \subseteq \Lambda$ such that $|\tilde{\Lambda}|/{|\Lambda|} &amp;gt;
\delta$, there is no monochromatic rectangle that covers the subset
$\tilde{\Lambda}$. Particularly, there is a $\frac{16\log|X| |Y|}{\mathsf{
Cov}(S)}$-fooling set of communication problem $S$. With this fact, we are able
to reprove the classic direct sum theorem of cover number with a simple double
counting argument. And we prove a new direct sum theorem about protocol size
which imply a better direct sum theorem for two functions in terms of protocol
size. Formally, let $\mathsf{L}$ denote the protocol szie, given a
communication problem $F:A \times B \rightarrow
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\{0,1\}$, $
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\log\mathsf{L}\left(F\times F\right)\geq
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\log \mathsf{L}\left(F\right)
+\Omega\left(\sqrt{\log\mathsf{L}\left(F\right)}\right)-\log\log|A||B| -4$.We
also prove a tight cover number lower bound for the agree problem introduced by
Amos Beimel et al.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Computing Smallest Convex Intersecting Polygons</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07567"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07567</id>
    <updated>2022-08-17T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Antoniadis_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Antonios Antoniadis&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Berg_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mark de Berg&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kisfaludi_Bak_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;S&amp;#xe1;ndor Kisfaludi-Bak&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Skarlatos_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Antonis Skarlatos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A polygon C is an intersecting polygon for a set O of objects in the plane if
C intersects each object in O, where the polygon includes its interior. We
study the problem of computing the minimum-perimeter intersecting polygon and
the minimum-area convex intersecting polygon for a given set O of objects. We
present an FPTAS for both problems for the case where O is a set of possibly
intersecting convex polygons in the plane of total complexity n.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, we present an exact polynomial-time algorithm for the
minimum-perimeter intersecting polygon for the case where O is a set of n
possibly intersecting segments in the plane. So far, polynomial-time exact
algorithms were only known for the minimum perimeter intersecting polygon of
lines or of disjoint segments.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Mean estimation when you have the source code; or, quantum Monte Carlo methods</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07544"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07544</id>
    <updated>2022-08-17T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Kothari_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Robin Kothari&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+ODonnell_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ryan O&amp;#x27;Donnell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Suppose $\boldsymbol{y}$ is a real random variable, and one is given access
to ``the code&#39;&#39; that generates it (for example, a randomized or quantum circuit
whose output is $\boldsymbol{y}$). We give a quantum procedure that runs the
code $O(n)$ times and returns an estimate $\widehat{\boldsymbol{\mu}}$ for $\mu
= \mathrm{E}[\boldsymbol{y}]$ that with high probability satisfies
$|\widehat{\boldsymbol{\mu}} - \mu| \leq \sigma/n$, where $\sigma =
\mathrm{stddev}[\boldsymbol{y}]$. This dependence on $n$ is optimal for quantum
algorithms. One may compare with classical algorithms, which can only achieve
the quadratically worse $|\widehat{\boldsymbol{\mu}} - \mu| \leq
\sigma/\sqrt{n}$. Our method improves upon previous works, which either made
additional assumptions about $\boldsymbol{y}$, and/or assumed the algorithm
knew an a priori bound on $\sigma$, and/or used additional logarithmic factors
beyond $O(n)$. The central subroutine for our result is essentially Grover&#39;s
algorithm but with complex phases.ally Grover&#39;s algorithm but with complex
phases.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Private Query Release via the Johnson-Lindenstrauss Transform</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07410"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07410</id>
    <updated>2022-08-17T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nikolov_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Aleksandar Nikolov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduce a new method for releasing answers to statistical queries with
differential privacy, based on the Johnson-Lindenstrauss lemma. The key idea is
to randomly project the query answers to a lower dimensional space so that the
distance between any two vectors of feasible query answers is preserved up to
an additive error. Then we answer the projected queries using a simple
noise-adding mechanism, and lift the answers up to the original dimension.
Using this method, we give, for the first time, purely differentially private
mechanisms with optimal worst case sample complexity under average error for
answering a workload of $k$ queries over a universe of size $N$. As other
applications, we give the first purely private efficient mechanisms with
optimal sample complexity for computing the covariance of a bounded
high-dimensional distribution, and for answering 2-way marginal queries. We
also show that, up to the dependence on the error, a variant of our mechanism
is nearly optimal for every given query workload.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Archimedes Meets Privacy: On Privately Estimating Quantiles in High Dimensions Under Minimal Assumptions</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07438"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07438</id>
    <updated>2022-08-17T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Ben_Eliezer_O/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Omri Ben-Eliezer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Mikulincer_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Dan Mikulincer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Zadik_I/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ilias Zadik&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last few years have seen a surge of work on high dimensional statistics
under privacy constraints, mostly following two main lines of work: the ``worst
case&#39;&#39; line, which does not make any distributional assumptions on the input
data; and the ``strong assumptions&#39;&#39; line, which assumes that the data is
generated from specific families, e.g., subgaussian distributions. In this work
we take a middle ground, obtaining new differentially private algorithms with
polynomial sample complexity for estimating quantiles in high-dimensions, as
well as estimating and sampling points of high Tukey depth, all working under
very mild distributional assumptions. From the technical perspective, our work
relies upon deep robustness results in the convex geometry literature,
demonstrating how such results can be used in a private context.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our main object of interest is the (convex) floating body (FB), a notion
going back to Archimedes, which is a robust and well studied high-dimensional
analogue of the interquantile range. We show how one can privately, and with
polynomially many samples, (a) output an approximate interior point of the FB
-- e.g., ``a typical user&#39;&#39; in a high-dimensional database -- by leveraging the
robustness of the Steiner point of the FB; and at the expense of polynomially
many more samples, (b) produce an approximate uniform sample from the FB, by
constructing a private noisy projection oracle.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Fine-Grained Complexity Lower Bounds for Families of Dynamic Graphs</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07572"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07572</id>
    <updated>2022-08-17T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Henzinger_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Monika Henzinger&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Paz_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ami Paz&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sricharan_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;A. R. Sricharan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A dynamic graph algorithm is a data structure that answers queries about a
property of the current graph while supporting graph modifications such as edge
insertions and deletions. Prior work has shown strong conditional lower bounds
for general dynamic graphs, yet graph families that arise in practice often
exhibit structural properties that the existing lower bound constructions do
not possess. We study three specific graph families that are ubiquitous, namely
constant-degree graphs, power-law graphs, and expander graphs, and give the
first conditional lower bounds for them. Our results show that even when
restricting our attention to one of these graph classes, any algorithm for
fundamental graph problems such as distance computation or approximation or
maximum matching, cannot simultaneously achieve a sub-polynomial update time
and query time. For example, we show that the same lower bounds as for general
graphs hold for maximum matching and ($s,t$)-distance in constant-degree
graphs, power-law graphs or expanders. Namely, in an $m$-edge graph, there
exists no dynamic algorithms with both $O(m^{1/2 - \epsilon})$ update time and
$ O(m^{1 -\epsilon})$ query time, for any small $\epsilon &amp;gt; 0$. Note that for
($s,t$)-distance the trivial dynamic algorithm achieves an almost matching
upper bound of constant update time and $O(m)$ query time. We prove similar
bounds for the other graph families and for other fundamental problems such as
densest subgraph detection and perfect matching.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Deletion Robust Non-Monotone Submodular Maximization over Matroids</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07582"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07582</id>
    <updated>2022-08-17T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Dutting_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Paul D&amp;#xfc;tting&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Fusco_F/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Federico Fusco&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lattanzi_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Silvio Lattanzi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Norouzi_Fard_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ashkan Norouzi-Fard&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zadimoghaddam_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Morteza Zadimoghaddam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Maximizing a submodular function is a fundamental task in machine learning
and in this paper we study the deletion robust version of the problem under the
classic matroids constraint. Here the goal is to extract a small size summary
of the dataset that contains a high value independent set even after an
adversary deleted some elements. We present constant-factor approximation
algorithms, whose space complexity depends on the rank $k$ of the matroid and
the number $d$ of deleted elements. In the centralized setting we present a
$(4.597+O(\varepsilon))$-approximation algorithm with summary size $O(
\frac{k+d}{\varepsilon^2}\log \frac{k}{\varepsilon})$ that is improved to a
$(3.582+O(\varepsilon))$-approximation with $O(k + \frac{d}{\varepsilon^2}\log
\frac{k}{\varepsilon})$ summary size when the objective is monotone. In the
streaming setting we provide a $(9.435 + O(\varepsilon))$-approximation
algorithm with summary size and memory $O(k + \frac{d}{\varepsilon^2}\log
\frac{k}{\varepsilon})$; the approximation factor is then improved to
$(5.582+O(\varepsilon))$ in the monotone case.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: O(n log n) algorithm for finding a solution of Erd\H{o}s-Ginzburg-Ziv theorem</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07728"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07728</id>
    <updated>2022-08-17T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Choi_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Seokhwan Choi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kang_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hanpil Kang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lim_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Dongjae Lim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Erd\H{o}s-Ginzburg-Ziv theorem is a popular theorem in additive number
theory, which states any sequence of $2n-1$ integers contains a subsequence of
$n$ elements, with their sum is a multiple of $n$. In this article, we provide
an algorithm finding a solution of Erd\H{o}s-Ginzburg-Ziv in $O(n \log n)$
time. This is the first known quasi-linear time algorithm finding a solution of
Erd\H{o}s-Ginzburg-Ziv theorem.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Polynomial kernel for immersion hitting in tournaments</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07789"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07789</id>
    <updated>2022-08-17T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Bozyk_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;&amp;#x141;ukasz Bo&amp;#x17c;yk&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Pilipczuk_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Micha&amp;#x142; Pilipczuk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a fixed simple digraph $H$ without isolated vertices, we consider the
problem of deleting arcs from a given tournament to get a digraph which does
not contain $H$ as an immersion. We prove that for every $H$, this problem
admits a polynomial kernel when parameterized by the number of deleted arcs.
The degree of the bound on the kernel size depends on $H$.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: New Parallel Order Maintenance Data Structure</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07800"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07800</id>
    <updated>2022-08-17T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Guo_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Bin Guo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sekerinski_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Emil Sekerinski&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The \emph{Order-Maintenance} (OM) data structure maintains a total order list
of items for insertions, deletions, and comparisons. As a basic data structure,
OM has many applications, such as maintaining the topological order, core
numbers, and truss in graphs, and maintaining ordered sets in Unified Modeling
Language (UML) Specification. The prevalence of multicore machines suggests
parallelizing such a basic data structure. This paper proposes a new parallel
OM data structure that supports insertions, deletions, and comparisons in
parallel. Specifically, parallel insertions and deletions are synchronized by
using locks efficiently, which achieve up to $7$x and $5.6$x speedups with $64$
workers. One big advantage is that the comparisons are lock-free so that they
can execute highly in parallel with other insertions and deletions, which
achieve up to $34.4$x speedups with $64$ workers. Typical real applications
maintain order lists that always have a much larger portion of comparisons than
insertions and deletions. For example, in core maintenance, the number of
comparisons is up to 297 times larger compared with insertions and deletions in
certain graphs. This is why the lock-free order comparison is a breakthrough in
practice.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Optimal algorithms for learning quantum phase states</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07851"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07851</id>
    <updated>2022-08-17T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Arunachalam_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Srinivasan Arunachalam&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Bravyi_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sergey Bravyi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Dutt_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Arkopal Dutt&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Yoder_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Theodore J. Yoder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analyze the complexity of learning $n$-qubit quantum phase states. A
degree-$d$ phase state is defined as a superposition of all $2^n$ basis vectors
$x$ with amplitudes proportional to $(-1)^{f(x)}$, where $f$ is a degree-$d$
Boolean polynomial over $n$ variables. We show that the sample complexity of
learning an unknown degree-$d$ phase state is $\Theta(n^d)$ if we allow
separable measurements and $\Theta(n^{d-1})$ if we allow entangled
measurements. Our learning algorithm based on separable measurements has
runtime $\textsf{poly}(n)$ (for constant $d$) and is well-suited for near-term
demonstrations as it requires only single-qubit measurements in the Pauli $X$
and $Z$ bases. We show similar bounds on the sample complexity for learning
generalized phase states with complex-valued amplitudes. We further consider
learning phase states when $f$ has sparsity-$s$, degree-$d$ in its
$\mathbb{F}_2$ representation (with sample complexity $O(2^d sn)$), $f$ has
Fourier-degree-$t$ (with sample complexity $O(2^{2t})$), and learning quadratic
phase states with $\varepsilon$-global depolarizing noise (with sample
complexity $O(n^{1+\varepsilon})$). These learning algorithms give us a
procedure to learn the diagonal unitaries of the Clifford hierarchy and IQP
circuits.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR22-114 |  Direct Sum  Theorems From Fortification | 

	Hao Wu</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/114"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/114</id>
    <updated>2022-08-16T13:21:16+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    We revisit  the direct sum theorems in communication complexity which askes whether the resource to solve $n$ communication problems together is (approximately) the sum of resources to solve these problems separately. Our work starts with the  observation that Meir and Dinur&amp;#39;s fortification lemma for protocol size over rectangles can be generalized to a general fortification lemma for a sub-additive measure over set. By applying this lemma to the case of cover number, we obtain a dual form of cover number, called ``$\delta$-fooling set&amp;#39;&amp;#39; which is a generalized fooling set. Given a communication problem $S\subseteq (X\times Y) \times Z$, let $\Lambda \subseteq  X\times Y$ be a $\delta$-fooling set of $S$, then given any subset $\tilde{\Lambda} \subseteq \Lambda$ such that $|\tilde{\Lambda}|/{|\Lambda|} &amp;gt; \delta$, there is no  monochromatic rectangle that covers  the subset $\tilde{\Lambda}$. Particularly, there is  a $\frac{16\log|X| |Y|}{{Cov}(S)}$-fooling set of communication problem $S$. 
	
With this fact, we are able to reprove the classic direct sum theorem of cover number with a simple double counting argument. Formally, let  $S  \subseteq (A\times B) \times O$ and $T \subseteq (P\times Q) \times Z$ be two communication problems, $
\log {Cov}\left(S\times T\right)
\geq  \log{Cov}\left(S\right) 
+ \log{Cov}(T)
-\log\log|P||Q|-4.$ where ${Cov}$ denotes the cover number. 

 One issue of current deterministic direct sum theorems about commutation complexity or protocol size is that they provide no information when $n$ is small, especially when $n=2$. In this work,  we prove a new direct sum theorem about protocol size which imply a better direct sum theorem for two functions in terms of protocol size. Formally, let ${L}$ denote the protocol size, given a communication problem $F:A \times B \rightarrow 
 \{0,1\}$, $
 \log{L}\left(F\times F\right)\geq
 \log {L}\left(F\right) +\Omega\left(\sqrt{\log{L}\left(F\right)}\right)-\log\log|A||B| -4$.
 
 We also address other direct sum type problem such like the agree problem introduced by Amos Beimel et. We prove a tight cover number lower bound for  the agree problem. Formally, let $S_i \subseteq X_i \times Y_i \times Z, i\in [k]$ be $k$ two-party communication problems, 
${Cov}
\left({agree}(S_1,\ldots,S_k)\right) \geq \min_{i\in [k]} 
\left\{ \frac{{Cov}(S_i)}{16\log|X_i| |Y_i|} \right\}. 
$

All our direct sum type results are obtained in a similar way, that is using the $\delta$-fooling set to construct a hardcore for the direct sum type problem.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">David Eppstein: Linkage</title>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/08/15/linkage.html"/>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/08/15/linkage</id>
    <updated>2022-08-15T17:28:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jdh.hamkins.org/the-logic-of-definite-descriptions/&quot;&gt;The logic of definite descriptions&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108752002958988947&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; Joel Hamkins wrestles with logical formulations of “the”, indicating that a description uniquely identifies something. If you define a logical operator whose value is the thing identified by its argument, and use it in a context that doesn’t uniquely identify something, does your overall formula still have a truth value? Fortunately(?) the stakes are low: several plausible choices produce logics with the same power as classical logic.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/QuantumYakar/status/1554432810664054784?s=20&amp;amp;t=0nXoTU04w7Qe1bitINS6QA&quot;&gt;DALL-E paintings of people using quantum computers, in the styles of famous artists&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108754837516429391&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6635&quot;&gt;via&lt;/a&gt;). I am super-impressed at how this sort of thing can be done quickly by software, rather than human artists with much more time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://eprint.iacr.org/2022/975.pdf&quot;&gt;Supersingular isogeny Diffie–Hellman broken&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108760153729341419&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2022/08/sike-once-a-post-quantum-encryption-contender-is-koed-in-nist-smackdown/&quot;&gt;via&lt;/a&gt;). This cryptosystem relied on the unpredictability of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supersingular_isogeny_graph&quot;&gt;supersingular isogeny graphs&lt;/a&gt;, expander graphs with vertices for elliptic curves and edges for certain morphisms between them. Apparently, these graphs are less unpredictable than thought. SIDH and the SIKE protocol built on it were hoped to be impenetrable to quantum computers but the attack does not use quantum.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.danapiazza.art/2020&quot;&gt;The warped grids of Dana Piazza’s artworks look like curvy woven textiles&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108767757342794473&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=947Ewgue4DM&quot;&gt;\(10^5\)-fold speedup for Matt Parker’s Wordle puzzle&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108777561081795507&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; This has nothing to do with actual Wordle puzzles; it’s about sets of five-letter words with no repeated letters (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_-AfhLQfb6w&quot;&gt;Parker’s original video&lt;/a&gt;). Two ideas for the speedup: first, save a 5! factor by only searching sorted sequences of words. And second, make the repetition tests blazingly fast using 26-bit bitvectors for the sets of characters already used, so repetitions can be found as a bitwise and.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://yangerard.wordpress.com/2019/06/18/open-problem-optimal-area-polygonalization/&quot;&gt;Cute puzzle from Sándor Fekete’s 1992 dissertation, via Yan Gerard&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108783731533422343&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/span&gt; prove that any finite set of points in the plane has a simple polygon with all of the points as vertices, covering more than half of the area of its convex hull. More generally, polygons using all of a given point set as vertices are called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polygonalization&quot;&gt;polygonalizations&lt;/a&gt;, and there are many unsolved problems concerning them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kindofdoon.com/2020/03/prioritizing-color-over-value.html&quot;&gt;Prioritizing value (lightness and darkness) versus color (legibility of hue) in imaging&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108786220837380811&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; With examples both from digital photo processing and the history of painting, and suggestions for how to achieve either desired effect in Photoshop-like editors. Daniel Dichter, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A philosophical/definitional question &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108791925057208437&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/span&gt; should “problem \(X\) on input class \(Y\) is \(\mathsf{NP}\)-complete” mean there is a specialized decision problem whose valid inputs are exactly \(Y\) that is \(\mathsf{NP}\)-compete, or should it mean that problem \(X\) (allowing wider inputs) is \(\mathsf{NP}\)-complete and has hard inputs in $Y$?&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Case in point: snarks (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snark_(graph_theory)&quot;&gt;new Good Article on Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;) are \(\mathsf{coNP}\)-complete to recognize. Can it ever be correct to say “problem \(X\) is \(\mathsf{NP}\)-complete for snarks”?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.metafilter.com/196124/Along-with-the-chicken-and-the-banana&quot;&gt;Interesting discussion on the repeated independent invention of zero as concept and as a digit in positional numbering, in many ancient cultures&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108797547774576065&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; prompted by a dubious jingoistic &lt;em&gt;Scientific American&lt;/em&gt; article (linked) that somehow assigns “ownership” (!?) of this concept to a Sumatran kingdom contemporary with medieval Europe, who somehow spread their knowledge backwards in time to the ancient world. What has happened to &lt;em&gt;Scientific American&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Summer is a time for transitions among my UC Irvine theory colleagues &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108803001555998759&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Sandy Irani went on leave to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://simons.berkeley.edu/news/Irani-Associate-Director&quot;&gt;associate director for the Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing in Berkeley&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Amelia Regan retired (emeritus) to direct the supply chain transportation &amp;amp; logistics graduate program in civil &amp;amp; environmental engineering at the University of Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Dan Hirschberg also retired as emeritus, but is teaching on recall.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Congratulations, Sandy, Amelia, and Dan!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you were thinking of submitting a paper to COCOA (the 16th Annual Conference on Combinatorial Optimization and Applications, previously scheduled with initial submission date August 12 and conference in Dallas Texas in December), as I was, think again &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108807238586218956&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; It’s now been &lt;a href=&quot;https://theory.utdallas.edu/COCOA2023/index.html&quot;&gt;pushed back a year and planned to be online-only&lt;/a&gt;. I have no more information than what is linked here.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m sad that an article with the headline &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lppfusion.com/scientists-protest-censorship-in-cosmology/&quot;&gt;“Scientists Protest Censorship in Cosmology”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108811940444664320&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=32443298&quot;&gt;via&lt;/a&gt;) is only about fringe papers getting rejected as off-topic by arXiv and MNRAS. I wanted it to be about scientists holding big marches with signs in the street in opposition to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosmic_censorship_hypothesis&quot;&gt;cosmic censorship hypotheses&lt;/a&gt;, that the universe conspires against scientists to make it impossible to see what singularities in space-time look like.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@xp_eileen_maths/108793591875610453&quot;&gt;Does anyone use “lemmata” as the plural of “lemma”&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aperiodical.com/2022/08/integer-sequence-review-a101544/&quot;&gt;David Cushing and Christian Lawson-Perfect critique more OEIS sequences&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@christianp/108815974308227304&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:WPBioPctChangedOccupation.png&quot;&gt;A bar chart showing occupations for which the English Wikipedia’s coverage of women (as a proportion of biographical articles for that occupation) most improved over the five years from 2016 to 2021&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108829181695783366&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; I’m happy to see “scientist” (13% to 25%) and “professor” (11% to 20%) made the list. But they’re still a long way from 50%.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By David Eppstein&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
      <uri>https://11011110.github.io/blog/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Gil Kalai: Answer to Test Your Intuition 50: Detecting a Deviator</title>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/08/15/answer-to-test-your-intuition-50-detecting-a-deviator/"/>
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=23212</id>
    <updated>2022-08-15T17:06:03+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago we asked:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ruth and Ron start together at the origin and take a walk on the integers. Every day they make a move. They take turns in flipping a coin and they move together right or left according to the outcome. Their coin flips create a simple random walk starting at the origin on the integers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know for sure that they we will return to the origin infinitely many times. However, their random walk never comes back to the origin, so we know for sure that one of them did not follow the rules!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Test your intuition: Is it possible to figure out from the walk whether it was Ruth or Ron who did not follow the coin-flipping rule?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the answer is &lt;strong&gt;yes!&lt;/strong&gt; This is proved in the following paper:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;title mathjax&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.03744&quot;&gt;Identifying the Deviator&lt;/a&gt;, by Noga Alon, Benjamin Gunby, Xiaoyu He, Eran Shmaya, and Eilon Solan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;title mathjax&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; A group of players are supposed to follow a prescribed profile of strategies. If they follow this profile, they will reach a given target. We show that if the target is not reached because some player deviates, then an outside observer can identify the deviator. We also construct identification methods in two nontrivial cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper gives a non-constructive proof for a strategy to identify the deviator and in the case of two-player random walk it gives an ingenious explicit identification method!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#0000ff;&quot;&gt;Here is a variant of the problem devoted to Itai Benjamini: Consider planar percolation on the rectangular grid. One player chooses every vertical edge with probability 1/2 and one player chooses every horizontal edge with probability 1/2. Lo and behold, there is an infinite open cluster. Can you (explicitely) detect the deviator?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/deviator.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; data-attachment-id=&quot;23223&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/08/15/answer-to-test-your-intuition-50-detecting-a-deviator/deviator/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/deviator.png&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;642,242&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;deviator&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/deviator.png?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/deviator.png?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-23223&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/deviator.png&quot; alt=&quot;deviator&quot; width=&quot;642&quot; height=&quot;242&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/deviator.png 642w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/deviator.png?w=150&amp;amp;h=57 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/deviator.png?w=300&amp;amp;h=113 300w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 642px) 100vw, 642px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Gil Kalai&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
      <uri>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Computational Complexity: A non-controversial question about the Documents Donald Trump had in his house</title>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/08/a-non-controversial-question-about.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-8900902852699534963</id>
    <updated>2022-08-15T12:13:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    This is a non-partisan post. In the interest of disclosure I will divulge that I do not think private citizens should have top secret government documents in their house.&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;One phrase I kept hearing in the reporting was (I paraphrase and may have the number wrong)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;i&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; The FBI removed 15 boxes of documents&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Documents? Like--- on paper?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;a) Are the documents also online someplace? Perhaps they intentionally are not so that they can&#39;t be hacked.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;b) Is having top secret documents only on paper safer than having them in electronic form? Normally I would think so. Donald Trump&amp;nbsp; having them is a very unusual case.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;c) Having to store all of those documents on paper would seem to have storage problems. I can imagine someone with NO bad purposes making copies and taking them home since they are tired of only being about to read them in a special room.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;d) A problem with having them ONLY on paper is that if an accident happens and they get destroyed there is no backup. Or is there? Are there copies somewhere? That leads to twice the storage problems.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;e) There is a tradeoff of security and convenience. Is having the documents only on paper is an extreme point on the tradeoff, but it may be the right one. It may depend on how important it is to keep the documents secret.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;f) I&#39;ve heard (apocryphal?) stories about some top secret document also available in public though quite legal sources (e.g., a physics journal that discusses nuclear stuff).&amp;nbsp; Does the government make to much classified? If so then the problem arises of people not taking the classification seriously and getting careless. I doubt that is what happened here.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;g) The question I am most curious about is why did he take them? For most of his other actions his motivations are clear (e.g., he is pushing STOP THE STEAL since he wants to be president). But for this one its not clear. Unfortunately,&amp;nbsp; I doubt we&#39;ll ever find out. Maybe the answer is in some documents either on paper or electronic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By gasarch&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Decentralized Thoughts: A new Dolev-Reischuk style Lower Bound</title>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2022-08-14-new-DR-LB/"/>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2022-08-14-new-DR-LB/</id>
    <updated>2022-08-14T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    In a previous post we discussed Crusader Broadcast and showed a $O(n^2)$ words, $O(1)$ time solution for $f&amp;lt;n$ and assuming a PKI. In this post, we overview a new Dolev-Reischuk style bower bound (see our full paper): Theorem AS22: In any deterministic protocol solving Crusader Broadcast with $f&amp;lt;n$ Byzantine failures...
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Decentralized Thoughts</name>
      <uri>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR22-113 |  Leakage-Resilient Hardness v.s. Randomness | 

	Yanyi Liu, 

	Rafael Pass</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/113"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/113</id>
    <updated>2022-08-14T08:05:23+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    A central open problem in complexity theory concerns the question of
whether all efficient randomized algorithms can be simulated by
efficient deterministic algorithms. The celebrated ``hardness
v.s. randomness” paradigm pioneered by Blum-Micali (SIAM JoC’84),
Yao (FOCS’84) and Nisan-Wigderson (JCSS’94) presents hardness
assumptions under which $\prBPP = \prP$, but these hardness assumptions 
are not known to also be necessary for such derandomization.
 
In this work, following the recent work by Chen and Tell (FOCS’21) that 
considers “almost-all-input” hardness of a function $f$ (i.e., hardness 
of computing $f$ on more than a finite number of inputs), we consider 
“almost-all-input” \emph{leakage-resilient hardness} of a function $f$
—that is, hardness of computing $f(x)$ even given, say, $\sqrt{|x|}$ 
bits of leakage of $f(x)$. We show that leakage-resilient hardness 
characterizes derandomization of $\prBPP$ (i.e., gives a both \emph{
necessary} and \emph{sufficient} condition for derandomization). In more 
detail, we show that there exists a constant $c$ such that the following 
are equivalent:

- $\prBPP = \prP$;
- Existence of a poly-time computable function $f :\{0, 1\}^n \rightarrow  \{0,1\}^n$
 that is almost-all-input leakage-resilient hard with respect to 
$n^c$-time probabilistic algorithms.

Our characterization naturally extends also to the low-end
derandomization regime, to derandomization of $\prMA$, and also to
average-case derandomization, by appropriately weakening the
requirements on the function $f$.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Scott Aaronson: Summer 2022 Quantum Supremacy Updates</title>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6645"/>
    <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6645</id>
    <updated>2022-08-13T19:22:09+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;mark style=&quot;background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0)&quot; class=&quot;has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color&quot;&gt;Update:&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; We&amp;#8217;re now finalizing the lecture notes&amp;#8212;basically, a textbook&amp;#8212;for the brand-new Quantum Information Science II course that I taught this past spring!  The notes will be freely shared on this blog.  But the bibliographies for the various lectures need to be merged, and we don&amp;#8217;t know how.  Would any TeXpert like to help us, in exchange for a generous acknowledgment?&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;hr class=&quot;wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity&quot;/&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I returned last week from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://chicagoquantum.org/events/nsf-workshop-quantum-advantage-and-next-steps&quot;&gt;NSF Workshop on Quantum Advantage and Next Steps&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Chicago.  Thanks so much to Chicago CS professor (and my former summer student) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.billfefferman.com/&quot;&gt;Bill Fefferman&lt;/a&gt; and the other organizers for making this workshop a reality.  Given how vividly I remember the situation 12 years ago, when the idea of sampling-based quantum supremacy was the weird obsession of me and a few others, it was particularly special to attend a workshop on the topic with well over a hundred participants, some in-person and some on Zoom, delayed by covid but still excited by the dramatic experimental progress of the past few years.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Of course there&amp;#8217;s a lot still to do.  Many of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://chicagoquantum.org/events/nsf-workshop-quantum-advantage-and-next-steps&quot;&gt;talks&lt;/a&gt; drew an exclamation point on something I&amp;#8217;ve been saying for the past couple years: that there&amp;#8217;s an urgent need for better quantum supremacy experiments, which will require both theoretical &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; engineering advances.  The experiments by Google and USTC and now Xanadu represent a big step forward for the field, but since they started being done, the classical spoofing attacks have also steadily improved, to the point that whether &amp;#8220;quantum computational supremacy&amp;#8221; still exists depends on exactly how you define it.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Briefly: if you measure by total operations, energy use, or CO2 footprint, then probably yes, quantum supremacy remains.  But if you measure by number of seconds, then it doesn&amp;#8217;t remain, not if you&amp;#8217;re willing to shell out for enough cores on AWS or your favorite supercomputer.  And even the quantum supremacy that does remain might eventually fall to, e.g., further improvements of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01657&quot;&gt;algorithm due to Gao et al&lt;/a&gt;.  For more details, see, e.g., the now-published work of &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.03011&quot;&gt;Pan, Chen, and Zhang&lt;/a&gt;, or this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/ordinary-computers-can-beat-google-s-quantum-computer-after-all&quot;&gt;good popular summary&lt;/a&gt; by Adrian Cho for &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;If the experimentalists care enough, they could easily regain the quantum lead, at least for a couple more years, by (say) repeating random circuit sampling with 72 qubits rather than 53-60, and hopefully circuit depth of 30-40 rather than just 20-25.  But the point I made in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scottaaronson.com/talks/whatihope.ppt&quot;&gt;my talk&lt;/a&gt; was that, as long as we remain in the paradigm of sampling experiments that take ~2&lt;sup&gt;n&lt;/sup&gt; time to verify classically and &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; ~2&lt;sup&gt;n&lt;/sup&gt; time to spoof classically (where n is the number of qubits), all quantum speedups that we can achieve will be fragile and contingent, however interesting and impressive.  As soon as we go way beyond what classical computers can keep up with, we&amp;#8217;ve &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; gone way beyond where classical computers can check what was done.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I argued that the only solution to this problem is to design new quantum supremacy experiments: ones where some secret has been inserted in the quantum circuit that lets a classical computer efficiently verify the results.  The fundamental problem is that we need three properties&amp;#8212;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;implementability on &lt;em&gt;near-term&lt;/em&gt; quantum computers,&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;efficient classical verifiability, and&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;confidence that quantum computers have a theoretical asymptotic advantage,&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;



&lt;p&gt;and right now we only know how to get any two out of the three.  We can get 1 and 2 with &lt;a href=&quot;https://qiskit.org/textbook/ch-applications/qaoa.html&quot;&gt;QAOA&lt;/a&gt; and various other heuristic quantum algorithms, 1 and 3 with BosonSampling and Random Circuit Sampling, or 2 and 3 with Shor&amp;#8217;s algorithm or &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02063&quot;&gt;Yamakawa-Zhandry&lt;/a&gt; or recent interactive protocols.  To get all three, there are three obvious approaches:&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Start with the heuristic algorithms and find a real advantage from them,&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Start with BosonSampling or Random Circuit Sampling or the like and figure out how to make them efficiently verifiable classically, or&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Start with protocols like &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2104.00687&quot;&gt;Kahanamoku-Meyer et al.&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt; and figure out how to run them on near-term devices.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;



&lt;p&gt;At the Chicago workshop, I&amp;#8217;d say that the most popular approach speakers talked about was 3, although my own focus was more on 2.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Anyway, until a &amp;#8220;best-of-all-worlds&amp;#8221; quantum supremacy experiment is discovered, there&amp;#8217;s plenty to do in the meantime: for example, better understand the classical hardness of spoofing Random Circuit Sampling with a constant or logarithmic number of gate layers.  Understand the best that classical algorithms can do to spoof the Linear Cross-Entropy Benchmark for BosonSampling, and build on &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.06964&quot;&gt;Grier et al.&lt;/a&gt; to understand the power of BosonSampling with a linear number of modes.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll be flying back with my family to Austin today after seven weeks at the Jersey shore, but I&amp;#8217;ll try to field any questions about the state of quantum supremacy in general or this workshop in particular in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Scott&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Scott Aaronson</name>
      <uri>https://scottaaronson.blog</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR22-112 |  Randomised Composition and Small-Bias Minimax | 

	Shalev Ben-David, 

	Eric Blais, 

	Mika Göös, 

	Gilbert Maystre</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/112"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/112</id>
    <updated>2022-08-12T19:53:38+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    We prove two results about randomised query complexity $\mathrm{R}(f)$. First, we introduce a linearised complexity measure $\mathrm{LR}$ and show that it satisfies an inner-optimal composition theorem: $\mathrm{R}(f\circ g) \geq \Omega(\mathrm{R}(f) \mathrm{LR}(g))$ for all partial $f$ and $g$, and moreover, $\mathrm{LR}$ is the largest possible measure with this property. In particular, $\mathrm{LR}$ can be polynomially larger than previous measures that satisfy an inner composition theorem, such as the max-conflict complexity of Gavinsky, Lee, Santha, and Sanyal (ICALP 2019).

Our second result addresses a question of Yao (FOCS 1977). He asked if $\epsilon$-error expected query complexity $\bar{\mathrm{R}}_\epsilon(f)$ admits a distributional characterisation relative to some hard input distribution. Vereshchagin (TCS 1998) answered this question affirmatively in the bounded-error case. We show that an analogous theorem fails in the small-bias case $\epsilon=1/2-o(1)$.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Decentralized Thoughts: He-HTLC - Revisiting Incentives in HTLC</title>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2022-08-12-hehtlc/"/>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2022-08-12-hehtlc/</id>
    <updated>2022-08-12T05:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    Hashed Time-locked Contracts (HTLC) find many useful applications in the L2 Layer such as the lightning network and atomic swaps. In this post, we will focus on discussing protocols for implementing HTLC when taking into consideration incentives for parties in the system. We will discuss a line of work —...
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Decentralized Thoughts</name>
      <uri>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Gil Kalai: To cheer you up in difficult times 36: The Immense Joy of Fake Reverse Parking</title>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/08/11/to-cheer-you-up-in-difficult-times-36-the-immense-joy-of-fake-reverse-parking/"/>
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=21813</id>
    <updated>2022-08-11T13:01:09+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; data-attachment-id=&quot;23155&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/08/11/to-cheer-you-up-in-difficult-times-36-the-immense-joy-of-fake-reverse-parking/frp9/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp9.png&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1051,668&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;frp9&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp9.png?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp9.png?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-23155&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp9.png&quot; alt=&quot;frp9&quot; width=&quot;1051&quot; height=&quot;668&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp9.png 1051w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp9.png?w=150&amp;amp;h=95 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp9.png?w=300&amp;amp;h=191 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp9.png?w=768&amp;amp;h=488 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp9.png?w=1024&amp;amp;h=651 1024w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 1051px) 100vw, 1051px&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;Fake reverse parking&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: fake reverse parking is known already as &lt;a href=&quot;//vancouverisland.ctvnews.ca/should-you-pull-through-in-parking-lots-experts-divided-1.4269504&quot;&gt;the much debated &amp;#8220;pull-through parking&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;. (Thanks to Gali Weinstein over Facebook for telling me about it.) It is also mentioned as &lt;a href=&quot;http://1000awesomethings.com/2008/12/08/879-the-parking-lot-pull-through/&quot;&gt;#879 among a thousand awesome things&lt;/a&gt; by Neil Pasricha.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was young my mother &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2015/08/02/carmella-kalai-1926-2015/&quot;&gt;Carmela Kalai&lt;/a&gt; told me: &amp;#8220;Always remember, Gili,&amp;nbsp; how wonderful movies are and how happy I was to be born in the era of movies.&amp;#8221; My father &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanoch_Kalai&quot;&gt;Hanoch Kalai&lt;/a&gt; told me: &amp;#8220;Everything is interesting! Every subject, no matter how marginal and unimportant or boring it may look to you, Gil, when you study it in depth you will find it fascinating!&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I tell my children is: &amp;#8220;Remember the joy of fake reverse parking!&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you in this post what fake reverse parking is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fake-reverse parking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brief explanation is simple: when there are two (&lt;strong&gt;unoccupied&lt;/strong&gt;) parking spaces, one after the other, you drive forward, pass one of the parking lots and locate your car in the second parking lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general law about parking is this: forward parking is often easier than reverse parking but it is often harder afterwards to drive your car away. Reverse parking is harder than forward parking but later it is easier to get out and drive away. Fake reverse driving is easier than both and it is just as easy as ordinary reverse parking when it comes to leaving your parking place and driving away.&lt;span id=&quot;more-21813&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; data-attachment-id=&quot;23147&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/08/11/to-cheer-you-up-in-difficult-times-36-the-immense-joy-of-fake-reverse-parking/frp5/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp5.png&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1000,664&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;frp5&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp5.png?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp5.png?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-23147&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp5.png&quot; alt=&quot;frp5&quot; width=&quot;1000&quot; height=&quot;664&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp5.png 1000w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp5.png?w=150&amp;amp;h=100 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp5.png?w=300&amp;amp;h=199 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp5.png?w=768&amp;amp;h=510 768w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px&quot;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ordinary reverse parking&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; data-attachment-id=&quot;23148&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/08/11/to-cheer-you-up-in-difficult-times-36-the-immense-joy-of-fake-reverse-parking/frp3/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp3.png&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1051,668&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;frp3&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp3.png?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp3.png?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-23148&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp3.png&quot; alt=&quot;frp3&quot; width=&quot;1051&quot; height=&quot;668&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp3.png 1051w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp3.png?w=150&amp;amp;h=95 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp3.png?w=300&amp;amp;h=191 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp3.png?w=768&amp;amp;h=488 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp3.png?w=1024&amp;amp;h=651 1024w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 1051px) 100vw, 1051px&quot;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fake reverse parking&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see and feel by looking at the pictures, fake reverse parking is much easier than ordinary reverse parking and allows you to achieve the same results. As a matter of fact, fake reverse parking is even easier than ordinary forward parking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; data-attachment-id=&quot;23152&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/08/11/to-cheer-you-up-in-difficult-times-36-the-immense-joy-of-fake-reverse-parking/frp7/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp7.png&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;954,600&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;frp7&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp7.png?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp7.png?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-23152&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp7.png&quot; alt=&quot;frp7&quot; width=&quot;954&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp7.png 954w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp7.png?w=150&amp;amp;h=94 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp7.png?w=300&amp;amp;h=189 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/frp7.png?w=768&amp;amp;h=483 768w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 954px) 100vw, 954px&quot;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;Ordinary forward parking&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#0000ff;&quot;&gt;Again, look at the three pictures above and witness for yourself how the pictures of ordinary reverse and ordinary forward parking can make you nervous, while the pictures of fake reverse parking evoke a calm and joyful mood!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff00ff;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caution in parking is advised!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many other joyous activities, some warnings are in place. In any kind of parking, it is a mistake to park your car in a parking place which is already occupied by another car. &lt;strong&gt;For fake reverse parking make sure that there is no simultaneous attempt by another driver to park, using the ordinary reverse parking method inthe same parking space.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fake-fake reverse parking?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day I went with my youngest son Lior to some parking lot near Rehovot. (Here is a lovely post based on a question of Lior &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/03/18/tyi38-lior-kalai-monty-hall-meets-survivor/&quot; rel=&quot;bookmark&quot;&gt;TYI38 Lior Kalai: Monty Hall Meets&amp;nbsp;Survivor&lt;/a&gt;.) It was a large parking lot and it was completely empty.&amp;nbsp; When I parked my son asked me &amp;#8220;why didn&amp;#8217;t you opt for fake reverse parking?&amp;#8221; &amp;#8220;Well&amp;#8221;, I said &amp;#8220;what I did is actually a &amp;#8216;fake-fake reverse parking&amp;#8217;. Later, when the parking space fills up, people will assume that I made a fake-reverse parking. But this was too easy with no cars around so my parking was actually a &amp;#8216;fake-fake-reverse parking&amp;#8217;, aimed at giving a feeling of fake reverse parking, while in reality it is not&amp;#8221;. Lior, thought about it for a minute and then said: &amp;#8220;Daddy, this is complete nonsense! There is no such thing as a &amp;#8216;fake-fake reverse parking&amp;#8217;. What you did is a simple reverse parking!&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Well&amp;#8221;, I thought, &amp;#8220;it is good that my children are skeptical about things I tell them, and shoot down incorrect or silly ideas that I raise.&amp;#8221; Moreover, quickly dismissing my idea about a &amp;#8220;fake-fake reverse parking&amp;#8221; strengthens the value of my classic idea about the importance and joy in ordinary fake reverse parking. Still, I was somewhat sad that my novel idea of fake-fake reverse parking was shot down so quickly. Maybe it has some deep meaning after all?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;an especially magical opportunity for fake reverse parking&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; data-attachment-id=&quot;23171&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/08/11/to-cheer-you-up-in-difficult-times-36-the-immense-joy-of-fake-reverse-parking/ftp11/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/ftp11.png&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1032,652&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;ftp11&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/ftp11.png?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/ftp11.png?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-23171&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/ftp11.png&quot; alt=&quot;ftp11&quot; width=&quot;1032&quot; height=&quot;652&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/ftp11.png 1032w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/ftp11.png?w=150&amp;amp;h=95 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/ftp11.png?w=300&amp;amp;h=190 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/ftp11.png?w=768&amp;amp;h=485 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/ftp11.png?w=1024&amp;amp;h=647 1024w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 1032px) 100vw, 1032px&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;My corner: To cheer you up in difficult times&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;p&gt;(Added August 18, 2022): Since the beginning of the corona pandemic I had a &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot; href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/page/5/?s=cheer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;corner on this blog&lt;/a&gt; “to cheer you up in difficult times”. I must admit that I tried to cheer my audience up with &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot; href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2008/05/23/mathematics-to-the-rescue/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;silly,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot; href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2008/05/12/drachmas/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;funny&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot; href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2008/11/28/the-simplified-pill-algorithm/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;educating&lt;/a&gt; stories earlier on, but since the beginning of the pandemic which largely represented difficult times for all humanity that was not caused by human malice, I thought that these attempts have special value. Now, with the war in Ukraine, I decided to go back to the previous format were the value of being cheered up is left to your own judgement. This post #36 to cheer you up in difficult times is the last one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Gil Kalai&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
      <uri>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Luca Aceto: CONCUR through time: A data- and graph-mining analysis</title>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2022/08/concur-through-time-data-and-graph.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-5531394238346888687</id>
    <updated>2022-08-10T13:55:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://concur2022.mimuw.edu.pl/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;33rd edition of the International Conference on Concurrency Theory (CONCUR&lt;/a&gt;) will be held in Warsaw, Poland, in the period 16–19 September 2022. The first CONCUR conference dates back to 1990 and was one of the conferences organized as part of the two-year &lt;a href=&quot;https://pure.tue.nl/ws/portalfiles/portal/4345371/589768.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ESPRIT Basic&amp;nbsp; Research&amp;nbsp; Action&amp;nbsp; 3006&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp; with&amp;nbsp; the&amp;nbsp; same&amp;nbsp; name.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The&amp;nbsp; CONCUR&amp;nbsp; community&amp;nbsp; has&amp;nbsp; run&amp;nbsp; the conference ever since and established the &lt;a href=&quot;https://concurrency-theory.org/organizations/ifip&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;IFIP WG 1.8 “Concurrency Theory”&lt;/a&gt; in 2005 under Technical Committee TC1 Foundations of Computer Science of IFIP1.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In light of the well-established nature of the CONCUR conference, and spurred by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://slides.com/piluc/icalp-50?token=fl3BBJ8j&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;data-and graph-mining comparative analysis&lt;/a&gt; carried out by Pierluigi Crescenzi and three of his students to celebrate the 50th anniversary of ICALP, Pierluigi and I undertook a similar study for the CONCUR conference using some, by now classic, tools from network science.&amp;nbsp; Our goal was to try and understand the evolution of the CONCUR conference throughout its history, the ebb and flow in the popularity of some research areas in concurrency theory, and the centrality of CONCUR authors, as measured by several metrics from network science, amongst other topics.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our article available &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.icetcs.ru.is/luca/CONCUR.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; reports on our findings.&amp;nbsp; We hope that members of the CONCUR community will enjoy reading it and playing with the web-based resources that accompany this piece.&amp;nbsp; It goes without saying that the data analysis we present has to be taken with a huge pinch of salt and is only meant to provide an overview of the evolution of CONCUR and to be food for thought for the concurrency theory community. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Luca Aceto&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      <uri>http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Theory Matters: NAS Held Prize: Call for nominations</title>
    <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/2022/08/09/nas-held-prize-call-for-nominations/"/>
    <id>http://thmatters.wordpress.com/?p=1380</id>
    <updated>2022-08-09T17:31:06+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;From chair of the committee, Dan Spielman:&lt;br&gt;Nominations are now being accepted for the National Academy of Sciences’ 2023 Michael and Sheila Held Prize. The Held Prize honors outstanding, innovative, creative, and influential research in the areas of combinatorial and discrete optimization, or related parts of computer science, such as the design and analysis of algorithms and complexity theory. This $100,000 prize is intended to recognize recent work (defined as published within the last eight years). Additional information, including past recipients, eligibility requirements, and more, can be found at &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot; href=&quot;http://www.nasonline.org/held&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.nasonline.org/held&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;All nominations must be submitted online. Unless otherwise stated, the following materials must be submitted:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A letter from the nominator&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;describing the candidate&amp;#8217;s work and why he or she should be selected for the award. No more than three (3) pages.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Curriculum vitae&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;No more than two (2) pages (similar to CVs included with NSF proposals).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bibliography&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;listing no more than twelve (12) of the nominee&amp;#8217;s most significant publications.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suggested citation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;. A 50-word summary stating why the nominee should be considered for this award&lt;/em&gt;. (Citation&lt;br&gt;examples)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two letters of support&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Support letters must be written by individuals from institutions outside both the&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;em&gt;nominator&amp;#8217;s and the nominee’s institution. Up to three letters of support are accepted.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Nominations will be accepted through&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;Monday, October 3, 2022&lt;/strong&gt;. Please help spread the word that the nomination process is underway.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shuchic&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Theory Matters</name>
      <uri>https://thmatters.wordpress.com</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


</feed>
