<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title>Theory of Computing Report</title>
  <link rel="self" href=""/>
  <link href=""/>
  <id></id>
  <updated></updated>
  <generator uri="http://feedreader.github.io/">Pluto 1.6.2 on Ruby 3.0.5 (2022-11-24) [x86_64-linux]</generator>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Meta-Diagrams for 2-Parameter Persistence</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08270"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08270</id>
    <updated>2023-03-16T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Clause_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nate Clause&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Dey_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tamal K. Dey&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Memoli_F/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Facundo M&amp;#xe9;moli&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Wang_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Bei Wang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We first introduce the notion of meta-rank for a 2-parameter persistence
module, an invariant that captures the information behind images of morphisms
between 1D slices of the module. We then define the meta-diagram of a
2-parameter persistence module to be the M\&quot;{o}bius inversion of the meta-rank,
resulting in a function that takes values from signed 1-parameter persistence
modules. We show that the meta-rank and meta-diagram contain information
equivalent to the rank invariant and the signed barcode. This equivalence leads
to computational benefits, as we introduce an algorithm for computing the
meta-rank and meta-diagram of a 2-parameter module $M$ indexed by a
bifiltration of $n$ simplices in $O(n^3)$ time. This implies an improvement
upon the existing algorithm for computing the signed barcode, which has
$O(n^4)$ runtime. This also allows us to improve the existing upper bound on
the number of rectangles in the rank decomposition of $M$ from $O(n^4)$ to
$O(n^3)$. In addition, we define notions of erosion distance between meta-ranks
and between meta-diagrams, and show that under these distances, meta-ranks and
meta-diagrams are stable with respect to the interleaving distance. Lastly, the
meta-diagram can be visualized in an intuitive fashion as a persistence diagram
of diagrams, which generalizes the well-understood persistence diagram in the
1-parameter setting.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Economical Convex Coverings and Applications</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08349"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08349</id>
    <updated>2023-03-16T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Arya_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sunil Arya&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Fonseca_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Guilherme D. da Fonseca&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mount_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;David M. Mount&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coverings of convex bodies have emerged as a central component in the design
of efficient solutions to approximation problems involving convex bodies.
Intuitively, given a convex body $K$ and $\epsilon&amp;gt; 0$, a covering is a
collection of convex bodies whose union covers $K$ such that a constant factor
expansion of each body lies within an $\epsilon$ expansion of $K$. Coverings
have been employed in many applications, such as approximations for diameter,
width, and $\epsilon$-kernels of point sets, approximate nearest neighbor
searching, polytope approximations, and approximations to the Closest Vector
Problem (CVP).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is known how to construct coverings of size $n^{O(n)} /
\epsilon^{(n-1)/2}$ for general convex bodies in $\textbf{R}^n$. In special
cases, such as when the convex body is the $\ell_p$ unit ball, this bound has
been improved to $2^{O(n)} / \epsilon^{(n-1)/2}$. This raises the question of
whether such a bound generally holds. In this paper we answer the question in
the affirmative.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate the power and versatility of our coverings by applying them to
the problem of approximating a convex body by a polytope, under the
Banach-Mazur metric. Given a well-centered convex body $K$ and an approximation
parameter $\epsilon&amp;gt; 0$, we show that there exists a polytope $P$ consisting of
$2^{O(n)} / \epsilon^{(n-1)/2}$ vertices (facets) such that $K \subset P
\subset K(1+\epsilon)$. This bound is optimal in the worst case up to factors
of $2^{O(n)}$. As an additional consequence, we obtain the fastest
$(1+\epsilon)$-approximate CVP algorithm that works in any norm, with a running
time of $2^{O(n)} / \epsilon ^{(n-1)/2}$ up to polynomial factors in the input
size, and we obtain the fastest $(1+\epsilon)$-approximation algorithm for
integer programming. We also present a framework for constructing coverings of
optimal size for any convex body (up to factors of $2^{O(n)}$).
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Statistical learning on measures: an application to persistence diagrams</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08456"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08456</id>
    <updated>2023-03-16T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hacquard_O/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Olympio Hacquard&lt;/a&gt; (LMO, DATASHAPE)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We consider a binary supervised learning classification problem where instead
of having data in a finite-dimensional Euclidean space, we observe measures on
a compact space $\mathcal{X}$. Formally, we observe data $D_N = (\mu_1, Y_1),
\ldots, (\mu_N, Y_N)$ where $\mu_i$ is a measure on $\mathcal{X}$ and $Y_i$ is
a label in $\{0, 1\}$. Given a set $\mathcal{F}$ of base-classifiers on
$\mathcal{X}$, we build corresponding classifiers in the space of measures. We
provide upper and lower bounds on the Rademacher complexity of this new class
of classifiers that can be expressed simply in terms of corresponding
quantities for the class $\mathcal{F}$. If the measures $\mu_i$ are uniform
over a finite set, this classification task boils down to a multi-instance
learning problem. However, our approach allows more flexibility and diversity
in the input data we can deal with. While such a framework has many possible
applications, this work strongly emphasizes on classifying data via topological
descriptors called persistence diagrams. These objects are discrete measures on
$\mathbb{R}^2$, where the coordinates of each point correspond to the range of
scales at which a topological feature exists. We will present several
classifiers on measures and show how they can heuristically and theoretically
enable a good classification performance in various settings in the case of
persistence diagrams.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: The Number of Edges in Maximal 2-planar Graphs</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08726"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08726</id>
    <updated>2023-03-16T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Hoffmann_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Michael Hoffmann&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Reddy_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Meghana M. Reddy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A graph is $2$-planar if it has local crossing number two, that is, it can be
drawn in the plane such that every edge has at most two crossings. A graph is
maximal $2$-planar if no edge can be added such that the resulting graph
remains $2$-planar. A $2$-planar graph on $n$ vertices has at most $5n-10$
edges, and some (maximal) $2$-planar graphs -- referred to as optimal
$2$-planar -- achieve this bound. However, in strong contrast to maximal planar
graphs, a maximal $2$-planar graph may have fewer than the maximum possible
number of edges. In this paper, we determine the minimum edge density of
maximal $2$-planar graphs by proving that every maximal $2$-planar graph on
$n\ge 5$ vertices has at least $2n$ edges. We also show that this bound is
tight, up to an additive constant. The lower bound is based on an analysis of
the degree distribution in specific classes of drawings of the graph. The upper
bound construction is verified by carefully exploring the space of admissible
drawings using computer support.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Combinatorial Designs Meet Hypercliques: Higher Lower Bounds for Klee&#39;s Measure Problem and Related Problems in Dimensions $d\ge 4$</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08612"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08612</id>
    <updated>2023-03-16T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gorbachev_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Egor Gorbachev&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kunnemann_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Marvin K&amp;#xfc;nnemann&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Klee&#39;s measure problem (computing the volume of the union of $n$
axis-parallel boxes in $\mathbb{R}^d$) is well known to have $n^{\frac{d}{2}\pm
o(1)}$-time algorithms (Overmars, Yap, SICOMP&#39;91; Chan FOCS&#39;13). Only recently,
a conditional lower bound (without any restriction to ``combinatorial&#39;&#39;
algorithms) could be shown for $d=3$ (K\&quot;unnemann, FOCS&#39;22). Can this result be
extended to a tight lower bound for dimensions $d\ge 4$?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we formalize the technique of the tight lower bound for $d=3$
using a combinatorial object we call prefix covering design. We show that these
designs, which are related in spirit to combinatorial designs, directly
translate to conditional lower bounds for Klee&#39;s measure problem and various
related problems. By devising good prefix covering designs, we give the
following lower bounds for Klee&#39;s measure problem in $\mathbb{R}^d$, the depth
problem for axis-parallel boxes in $\mathbb{R}^d$, the
largest-volume/max-perimeter empty (anchored) box problem in $\mathbb{R}^{2d}$,
and related problems:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- $\Omega(n^{1.90476})$ for $d=4$,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- $\Omega(n^{2.22222})$ for $d=5$,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- $\Omega(n^{d/3 + 2\sqrt{d}/9-o(\sqrt{d})})$ for general $d$,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;assuming the 3-uniform hyperclique hypothesis. For Klee&#39;s measure problem and
the depth problem, these bounds improve previous lower bounds of
$\Omega(n^{1.777...}), \Omega(n^{2.0833...})$ and $\Omega(n^{d/3 + 1/3 +
\Theta(1/d)})$ respectively.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our improved prefix covering designs were obtained by (1) exploiting a
computer-aided search using problem-specific insights as well as SAT solvers,
and (2) showing how to transform combinatorial covering designs known in the
literature to strong prefix covering designs. In contrast, we show that our
lower bounds are close to best possible using this proof technique.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: A 2-opt Algorithm for Locally Optimal Set Partition Optimization</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08219"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08219</id>
    <updated>2023-03-16T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gokcesu_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Kaan Gokcesu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gokcesu_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hakan Gokcesu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our research deals with the optimization version of the set partition
problem, where the objective is to minimize the absolute difference between the
sums of the two disjoint partitions. Although this problem is known to be
NP-hard and requires exponential time to solve, we propose a less demanding
version of this problem where the goal is to find a locally optimal solution.
In our approach, we consider the local optimality in respect to any movement of
at most two elements. To accomplish this, we developed an algorithm that can
generate a locally optimal solution in at most $O(N^2)$ time and $O(N)$ space.
Our algorithm can handle arbitrary input precisions and does not require
positive or integer inputs. Hence, it can be applied in various problem
scenarios with ease.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR23-028 |  An Algorithmic Approach to Uniform Lower Bounds | 

	Rahul Santhanam</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/028"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/028</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T21:40:54+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    We propose a new family of circuit-based sampling tasks, such that non-trivial algorithmic solutions to certain tasks from this family imply frontier uniform lower bounds such as ``NP is not in uniform ACC^0&amp;quot; and ``NP does not have uniform polynomial-size depth-two threshold circuits&amp;quot;. Indeed, the most general versions of our sampling tasks have implications for central open problems such as NP vs P and PSPACE vs P.

We argue the soundness of our approach by showing that the non-trivial algorithmic solutions we require do follow from standard cryptographic assumptions. In addition, we give evidence that a version of our approach for uniform circuits is necessary in order to separate NP from P or PSPACE from P. We give an algorithmic characterization for the PSPACE vs P question: PSPACE is not equal to P iff either E has sub-exponential time non-uniform algorithms infinitely often or there are non-trivial space-efficient solutions to our sampling tasks for uniform Boolean circuits.

We show how to use our framework to capture uniform versions of known non-uniform lower bounds, as well as classical uniform lower bounds such as the space hierarchy theorem and Allender&amp;#39;s uniform lower bound for the Permanent. We also apply our framework to prove new lower bounds: NP does not have uniform polynomial-size AC^0 circuits with a bottom layer of MOD 6 gates, nor does it have uniform polynomial-size  AC^0 circuits with a bottom layer of threshold gates.

Our proofs exploit recently defined probabilistic time-bounded variants of Kolmogorov complexity [Lu-Oliveira-Zimand22, Goldberg-Kabanets-Lu-Oliveira22, Lu-Oliveira22].
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR23-027 |  Some Lower Bounds Related to the Missing String Problem | 

	Joseph Zalewski</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/027"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/027</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T21:23:50+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    We prove that a $O(k \log k)$-probe local algorithm for $k$-Missing String presented by Vyas and Williams is asymptotically optimal among a certain class of algorithms for this problem. The best lower bound we are aware of for the general case is still $\Omega(k)$.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR23-026 |  Hardness Self-Amplification: Simplified, Optimized, and Unified | 

	Shuichi Hirahara, 

	Nobutaka Shimizu</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/026"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/026</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T21:21:12+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    Strong (resp. weak) average-case hardness refers to the properties of a computational problem in which a large (resp. small) fraction of instances are hard to solve. We develop a general framework for proving hardness self-amplification, that is, the equivalence between strong and weak average-case hardness. Using this framework, we prove hardness self-amplification for popular problems, such as matrix multiplication, online matrix-vector multiplication, triangle counting of Erd\H{o}s--R\&amp;#39;enyi random graphs, and the planted clique problem. As a corollary, we obtain the first search-to-decision reduction for the planted clique problem in a high-error regime. Our framework simplifies, improves, and unifies the previous hardness self-amplification results.
   
Our approach uses a one-query upward self-reduction, that is, a reduction that maps a small instance to a large instance. We demonstrate that this reduction yields hardness self-amplification if the bipartite graph, whose left and right vertices correspond to small and large instances, respectively, has an expansion property. Our key technical contribution is to show the expansion property of the bipartite graph naturally constructed from the planted clique problem by using the coupling method of Markov chains.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR23-025 |  Multivariate to Bivariate Reduction for Noncommutative   Polynomial Factorization | 

	Pushkar Joglekar, 

	Vikraman Arvind</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/025"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/025</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T21:15:04+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    Based on a theorem of Bergman we show that multivariate noncommutative polynomial factorization is deterministic polynomial-time reducible to the factorization of bivariate noncommutative polynomials. More precisely, we show the following:

  (1) In the white-box setting, given an n-variate noncommutative polynomial f in F over a field F (either a finite field or the rationals) as an arithmetic circuit (or algebraic branching program), computing a complete factorization of f is deterministic polynomial-time reducible to white-box factorization of a noncommutative bivariate polynomial g in F; the reduction transforms f into a circuit for g (resp. ABP for g), and given a complete factorization of g the reduction recovers a complete factorization of f in polynomial time. We also obtain a similar deterministic polynomial-time reduction in the black-box setting.

  (2) Additionally, we show over the field of rationals that bivariate linear matrix factorization of 4 x 4 matrices is at least as hard as factoring square-free integers. This indicates that reducing noncommutative polynomial factorization to linear matrix factorization (as done in our recent work [AJ22]) is unlikely to succeed over the field of rationals even in the bivariate case.
  In contrast, multivariate linear matrix factorization for 3 x 3 matrices over rationals is in polynomial time.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR23-024 |  Approximate degree lower bounds for oracle identification problems | 

	Mark Bun, 

	Nadezhda Voronova</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/024"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/024</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T21:14:17+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    The approximate degree of a Boolean function is the minimum degree of real polynomial that approximates it pointwise. For any Boolean function, its approximate degree serves as a lower bound on its quantum query complexity, and generically lifts to a quantum communication lower bound for a related function.

    We introduce a framework for proving approximate degree lower bounds for certain oracle identification problems, where the goal is to recover a hidden binary string $x \in \{0, 1\}^n$ given possibly non-standard oracle access to it. We apply this framework to the ordered search and hidden string problems, proving nearly tight approximate degree lower bounds of $\Omega(n/\log^2 n)$ for each. These new lower bounds are driven by randomized communication upper bounds for the greater-than and equality functions.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR23-023 |  Two Source Extractors for Asymptotically Optimal Entropy, and (Many) More | 

	Xin Li</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/023"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/023</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T20:01:28+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    A long line of work in the past two decades or so established close connections between several different pseudorandom objects and applications, including seeded or seedless non-malleable extractors, two source extractors, (bipartite) Ramsey graphs, privacy amplification protocols with an active adversary, non-malleable codes and many more. These connections essentially show that an asymptotically optimal construction of one central object will lead to asymptotically optimal solutions to all the others. However, despite considerable effort, previous works can get close but still lack one final step to achieve truly asymptotically optimal constructions.

In this paper we provide the last missing link, thus simultaneously achieving explicit, asymptotically optimal constructions and solutions for various well studied extractors and applications, that have been the subjects of long lines of research. Our results include:

(1) Asymptotically optimal seeded non-malleable extractors, which in turn give two source extractors for asymptotically optimal min-entropy of $O(\log n)$, explicit constructions of $K$-Ramsey graphs on $N$ vertices with $K=\log^{O(1)} N$, and truly optimal privacy amplification protocols with an active adversary.

(2) Two source non-malleable extractors and affine non-malleable extractors for some linear min-entropy with exponentially small error, which in turn give the first explicit construction of non-malleable codes against $2$-split state tampering and affine tampering with constant rate and \emph{exponentially} small error.
  
(3) Explicit extractors for affine sources, sumset sources, interleaved sources, and small space sources that achieve asymptotically optimal min-entropy of $O(\log n)$ or $2s+O(\log n)$ (for space $s$ sources).

(4) An explicit function that requires strongly linear read once branching programs of size $2^{n-O(\log n)}$, which is optimal up to the constant in $O(\cdot)$. Previously, even for standard read once branching programs, the best known size lower bound for an explicit function is $2^{n-O(\log^2 n)}$.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">CCI: jobs: Tenure-track Faculty Positions in Computer Science  at IE University, Madrid (apply by May 28, 2023)</title>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/03/15/tenure-track-faculty-positions-in-computer-science-at-ie-university-madrid-apply-by-may-28-2023/"/>
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/03/15/tenure-track-faculty-positions-in-computer-science-at-ie-university-madrid-apply-by-may-28-2023/</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T15:47:51+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;IE University&amp;#8217;s School of Science and Technology (Sci-Tech) invites qualified applicants for full-time, tenure-track faculty positions in Computer and Data Science beginning September 2023, in Madrid. We are currently offering 6 positions in this area, which will remain open until filled with suitable candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://apply.interfolio.com/36317/positions&quot;&gt;https://apply.interfolio.com/36317/positions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: manuele.leonelli@ie.edu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>CCI: jobs</name>
      <uri>https://cstheory-jobs.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Drawings of Complete Multipartite Graphs Up to Triangle Flips</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07401"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07401</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Aichholzer_O/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Oswin Aichholzer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chiu_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Man-Kwun Chiu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hoang_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hung P. Hoang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hoffmann_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Michael Hoffmann&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kyncl_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jan Kyn&amp;#x10d;l&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Maus_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yannic Maus&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Vogtenhuber_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Birgit Vogtenhuber&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Weinberger_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Alexandra Weinberger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a drawing of a labeled graph, the rotation of a vertex or crossing is the
cyclic order of its incident edges, represented by the labels of their other
endpoints. The extended rotation system (ERS) of the drawing is the collection
of the rotations of all vertices and crossings. A drawing is simple if each
pair of edges has at most one common point. Gioan&#39;s Theorem states that for any
two simple drawings of the complete graph $K_n$ with the same crossing edge
pairs, one drawing can be transformed into the other by a sequence of triangle
flips (a.k.a. Reidemeister moves of Type 3). This operation refers to the act
of moving one edge of a triangular cell formed by three pairwise crossing edges
over the opposite crossing of the cell, via a local transformation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We investigate to what extent Gioan-type theorems can be obtained for wider
classes of graphs. A necessary (but in general not sufficient) condition for
two drawings of a graph to be transformable into each other by a sequence of
triangle flips is that they have the same ERS. As our main result, we show that
for the large class of complete multipartite graphs, this necessary condition
is in fact also sufficient. We present two different proofs of this result, one
of which is shorter, while the other one yields a polynomial time algorithm for
which the number of needed triangle flips for graphs on $n$ vertices is bounded
by $O(n^{16})$. The latter proof uses a Carath\&#39;eodory-type theorem for simple
drawings of complete multipartite graphs, which we believe to be of independent
interest.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, we show that our Gioan-type theorem for complete multipartite
graphs is essentially tight in the sense that having the same ERS does not
remain sufficient when removing or adding very few edges.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Finding a Maximum Clique in a Disk Graph</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07645"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07645</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Espenant_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jared Espenant&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Keil_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;J. Mark Keil&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mondal_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Debajyoti Mondal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A disk graph is an intersection graph of disks in the Euclidean plane, where
the disks correspond to the vertices of the graph and a pair of vertices are
adjacent if and only if their corresponding disks intersect. The problem of
determining the time complexity of computing a maximum clique in a disk graph
is a long-standing open question. The problem is known to be open even when the
radii of all the disks are in the interval $[1,(1+\varepsilon)]$, where
$\varepsilon&amp;gt;0$. However, the maximum clique problem is known to be APX-hard
for the intersection graphs of many other convex objects such as intersection
graphs of ellipses, triangles, and a combination of unit disks and
axis-parallel rectangles. Furthermore, there exists an $O(n^3\log n)$-time
algorithm to compute a maximum clique for unit disks. Here we obtain the
following results.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- We give an algorithm to compute a maximum clique in a unit disk graph in
$O(n^{2.5}\log n)$-time, which improves the previously best known running time
of $O(n^3\log n)$ [Eppstein &#39;09].
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- We extend a widely used `co-2-subdivision approach&#39; to prove that computing
a maximum clique in a combination of unit disks and axis-parallel rectangles is
NP-hard to approximate within $4448/4449 \approx 0.9997 $. The use of a
`co-2-subdivision approach&#39; was previously thought to be unlikely in this
setting [Bonnet et al. &#39;20]. Our result improves the previously known
inapproximability factor of $7633010347/7633010348\approx 0.9999$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- We show that the parameter minimum lens width of the disk arrangement may
be used to make progress in the case when disk radii are in
$[1,(1+\varepsilon)]$. For example, if the minimum lens width is at least
$0.265$ and $ \varepsilon\le 0.0001$, which still allows for non-Helly triples
in the arrangement, then one can find a maximum clique in polynomial time.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Shadoks Approach to Convex Covering</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07696"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07696</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Fonseca_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Guilherme D. da Fonseca&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We describe the heuristics used by the Shadoks team in the CG:SHOP 2023
Challenge. The Challenge consists of 206 instances, each being a polygon with
holes. The goal is to cover each instance polygon with a small number of convex
polygons. Our general strategy is the following. We find a big collection of
large (often maximal) convex polygons inside the instance polygon and then
solve several set cover problems to find a small subset of the collection that
covers the whole polygon.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: A note on the flip distance between non-crossing spanning trees</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07710"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07710</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Bousquet_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nicolas Bousquet&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gledel_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Valentin Gledel&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Narboni_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jonathan Narboni&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Pierron_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Th&amp;#xe9;o Pierron&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We consider spanning trees of $n$ points in convex position whose edges are
pairwise non-crossing. Applying a flip to such a tree consists in adding an
edge and removing another so that the result is still a non-crossing spanning
tree. Given two trees, we investigate the minimum number of flips required to
transform one into the other. The naive $2n-\Omega(1)$ upper bound stood for 25
years until a recent breakthrough from Aichholzer et al. yielding a
$2n-\Omega(\log n)$ bound. We improve their result with a $2n-\Omega(\sqrt{n})$
upper bound, and we strengthen and shorten the proofs of several of their
results.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Canonical Sphere Bases for Simplicial and Cubical Complexes</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07947"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07947</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Kainen_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Paul C. Kainen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sphere-bases are constructed for the $\mathbb{Z}_2$ vector space formed by
the $k$-dimensional subcomplexes, of $n$-simplex (or $n$-cube), for which every
$(k{-}1)$-face is contained in a positive even number of $k$-cells; addition is
symmetric difference of the corresponding sets of $k$-cells. The bases consist
of the boundaries of an algorithmically-specified family of $k{+}1$-simplexes
or $k{+}1$-cubes. Geometric properties of these bases are investigated.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: A Structural Approach to Tree Decompositions of Knots and Spatial Graphs</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07982"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07982</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lunel_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Corentin Lunel&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mesmay_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Arnaud de Mesmay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Knots are commonly represented and manipulated via diagrams, which are
decorated planar graphs. When such a knot diagram has low treewidth,
parameterized graph algorithms can be leveraged to ensure the fast computation
of many invariants and properties of the knot. It was recently proved that
there exist knots which do not admit any diagram of low treewidth, and the
proof relied on intricate low-dimensional topology techniques. In this work, we
initiate a thorough investigation of tree decompositions of knot diagrams (or
more generally, diagrams of spatial graphs) using ideas from structural graph
theory. We define an obstruction on spatial embeddings that forbids low tree
width diagrams, and we prove that it is optimal with respect to a related width
invariant. We then show the existence of this obstruction for knots of high
representativity, which include for example torus knots, providing a new and
self-contained proof that those do not admit diagrams of low treewidth. This
last step is inspired by a result of Pardon on knot distortion.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Algorithms for Length Spectra of Combinatorial Tori</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08036"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08036</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Delecroix_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vincent Delecroix&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ebbens_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Matthijs Ebbens&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lazarus_F/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Francis Lazarus&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Yakovlev_I/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ivan Yakovlev&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consider a weighted, undirected graph cellularly embedded on a topological
surface. The function assigning to each free homotopy class of closed curves
the length of a shortest cycle within this homotopy class is called the marked
length spectrum. The (unmarked) length spectrum is obtained by just listing the
length values of the marked length spectrum in increasing order.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we describe algorithms for computing the (un)marked length
spectra of graphs embedded on the torus. More specifically, we preprocess a
weighted graph of complexity $n$ in time $O(n^2 \log \log n)$ so that, given a
cycle with $\ell$ edges representing a free homotopy class, the length of a
shortest homotopic cycle can be computed in $O(\ell+\log n)$ time. Moreover,
given any positive integer $k$, the first $k$ values of its unmarked length
spectrum can be computed in time $O(k \log n)$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our algorithms are based on a correspondence between weighted graphs on the
torus and polyhedral norms. In particular, we give a weight independent bound
on the complexity of the unit ball of such norms. As an immediate consequence
we can decide if two embedded weighted graphs have the same marked spectrum in
polynomial time. We also consider the problem of comparing the unmarked spectra
and provide a polynomial time algorithm in the unweighted case and a randomized
polynomial time algorithm otherwise.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Quantum Steering Algorithm for Estimating Fidelity of Separability</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07911"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07911</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Philip_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Aby Philip&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Rethinasamy_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Soorya Rethinasamy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Russo_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vincent Russo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Wilde_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mark M. Wilde&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Quantifying entanglement is an important task by which the resourcefulness of
a state can be measured. Here we develop a quantum algorithm that tests for and
quantifies the separability of a general bipartite state, by making use of the
quantum steering effect. Our first separability test consists of a distributed
quantum computation involving two parties: a computationally limited client,
who prepares a purification of the state of interest, and a computationally
unbounded server, who tries to steer the reduced systems to a probabilistic
ensemble of pure product states. To design a practical algorithm, we replace
the role of the server by a combination of parameterized unitary circuits and
classical optimization techniques to perform the necessary computation. The
result is a variational quantum steering algorithm (VQSA), which is our second
separability test that is better suited for the capabilities of quantum
computers available today. This VQSA has an additional interpretation as a
distributed variational quantum algorithm (VQA) that can be executed over a
quantum network, in which each node is equipped with classical and quantum
computers capable of executing VQA. We then simulate our VQSA on noisy quantum
simulators and find favorable convergence properties on the examples tested. We
also develop semidefinite programs, executable on classical computers, that
benchmark the results obtained from our VQSA. Our findings here thus provide a
meaningful connection between steering, entanglement, quantum algorithms, and
quantum computational complexity theory. They also demonstrate the value of a
parameterized mid-circuit measurement in a VQSA and represent a
first-of-its-kind application for a distributed VQA. Finally, the whole
framework generalizes to the case of multipartite states and entanglement.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Logarithmic Weisfeiler--Leman and Treewidth</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07985"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07985</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Levet_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Michael Levet&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rombach_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Puck Rombach&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sieger_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nicholas Sieger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we show that the $(3k+4)$-dimensional Weisfeiler--Leman
algorithm can identify graphs of treewidth $k$ in $O(\log n)$ rounds. This
improves the result of Grohe &amp;amp; Verbitsky (ICALP 2006), who previously
established the analogous result for $(4k+3)$-dimensional Weisfeiler--Leman. In
light of the equivalence between Weisfeiler--Leman and the logic $\textsf{FO} +
\textsf{C}$ (Cai, F\&quot;urer, &amp;amp; Immerman, Combinatorica 1992), we obtain an
improvement in the descriptive complexity for graphs of treewidth $k$.
Precisely, if $G$ is a graph of treewidth $k$, then there exists a
$(3k+5)$-variable formula $\varphi$ in $\textsf{FO} + \textsf{C}$ with
quantifier depth $O(\log n)$ that identifies $G$ up to isomorphism.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Polynomial-Time Approximation Schemes for Independent Packing Problems on Fractionally Tree-Independence-Number-Fragile Graphs</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07444"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07444</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Galby_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Esther Galby&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Munaro_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Andrea Munaro&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Yang_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Shizhou Yang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We investigate a relaxation of the notion of treewidth-fragility, namely
tree-independence-number-fragility. In particular, we obtain polynomial-time
approximation schemes for independent packing problems on fractionally
tree-independence-number-fragile graph classes. Our approach unifies and
extends several known polynomial-time approximation schemes on seemingly
unrelated graph classes, such as classes of intersection graphs of fat objects
in a fixed dimension or proper minor-closed classes. We also study the related
notion of layered tree-independence number, a relaxation of layered treewidth.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Efficient Yao Graph Construction</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07858"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07858</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Funke_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Daniel Funke&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sanders_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Peter Sanders&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yao graphs are geometric spanners that connect each point of a given point
set to its nearest neighbor in each of $k$ cones drawn around it. Yao graphs
were introduced to construct minimum spanning trees in $d$ dimensional spaces.
Moreover, they are used for instance in topology control in wireless networks.
An optimal \Onlogn time algorithm to construct Yao graphs for given point set
has been proposed in the literature but -- to the best of our knowledge --
never been implemented. Instead, algorithms with a quadratic complexity are
used in popular packages to construct these graphs. In this paper we present
the first implementation of the optimal Yao graph algorithm. We develop and
tune the data structures required to achieve the O(n log n) bound and detail
algorithmic adaptions necessary to take the original algorithm from theory to
practice. We propose a priority queue data structure that separates static and
dynamic events and might be of independent interest for other sweepline
algorithms. Additionally, we propose a new Yao graph algorithm based on a
uniform grid data structure that performs well for medium-sized inputs. We
evaluate our implementations on a wide variety synthetic and real-world
datasets and show that our implementation outperforms current publicly
available implementations by at least an order of magnitude.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: FPT Constant-Approximations for Capacitated Clustering to Minimize the Sum of Cluster Radii</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07923"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07923</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Bandyapadhyay_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sayan Bandyapadhyay&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lochet_W/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;William Lochet&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Saurabh_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Saket Saurabh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clustering with capacity constraints is a fundamental problem that attracted
significant attention throughout the years. In this paper, we give the first
FPT constant-factor approximation algorithm for the problem of clustering
points in a general metric into $k$ clusters to minimize the sum of cluster
radii, subject to non-uniform hard capacity constraints. In particular, we give
a $(15+\epsilon)$-approximation algorithm that runs in $2^{0(k^2\log k)}\cdot
n^3$ time. When capacities are uniform, we obtain the following improved
approximation bounds: A (4 + $\epsilon$)-approximation with running time
$2^{O(k\log(k/\epsilon))}n^3$, which significantly improves over the FPT
28-approximation of Inamdar and Varadarajan [ESA 2020]; a (2 +
$\epsilon$)-approximation with running time $2^{O(k/\epsilon^2
\cdot\log(k/\epsilon))}dn^3$ and a $(1+\epsilon)$-approximation with running
time $2^{O(kd\log ((k/\epsilon)))}n^{3}$ in the Euclidean space; and a (1 +
$\epsilon$)-approximation in the Euclidean space with running time
$2^{O(k/\epsilon^2 \cdot\log(k/\epsilon))}dn^3$ if we are allowed to violate
the capacities by (1 + $\epsilon$)-factor. We complement this result by showing
that there is no (1 + $\epsilon$)-approximation algorithm running in time
$f(k)\cdot n^{O(1)}$, if any capacity violation is not allowed.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Enumerating all minimal hitting sets in polynomial total time</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07708"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07708</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Wild_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Marcel Wild&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consider a hypergraph (=set system) $\mathbb{H}$ whose $h$ hyperedges are
subsets of a set with w elements. We show that the $R$ minimal hitting sets of
$\mathbb{H}$ can be enumerated in polynomial total time $O(Rh^2 w^2)$.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Asymptotically Sharp Upper Bound for the Column Subset Selection Problem</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07984"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07984</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Cai_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jian-Feng Cai&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Xu_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zhiqiang Xu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Xu_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zili Xu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper investigates the spectral norm version of the column subset
selection problem. Given a matrix $\mathbf{A}\in\mathbb{R}^{n\times d}$ and a
positive integer $k\leq\text{rank}(\mathbf{A})$, the objective is to select
exactly $k$ columns of $\mathbf{A}$ that minimize the spectral norm of the
residual matrix after projecting $\mathbf{A}$ onto the space spanned by the
selected columns. We use the method of interlacing polynomials introduced by
Marcus-Spielman-Srivastava to derive an asymptotically sharp upper bound on the
minimal approximation error, and propose a deterministic polynomial-time
algorithm that achieves this error bound (up to a computational error).
Furthermore, we extend our result to a column partition problem in which the
columns of $\mathbf{A}$ can be partitioned into $r\geq 2$ subsets such that
$\mathbf{A}$ can be well approximated by subsets from various groups. We show
that the machinery of interlacing polynomials also works in this context, and
establish a connection between the relevant expected characteristic polynomials
and the $r$-characteristic polynomials introduced by Ravichandran and Leake. As
a consequence, we prove that the columns of a rank-$d$ matrix
$\mathbf{A}\in\mathbb{R}^{n\times d}$ can be partitioned into $r$ subsets
$S_1,\ldots S_r$, such that the column space of $\mathbf{A}$ can be well
approximated by the span of the columns in the complement of $S_i$ for each
$1\leq i\leq r$.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Parameterised Approximation of the Fixation Probability of the Dominant Mutation in the Multi-Type Moran Process</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08118"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08118</id>
    <updated>2023-03-15T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Goldberg_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Leslie Ann Goldberg&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Roth_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Marc Roth&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Schwarz_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tassilo Constantin Schwarz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The multi-type Moran process is an evolutionary process on a connected graph
$G$ in which each vertex has one of $k$ types and, in each step, a vertex $v$
is chosen to reproduce its type to one of its neighbours. The probability of a
vertex $v$ being chosen for reproduction is proportional to the fitness of the
type of $v$. So far, the literature was almost solely concerned with the
$2$-type Moran process in which each vertex is either healthy (type $0$) or a
mutant (type $1$), and the main problem of interest has been the (approximate)
computation of the so-called fixation probability, i.e., the probability that
eventually all vertices are mutants.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this work we initiate the study of approximating fixation probabilities in
the multi-type Moran process on general graphs. Our main result is an FPTRAS
(fixed-parameter tractable randomised approximation scheme) for computing the
fixation probability of the dominant mutation; the parameter is the number of
types and their fitnesses. In the course of our studies we also provide novel
upper bounds on the expected absorption time, i.e., the time that it takes the
multi-type Moran process to reach a state in which each vertex has the same
type.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Richard Lipton: Is Pi Informative?</title>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/03/14/is-pi-informative/"/>
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=21239</id>
    <updated>2023-03-14T06:39:38+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;
&lt;font color=&quot;#0044cc&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Some musings on the meanings of information content&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;font color=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;image alignright&quot;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/03/14/is-pi-informative/frank-longbio/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-21241&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;21241&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/03/14/is-pi-informative/frank-longbio/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/frank-longbio.jpg?fit=200%2C222&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;200,222&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;frank-longbio&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/frank-longbio.jpg?fit=200%2C222&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/frank-longbio.jpg?fit=200%2C222&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/frank-longbio.jpg?resize=134%2C148&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; height=&quot;148&quot; class=&quot;alignright wp-image-21241&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;caption alignright&quot;&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;-2&quot;&gt;SF Exploratorium &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.exploratorium.edu/files/frank/bio/bio-long.html&quot;&gt;tribute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Frank Oppenheimer was a physicist who made pioneering studies of cosmic rays via high-altitude balloons in the late 1940s. He was later the founding directorof the San Francicso Exploratorium. There he hired the physicist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Larry_Shaw_(physicist)&quot;&gt;Larry Shaw&lt;/a&gt;, who became the creator of Pi Day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today we discuss what information&amp;#8212;if any&amp;#8212;is conveyed by the digits of pi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Oppenheimer&amp;#8217;s older brother Julius is better known as J. Robert Oppenheimer. He is the title subject of a major Hollywood &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oppenheimer_(film)&quot;&gt;biopic&lt;/a&gt; directed by Christopher Nolan, to be released in July. The film will cover not only his work on the atomic bomb but also the revocation of his security clearance over ties to the Communist Party, of which Frank had been a card-carrying member. Frank lost his faculty position at the University of Minnesota and was blackballed from teaching physics anywhere until gaining a high school position in 1957 and joining the University of Colorado in 1959.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We are thinking of another movie, &lt;em&gt;Everything, Everywhere, All at Once&lt;/em&gt;, which just won the Best Picture Oscar. It involves the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiverse&quot;&gt;multiverse&lt;/a&gt; as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MacGuffin&quot;&gt;macguffin&lt;/a&gt;. Could pi have a different value in another universe? As card-carrying Platonists, our instinct is to just say &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;. But a related question lends some subtlety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; Does Pi Equal 0/(2i)? &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I considered titling this post, &amp;#8220;Does Pi Equal Zero?&amp;#8221; I realized that, if anything, it is &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5Cpi+i%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{2&amp;#92;pi i}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; that equals zero&amp;#8212;if you are raising &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{e}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; to that number. Then &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi+%3D+%5Cfrac%7B0%7D%7B2i%7D%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi = &amp;#92;frac{0}{2i}}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What I really mean is to ask:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; Does &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=e8e8e8&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; have zero information content? &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Here is a sense in which the answer is basically yes: Pi comes from a short program. Perhaps the simplest one is &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=center&gt;&lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cpi+%3D+4%5Cleft%281+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B3%7D+%2B+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B5%7D+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B7%7D+%2B+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B9%7D+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B11%7D+%2B+%5Ccdots%5Cright%29+&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;#92;displaystyle  &amp;#92;pi = 4&amp;#92;left(1 - &amp;#92;frac{1}{3} + &amp;#92;frac{1}{5} - &amp;#92;frac{1}{7} + &amp;#92;frac{1}{9} - &amp;#92;frac{1}{11} + &amp;#92;cdots&amp;#92;right) &quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;via the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madhava_series&quot;&gt;Madhava series&lt;/a&gt;. There are less-simple programs that converge more quickly&amp;#8212;plus we long ago covered &lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2009/03/15/cooks-class-contains-pi/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2010/07/14/making-an-algorithm-an-algorithm-bbp/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8212;but speed of approximation does not matter for the information content of the specification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We can also say that the specification is just &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbigcirc%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;bigcirc}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;. Or more clearly, a circle with a diameter: &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cominus%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;ominus}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;. That is literally minuscule. By Claude Shannon&amp;#8217;s information theory, this little speck of spec is the information content of pi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; Making Contact With Our Question &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Our question is joined by Carl Sagan&amp;#8217;s novel &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Contact_(novel)&quot;&gt;Contact&lt;/a&gt;, especially the last two pages. Having been tipped by the aliens to look for evidence of super-intelligence in fundamental constants, Ellie Arroway sets a super-computer onto &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; and receives a statistically significant pattern in its expansion. It gives a raster image using only the digits &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{0}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; and &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{1}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; of a nearly perfect circle. Arroway regards this also as a personal message symbolizing her full-circle journey. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To quote the last page:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; In whatever galaxy you happen to find yourself, you take the circumference of a circle, divide it by a diameter, measure closely enough, and uncover a miracle&amp;#8212;another circle, drawn kilometers downstream of the decimal point. There would be richer messages further in. &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
This causes a &amp;#8220;wait-a-sec&amp;#8230;&amp;#8221; reaction. If &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; has minuscule information content, then how can any meaningful block of information be contained in it? By &lt;em&gt;meaningful&lt;/em&gt; we mean that the block has more information than the effort needed to specify the block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hereby hangs a tale. It is almost universally believed that every finite sequence of digits appears somewhere in the base-10 expansion of &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;. It is believed further that &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Normal_number&quot;&gt;normal&lt;/a&gt;, meaning that for every &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{k}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; and &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{n}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;, every word in &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Bk%5D%5En%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{[k]^n}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; appears with frequency converging to &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%5E%7B-n%7D%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{k^{-n}}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; in the base-&lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{k}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; expansion of &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;. Thus, &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; almost certainly contains &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waiting_for_Godot&quot;&gt;Waiting for Godot&lt;/a&gt; in the original French in base 16, taking every two hex digits as an ASCII character. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But you have to wait a long time to find it&amp;#8212;and specifying an offset &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{r}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; where it begins expends as much information as is gained by reading it. There is no net gain of information from the tumbling hexadecimals. This reality is consistent with the zero-information picture, in the same sense that the vacuum of space teems with dancing particles and antiparticles that ultimately cancel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; Baking a Base Into Pi &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Contact&lt;/em&gt;, however, includes a twist different from having strings in base 10 or base 16. The raster message appears when &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; is written in base &lt;i&gt;eleven&lt;/i&gt;.  We could quibble that Sagan should have written, &amp;#8220;&amp;#8230;kilometers downstream of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Undecimal&quot;&gt;undecimal&lt;/a&gt; point.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Base eleven must count as an &amp;#8220;unusual&amp;#8221; base. Maybe a choice like base 57&amp;#8212;the first Grothendieck &lt;a href=&quot;https://hsm.stackexchange.com/questions/6358/story-of-grothendiecks-prime-number&quot;&gt;prime&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8212;would be more unusual. Choosing a base is a sneaky way to inflate the resulting expansion of &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; with more information&amp;#8212;the information from specifying the base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Taking this idea further, we could consider bases that are fractional, or algebraic irrational, or even transcendental. We can do expansions in base &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; itself. In that base, &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; has a simple representation: &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi+%3D+10_%7B%5Cpi%7D%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi = 10_{&amp;#92;pi}}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We may, however, have to regard cherry-picking the base &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{k}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; as a similar statistical fools&amp;#8217; errand to picking the offset &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{r}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; (in whatever base). Base eleven is simple enough to allow that the &lt;em&gt;elective bias&lt;/em&gt; of choosing it is minimal, so that the raster-circle message would retain its significance. But that is in a novel, anway. In reality, the ability to select the base raises the bar of how much information is needed to glean in order to infer structure rather than chance. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; E Replies &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The transcendental partner of &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; in the unifying equation &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%5E%7B%5Cpi+i%7D+%2B+1+%3D+0%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{e^{&amp;#92;pi i} + 1 = 0}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; replies to this statistical nullification with thunder:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; e = 2.7&lt;b&gt;18281828&lt;/b&gt;&amp;#8230;, you fools. &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
This is in our native base-ten representation. Perhaps this is the true message from the cosmos, ordaining that we have ten fingers and ten toes, so that no artifice of choosing the base is needed to reveal it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There is a real-life claim of a significant find in the base-ten expansion of pi. It is by Arne Bergstrom in a 2014 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Carl-Sagan&#39;s-Conjecture-of-a-Message-in-Pi-Bergstrom/05e8ec7f5875a65ef854a235ffaac8a4b73329b0&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; titled, &amp;#8220;Carl Sagan&amp;#8217;s Conjecture of a Message in &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;.&amp;#8221; It is in the number &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ctau+%3D+2%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;tau = 2&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;, whose primacy over &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; we &lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/03/14/the-value-of-pi/&quot;&gt;argued&lt;/a&gt; two years ago today. From its abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; The present article looks for markers that might possibly support such a hypothesis, and surprisingly finds a sequence of seven successive zeros (actually seven successive nines rounded off) at a depth of 3,256 digits into the representation of &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=e8e8e8&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{2&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; in the special case of base ten. Finding such a sequence of zeros within the first 1,000 digits has a probability of 1 in 10,000. No such occurrences happen even remotely for &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=e8e8e8&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{2&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; at any base other than ten, nor even remotely in corresponding representations of other common transcendental numbers, such as &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%7D&amp;#038;bg=e8e8e8&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{e}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;, which appear in physical applications. &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The abstract goes on to concede, however, that &amp;#8220;these effects are most probably just numerical coincidences without physical relevance.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The reference to physics brings us full-circle. Non-Euclidean spaces can have notions of &amp;#8220;circle&amp;#8221; defined by equidistance and of &amp;#8220;diameter&amp;#8221; whose ratio is not &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;. If we ever find that we live in a space that in large scales is curved, however slightly, might this dislodge our conviction that Euclidean space is salient? If so, then we might regard the value &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B3.14159265358...%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{3.14159265358...}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; as having elective bias after all. This change in attitude would be accompanied, so I conjecture, by the pre-actuated infusion of a huge amount of genuine information in the digits of&amp;#8212;the Euclidean value of&amp;#8212;&lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; Open Problems &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Where does this leave us in regard to the information content of &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;pi}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;? How does it differ in this regard from the measure-one set of real numbers in the unit interval that are both algorithmically and statistically random?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[fixed pi in base pi = 10, not 1]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By KWRegan&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Lipton</name>
      <uri>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: A Quantum Outlier Theorem</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06256"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06256</id>
    <updated>2023-03-14T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Epstein_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Samuel Epstein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In recent results, it has been proven that all sampling methods produce
outliers. In this paper, we extend these results to quantum information theory.
Projectors of large rank must contain pure quantum states in their images that
are outlying states. Otherwise, the projectors are exotic, in that they have
high mutual information with the halting sequence. Thus quantum coding schemes
that use projections, such as Schumacher compression, must communicate using
outlier quantum states.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Finding large counterexamples by selectively exploring the Pachner graph</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06321"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06321</id>
    <updated>2023-03-14T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Burton_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Benjamin A. Burton&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+He_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Alexander He&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We often rely on censuses of triangulations to guide our intuition in
$3$-manifold topology. However, this can lead to misplaced faith in conjectures
if the smallest counterexamples are too large to appear in our census. Since
the number of triangulations increases super-exponentially with size, there is
no way to expand a census beyond relatively small triangulations; the current
census only goes up to $10$ tetrahedra. Here, we show that it is feasible to
search for large and hard-to-find counterexamples by using heuristics to
selectively (rather than exhaustively) enumerate triangulations. We use this
idea to find counterexamples to three conjectures which ask, for certain
$3$-manifolds, whether one-vertex triangulations always have a &quot;distinctive&quot;
edge that would allow us to recognise the $3$-manifold.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Betti Number for Point Sets</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06354"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06354</id>
    <updated>2023-03-14T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wang_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hao Wang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Topology is the foundation for many industrial applications ranging from CAD
to simulation analysis. Computational topology mostly focuses on structured
data such as mesh, however unstructured dataset such as point set remains a
virgin land for topology scientists. The significance of point-based topology
can never be overemphasized, especially in the area of reverse engineering,
geometric modeling and algorithmic analysis. In this paper, we propose a novel
approach to compute the Betti number for point set data and illustrate its
usefulness in real world examples. To the best of our knowledge, our work is
pioneering and first of its kind in the fields of computational topology.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Generalizing Greenwald-Khanna Streaming Quantile Summaries for Weighted Inputs</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06288"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06288</id>
    <updated>2023-03-14T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Assadi_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sepehr Assadi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Joshi_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nirmit Joshi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Prabhu_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Milind Prabhu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Shah_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vihan Shah&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Estimating quantiles, like the median or percentiles, is a fundamental task
in data mining and data science. A (streaming) quantile summary is a data
structure that can process a set S of n elements in a streaming fashion and at
the end, for any phi in (0,1], return a phi-quantile of S up to an eps error,
i.e., return a phi&#39;-quantile with phi&#39;=phi +- eps. We are particularly
interested in comparison-based summaries that only compare elements of the
universe under a total ordering and are otherwise completely oblivious of the
universe. The best known deterministic quantile summary is the 20-year old
Greenwald-Khanna (GK) summary that uses O((1/eps) log(eps n)) space
[SIGMOD&#39;01]. This bound was recently proved to be optimal for all deterministic
comparison-based summaries by Cormode and Vesle\&#39;y [PODS&#39;20].
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we study weighted quantiles, a generalization of the quantiles
problem, where each element arrives with a positive integer weight which
denotes the number of copies of that element being inserted. The only known
method of handling weighted inputs via GK summaries is the naive approach of
breaking each weighted element into multiple unweighted items and feeding them
one by one to the summary, which results in a prohibitively large update time
(proportional to the maximum weight of input elements).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We give the first non-trivial extension of GK summaries for weighted inputs
and show that it takes O((1/eps) log(eps n)) space and O(log(1/eps)+ log
log(eps n)) update time per element to process a stream of length n (under some
quite mild assumptions on the range of weights and eps). En route to this, we
also simplify the original GK summaries for unweighted quantiles.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Binary Search with Distance-Dependent Costs</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06488"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06488</id>
    <updated>2023-03-14T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Leng_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Calvin Leng&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kempe_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;David Kempe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduce a search problem generalizing the typical setting of Binary
Search on the line. Similar to the setting for Binary Search, a target is
chosen adversarially on the line, and in response to a query, the algorithm
learns whether the query was correct, too high, or too low. Different from the
Binary Search setting, the cost of a query is a monotone non-decreasing
function of the distance between the query and the correct answer; different
functions can be used for queries that are too high vs. those that are too low.
The algorithm&#39;s goal is to identify an adversarially chosen target with minimum
total cost. Note that the algorithm does not even know the cost it incurred
until the end, when the target is revealed. This abstraction captures many
natural settings in which a principal experiments by setting a quantity (such
as an item price, bandwidth, tax rate, medicine dosage, etc.) where the cost or
regret increases the further the chosen setting is from the optimal one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we show that for arbitrary symmetric cost functions (i.e.,
overshooting vs. undershooting by the same amount leads to the same cost), the
standard Binary Search algorithm is a 4-approximation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then show that when the cost functions are bounded-degree polynomials of
the distance, the problem can be solved optimally using Dynamic Programming;
this relies on a careful encoding of the combined cost of past queries (which,
recall, will only be revealed in the future). We then generalize the setting to
finding a node on a tree; here, the response to a query is the direction on the
tree in which the target is located, and the cost is increasing in the distance
on the tree from the query to the target. Using the k-cut search tree framework
of Berendsohn and Kozma and the ideas we developed for the case of the line, we
give a PTAS when the cost function is a bounded-degree polynomial.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">CCI: jobs: PhD and Post-doctoral Positions  at Augusta University (apply by June 1, 2023)</title>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/03/13/phd-and-post-doctoral-positions-at-augusta-university-apply-by-june-1-2023/"/>
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/03/13/phd-and-post-doctoral-positions-at-augusta-university-apply-by-june-1-2023/</id>
    <updated>2023-03-13T18:13:12+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;The Concurrency In Reversible Computations (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/CinRC&quot;&gt;https://github.com/CinRC&lt;/a&gt;) project is actively seeking a PhD student to fund starting Spring 2024. The funding for an admitted PhD student includes tuition waiver, stipend, health benefits, (international) conference travel and possibly equipment. Funding is currently available for the first three years of the appointment through a new NSF funded project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://spots.augusta.edu/caubert/research/cinrc/phd_ad.html&quot;&gt;https://spots.augusta.edu/caubert/research/cinrc/phd_ad.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: clement.aubert@math.cnrs.fr&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>CCI: jobs</name>
      <uri>https://cstheory-jobs.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Computational Complexity: Problems we assume are hard. Are they? ALSO- revised version of Demaine-Gasarch-Hajiaghayi is posted!</title>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2023/03/problems-we-assume-are-hard-are-they.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-6482721495747819843</id>
    <updated>2023-03-13T15:39:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;(The latest version of&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Computational Intractability: A Guide to Algorithmic Lower Bounds&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;by Demaine-Gasarch-Hajiaghayi is posted&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hardness.mit.edu/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Its new and improved: (1) we have made all or most of the corrections send to us by proofreaders,&amp;nbsp; (2) there is a chapter on quantum computing, (3) there is an index.&amp;nbsp; Feel free to read it and send us corrections!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This post is related to it in that most of the problems-assumed-hard mentioned in this post were the basis for chapters of the book.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We think SAT is hard because (1) its NPC, and (2) many years of effort have failed to get it into P.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Imagine a world where we didn&#39;t have the Cook-Levin Theorem. We may still think SAT is hard. We may even take it as a hardness assumption to prove other things hard by showing SAT \le A. We may also be curious if they are equivalent and have lots of reductions A \le SAT. The reductions might be Karp or Cook.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You do not have to imagine this world! We already have it- in different contexts. In other areas of complexity theory there are problems that are assumed hard, but for which there is no analog of Cook-Levin. Are they hard? They seem to be- but the evidence is empirical. Not that there&#39;s anything wrong with that.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will list out problems that&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;a) we assume are hard, for some definition of&amp;nbsp; &lt;i&gt;we &lt;/i&gt;and &lt;i&gt;hard.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;b) we have NO proof of that and NO completeness or hardness result.&amp;nbsp; ADDED LATER- a commenter wanted me to clarify this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;For SAT there is a well defined set of problems, NP, defined independent of any particular problem (that is, NP was NOT defined as all sets Karp-Red to TSP or anything of the sort) and by Cook-Levin we have&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;if SAT is in P then NP is contained in P.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For FPT (the class the commenter was interested in) there IS the result&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;if weighed k-SAT is in FPT then W[1] is contained in FPT.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;but W[1] is DEFINED as the set of problems FPT reducible to Weft-1 circuits (some books use a different basic problems) which IN MY OPINION is not a natural class. One may disagree with this of course.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;COUNTERAUGMENT: but W[1] Was defined as all problems FPT-reducible to Weft-1 circuits. And this is not the same&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(I do not include hardness assumptions for crypto because that&#39;s not quite the same thing. Also there are just so many of them!)&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am sure I missed some- which is where YOU come in! Please leave comments with additional problems that I forgot (or perhaps did not know) to include.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1) 1vs2 cycle: Given a graph that you are guaranteed is 1 cycle or the union of 2 cycles, determine which is the case. This is assumed to be hard to parallelize (we omit details&amp;nbsp;of defining that formally).&amp;nbsp; This has been used for lower bounds in parallelism. See&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1109/FOCS.2019.00097&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;2) 3SUM: Given x1,..,xn an array of integers, are there 3 that add to 0? There is an O(n^2) algorithm. The hardness assumption is that, for all epsilon, there is no O(n^{2-\epsilon}) algorithm. This assumption has been used to get lower bounds in comp. geom. See the Wikipedia entry&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/3SUM&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;or the introduction of this paper&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.08356.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;4) APSP (All Pairs Shortest Path) Given a graph G, find for each pair of vertices&amp;nbsp; the length of the shortest path. There is an O(n^3) algorithm. The hardness assumption is that, for all epsilon, there is no O(n^{3-epsilon}) algorithm. This assumption has been used to get lower bounds on graph problems. For more details see the introduction of this paper:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.08356.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;5)&amp;nbsp; Weighted-SAT-k: Given a Boolean formula (it can be taken to be in 2CNF form) is there a satisfying assignment that has exactly k of the variables set to TRUE. This is assumed to not be fixed parameter tractable (that is no function f such that this problem is in&amp;nbsp; O(f(k)n^{O(1)}) time). Problems that are FPT-equiv to it are called W[1]-complete and are all thought to not be in FPT. W[2], W[t] are also defined but we omit this. W[1]-complete has also been defined in other ways, but I can&#39;t seem to find a Cook-Levin type theorem for them.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;6) Graph Isom.&amp;nbsp; One of he few problems that are in NP but thought to not be NP-complete and, at least for now, is not in P. Babai has shown its in quasi-poly time (n^{(log n)^{O(1)}). There is a notion of GI-hard: problems that, if they are in P then GI is in P. See he Wikipedia entry&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Graph_isomorphism_problem&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Most of the GI-hard problems are variants of GI, e.g., graph isom. for directed graphs. GI could be in P without unbelievable consequences for complexity and without terrifying consequences for cryptography.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;7) Unique Games Conj: I won&#39;t define it formally here, see the Wikipedia entry&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unique_games_conjecture&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. From UGC you get several approximation results are optimal. Does that argue for UGC being true-- having consequences we believe? I would say YES since in some cases the algorithm that gives a good approx has an alpha-approx for some weird number alpha, and assuming UGC you get the SAME alpha as a lower bound.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;8) Existential&amp;nbsp; Theory of the Reals. Easier for you to read the Wikipedia entry&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Existential_theory_of_the_reals&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It is used for problems that are inbetween NP and PSPACE. (ADDED LATER: One of the commenters says that Blum-Shub-Smale showed ETR is complete for the real version of&amp;nbsp; NP, so this item should not be on my list.)&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;9) Orthogonal vector conjecture. See this paper:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mit.edu/~lijieche/SODA_2019_OV-Equiv-Fullversion.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This is used to show problems are not in subquadratic time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Possible research directions and thoughts&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;a) Try to prove a Cook-Levin type theorem for one of these problems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;b) Build classes analogous to the poly-hiearchy on one of these problems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;c) Ask bounded-query questions. For example: Are k queries to 3SUM more powerful than k-1 (This is a VERY Gasarchian question.)&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;d) Try to prove that one of these problems is actually hard. That seems hard. Perhaps on a weaker model (thats prob already been done for at least one of them.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By gasarch&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Francis Bach: Revisiting the classics: Jensens inequality</title>
    <link href="https://francisbach.com/jensen-inequality/"/>
    <id>https://francisbach.com/?p=8823</id>
    <updated>2023-03-13T13:47:14+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;justify-text&quot;&gt;There are a few mathematical results that any researcher in applied mathematics uses on a daily basis. One of them is Jensen&amp;#8217;s inequality, which allows bounding expectations of functions of random variables. This really happens a lot in any probabilistic arguments but also as a tool to generate inequalities and optimization algorithms. In this blog post, I will present a collection of fun facts about the inequality, from very classical to more obscure. If you know other cool ones, please add them as comments.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;justify-text&quot;&gt;But before, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;let me be very clear&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;: Jensen&amp;#8217;s inequality is often not in the direction that you would hope it to be. So, to avoid embarrassing mistakes, I always draw at least in my mind the figure below before using it.  &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;wp-block-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;aligncenter size-full is-resized&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/jensen-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;wp-image-8873&quot; width=&quot;546&quot; height=&quot;243&quot; srcset=&quot;https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/jensen-3.png 1616w, https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/jensen-3-300x134.png 300w, https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/jensen-3-1024x456.png 1024w, https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/jensen-3-768x342.png 768w, https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/jensen-3-1536x684.png 1536w, https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/jensen-3-850x379.png 850w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 546px) 100vw, 546px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Simplest formulation and proof&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;justify-text&quot;&gt;Given a convex function defined on a convex subset \(C\) of \(\mathbb{R}^d\), and a random vector \(X\) with values in \(C\), then $$ f\big( \mathbb{E}[X] \big) \leqslant \mathbb{E} \big[ f(X) \big],$$ as soon as the expectations exist. For a strictly convex function, there is equality if and only if \(X\) is almost surely constant. This is often stated with \(\mu\) taking finitely many values, like in the plot below.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;justify-text&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proof.&lt;/strong&gt; Starting with the standard definition of convexity that corresponds to random variables that take only two values in \(C\), this can be extended by recursion to all random variables taking finitely many values, and then by a density argument, to all random variables. See the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jensen%27s_inequality&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;justify-text&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proof without words.&lt;/strong&gt; As nicely explained in this &lt;a href=&quot;https://mark.reid.name/blog/behold-jensens-inequality.html&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; by Mark Reid, a simple argument based on epigraphs leads to the inequality for discrete measures supported on \(x_1,\dots,x_n\), with non-negative weights \(\lambda_1, \dots,\lambda_n\) that sum to one, with an illustration below for \(n=4\): any convex combination of points \((x_i,f(x_i))\) has to be in the red convex polygon, which is above the function.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;wp-block-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;aligncenter size-large is-resized&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/jensen_multi-3-1024x474.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;wp-image-8889&quot; width=&quot;542&quot; height=&quot;250&quot; srcset=&quot;https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/jensen_multi-3-1024x474.png 1024w, https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/jensen_multi-3-300x139.png 300w, https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/jensen_multi-3-768x355.png 768w, https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/jensen_multi-3-1536x711.png 1536w, https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/jensen_multi-3-850x393.png 850w, https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/jensen_multi-3.png 1549w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 542px) 100vw, 542px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;A bit of history&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;justify-text&quot;&gt;The result is typically attributed to the Danish mathematician &lt;a href=&quot;https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johan_Jensen&quot;&gt;Johan Jensen&lt;/a&gt; [&lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/2371297/files/article.pdf&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, in French] who proved in 1906 the result for convex functions on the real line (in fact all continuous &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convex_function&quot;&gt;mid-point convex&lt;/a&gt; functions), but &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otto_H%C3%B6lder&quot;&gt;Otto Hlder&lt;/a&gt; had shown it earlier for twice differentiable functions [&lt;a href=&quot;http://gdz.sub.uni-goettingen.de/dms/resolveppn/?PPN=GDZPPN00252421X&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, in German]. It turns out this was known thirty years earlier for uniform measures on finite sets, as shown by Jules Grolous [&lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.fr/books?id=z_BFnsBAx18C&amp;amp;hl=fr&amp;amp;pg=PA401#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=true&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;], a relatively unknown former student from Ecole Polytechnique. See also [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/pdf/43667702.pdf?refreqid=excelsior%3A29d60497a1ddcba74004c27f25c39cd1&amp;amp;ab_segments=&amp;amp;origin=&amp;amp;initiator=&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;] for more details on the history of Jensen&amp;#8217;s inequality.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;Classical applications&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;justify-text&quot;&gt;Jensen&amp;#8217;s inequality can be used to derive many other classical inequalities, typically applied to the exponential, logarithm or powers.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;justify-text&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arithmetic, harmonic, and geometric means.&lt;/strong&gt; For \(X\) with positive real values, we have: $$ \mathbb{E}[X]\geqslant \exp \Big( \mathbb{E}\big[ \log(X)\big]\Big)  \ \mbox{ and } \  \mathbb{E}[X]  \geqslant \frac{1}{\mathbb{E}\big[\frac{1}{X}\big]},$$ which corresponds for empirical measures to classical &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HM-GM-AM-QM_inequalities&quot;&gt;inequalities between means&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;justify-text&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Young&amp;#8217;s inequality.&lt;/strong&gt; For \(p,q&amp;gt;1\) such that \(\frac{1}{p}+\frac{1}{q}=1\), and two non-negative real numbers \(x,y\), we get by Jensen&amp;#8217;s inequality, $$ \log\big(\frac{1}{p} x^p + \frac{1}{q} y^q \big) \geqslant \frac{1}{p} \log(x^p) + \frac{1}{q} \log(y^q) = \log(xy),$$ leading to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Young%27s_inequality_for_products&quot;&gt;Young&amp;#8217;s inequality&lt;/a&gt; \(\displaystyle xy \leqslant \frac{1}{p} x^p + \frac{1}{q} y^q.\)&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;justify-text&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hlder&amp;#8217;s inequality.&lt;/strong&gt; For any positive \(x_1,\dots,x_n,y_1,\dots,y_n\), we can write $$\sum_{i=1}^n x_i y_i = \sum_{j=1}^n y_j^q \cdot \sum_{i=1}^n x_i y_i^{1-q} \frac{y_i^q}{\sum_{j=1}^n y_j^q} \leqslant \sum_{j=1}^n y_j^q \cdot \Big( \sum_{i=1}^n (x_i y_i^{1-q})^p \frac{y_i^q}{\sum_{j=1}^n y_j^q} \Big)^{1/p},$$ leading to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H%C3%B6lder%27s_inequality&quot;&gt;Hlder&amp;#8217;s inequality&lt;/a&gt; (with the same relationship between \(p\) and \(q\) as above): $$\sum_{i=1}^n x_i y_i \leqslant \Big( \sum_{j=1}^n y_j^q \Big)^{1/q} \Big( \sum_{j=1}^n x_j^p \Big)^{1/p}.$$ This includes also &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cauchy%E2%80%93Schwarz_inequality&quot;&gt;Cauchy-Schwarz inequality&lt;/a&gt; if \(p=q=2\), and also multiple versions of the &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&quot;https://francisbach.com/the-%ce%b7-trick-or-the-effectiveness-of-reweighted-least-squares/&quot;&gt;eta-trick&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8220;.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;Majorization-minimization&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;justify-text&quot;&gt;Within data science, Jensen&amp;#8217;s inequality is often used to derive auxiliary functions used in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MM_algorithm&quot;&gt;majorization-minimization&lt;/a&gt; algorithms, with two classical examples below.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;justify-text&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-negative matrix factorization (NMF).&lt;/strong&gt; Given a non-negative matrix \(V \in \mathbb{R}_+^{n \times d}\), the goal of NMF is to decompose it as \(V = WH\) with \(W \in \mathbb{R}_+^{n \times m}\) and \(H \in \mathbb{R}_+^{m \times d}\). This has many applications, in particular in source separation [&lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.nips.cc/paper/2000/file/f9d1152547c0bde01830b7e8bd60024c-Paper.pdf&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://perso.ens-lyon.fr/patrice.abry/ENSEIGNEMENTS/14M2SCExam/Bertin.pdf&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;justify-text&quot;&gt; A classical cost function which is used to estimate \(W\) and \(H\) is the Kullback-Leibler divergence [&lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.nips.cc/paper/2000/file/f9d1152547c0bde01830b7e8bd60024c-Paper.pdf&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;] $$ D(V \| WH) = \sum_{i=1}^n \sum_{j=1}^d \Big\{ V_{ij} \log \frac{ V_{ij} }{ ( WH)_{ij} }\  &amp;#8211; V_{ij} + (WH)_{ij} \Big\}.$$ To minimize the cost function above with respect to \(H\) only, the problematic term is \(\log  ( WH)_{ij} = \log \big( \sum_{k=1}^m W_{ik} H_{kj} \big)\), which is a &amp;#8220;log of a sum&amp;#8221;. To turn it into a &amp;#8220;sum of logs&amp;#8221;, we use Jensen&amp;#8217;s inequality for the logarithm, by introducing a probability vector \(q^{ij} \in \mathbb{R}_+^m\) (with non-negative values that sum to one), and lower-bounding $$ \log  ( WH)_{ij} = \log \Big( \sum_{k=1}^m q^{ij}_k \frac{W_{ik} H_{kj} }{q^{ij}_k} \Big) \geqslant \sum_{k=1}^n q^{ij}_{k} \log \frac{W_{ik} H_{kj}}{q^{ij}_k}.$$ For a fixed \(H\), the bound is tight for \(\displaystyle q^{ij}_k = \frac{W_{ik} H_{kj}}{(WH)_{ij}},\) and given all \(q\)&amp;#8217;s, we can minimize with respect to \(H_{ki}\) in closed form to get the update $$H_{kj} \leftarrow H_{kj}    \frac{\sum_{i=1}^n \! V_{ij} W_{ik}  \, /\,  (WH)_{ij} }{\sum_{i&amp;#8217;=1}^n \! W_{i&amp;#8217;k}}.$$ Because we had a tight upper bound at the current \(H\) (before the update), this is a descent algorithm. We can derive a similar update for \(W\). As shown in [&lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.nips.cc/paper/2000/file/f9d1152547c0bde01830b7e8bd60024c-Paper.pdf&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;], this is a simple parameter-free descent algorithm that converges to a stationary point, often referred to as a multiplicative update algorithm. See a convergence analysis in [&lt;a href=&quot;https://perso.telecom-paristech.fr/rbadeau/assets/ieee-tnn-10.pdf&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;] and alternatives based on relative smoothness [&lt;a href=&quot;https://publications.ut-capitole.fr/id/eprint/25852/1/25852.pdf&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;] or on primal-dual formulations [&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1608.01264&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://hal.science/hal-01079229/document&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;justify-text&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expectation-maximization (EM).&lt;/strong&gt; The exact same technique of introducing a probability vector within the log and using Jensen&amp;#8217;s inequality is at the core of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expectation%E2%80%93maximization_algorithm&quot;&gt;EM for latent variable models&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evidence_lower_bound&quot;&gt;variational inference&lt;/a&gt; (in fact NMF is simply a particular instance for a Poisson likelihood), which are two good topics for future posts (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://lips.cs.princeton.edu/the-elbo-without-jensen-or-kl/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for a simple derivation of the &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evidence_lower_bound&quot;&gt;evidence lower bound&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8220;).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;Information theory&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;justify-text&quot;&gt;Within &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information_theory&quot;&gt;information theory&lt;/a&gt;, the concavity of the logarithm and the use of Jensen&amp;#8217;s inequality play a major role in most classical results, e.g., positivity of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kullback%E2%80%93Leibler_divergence&quot;&gt;Kullback-Leilbler divergence&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_processing_inequality&quot;&gt;data processing inequality&lt;/a&gt;. This also extends to all &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/F-divergence&quot;&gt;f-divergences&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;Operator convexity&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;justify-text&quot;&gt;When considering convexity with respect to a generalized inequaility (such as based on the Lwner order), we can extend many of the classical formulas above (relationship between means, Young&amp;#8217;s and Hlder&amp;#8217;s inequality) to matrices. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://francisbach.com/matrix-monotony-and-convexity/&quot;&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt; for an introduction. For a certain set of functions (such as the square or the negative logarithm) \(f: \mathbb{R} \to \mathbb{R}\), then for a random symmetric matrix \(X\), we have (for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loewner_order&quot;&gt;Lwner order&lt;/a&gt;): $$ f\big( \mathbb{E}[X] \big) \preccurlyeq  \mathbb{E} \big[ f(X) \big].$$ An intriguing extension is the operator version of Jensen&amp;#8217;s inequality [&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/math/0204049&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;], for potentially dependent random variables \((X,Y)\), where \(X\) is symmetric, and the sizes of \(X\) and \(Y\) are compatible: $$ f \Big( \mathbb{E} \big[ Y^\top X Y \big] \Big) \preccurlyeq \mathbb{E} \big[ Y^\top f(X) Y \big]  \ \mbox{ as soon as } \ \mathbb{E}[  Y^\top Y ] = I.$$&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;Exact expression of the remainder&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;justify-text&quot;&gt;There is a large literature on extensions, refinements on Jensen&amp;#8217;s inequality. I have a cute one of my own, which has probably been derived before. For twice differentiable functions \(f\), we can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taylor%27s_theorem&quot;&gt;Taylor formula with integral remainder&lt;/a&gt; on the segment between \(X\) and \(\mathbb{E}[X]\), leading to, with \(g(t) =  f\big( t X + (1-t) \mathbb{E}[X]\big)\), $$g(1) = g(0) + g&#39;(0) + \int_0^1 \! g^{\prime \prime}(t)(1-t)dt.$$ Taking expectations, this leads to $$\mathbb{E} \big[f(X)\big] &amp;#8211; f\big( \mathbb{E}[X]\big) = \mathbb{E} \bigg[ \int_0^1 \! ( X &amp;#8211; \mathbb{E}[X])^\top f^{\prime\prime}\big( t X + (1-t) \mathbb{E}[X]\big) ( X &amp;#8211; \mathbb{E}[X]) (1-t) dt \bigg].$$ From this expression, we recover traditional refinements or reversing of the order if \(f^{\prime\prime}\) has bounded eigenvalues. This can for example be used also for characterizing the equality cases in non-strictly convex situations [&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.08545.pdf&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;, page 31].&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;justify-text&quot;&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johan_Jensen_(mathematician)&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Johan L. Jensen.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/2371297/files/article.pdf&quot;&gt;Sur les fonctions convexes et les ingalits entre les valeurs moyennes.&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Acta Mathematica&lt;/em&gt;,&amp;nbsp;30(1): 175193, 1906.&lt;br&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: revert; color: initial; font-family: -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Roboto, Oxygen-Sans, Ubuntu, Cantarell, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, sans-serif;&quot;&gt;[2] Otto Hlder, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;font-size: revert; font-family: -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Roboto, Oxygen-Sans, Ubuntu, Cantarell, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, sans-serif;&quot; href=&quot;http://gdz.sub.uni-goettingen.de/dms/resolveppn/?PPN=GDZPPN00252421X&quot;&gt;Ueber einen Mittelwerthssatz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: revert; color: initial; font-family: -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Roboto, Oxygen-Sans, Ubuntu, Cantarell, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, sans-serif;&quot;&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;Nachrichten von der Knigl. Gesellschaft der Wissenschaften und der Georg-Augusts-Universitt zu&amp;nbsp;Gttingen&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: revert; color: initial; font-family: -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Roboto, Oxygen-Sans, Ubuntu, Cantarell, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, sans-serif;&quot;&gt;, (1):38-47&lt;/span&gt;, 1889.&lt;br&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: revert; color: initial; font-family: -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Roboto, Oxygen-Sans, Ubuntu, Cantarell, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, sans-serif;&quot;&gt;[3] Jules Grolous. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;font-size: revert; font-family: -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Roboto, Oxygen-Sans, Ubuntu, Cantarell, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, sans-serif;&quot; href=&quot;https://books.google.fr/books?id=z_BFnsBAx18C&amp;amp;hl=fr&amp;amp;pg=PA401#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=true&quot;&gt;Un thorme sur les fonctions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em style=&quot;font-size: revert; color: initial; font-family: -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Roboto, Oxygen-Sans, Ubuntu, Cantarell, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, sans-serif;&quot;&gt;. LInstitut, Journal Universel des Sciences et des Socits Savantes en France et  lEtranger&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: revert; color: initial; font-family: -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Roboto, Oxygen-Sans, Ubuntu, Cantarell, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, sans-serif;&quot;&gt;, 3(153):401, 1875.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;[4] D. S. Mitrinovi and P. M. Vasi. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/pdf/43667702.pdf?refreqid=excelsior%3A29d60497a1ddcba74004c27f25c39cd1&amp;amp;ab_segments=&amp;amp;origin=&amp;amp;initiator=&quot;&gt;The centroid method in inequalities&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Publikacije Elektrotehnikog fakulteta. Serija Matematika i fizika&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;498/541:3-16, 1975.&lt;br&gt;[5] Daniel D. Lee and H. Sebastian Seung. &lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.nips.cc/paper/2000/file/f9d1152547c0bde01830b7e8bd60024c-Paper.pdf&quot;&gt;Algorithms for non-negative matrix factorization&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems&lt;/em&gt;, 13, 2000.&lt;br&gt;[6] Cdric Fvotte, Nancy Bertin, and Jean-Louis Durrieu. &lt;a href=&quot;http://perso.ens-lyon.fr/patrice.abry/ENSEIGNEMENTS/14M2SCExam/Bertin.pdf&quot;&gt;Nonnegative matrix factorization with the Itakura-Saito divergence: With application to music analysis&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Neural computation&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;21(3):793-830, 2009.&lt;br&gt;[6] Roland Badeau, Nancy Bertin, and Emmanuel Vincent. &lt;a href=&quot;https://perso.telecom-paristech.fr/rbadeau/assets/ieee-tnn-10.pdf&quot;&gt;Stability analysis of multiplicative update algorithms and application to nonnegative matrix factorization&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks&lt;/em&gt;,&amp;nbsp;21(12):1869-1881, 2010.&lt;br&gt;[7] Heinz H. Bauschke, Jrme Bolte, and Marc Teboulle. &lt;a href=&quot;https://publications.ut-capitole.fr/id/eprint/25852/1/25852.pdf&quot;&gt;A descent lemma beyond Lipschitz gradient continuity: first-order methods revisited and applications&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Mathematics of Operations Research&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;42(2):330-348, 2017.&lt;br&gt;[8] Niao He, Zaid Harchaoui, Yichen Wang, and Le Song. &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1608.01264&quot;&gt;Fast and simple optimization for Poisson likelihood models&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;Technical report,&lt;em&gt; arXiv:1608.01264&lt;/em&gt;, 2016.&lt;br&gt;[9] Felipe Yanez and Francis Bach. &lt;a href=&quot;https://hal.science/hal-01079229/document&quot;&gt;Primal-dual algorithms for non-negative matrix factorization with the Kullback-Leibler divergence&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP)&lt;/em&gt;, 2017.&lt;br&gt;[10] Frank Hansen, Gert K. Pedersen. &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/math/0204049&quot;&gt;Jensen&amp;#8217;s Operator Inequality&lt;/a&gt;. Technical report,&lt;em&gt; arXiv:0204049&lt;/em&gt;, 2002.&lt;br&gt;[11] Francis Bach. &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.08545.pdf&quot;&gt;Information theory with kernel methods&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;IEEE Transactions in Information Theor&lt;/em&gt;y, 69(2):752-775, 2022.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Francis Bach&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Francis Bach</name>
      <uri>https://francisbach.com</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">CCI: jobs: PhD and Postdoc at Algorithms group in Bar-Ilan University  (Israel) (apply by June 1, 2023)</title>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/03/13/phd-and-postdoc-at-algorithms-group-in-bar-ilan-university-israel-apply-by-june-1-2023/"/>
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/03/13/phd-and-postdoc-at-algorithms-group-in-bar-ilan-university-israel-apply-by-june-1-2023/</id>
    <updated>2023-03-13T10:00:02+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;I am (Arnold Filtser) looking for both PhD and Postdoc applicants in the broad area of algorithms. We have a strong and thriving algorithms group here in BIU, and you will have many further options for collaboration. My research interest include (but not limited to): Metric Spaces, Low-Distortion Embeddings, Randomized Algorithms, approximation, and streaming algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arnold.filtser.com/&quot;&gt;https://arnold.filtser.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: filtsea@cs.biu.ac.il&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>CCI: jobs</name>
      <uri>https://cstheory-jobs.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: On the Existence of Anomalies, The Reals Case</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.05614"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.05614</id>
    <updated>2023-03-13T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Epstein_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Samuel Epstein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Independence Postulate (IP) is a finitary Church-Turing Thesis, saying
mathematical sequences are independent from physical ones. Modelling
observations as infinite sequences of real numbers, IP implies the existence of
anomalies.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: How to Compress the Solution</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.05616"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.05616</id>
    <updated>2023-03-13T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Epstein_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Samuel Epstein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using derandomization, we provide an upper bound on the compression size of
solutions to the graph coloring problem. In general, if solutions to a
combinatorial problem exist with high probability and the probability is
simple, then there exists a simple solution to the problem. Otherwise the
problem instance has high mutual information with the halting problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Uniform Tests and Algorithmic Thermodynamic Entropy</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.05619"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.05619</id>
    <updated>2023-03-13T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Epstein_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Samuel Epstein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We prove that given a computable metric space and two computable measures,
the set of points that have high universal uniform test scores with respect to
the first measure will have a lower bound with respect to the second measure.
This result is transferred to thermodynamics, showing that algorithmic
thermodynamic entropy must oscillate in the presence of dynamics. Another
application is that outliers will become emergent in computable dynamics of
computable metric spaces.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: DAG Scheduling in the BSP Model</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.05989"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.05989</id>
    <updated>2023-03-13T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Papp_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;P&amp;#xe1;l Andr&amp;#xe1;s Papp&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Anegg_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Georg Anegg&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Yzelman_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;A. N. Yzelman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the problem of scheduling an arbitrary computational DAG on a fixed
number of processors while minimizing the makespan. While previous works have
mostly studied this problem in relatively restricted models, we define and
analyze DAG scheduling in the Bulk Synchronous Parallel (BSP) model, which is a
well-established parallel computing model that captures the communication cost
between processors much more accurately. We provide a detailed taxonomy of
simpler scheduling models that can be understood as variants or special cases
of BSP, and discuss the properties of the problem and the optimum cost in these
models, and how they differ from BSP. This essentially allows us to dissect the
different building blocks of the BSP model, and gain insight into how each of
these influences the scheduling problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then analyze the hardness of DAG scheduling in BSP in detail. We show that
the problem is solvable in polynomial time for some very simple classes of
DAGs, but it is already NP-hard for in-trees or DAGs of height 2. We also
separately study the subproblem of scheduling communication steps, and we show
that the NP-hardness of this problem can depend on the problem parameters and
the communication rules within the BSP model. Finally, we present and analyze a
natural formulation of our scheduling task as an Integer Linear Program.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Multivariate to Bivariate Reduction for Noncommutative Polynomial Factorization</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06001"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06001</id>
    <updated>2023-03-13T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Arvind_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;V. Arvind&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Joglekar_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Pushkar S. Joglekar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on a theorem of Bergman we show that multivariate noncommutative
polynomial factorization is deterministic polynomial-time reducible to the
factorization of bivariate noncommutative polynomials. More precisely, we show
the following:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(1) In the white-box setting, given an n-variate noncommutative polynomial f
in F&amp;lt;X&amp;gt; over a field F (either a finite field or the rationals) as an
arithmetic circuit (or algebraic branching program), computing a complete
factorization of f is deterministic polynomial-time reducible to white-box
factorization of a noncommutative bivariate polynomial g in F&amp;lt;x,y&amp;gt;; the
reduction transforms f into a circuit for g (resp. ABP for g), and given a
complete factorization of g the reduction recovers a complete factorization of
f in polynomial time. We also obtain a similar deterministic polynomial-time
reduction in the black-box setting.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(2) Additionally, we show over the field of rationals that bivariate linear
matrix factorization of 4 x 4 matrices is at least as hard as factoring
square-free integers. This indicates that reducing noncommutative polynomial
factorization to linear matrix factorization (as done in our recent work
[AJ22]) is unlikely to succeed over the field of rationals even in the
bivariate case.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, multivariate linear matrix factorization for 3 x 3 matrices over
rationals is in polynomial time.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Scalable and Efficient Functional Map Computations on Dense Meshes</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.05965"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.05965</id>
    <updated>2023-03-13T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Magnet_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Robin Magnet&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ovsjanikov_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Maks Ovsjanikov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spectral geometric methods have brought revolutionary changes to the field of
geometry processing. Of particular interest is the study of the Laplacian
spectrum as a compact, isometry and permutation-invariant representation of a
shape. Some recent works show how the intrinsic geometry of a full shape can be
recovered from its spectrum, but there are approaches that consider the more
challenging problem of recovering the geometry from the spectral information of
partial shapes. In this paper, we propose a possible way to fill this gap. We
introduce a learning-based method to estimate the Laplacian spectrum of the
union of partial non-rigid 3D shapes, without actually computing the 3D
geometry of the union or any correspondence between those partial shapes. We do
so by operating purely in the spectral domain and by defining the union
operation between short sequences of eigenvalues. We show that the approximated
union spectrum can be used as-is to reconstruct the complete geometry [MRC*19],
perform region localization on a template [RTO*19] and retrieve shapes from a
database, generalizing ShapeDNA [RWP06] to work with partialities. Working with
eigenvalues allows us to deal with unknown correspondence, different sampling,
and different discretizations (point clouds and meshes alike), making this
operation especially robust and general. Our approach is data-driven and can
generalize to isometric and non-isometric deformations of the surface, as long
as these stay within the same semantic class (e.g., human bodies or horses), as
well as to partiality artifacts not seen at training time.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Decomposition of zero-dimensional persistence modules via rooted subsets</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06118"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06118</id>
    <updated>2023-03-13T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Alonso_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;&amp;#xc1;ngel Javier Alonso&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Kerber_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Michael Kerber&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the decomposition of zero-dimensional persistence modules, viewed as
functors valued in the category of vector spaces factorizing through sets.
Instead of working directly at the level of vector spaces, we take a step back
and first study the decomposition problem at the level of sets.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach allows us to define the combinatorial notion of rooted subsets.
In the case of a filtered metric space $M$, rooted subsets relate the
clustering behavior of the points of $M$ with the decomposition of the
associated persistence module. In particular, we can identify intervals in such
a decomposition quickly. In addition, rooted subsets can be understood as a
generalization of the elder rule, and are also related to the notion of
constant conqueror of Cai, Kim, M\&#39;emoli and Wang. As an application, we give a
lower bound on the number of intervals that we can expect in the decomposition
of zero-dimensional persistence modules of a density-Rips filtration in
Euclidean space: in the limit, and under very general circumstances, we can
expect that at least 25% of the indecomposable summands are interval modules.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Optimal-Hash Exact String Matching Algorithms</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.05799"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.05799</id>
    <updated>2023-03-13T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lecroq_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Thierry Lecroq&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;String matching is the problem of finding all the occurrences of a pattern in
a text. We propose improved versions of the fast family of string matching
algorithms based on hashing $q$-grams. The improvement consists of considering
minimal values $q$ such that each $q$-grams of the pattern has a unique hash
value. The new algorithms are fastest than algorithm of the HASH family for
short patterns on large size alphabets.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Faster Matroid Partition Algorithms</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.05920"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.05920</id>
    <updated>2023-03-13T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Terao_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tatsuya Terao&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the matroid partitioning problem, we are given $k$ matroids $\mathcal{M}_1
= (V, \mathcal{I}_1), \dots , \mathcal{M}_k = (V, \mathcal{I}_k)$ defined over
a common ground set $V$ of $n$ elements, and we need to find a partitionable
set $S \subseteq V$ of largest possible cardinality, denoted by $p$. Here, a
set $S \subseteq V$ is called partitionable if there exists a partition $(S_1,
\dots , S_k)$ of $S$ with $S_i \in \mathcal{I}_i$ for $i = 1, \ldots, k$. In
1986, Cunningham presented a matroid partition algorithm that uses $O(n p^{3/2}
+ k n)$ independence oracle queries, which was the previously known best
algorithm. This query complexity is $O(n^{5/2})$ when $k \leq n$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our main result is to present a matroid partition algorithm that uses
$\tilde{O}(k^{1/3} n p + k n)$ independence oracle queries, which is
$\tilde{O}(n^{7/3})$ when $k \leq n$. This improves upon previous Cunningham&#39;s
algorithm. To obtain this, we present a new approach \emph{edge recycling
augmentation}, which can be attained through new ideas: an efficient
utilization of the binary search technique by Nguyen and
Chakrabarty-Lee-Sidford-Singla-Wong and a careful analysis of the number of
independence oracle queries. Our analysis differs significantly from the one
for matroid intersection algorithms, because of the parameter $k$. We also
present a matroid partition algorithm that uses $\tilde{O}((n + k) \sqrt{p})$
rank oracle queries.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Simple and efficient four-cycle counting on sparse graphs</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06090"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06090</id>
    <updated>2023-03-13T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Burkhardt_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Paul Burkhardt&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Harris_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;David G. Harris&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We consider the problem of counting 4-cycles ($C_4$) in a general undirected
graph $G$ of $n$ vertices and $m$ edges (in bipartite graphs, 4-cycles are also
often referred to as $\textit{butterflies}$). There have been a number of
previous algorithms for this problem; some of these are based on fast matrix
multiplication, which is attractive theoretically but not practical, and some
of these are based on randomized hash tables.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We develop a new simpler algorithm for counting $C_4$, which has several
practical improvements over previous algorithms; for example, it is fully
deterministic and avoids any expensive arithmetic in its inner loops. The
algorithm can also be adapted to count 4-cycles incident to each vertex and
edge. Our algorithm runs in $O(m\bar\delta(G))$ time and $O(n)$ space, where
$\bar \delta(G) \leq O(\sqrt{m})$ is the $\textit{average degeneracy}$
parameter introduced by Burkhardt, Faber &amp;amp; Harris (2020).
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Bootstrapping Dynamic Distance Oracles</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06102"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06102</id>
    <updated>2023-03-13T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Forster_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sebastian Forster&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Goranci_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Gramoz Goranci&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nazari_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yasamin Nazari&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Skarlatos_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Antonis Skarlatos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Designing approximate all-pairs distance oracles in the fully dynamic setting
is one of the central problems in dynamic graph algorithms. Despite extensive
research on this topic, the first result breaking the $O(\sqrt{n})$ barrier on
the update time for any non-trivial approximation was introduced only recently
by Forster, Goranci and Henzinger [SODA&#39;21] who achieved $m^{1/\rho+o(1)}$
amortized update time with a $O(\log n)^{3\rho-2}$ factor in the approximation
ratio, for any parameter $\rho \geq 1$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we give the first constant-stretch fully dynamic distance
oracle with a small polynomial update and query time. Prior work required
either at least a poly-logarithmic approximation or much larger update time.
Our result gives a more fine-grained trade-off between stretch and update time,
for instance we can achieve constant stretch of $O(\frac{1}{\rho^2})^{4/\rho}$
in amortized update time $\tilde{O}(n^{\rho})$, and query time
$\tilde{O}(n^{\rho/8})$ for a constant parameter $\rho &amp;lt;1$. Our algorithm is
randomized and assumes an oblivious adversary.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A core technical idea underlying our construction is to design a black-box
reduction from decremental approximate hub-labeling schemes to fully dynamic
distance oracles, which may be of independent interest. We then apply this
reduction repeatedly to an existing decremental algorithm to bootstrap our
fully dynamic solution.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Any-Order Online Interval Selection</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06127"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06127</id>
    <updated>2023-03-13T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Borodin_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Allan Borodin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Karavasilis_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Christodoulos Karavasilis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We consider the problem of online interval scheduling on a single machine,
where intervals arrive online in an order chosen by an adversary, and the
algorithm must output a set of non-conflicting intervals. Traditionally in
scheduling theory, it is assumed that intervals arrive in order of increasing
start times. We drop that assumption and allow for intervals to arrive in any
possible order. We call this variant any-order interval selection (AOIS). We
assume that some online acceptances can be revoked, but a feasible solution
must always be maintained. For unweighted intervals and deterministic
algorithms, this problem is unbounded. Under the assumption that there are at
most $k$ different interval lengths, we give a simple algorithm that achieves a
competitive ratio of $2k$ and show that it is optimal amongst deterministic
algorithms, and a restricted class of randomized algorithms we call memoryless,
contributing to an open question by Adler and Azar 2003; namely whether a
randomized algorithm without access to history can achieve a constant
competitive ratio. We connect our model to the problem of call control on the
line, and show how the algorithms of Garay et al. 1997 can be applied to our
setting, resulting in an optimal algorithm for the case of proportional
weights. We also consider the case of intervals arriving in a random order, and
show that for single-lengthed instances, a one-directional algorithm (i.e.
replacing intervals in one direction), is the only deterministic memoryless
algorithm that can possibly benefit from random arrivals. Finally, we briefly
discuss the case of intervals with arbitrary weights.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


</feed>
