<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title>Theory of Computing Report</title>
  <link rel="self" href=""/>
  <link href=""/>
  <id></id>
  <updated></updated>
  <generator uri="http://feedreader.github.io/">Pluto 1.6.2 on Ruby 3.0.5 (2022-11-24) [x86_64-linux]</generator>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Property Testing Review: News for October 2022</title>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/2022/12/news-for-october-2022-2/"/>
    <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1784</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T18:22:31+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;All the best to everyone for a Happy 2023. The holiday season is ripe with lots of papers to engage our readers. So, we have nine papers and we hope some of those will catch your fancy. As a new year treat, we also feature Gilmer&amp;#8217;s constant lower bound on the union-closed sets problem of Frankl. On we go.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sublinear Time Algorithms and Complexity of Approximate Maximum Matching&lt;/strong&gt; by Soheil Behnezhad, Mohammad Roghani, Aviad Rubinstein (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.15843&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;) This paper makes significantly advances our understanding of the maximum matching problem in the sublinear regime. Your goal is to estimate the size of the maximum matching and you may assume that you have query access to the adjacency list of your graph. Our posts from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ptreview.sublinear.info/2021/12/&quot;&gt;Dec 2021&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ptreview.sublinear.info/2022/07/news-for-june-2022/&quot;&gt;June 2022&lt;/a&gt; reported some impressive progress on this problem. The upshot from these works essentially said that you can beat greedy matching and obtain a \(\frac{1}{2} + \Omega(1)\) approximate maximum matching in sublinear time. The question remained &amp;#8212; can we show a lower bound that grows superlinearly with \(n\). The current work achieves this and shows that &lt;em&gt;even on bipartite graphs&lt;/em&gt;, you must make at least \(n^{1.2 &amp;#8211; o(1)}\) &lt;em&gt;queries &lt;/em&gt;to the adjacency list to get a better than \(2/3 + \Omega(1)\) approximation. On the other hand, the paper also presents an algorithm that runs in time \(n^{2 &amp;#8211; \Omega_{\varepsilon}(1)}\) (strongly sublinear time) and returns a \(2/3 &amp;#8211; \varepsilon\) approximation to the maximum matching size. Thus, in particular, you cannot shoot for a bonafide quadratic lower bound on the number of queries to beat a two-thirds approximation to the maximum matching size.  (An aside: A concurrent work by &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.00189&quot;&gt;Bhattacharya-Kiss-Saranurak&lt;/a&gt; from December also obtains similar results) &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Directed Isoperimetric Theorems for Boolean Functions on the Hypergrid and an \(\widetilde{O}(n \sqrt d)\) Monotonicity Tester&lt;/strong&gt; by Hadley Black, Deeparnab Chakrabarty, C. Seshadhri (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05281&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;) Boolean Monotonicity testing is as classic as classic gets in property testing. Encouraged by the success of isoperimetric theorems over the hypercube domain and the monotonicity testers powered by these isoperimetries (over the hypercube), one may wish to obtain efficient monotonicity testers for the hypergrid \([n]^d\). Indeed, the same gang of authors as above showed in a previous work that a Margulis style directed isoperimetry can be extended from the lowly hypercube to the hypergrid. This resulted in a tester with \(\widetilde{O}(d^{5/6})\) queries. The more intricate task of proving a directed Talagrand style isoperimetry that underlies the Khot-Minzer-Safra breakthrough was a challenge. Was. The featured work extends this isoperimetry from the hypercube to the hypergrid and this gives a tester with query complexity \(\widetilde{O}(n \sqrt d)\) which is an improvement over the \(d^{5/6}\) bound for domains where \(n\) is (say) some small constant. But as they say, when it rains, it pours. This brings us to a concurrent paper with the same result.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improved Monotonicity Testers via Hypercube Embeddings&lt;/strong&gt; by Mark Braverman, Subhash Khot, Guy Kindler, Dor Minzer (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.09229&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;) Similar to the paper above, this paper also obtains monotonicity testers over the hypergrid domain, \([n]^d\), with \(\widetilde{O}(n^3 \sqrt d)\) queries. This paper also presents monotonicity testers over the standard hypercube domain &amp;#8212; \(\{0,1\}^d\) in the \(p\)-biased setting. In particular, their tester issues \(\widetilde{O}(\sqrt d)\) queries to successfully test monotonicity on the \(p\)-biased cube. Coolly enough, this paper also proves directed Talagrand style isoperimetric inequalities both over the hypergrid and the \(p\)-biased hypercube domains.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Toeplitz Low-Rank Approximation with Sublinear Query Complexity&lt;/strong&gt; by Michael Kapralov, Hannah Lawrence, Mikhail Makarov, Cameron Musco, Kshiteej Sheth (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.11328&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;) Another intriguing paper for the holiday month. So, take a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toeplitz_matrix&quot;&gt;Toeplitz matrix&lt;/a&gt;. Did you know that any &lt;em&gt;psd&lt;/em&gt; Toeplitz matrix admits a (near-optimal in the Frobenius norm) low-rank approximation which is itself Toeplitz? This is a remarkable statement. The featured paper proves this result and uses it to get more algorithmic mileage. In particular, suppose you are given a \(d \times d\) Toeplitz matrix \(T\). Armed with the techniques from the paper you get algorithms that return a Toeplitz matrix \(\widetilde{T}\) with rank slightly bigger than \(rank(T)\) which is a very good approximation to \(T\) in the Frobenius norm. Moreover, the algorithm only issues a number of queries sublinear in the size of \(T\).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sampling an Edge in Sublinear Time Exactly and Optimally&lt;/strong&gt; by Talya Eden, Shyam Narayanan and Jakub Tětek (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.04981&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;) Regular readers of PTReview are no strangers to the fundamental task of sampling a random edge from a graph which you can access via query access to its vertices. Of course, you don&amp;#8217;t have direct access to the edges of this graph. This paper considers the task of sampling a truly uniform edge from the graph \(G = (V,E)\) with \(|V| = n, |E| = m\). In STOC 22, Tětek and Thorup presented an algorithm for a relaxation of this problem where you want an \(\varepsilon\)-approximately unifrom edge. This algorithm runs in time \(O\left(\frac{n}{\sqrt{m}} \cdot \log(1/\varepsilon) \right)\). The featured paper presents an algorithm that samples an honest to goodness uniform edge in expected time \(O(n/\sqrt{m})\). This closes the problem as we already know a matching lower bound. Indeed, just consider a graph with \(O(\sqrt m)\) vertices which induce a clique and all the remaining components are singletons. You need to sample at least \(\Omega(n/\sqrt m)\) vertices before you see any edge.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Support Size Estimation: The Power of Conditioning&lt;/strong&gt; by Diptarka Chakraborty, Gunjan Kumar, Kuldeep S. Meel (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.11967&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;) This work considers the classic problem of support size estimation with a slight twist. You are given access to a stronger (conditioning based) sampling oracle. Let me highlight one of the results from this paper. So, you are given a distribution \(D\) where \(supp(D) \subseteq [n]\). You want to obtain an estimate to \(supp(D)\) that lies within \(supp(D) \pm \varepsilon n\) with high probability. Suppose you are also given access to the following sampling oracle. You may choose any subset \(S \subseteq [n]\) and you may request a sample \(x \sim D\vert_S\). An element \(x \in S\) is returned with probability \(D\vert_S(x) = D(x)/D(S)\) (for simplicity of this post, let us assume \(D(S) &gt; 0\)). In addition, this oracle also reveals for you the value \(D(x)\). The paper shows that the algorithmic task of obtaining a high probability estimate to the support size (to within \(\pm \varepsilon n\)) with this sampling oracle admits a lower bound of \(\Omega(\log (\log n)\) calls to the sampling oracle.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Computing (1+epsilon)-Approximate Degeneracy in Sublinear Time&lt;/strong&gt; by Valerie King, Alex Thomo, Quinton Yong (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.04627&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;) Degeneracy is one of the important graph parameters which is relevant to several problems in algorithmic graph theory. A graph \(G = (V,E)\) is \(\delta\)-degenerate if all induced subgraphs of \(G\) contain a vertex with degree at most \(\delta\). The featured paper presents algorithms for a \((1 + \varepsilon)\)-approximation to degeneracy of \(G\) where you are given access to \(G\) via its adjacency list. &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning and Testing Latent-Tree Ising Models Efficiently&lt;/strong&gt; by Davin Choo, Yuval Dagan, Constantinos Daskalakis, Anthimos Vardis Kandiros (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.13291&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;) Ising models are emerging as a rich and fertile frontier for Property Testing and Learning Theory researchers (at least to the uninitiated ones like me). This paper considers latent-tree ising models. These are ising models that can only be observed at their leaf nodes. One of the results in this paper gives an algorithm for testing whether the leaf distributions attached to two latent-tree ising models are close or far in the TV distance.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A constant lower bound for the union-closed sets conjecture&lt;/strong&gt; by Justin Gilmer (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.09055&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;) The union-closed sets conjecture of Frankl states that for any union closed set system \(\mathcal{F} \subseteq 2^{[n]}\), it holds that there is a mysterious element \(i \in [n]\) that shows up in at least \(c = 1/2\) of the sets in \(\mathcal{F}\). Gilmer took a first swipe on this problem and gave a constant lower bound of \(c = 0.01\). This has already been improved by at least four different groups to \(\frac{3-\sqrt{5}}{2}\), a bound which is the limit of Gilmer&amp;#8217;s method (which takes all of only 9 pages!). &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The key lemma Gilmer proves is the following. Suppose you sample two sets: \(A, B \sim \mathcal{D}_n\) &lt;em&gt;(iid)&lt;/em&gt; from some distribution \(\mathcal{D}_n\) over the subsets of \([n]\). Suppose for every index \(i \in [n]\), it holds that the probability that the element \(i\) shows up in the random set \(A\) is at most $0.01$. Then you have \(H(A \cup B) \geq 1.26 H(A)\). This is all you need to finish Gilmer&amp;#8217;s proof (of \(c = 0.01\)). The remaining argument is as follows. Suppose, by the way of contradiction, that no element shows up in at least \(0.01\) fraction of sets in the union closed family \(\mathcal{F}\). An application of the key lemma would then give \(H(A \cup B) &gt; H(A)\) which is a contradiction if \(A,B\) are chosen uniformly from \(\mathcal{F}\). The proof of the key lemma is also fairly slick and uses pretty simple information theoretic tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Akash&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Property Testing Review</name>
      <uri>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Computational Complexity: Harry Lewis&#39;s talk  on The Birth of Binary on Dec 8 (Thats today!)</title>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/12/harry-lewiss-talk-on-birth-of-binary-on.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-8537518250187298951</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T15:38:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;More on the information on Harry Lewis&#39;s&amp;nbsp; talk is in his blog post about it:&lt;a href=&quot;http://harry-lewis.blogspot.com/2022/11/skolem-lecture-on-birth-of-binary-8.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1) On Dec 8, 2022 Harry Lewis is giving the annual Thoraf Skolem Memorial Lecture on&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;The Birth of binary&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Its in Oslo. BOO- I can&#39;t get there!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It will be on Zoom- YEAH I can see it! Here is the link:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://uio.zoom.us/j/63956167845&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;It will be at 7:15AM East Coast Time- BOO- I needs my sleep!&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;(Plus, I am posting this after its over)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;It will be recorded-YEAH I can see it later. CAVEAT- Will I?&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;(It will be linked to at the link in item 4 below.)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;2) Lloyd Strickland and Harry Lewis have a book on the subject:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262544344/leibniz-on-binary/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;titled&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;i&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;Leibniz on binary: The Invention of Computer Arithmetic.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;3) Questions like &lt;i&gt;who invented binary&amp;nbsp; &lt;/i&gt;or &lt;i&gt;who invented parallelism&lt;/i&gt; or&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;who first proved the dual-muffin theorem&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;can be hard to answer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;First&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp; is an ill defined term. In the current era we can see who published first, which is usually well defined, though might not get at the heart of the issue.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Which brings us to Leibnitz on Binary.&amp;nbsp; He had lots of notes, not really intended for modern readers or even for readers in his own time. The notes lay out binary notation and some algorithms, but not in a modern way. Hence the book is quite valuable to tell a modern audience what Leibnitz did. Leibnitz published very little of it.&amp;nbsp; Even so, seeing what he did, the statement&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;i&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;Leibnitz invented binary&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt; is reasonable. Some of his notes dealt with what we would now call complexity, so I need to add him to my already-long list of people who had modern ideas about complexity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;4) For more on the Skolem Lecture, see&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hf.uio.no/ifikk/english/research/groups/logic/events/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By gasarch&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR22-178 |  A Strongly Polynomial Algorithm for Approximate Forster Transforms and its Application to Halfspace Learning | 

	Ilias Diakonikolas, 

	Christos Tzamos, 

	Daniel Kane</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/178"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/178</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T13:27:12+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    The Forster transform is a method of regularizing a dataset 
by placing it in {\em radial isotropic position}
while maintaining some of its essential properties.
Forster transforms have played a key role in a diverse range of settings
spanning computer science and functional analysis. Prior work had given
{\em weakly} polynomial time algorithms for computing Forster transforms, when they exist.
Our main result is the first {\em strongly polynomial time} algorithm to
compute an approximate Forster transform of a given dataset 
or certify that no such transformation exists. By leveraging our strongly polynomial Forster algorithm, 
we obtain the first strongly polynomial time algorithm for {\em distribution-free} PAC learning of halfspaces.
This learning result is surprising because {\em proper} PAC learning of halfspaces 
is {\em equivalent} to linear programming.
Our learning approach extends to give a strongly polynomial halfspace learner
in the presence of random classification noise and, more generally, Massart noise.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Partial gathering of mobile agents in dynamic rings</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03457"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03457</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Shibataa_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Masahiro Shibataa&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sudo_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yuichi Sudo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nakamura_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Junya Nakamura&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kim_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yonghwan Kim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we consider the partial gathering problem of mobile agents in
synchronous dynamic bidirectional ring networks. When k agents are distributed
in the network, the partial gathering problem requires, for a given positive
integer g (&amp;lt; k), that agents terminate in a configuration such that either at
least g agents or no agent exists at each node. So far, the partial gathering
problem has been considered in static graphs. In this paper, we start
considering partial gathering in dynamic graphs. As a first step, we consider
this problem in 1-interval connected rings, that is, one of the links in a ring
may be missing at each time step. In such networks, focusing on the
relationship between the values of k and g, we fully characterize the
solvability of the partial gathering problem and analyze the move complexity of
the proposed algorithms when the problem can be solved. First, we show that the
g-partial gathering problem is unsolvable when k &amp;lt;= 2g. Second, we show that
the problem can be solved with O(n log g) time and the total number of O(gn log
g) moves when 2g + 1 &amp;lt;= k &amp;lt;= 3g - 2. Third, we show that the problem can be
solved with O(n) time and the total number of O(kn) moves when 3g - 1 &amp;lt;= k &amp;lt;=
8g - 4. Notice that since k = O(g) holds when 3g - 1 &amp;lt;= k &amp;lt;= 8g - 4, the move
complexity O(kn) in this case can be represented also as O(gn). Finally, we
show that the problem can be solved with O(n) time and the total number of
O(gn) moves when k &amp;gt;= 8g - 3. These results mean that the partial gathering
problem can be solved also in dynamic rings when k &amp;gt;= 2g + 1. In addition,
agents require a total number of \Omega(gn) moves to solve the partial (resp.,
total) gathering problem. Thus, when k &amp;gt;= 3g - 1, agents can solve the partial
gathering problem with the asymptotically optimal total number of O(gn) moves.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Recognizing when a preference system is close to admitting a master list</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03521"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03521</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Schlotter_I/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ildik&amp;#xf3; Schlotter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A preference system $\mathcal{I}$ is an undirected graph where vertices have
preferences over their neighbors, and $\mathcal{I}$ admits a master list if all
preferences can be derived from a single ordering over all vertices. We study
the problem of deciding whether a given preference system~$\mathcal{I}$ is
close to admitting a master list based on three different distance measures. We
determine the computational complexity of the following questions: can
$\mathcal{I}$ be modified by (i) $k$ swaps in the preferences, (ii) $k$ edge
deletions, or (iii) $k$ vertex deletions so that the resulting instance admits
a master list? We investigate these problems in detail from the viewpoint of
parameterized complexity and of approximation. We also present two applications
related to stable and popular matchings.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Quantum Worst-Case to Average-Case Reductions for All Linear Problems</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03348"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03348</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Asadi_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vahid R. Asadi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Golovnev_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Alexander Golovnev&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Gur_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tom Gur&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Shinkar_I/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Igor Shinkar&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Subramanian_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sathyawageeswar Subramanian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the problem of designing worst-case to average-case reductions for
quantum algorithms. For all linear problems, we provide an explicit and
efficient transformation of quantum algorithms that are only correct on a small
(even sub-constant) fraction of their inputs into ones that are correct on all
inputs. This stands in contrast to the classical setting, where such results
are only known for a small number of specific problems or restricted
computational models. En route, we obtain a tight $\Omega(n^2)$ lower bound on
the average-case quantum query complexity of the Matrix-Vector Multiplication
problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our techniques strengthen and generalise the recently introduced additive
combinatorics framework for classical worst-case to average-case reductions
(STOC 2022) to the quantum setting. We rely on quantum singular value
transformations to construct quantum algorithms for linear verification in
superposition and learning Bogolyubov subspaces from noisy quantum oracles. We
use these tools to prove a quantum local correction lemma, which lies at the
heart of our reductions, based on a noise-robust probabilistic generalisation
of Bogolyubov&#39;s lemma from additive combinatorics.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Extending Utility Functions on Arbitrary Sets</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03394"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03394</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Chebotarev_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Pavel Chebotarev&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We consider the problem of whether a function $f^{}_P$ defined on a subset
$P$ of an arbitrary set $X$ can be extended to $X$ monotonically with respect
to a preorder $\succcurlyeq$ defined on $X$. We prove that whenever
$\succcurlyeq$ has a utility representation, such an extension exists if and
only if $f^{}_P$ is gap-safe increasing. An explicit construction for a
monotone extension of this kind involving an arbitrary utility representation
of $\succcurlyeq$ is presented. The special case where $P$ is a Pareto subset
of $X$ is considered. The problem under study does not include continuity
constraints.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: A Decision Diagram Operation for Reachability</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03684"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03684</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Brand_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sebastiaan Brand&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Back_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Thomas B&amp;#xe4;ck&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Laarman_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Alfons Laarman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Saturation is considered the state-of-the-art method for computing fixpoints
with decision diagrams. We present a relatively simple decision diagram
operation called REACH that also computes fixpoints. In contrast to saturation,
it does not require a partitioning of the transition relation. We give
sequential algorithms implementing the new operation for both binary and
multi-valued decision diagrams, and moreover provide parallel counterparts. We
implement these algorithms and experimentally compare their performance against
saturation on 692 model checking benchmarks in different languages. The results
show that the REACH operation often outperforms saturation, especially on
transition relations with low locality. In a comparison between parallelized
versions of REACH and saturation we find that REACH obtains comparable speedups
up to 16 cores, although falls behind saturation at 64 cores. Finally, in a
comparison with the state-of-the-art model checking tool ITS-tools we find that
REACH outperforms ITS-tools on 29% of models, suggesting that REACH can be
useful as a complementary method in an ensemble tool.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Density Approximation for Kinetic Groups</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03685"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03685</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mulken_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Max van Mulken&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Speckmann_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Bettina Speckmann&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Verbeek_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Kevin Verbeek&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sets of moving entities can form groups which travel together for significant
amounts of time. Tracking such groups is an important analysis task in a
variety of areas, such as wildlife ecology, urban transport, or sports
analysis. Correspondingly, recent years have seen a multitude of algorithms to
identify and track meaningful groups in sets of moving entities. However, not
only the mere existence of one or more groups is an important fact to discover;
in many application areas the actual shape of the group carries meaning as
well. In this paper we initiate the algorithmic study of the shape of a moving
group. We use kernel density estimation to model the density within a group and
show how to efficiently maintain an approximation of this density description
over time. Furthermore, we track persistent maxima which give a meaningful
first idea of the time-varying shape of the group. By combining several
approximation techniques, we obtain a kinetic data structure that can
approximately track persistent maxima efficiently.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: An improved approximation guarantee for Prize-Collecting TSP</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03776"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03776</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Blauth_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jannis Blauth&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nagele_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Martin N&amp;#xe4;gele&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present a new approximation algorithm for the (metric) prize-collecting
traveling salesperson problem (PCTSP). In PCTSP, opposed to the classical
traveling salesperson problem (TSP), one may not include a vertex of the input
graph in the returned tour at the cost of a given vertex-dependent penalty, and
the objective is to balance the length of the tour and the incurred penalties
for omitted vertices by minimizing the sum of the two. We present an algorithm
that achieves an approximation guarantee of $1.774$ with respect to the natural
linear programming relaxation of the problem. This significantly reduces the
gap between the approximability of classical TSP and PCTSP, beating the
previously best known approximation factor of $1.915$. As a key ingredient of
our improvement, we present a refined decomposition technique for solutions of
the LP relaxation, and show how to leverage components of that decomposition as
building blocks for our tours.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Why the equivalence problem for unambiguous grammars has not been solved back in 1966?</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03786"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03786</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Makarov_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vladislav Makarov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1966, Semenov, by using a technique based on power series, suggested an
algorithm that tells apart the languages described by an unambiguous grammar
and a DFA. At the first glance, it may appear that the algorithm can be easily
modified to yield a full solution of the equivalence problem for unambiguous
grammars. This article shows why this hunch is, in fact, incorrect.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Computing linear sections of varieties: quantum entanglement, tensor decompositions and beyond</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03851"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03851</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Johnston_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nathaniel Johnston&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lovitz_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Benjamin Lovitz&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Vijayaraghavan_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Aravindan Vijayaraghavan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the problem of finding elements in the intersection of an arbitrary
conic variety in $\mathbb{F}^n$ with a given linear subspace (where
$\mathbb{F}$ can be the real or complex field). This problem captures a rich
family of algorithmic problems under different choices of the variety. The
special case of the variety consisting of rank-1 matrices already has strong
connections to central problems in different areas like quantum information
theory and tensor decompositions. This problem is known to be NP-hard in the
worst-case, even for the variety of rank-1 matrices.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, despite these hardness results we give efficient algorithms
that solve this problem for &quot;typical&quot; subspaces. Here, the subspace $U
\subseteq \mathbb{F}^n$ is chosen generically of a certain dimension,
potentially with some generic elements of the variety contained in it. Our main
algorithmic result is a polynomial time algorithm that recovers all the
elements of $U$ that lie in the variety, under some mild non-degeneracy
assumptions on the variety. As corollaries, we obtain the following results:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\bullet$ Uniqueness results and polynomial time algorithms for generic
instances of a broad class of low-rank decomposition problems that go beyond
tensor decompositions. Here, we recover a decomposition of the form
$\sum_{i=1}^R v_i \otimes w_i$, where the $v_i$ are elements of the given
variety $X$. This implies new algorithmic results even in the special case of
tensor decompositions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\bullet$ Polynomial time algorithms for several entangled subspaces problems
in quantum entanglement, including determining $r$-entanglement, complete
entanglement, and genuine entanglement of a subspace. While all of these
problems are NP-hard in the worst case, our algorithm solves them in polynomial
time for generic subspaces of dimension up to a constant multiple of the
maximum possible.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Cocke--Younger--Kasami--Schwartz--Zippel algorithm and relatives</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03861"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03861</id>
    <updated>2022-12-08T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Makarov_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vladislav Makarov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The equivalence problem for unambiguous grammars is an important, but very
difficult open question in formal language theory. Consider the \emph{limited}
equivalence problem for unambiguous grammars -- for two unambiguous grammars
$G_1$ and $G_2$, tell whether or not they describe the same set of words of
length $n$. Obviously, the naive approach requires exponential time with
respect to $n$. By combining two classic algorithmic ideas, I introduce a
$O({\rm poly}(n, |G_1|, |G_2|))$ algorithm for this problem. Moreover, the
ideas behind the algorithm prove useful in various other scenarious.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Richard Lipton: Quantum Circuits in the New York Times</title>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/07/quantum-circuits-in-the-new-york-times/"/>
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=20531</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T19:16:32+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;
&lt;font color=&quot;#0044cc&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Can quantum circuits have something to do with wormholes?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;font color=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;image alignright&quot;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/07/quantum-circuits-in-the-new-york-times/ms-3/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-20534&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;20534&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/07/quantum-circuits-in-the-new-york-times/ms-3/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/ms.jpeg?fit=259%2C194&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;259,194&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;ms&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/ms.jpeg?fit=259%2C194&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/ms.jpeg?fit=259%2C194&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/ms.jpeg?resize=200%2C150&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; height=&quot;150&quot; class=&quot;alignright wp-image-20534&quot; srcset=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/ms.jpeg?w=259&amp;amp;ssl=1 259w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/ms.jpeg?resize=200%2C150&amp;amp;ssl=1 200w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;caption alignright&quot;&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;-2&quot;&gt;Wikipedia &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_Spiropulu&quot;&gt;src&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Maria Spiropulu, a physicist &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hep.caltech.edu/~smaria/&quot;&gt;at&lt;/a&gt; the California Institute of Technology, is featured in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2022/11/30/science/physics-wormhole-quantum-computer.html&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; in last week&amp;#8217;s Tuesday Science section of the New York Times about teleporting qubits through what might be described as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wormhole&quot;&gt;wormhole&lt;/a&gt;. The article says that physicists such as she&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;#038;bg=e8e8e8&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;dots}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt; like to compare the teleportation process to two cups of tea. Drop a cube of sugar into one teacup, and it promptly dissolves&amp;#8212;then, after a tick of the quantum clock, the cube reappears intact in the other teacup. &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Today (yesterday? tomorrow? &lt;a href=&quot;https://chadorzel.substack.com/p/wormhole-to-2006&quot;&gt;years ago?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8212;with a quantum clock, does it &lt;a href=&quot;https://phys.org/news/2019-03-physicists-reverse-quantum.html&quot;&gt;matter&lt;/a&gt;?) we ask what the paper referenced in the NYT story might really be about. This is after trying to work through a lot of hype and pushback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first trouble is that we cannot tick a real quantum clock quite yet. But Spiropulu and her group were able to simulate a quantum clock via using a quantum computer. The group comprises: first author Daniel Jafferis, then Alexander Zlokapa, Joseph Lykken, David Kolchmeyer, Samantha Davis, Nikolai Lauk, Hartmut Neven, and then Spiropulu. Their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-022-05424-3&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; was just reported in &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt;. The whole buzz makes us recall an exchange that never took place:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; Albert Einstein: &amp;#8220;Reality is merely an illusion, albeit a persistent one.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Woody Allen: &amp;#8220;[If] everything is an illusion and nothing exists, [then] I definitely overpaid for my carpet.&amp;#8221; &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; The Quantum Experiment &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Spiropulu&amp;#8217;s group could not build a quantum experiment to directly test this kind of teleportation. At least it seemed like that would be impossible. But they cleverly used the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sycamore_processor&quot;&gt;Sycamore&lt;/a&gt; chip developed by Google in 2019. It uses a type of quantum computing called superconducting qubits, which send electric currents flowing through superconducting materials to store and process information. Google created the chip to study &amp;#8220;quantum supremacy&amp;#8221; as we &lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2019/10/27/quantum-supremacy-at-last/&quot;&gt;covered&lt;/a&gt; three years ago. A wonderful &lt;a href=&quot;https://jonathan-hui.medium.com/quantum-supremacy-google-sycamore-processor-6f30073a17fa&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;em&gt;Medium&lt;/em&gt; by Jonathan Hui runs helpful commentary around circuit diagrams of the processor from the Google team&amp;#8217;s original &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-019-1666-5&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;. Hui says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; Regardless of other claims, Google’s processor is a significant milestone because it demonstrates a problem with some real value. Whether classical computers will take 100,000 years or 2.5 days for the pseudo-random generator, this kind of speed improvement is rarely or never demonstrated with a general-purpose quantum computer. &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
What we find significant is that Google&amp;#8217;s processor is not limited to the pseudo-randomness application to demonstrate what we&amp;#8217;ll call &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ibm.com/blogs/research/tag/quantum-advantage/&quot;&gt;advantage&lt;/a&gt;. It has plug-and-play capabilities. Google may not have created Sycamore to study quantum teleportation. But it was possible to exploit its quantum ability to demonstrate teleportation. See their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-022-05424-3&quot;&gt;Nature&lt;/a&gt; paper for how. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; Wormholes and Their Duals &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The NYT story and an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantamagazine.org/physicists-create-a-wormhole-using-a-quantum-computer-20221130/&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; by Natalie Wolchover in &lt;em&gt;Quanta&lt;/em&gt; have some pithy quotes from people well-known to us:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
John Preskill, about &amp;#8216;the evolving system of qubits in the Sycamore chip&amp;#8217;: &amp;#8220;[It] has this really cool alternative description. You can think of the system in a very different language as being gravitational.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Leonard Susskind: &amp;#8220;The really interesting thing here is the possibility of analyzing purely quantum phenomena using general relativity, and who knows where that’s going to go.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Scott Aaronson: &amp;#8220;If this experiment has brought a wormhole into actual physical existence, then a strong case could be made that you, too, bring a wormhole into actual physical existence every time you sketch one with pen and paper.&amp;#8221; (See also Scott&amp;#8217;s post &lt;a href=&quot;https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6871&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
These quotes allude to a duality, both ends of which connect Einstein and the Israeli-American physicist Nathan Rosen. Their 1935 paper, abbreviated ER, showed how a wormhole could arise in the specific form of an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wormhole&quot;&gt;Einstein-Rosen bridge&lt;/a&gt; according to the equations of general relativity. They were joined that same year by Boris Podolsky in a paper that described quantum &lt;em&gt;entanglement&lt;/em&gt; via the so-called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EPR_paradox&quot;&gt;EPR paradox&lt;/a&gt;. In 2013, Juan Maldacena wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1306.0533&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; with Susskind claiming a correspondence between them. This was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev_model&quot;&gt;expanded&lt;/a&gt; by Alexei Kitaev following work by Subir Sachdev and Jinwu Ye. All this draws on Maldacena&amp;#8217;s work in the 1990s showing a duality between two cosmic models that have different dimensionalities, in the manner of a hologram. Maldacena and Susskind&amp;#8217;s claim is pithily expressed as the title of section 3 of their paper: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=center&gt;&lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cmathsf%7BER+%3D+EPR%7D+&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;#92;displaystyle  &amp;#92;mathsf{ER = EPR} &quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equality is enticing because this could effect the communion of relativity and quantum mechanics. This matter found its way into another New York Times &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2022/10/10/science/black-holes-cosmology-hologram.html&quot;&gt;story&lt;/a&gt; in October, where Susskind is quoted as saying in 2017:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; &amp;#8220;It may be too strong to say that gravity and quantum mechanics are exactly the same thing. But those of us who are paying attention may already sense that the two are inseparable, and that neither makes sense without the other.&amp;#8221; &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
That story centered the duality on black holes, but Will Kinney, a colleague of Ken&amp;#8217;s at Buffalo, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/WKCosmo/status/1600153143702016001&quot;&gt;observed&lt;/a&gt; that Maldacena and Susskind &amp;#8220;conjectured that ANY entangled particle pair is dual to a wormhole solution.&amp;#8221; Kinney also &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/WKCosmo/status/1598323058476982273&quot;&gt;quoted&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Quanta&lt;/em&gt; editor Thomas Lin as saying,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; &amp;#8220;In the context of the article, it should be clear that a quantum system was created that was dual to a holographic wormhole.&amp;#8221; &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
What fascinates us is that the quantum system had the form of direct simulation of quantum circuitry. In fact, Spiropulu&amp;#8217;s team used only 9 of 72 available qubits on a Sycamore chip. The NYT article has a big graphic on the role of ordinary quantum circuits, from which we snip this detail:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/07/quantum-circuits-in-the-new-york-times/nytcircuitdetail/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-20535&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;20535&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/12/07/quantum-circuits-in-the-new-york-times/nytcircuitdetail/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/NYTcircuitdetail.jpg?fit=794%2C466&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;794,466&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;KWRegan&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1670368563&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;NYTcircuitdetail&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/NYTcircuitdetail.jpg?fit=300%2C176&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/NYTcircuitdetail.jpg?fit=600%2C352&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/NYTcircuitdetail.jpg?resize=450%2C264&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;450&quot; height=&quot;264&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter wp-image-20535&quot; srcset=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/NYTcircuitdetail.jpg?w=794&amp;amp;ssl=1 794w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/NYTcircuitdetail.jpg?resize=300%2C176&amp;amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/NYTcircuitdetail.jpg?resize=768%2C451&amp;amp;ssl=1 768w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This leads us to some speculations of our own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; Dualling Quantum Circuits? &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Setting aside the question of wormholes or their duals, Spiropulu&amp;#8217;s team did observe behavior that could be forecasted only after running an exhaustive classical simulation tied to the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model on the 9-qubit scale. This is described in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uOJCS1W1uzgstarting&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Quanta&lt;/em&gt; about their work, starting about &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/uOJCS1W1uzg?t=660&quot;&gt;11:00&lt;/a&gt;. As Wolchover summarizes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; &amp;#8220;[A]n ineffable quantum phenomenon&amp;#8212;information teleporting between particles&amp;#8212;has a tangible interpretation as a particle receiving a kick of energy and moving at a calculable speed from A to B.&amp;#8221; &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Maybe there is no actual burst of energy, as Mateus Ara&amp;uacute;jo &lt;a href=&quot;https://mateusaraujo.info/2022/12/01/the-death-of-quanta-magazine/&quot;&gt;underscored&lt;/a&gt; while criticizing this segment of the video. But is the physical process in the circuit nevertheless subject to instability and noise? We reiterate a question that we &lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/11/01/quantum-trick-or-treat/&quot;&gt;posed&lt;/a&gt; a year ago after describing how small quantum circuits can embody quantum walks that are &lt;em&gt;chaotic&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; When a quantum circuit simulates an unstable physical process with full quantum advantage, what is the boundary between the simulation and the behavior being simulated?  Is potential bridging of this boundary a stumbling block to maintaining coherent operation while scaling up quantum hardware? &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
In the context of the November 2021 post, we noted that when one simulates chaotic physical systems in, say, FORTRAN or C++ or Python on a classical computer, one would not say the physical classical chips are themselves behaving chaotically. In the quantum case, we note Peter Shor&amp;#8217;s response to Wolchover&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nattyover/status/1598476586164035585&quot;&gt;referencing&lt;/a&gt; a 2017 lecture video on simulating physical systems. Shor retorts that a quantum computer simulating fusion doesn&amp;#8217;t shine like the sun, nor can quantum circuits both using and simulating superconductivity power the nation&amp;#8217;s electric grid. But our instances of chaotic quantum walks, and now possibly wormhole duality, strike us as more closely attached to the relation of physical behavior to computation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The new question we have is even more speculative, but may work as a counterpoint to the current discussion of the new paper. If ER=EPR is correct, then ordinary entanglements are dual to wormholes. That maximal entanglements are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monogamy_of_entanglement&quot;&gt;binary-only&lt;/a&gt; may correspond to the simplest wormholes going only from a point A to a point B. Entanglements are bread-and-butter to quantum circuits, so if this duality has any force, it should extend to the circuits themselves:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; If the team could possibly create a theoretical dual to a wormhole in a quantum circuit, then does the correspondence in the other direction yield &lt;b&gt;duals to quantum circuits&lt;/b&gt; that could house wormholes? Might the notion of such a circuit dual, expressed within general relativity, furnish an organizing principle about how the universe processes information to build structures on cosmic scales? &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
A 2018 &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1808.09072&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; by Tadashi Takayanagi titled &amp;#8220;Holographic Spacetimes as Quantum Circuits of Path-Integrations&amp;#8221; seems to open at least one direction of a cosmos-to-quantum-circuits correspondence.  A very recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.15601&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; by Scott with Jason Pollack, on how Maldacena&amp;#8217;s correspondence treats quantum states, draws on earlier work by Takayanagi, but seems to stop short of such duality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; Open Problems &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
What do you think of the questions raised by the new paper? As we highlighted at the start, it is couched in down-to-earth terms of quantum circuits. Setting aside the rampant controversy on the physics side&amp;#8212;there are more &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/?p=13181&quot;&gt;links&lt;/a&gt; collected by Peter Woit besides those we&amp;#8217;ve used&amp;#8212;what does this say about realizing the quantum circuit model?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[some slight word changes]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By RJLipton+KWRegan&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Lipton</name>
      <uri>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Emanuele Viola: |Northeastern – Simons Institute| &lt; 10, EXP, and PhD in complexity theory</title>
    <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2022/12/07/northeastern-simons-institute-10-exp-and-phd-in-complexity-theory/"/>
    <id>http://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?p=1101</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T13:32:01+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;Northeastern recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://mills.northeastern.edu/merger/&quot;&gt;merged with Mills College, in Oakland, California.  &lt;/a&gt;The massive campus is less than 10 miles from the Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing.  This is the n+1 growth in an amazing streak, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.northeastern.edu/graduate/our-campus-network/&quot;&gt;multiple campuses all over the world, &lt;/a&gt;naming &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bizjournals.com/boston/news/2018/12/17/northeastern-to-rename-computer-science-school.html&quot;&gt;gifts&lt;/a&gt;, and new buildings, including one named after a complexity class: &lt;a href=&quot;https://facilities.northeastern.edu/exp/&quot;&gt;EXP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;This expansion puts Northeastern at the center of the two main hubs for theory in the U.S., the Bay State and the Bay Area.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;If you want to work on theory apply to join our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.ccs.neu.edu/theory/&quot;&gt;theory group.&lt;/a&gt;  I always have room for strong students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Manu&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Emanuele Viola</name>
      <uri>https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Finite model theory for pseudovarieties and universal algebra: preservation, definability and complexity</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02653"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02653</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Ham_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Lucy Ham&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Jackson_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Marcel Jackson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We explore new interactions between finite model theory and a number of
classical streams of universal algebra and semigroup theory. After refocussing
some finite model theoretic tools in universal algebraic context, we present a
number of results. A key result is an example of a finite algebra whose variety
is not finitely axiomatisable in first order logic, but which has first order
definable finite membership problem. This algebra witnesses the simultaneous
failure of the {\L}os-Tarski Theorem, the SP-preservation theorem and
Birkhoff&#39;s HSP-preservation theorem at the finite level as well as providing a
negative solution to the first order formulation of the long-standing Eilenberg
Sch\&quot;utzenberger problem. The example also shows that a pseudovariety without
any finite pseudo-identity basis may be finitely axiomatisable in first order
logic. Other results include the undecidability of deciding first order
definability of the pseudovariety of a finite algebra and a mapping from any
fixed template constraint satisfaction problem to a first order equivalent
variety membership problem, thereby providing examples of variety membership
problems complete in each of the classes $\texttt{L}$, $\texttt{NL}$,
$\texttt{Mod}_p(\texttt{L})$, $\texttt{P}$ (provided they are nonempty), and
infinitely many others (depending on complexity-theoretic assumptions).
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CC/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: On the Size of Chromatic Delaunay Mosaics</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03121"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03121</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Biswas_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ranita Biswas&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Montesano_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sebastiano Cultrera di Montesano&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Draganov_O/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ond&amp;#x159;ej Draganov&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Edelsbrunner_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Herbert Edelsbrunner&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Saghafian_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Morteza Saghafian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given a locally finite set $A \subseteq \mathbb{R}^d$ and a coloring $\chi
\colon A \to \{0,1,\ldots,s\}$, we introduce the chromatic Delaunay mosaic of
$\chi$, which is a Delaunay mosaic in $\mathbb{R}^{s+d}$ that represents how
points of different colors mingle. Our main results are bounds on the size of
the chromatic Delaunay mosaic, in which we assume that $d$ and $s$ are
constants. For example, if $A$ is finite with $n = \#{A}$, and the coloring is
random, then the chromatic Delaunay mosaic has $O(n^{\lceil{d/2}\rceil})$ cells
in expectation. In contrast, for Delone sets and Poisson point processes in
$\mathbb{R}^d$, the expected number of cells within a closed ball is only a
constant times the number of points in this ball. Furthermore, in
$\mathbb{R}^2$ all colorings of a dense set of $n$ points have chromatic
Delaunay mosaics of size $O(n)$. This encourages the use of chromatic Delaunay
mosaics in applications.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Persistent Homology of Chromatic Alpha Complexes</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03128"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03128</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Montesano_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sebastiano Cultrera di Montesano&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Draganov_O/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ond&amp;#x159;ej Draganov&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Edelsbrunner_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Herbert Edelsbrunner&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Saghafian_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Morteza Saghafian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Motivated by applications in medical sciences, we study finite chromatic sets
in Euclidean space from a topological perspective. Based on persistent homology
for images, kernels and cokernels, we design provably stable homological
quantifiers that describe the geometric micro- and macro-structure of how the
color classes mingle. These can be efficiently computed using chromatic
variants of Delaunay mosaics and Alpha complexes.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Computational Geometry</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.CG/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Improved Approximation Schemes for (Un-)Bounded Subset-Sum and Partition</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02883"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02883</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wu_X/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Xiaoyu Wu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chen_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Lin Chen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We consider the SUBSET SUM problem and its important variants in this paper.
In the SUBSET SUM problem, a (multi-)set $X$ of $n$ positive numbers and a
target number $t$ are given, and the task is to find a subset of $X$ with the
maximal sum that does not exceed $t$. It is well known that this problem is
NP-hard and admits fully polynomial-time approximation schemes (FPTASs). In
recent years, it has been shown that there does not exist an FPTAS of running
time $\tilde\OO( 1/\epsilon^{2-\delta})$ for arbitrary small $\delta&amp;gt;0$
assuming ($\min$,+)-convolution conjecture~\cite{bringmann2021fine}. However,
the lower bound can be bypassed if we relax the constraint such that the task
is to find a subset of $X$ that can slightly exceed the threshold $t$ by
$\epsilon$ times, and the sum of numbers within the subset is at least
$1-\tilde\OO(\epsilon)$ times the optimal objective value that respects the
constraint. Approximation schemes that may violate the constraint are also
known as weak approximation schemes. For the SUBSET SUM problem, there is a
randomized weak approximation scheme running in time $\tilde\OO(n+
1/\epsilon^{5/3})$ [Mucha et al.&#39;19]. For the special case where the target $t$
is half of the summation of all input numbers, weak approximation schemes are
equivalent to approximation schemes that do not violate the constraint, and the
best-known algorithm runs in $\tilde\OO(n+1/\epsilon^{{3}/{2}})$ time
[Bringmann and Nakos&#39;21].
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: A Strongly Polynomial Algorithm for Approximate Forster Transforms and its Application to Halfspace Learning</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03008"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03008</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Diakonikolas_I/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ilias Diakonikolas&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Tzamos_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Christos Tzamos&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kane_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Daniel M. Kane&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Forster transform is a method of regularizing a dataset by placing it in
{\em radial isotropic position} while maintaining some of its essential
properties. Forster transforms have played a key role in a diverse range of
settings spanning computer science and functional analysis. Prior work had
given {\em weakly} polynomial time algorithms for computing Forster transforms,
when they exist. Our main result is the first {\em strongly polynomial time}
algorithm to compute an approximate Forster transform of a given dataset or
certify that no such transformation exists. By leveraging our strongly
polynomial Forster algorithm, we obtain the first strongly polynomial time
algorithm for {\em distribution-free} PAC learning of halfspaces. This learning
result is surprising because {\em proper} PAC learning of halfspaces is {\em
equivalent} to linear programming. Our learning approach extends to give a
strongly polynomial halfspace learner in the presence of random classification
noise and, more generally, Massart noise.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Inapproximability of counting independent sets in linear hypergraphs</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03072"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03072</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Qiu_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Guoliang Qiu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wang_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jiaheng Wang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is shown in this note that approximating the number of independent sets in
a $k$-uniform linear hypergraph with maximum degree at most $\Delta$ is NP-hard
if $\Delta\geq 5\cdot 2^{k-1}+1$. This confirms that for the relevant sampling
and approximate counting problems, the regimes on the maximum degree where the
state-of-the-art algorithms work are tight, up to some small factors. These
algorithms include: the approximate sampler and randomised approximation scheme
by Hermon, Sly and Zhang (2019), the perfect sampler by Qiu, Wang and Zhang
(2022), and the deterministic approximation scheme by Feng, Guo, Wang, Wang and
Yin (2022).
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Higher Lower Bounds for Sparse Oblivious Subspace Embeddings</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02913"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02913</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Li_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yi Li&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Liu_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mingmou Liu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An oblivious subspace embedding (OSE), characterized by parameters
$m,n,d,\epsilon,\delta$, is a random matrix $\Pi\in \mathbb{R}^{m\times n}$
such that for any $d$-dimensional subspace $T\subseteq \mathbb{R}^n$,
$\Pr_\Pi[\forall x\in T, (1-\epsilon)\|x\|_2 \leq \|\Pi x\|_2\leq
(1+\epsilon)\|x\|_2] \geq 1-\delta$. When an OSE has $1/(9\epsilon)$ nonzero
entries in each column, we show it must hold that $m =
\Omega(d^2/\epsilon^{1-O(\delta)})$, which is the first lower bound with
multiplicative factors of $d^2$ and $1/\epsilon$, improving on the previous
$\Omega(\epsilon^{O(\delta)}d^2)$ lower bound due to Li and Liu (PODS 2022).
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Improved Algebraic Degeneracy Testing</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03030"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03030</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Cardinal_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jean Cardinal&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sharir_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Micha Sharir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the classical linear degeneracy testing problem, we are given $n$ real
numbers and a $k$-variate linear polynomial $F$, for some constant $k$, and
have to determine whether there exist $k$ numbers $a_1,\ldots,a_k$ from the set
such that $F(a_1,\ldots,a_k) = 0$. We consider a generalization of this problem
in which $F$ is an arbitrary constant-degree polynomial, we are given $k$ sets
of $n$ numbers, and have to determine whether there exist a $k$-tuple of
numbers, one in each set, on which $F$ vanishes. We give the first improvement
over the na\&quot;ive $O^*(n^{k-1})$ algorithm for this problem (where the
$O^*(\cdot)$ notation omits subpolynomial factors).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We show that the problem can be solved in time $O^*\left( n^{k - 2 + \frac
4{k+2}}\right)$ for even $k$ and in time $O^*\left( n^{k - 2 +
\frac{4k-8}{k^2-5}}\right)$ for odd $k$ in the real RAM model of computation.
We also prove that for $k=4$, the problem can be solved in time
$O^*(n^{2.625})$ in the algebraic decision tree model, and for $k=5$ it can be
solved in time $O^*(n^{3.56})$ in the same model, both improving on the above
uniform bounds.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All our results rely on an algebraic generalization of the standard
meet-in-the-middle algorithm for $k$-SUM, powered by recent algorithmic
advances in the polynomial method for semi-algebraic range searching. In fact,
our main technical result is much more broadly applicable, as it provides a
general tool for detecting incidences and other interactions between points and
algebraic surfaces in any dimension. In particular, it yields an efficient
algorithm for a general, algebraic version of Hopcroft&#39;s point-line incidence
detection problem in any dimension.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Robustness of Quantum Algorithms for Nonconvex Optimization</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02548"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02548</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Gong_W/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Weiyuan Gong&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Zhang_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Chenyi Zhang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Li_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tongyang Li&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recent results suggest that quantum computers possess the potential to speed
up nonconvex optimization problems. However, a crucial factor for the
implementation of quantum optimization algorithms is their robustness against
experimental and statistical noises. In this paper, we systematically study
quantum algorithms for finding an $\epsilon$-approximate second-order
stationary point ($\epsilon$-SOSP) of a $d$-dimensional nonconvex function, a
fundamental problem in nonconvex optimization, with noisy zeroth- or
first-order oracles as inputs. We first prove that, up to noise of
$O(\epsilon^{10}/d^5)$, accelerated perturbed gradient descent with quantum
gradient estimation takes $O(\log d/\epsilon^{1.75})$ quantum queries to find
an $\epsilon$-SOSP. We then prove that perturbed gradient descent is robust to
the noise of $O(\epsilon^6/d^4)$ and $O(\epsilon/d^{0.5+\zeta})$ for $\zeta&amp;gt;0$
on the zeroth- and first-order oracles, respectively, which provides a quantum
algorithm with poly-logarithmic query complexity. We then propose a stochastic
gradient descent algorithm using quantum mean estimation on the Gaussian
smoothing of noisy oracles, which is robust to $O(\epsilon^{1.5}/d)$ and
$O(\epsilon/\sqrt{d})$ noise on the zeroth- and first-order oracles,
respectively. The quantum algorithm takes $O(d^{2.5}/\epsilon^{3.5})$ and
$O(d^2/\epsilon^3)$ queries to the two oracles, giving a polynomial speedup
over the classical counterparts. Moreover, we characterize the domains where
quantum algorithms can find an $\epsilon$-SOSP with poly-logarithmic,
polynomial, or exponential number of queries in $d$, or the problem is
information-theoretically unsolvable even by an infinite number of queries. In
addition, we prove an $\Omega(\epsilon^{-12/7})$ lower bound in $\epsilon$ for
any randomized classical and quantum algorithm to find an $\epsilon$-SOSP using
either noisy zeroth- or first-order oracles.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Collabs: Composable Collaborative Data Structures</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02618"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02618</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Weidner_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Matthew Weidner&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Miller_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Heather Miller&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Qi_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Huairui Qi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kjaer_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Maxime Kjaer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Pradeep_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ria Pradeep&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Geordie_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Benito Geordie&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Meiklejohn_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Christopher Meiklejohn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Replicated data types (RDTs), such as Conflict-free Replicated Data Types
(CRDTs), provide an abstraction for reasoning about replication and consistency
in distributed systems. To make them as useful as ordinary, local data
structures, RDTs need to be both modular and composable, so that programmers
can create new app-specific RDTs by composing existing ones. However, no
existing RDT libraries combine these properties; either they use monolithic
architectures that rule out new RDTs or they do not support composition
techniques.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this work, we introduce the Collab (collaborative data structure), a novel
abstraction for modular and composable RDTs. We also describe the collabs
library, an open-source TypeScript library that we built around this
abstraction. Our library supports arbitrary programmer-added RDTs and includes
composition techniques that make them easier to implement. This allows
programmers to work at a higher level of abstraction: custom RDTs for arbitrary
concepts in their application, instead of just a fixed menu of generic RDTs. It
also allows programmers to extend the library with new RDT algorithms as they
are published, instead of waiting for the library to implement them. Our
library includes a collection of built-in op-based CRDT implementations,
including several that were not previously implemented. To demonstrate the
library, we built numerous apps on top of it, including decentralized
collaborative apps that can be deployed from a static web page. Benchmarks show
that its CRDTs have performance comparable to state-of-the-art CRDT libraries
for web apps, and that unlike existing libraries, it can support 100
simultaneous users with low latency in a geo-distributed collaborative app.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Stars: Tera-Scale Graph Building for Clustering and Graph Learning</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02635"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02635</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Carey_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;CJ Carey&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Halcrow_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jonathan Halcrow&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Jayaram_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Rajesh Jayaram&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mirrokni_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vahab Mirrokni&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Schudy_W/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Warren Schudy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zhong_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Peilin Zhong&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A fundamental procedure in the analysis of massive datasets is the
construction of similarity graphs. Such graphs play a key role for many
downstream tasks, including clustering, classification, graph learning, and
nearest neighbor search. For these tasks, it is critical to build graphs which
are sparse yet still representative of the underlying data. The benefits of
sparsity are twofold: firstly, constructing dense graphs is infeasible in
practice for large datasets, and secondly, the runtime of downstream tasks is
directly influenced by the sparsity of the similarity graph. In this work, we
present $\textit{Stars}$: a highly scalable method for building extremely
sparse graphs via two-hop spanners, which are graphs where similar points are
connected by a path of length at most two. Stars can construct two-hop spanners
with significantly fewer similarity comparisons, which are a major bottleneck
for learning based models where comparisons are expensive to evaluate.
Theoretically, we demonstrate that Stars builds a graph in nearly-linear time,
where approximate nearest neighbors are contained within two-hop neighborhoods.
In practice, we have deployed Stars for multiple data sets allowing for graph
building at the $\textit{Tera-Scale}$, i.e., for graphs with tens of trillions
of edges. We evaluate the performance of Stars for clustering and graph
learning, and demonstrate 10~1000-fold improvements in pairwise similarity
comparisons compared to different baselines, and 2~10-fold improvement in
running time without quality loss.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Low Power Mesh Algorithms for Image Problems</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02640"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02640</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Stout_Q/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Quentin Stout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analyze a physically motivated fine-grained mesh-connected computer model,
assuming that a word of information takes a fixed area and that it takes unit
time and unit energy to move a word unit distance. This is a representation of
computing on a chip with myriad tiny processors arranged as a mesh. While most
mesh algorithms assume all processors are active at all times, we give
algorithms that have only a few processors on at any one time, which reduces
the power required. We apply this approach to basic problems involving images,
showing that there can be dramatic reductions in the peak power with only
small, if any, changes in the time required. We also show that these algorithms
give a more efficient way to utilize power when more power is available.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Online Min-Max Paging</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03016"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03016</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chiplunkar_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ashish Chiplunkar&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Henzinger_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Monika Henzinger&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kale_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sagar Sudhir Kale&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Votsch_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Maximilian V&amp;#xf6;tsch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Motivated by fairness requirements in communication networks, we introduce a
natural variant of the online paging problem, called \textit{min-max} paging,
where the objective is to minimize the maximum number of faults on any page.
While the classical paging problem, whose objective is to minimize the total
number of faults, admits $k$-competitive deterministic and $O(\log
k)$-competitive randomized algorithms, we show that min-max paging does not
admit a $c(k)$-competitive algorithm for any function $c$. Specifically, we
prove that the randomized competitive ratio of min-max paging is
$\Omega(\log(n))$ and its deterministic competitive ratio is
$\Omega(k\log(n)/\log(k))$, where $n$ is the total number of pages ever
requested.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We design a fractional algorithm for paging with a more general objective --
minimize the value of an $n$-variate differentiable convex function applied to
the vector of the number of faults on each page. This gives an
$O(\log(n)\log(k))$-competitive fractional algorithm for min-max paging. We
show how to round such a fractional algorithm with at most a $k$ factor loss in
the competitive ratio, resulting in a deterministic
$O(k\log(n)\log(k))$-competitive algorithm for min-max paging. This matches our
lower bound modulo a $\mathrm{poly}(\log(k))$ factor. We also give a randomized
rounding algorithm that results in a $O(\log^2 n \log k)$-competitive
algorithm.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Pareto Optimal Compression of Genomic Dictionaries, with or without Random Access in Main Memory</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03067"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03067</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Giancarlo_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Raffaele Giancarlo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Grimaudo_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Gennaro Grimaudo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Motivation: A Genomic Dictionary, i.e., the set of the k-mers appearing in a
genome, is a fundamental source of genomic information: its collection is the
first step in strategic computational methods ranging from assembly to sequence
comparison and phylogeny. Unfortunately, it is costly to store. This motivates
some recent studies regarding the compression of those k-mer sets. However,
such an area does not have the maturity of genomic compression, lacking an
homogeneous and methodologically sound experimental foundation that allows to
fairly compare the relative merits of the available solutions, and that takes
into account also the rich choices of compression methods that can be used.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: We provide such a foundation here, supporting it with an extensive
set of experiments that use reference datasets and a carefully selected set of
representative data compressors. Our results highlight the spectrum of
compressor choices one has in terms of Pareto Optimality of compression vs.
post-processing, this latter being important when the Dictionary needs to be
decompressed many times. In addition to the useful indications, not available
elsewhere, that this study offers to the researchers interested in storing
k-mer dictionaries in compressed form, a software system that can be readily
used to explore the Pareto Optimal solutions available r a given Dictionary is
also provided.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Availability: The software system is available at
https://github.com/GenGrim76/Pareto-Optimal-GDC, together with user manuals and
installation instructions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contact: raffaele.giancarlo@unipa.it
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary information: Additional data are available in the Supplementary
Material.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Extending Snow&#39;s algorithm for computations in the finite Weyl groups</title>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03156"/>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03156</id>
    <updated>2022-12-07T01:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Stekolshchik_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Rafael Stekolshchik&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1990, D.Snow proposed an effective algorithm for computing the orbits of
finite Weyl groups. Snow&#39;s algorithm is designed for computation of weights,
$W$-orbits and elements of the Weyl group. An extension of Snow&#39;s algorithm is
proposed, which allows to find pairs of mutually inverse elements together with
the calculation of $W$-orbits in the same runtime cycle. This simplifies the
calculation of conjugacy classes in the Weyl group. As an example, the complete
list of elements of the Weyl group $W(D_4)$ obtained using the extended Snow&#39;s
algorithm is given. The elements of $W(D_4)$ are specified in two ways: as
reduced expressions and as matrices of the faithful representation. We present
a partition of this group into conjugacy classes with elements specified as
reduced expressions. Various forms are given for representatives of the
conjugacy classes of $W(D_4)$: using Carter diagrams, using reduced expressions
and using signed cycle-types. In the appendix, we provide an implementation of
the algorithm in Python.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</name>
      <uri>https://arxiv.org/list/cs.DS/recent</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR22-177 |  Quantum Worst-Case to Average-Case Reductions for All Linear Problems | 

	Vahid Reza Asadi, 

	Alexander Golovnev, 

	Tom Gur, 

	Igor Shinkar, 

	Sathyawageeswar Subramanian</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/177"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/177</id>
    <updated>2022-12-06T22:35:48+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    We study the problem of designing worst-case to average-case reductions for quantum algorithms. For all linear problems, we provide an explicit and efficient transformation of quantum algorithms that are only correct on a small (even sub-constant) fraction of their inputs into ones that are correct on all inputs. This stands in contrast to the classical setting, where such results are only known for a small number of specific problems or restricted computational models. En route, we obtain a tight $\Omega(n^2)$ lower bound on the average-case quantum query complexity of the Matrix-Vector Multiplication problem. 

Our techniques strengthen and generalise the recently introduced additive combinatorics framework for classical worst-case to average-case reductions (STOC 2022) to the quantum setting. We rely on quantum singular value transformations to construct quantum algorithms for linear verification in superposition and learning Bogolyubov subspaces from noisy quantum oracles. We use these tools to prove a quantum local correction lemma, which lies at the heart of our reductions, based on a noise-robust probabilistic generalisation of Bogolyubov&amp;#39;s lemma from additive combinatorics.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Theory Dish: Stanford Blog: 2023 Motwani Postdoc Announced</title>
    <link href="https://theorydish.blog/2022/12/05/2023-motwani-postdoc-announced/"/>
    <id>http://theorydish.blog/?p=2859</id>
    <updated>2022-12-06T02:29:30+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;The theory group at Stanford invites applications for the Motwani postdoctoral fellowship in theoretical computer science. Information and application instructions below. Applications will be accepted until the positions are filled, but review of applicants will begin after Dec 15.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Website:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/23929&quot;&gt;https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/23929&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;Email: theory.stanford@gmail.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Omer Reingold&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Theory Dish: Stanford Blog</name>
      <uri>https://theorydish.blog</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">CCI: jobs: Postdoc at George Mason University (apply by December 31, 2022)</title>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/12/05/postdoc-at-george-mason-university-apply-by-december-31-2022/"/>
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/12/05/postdoc-at-george-mason-university-apply-by-december-31-2022/</id>
    <updated>2022-12-05T21:30:49+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;Postdoc in theoretical foundations of Algorithms and AI at George Mason University. Starting Fall’23 and hosted by Grigory Yaroslavtsev (&lt;a href=&quot;http://grigory.ai&quot;&gt;http://grigory.ai&lt;/a&gt;). GMU is located in the Washington, DC metro area, is the largest public university in Virginia and has one of the fastest growing CS departments in the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To apply email CV and research statement. Reference letters will be requested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://grigory.ai&quot;&gt;http://grigory.ai&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: grigory@grigory.us&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>CCI: jobs</name>
      <uri>https://cstheory-jobs.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Computational Complexity: The Future of Education is Personal</title>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/12/the-future-of-education-is-personal.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-2041922047028548572</id>
    <updated>2022-12-05T13:53:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgbsNuEriIphlZE_oc0Xj44gFxfBp1LCCnFM4ps7FL2KtdUjta77CAddfqgxJQa24OCZ2mv2gqaxRisUhVgvhSj4QIl9Cov-phWAb2wwyIy-rJmHdcsIPcv-60JGncHmMJAIbgi8KwGHExESHI_12_H5TGV2woNv6dn38DtzD2vRo9wXF635Q/s1024/DALL%C2%B7E%202022-12-03%2014.23.49%20-%20An%20oil%20painting%20of%20a%20Darth%20Vader%20tutoring%20a%20human%20student.png&quot; style=&quot;clear: right; float: right; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; data-original-height=&quot;1024&quot; data-original-width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;320&quot; src=&quot;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgbsNuEriIphlZE_oc0Xj44gFxfBp1LCCnFM4ps7FL2KtdUjta77CAddfqgxJQa24OCZ2mv2gqaxRisUhVgvhSj4QIl9Cov-phWAb2wwyIy-rJmHdcsIPcv-60JGncHmMJAIbgi8KwGHExESHI_12_H5TGV2woNv6dn38DtzD2vRo9wXF635Q/s320/DALL%C2%B7E%202022-12-03%2014.23.49%20-%20An%20oil%20painting%20of%20a%20Darth%20Vader%20tutoring%20a%20human%20student.png&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With all the excitement about &lt;a href=&quot;https://chat.openai.com/&quot;&gt;ChatGPT&lt;/a&gt;, how will machine learning disrupt education, say five to ten years down the road?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My guess: individualized tutors. Imagine a tutor working with you teaching you important concepts, walking you through examples, answering your questions, going at your own pace, like the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.new.ox.ac.uk/tutorial-system&quot;&gt;Oxford system&lt;/a&gt;. The Oxford tutor system doesn&#39;t scale well, or at least it wouldn&#39;t if we have human tutors. But we can scale using machine learning and we&#39;re not far away from being able to do so. Such tutors will be infinitely patient, have full knowledge of all written material, speak in any language with any voice and personality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can &quot;meet&quot; with your tutor in many different ways, from a deep fake video chat or with augmented or virtual reality to have a tutor in the room with you, or perhaps a physical robot, neural implant or something we haven&#39;t even though of yet. In poorer countries you can get tutored with something as simple as text messages on a cell phone.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A tutor can take on any form. You could get tutored by fictional characters such as Yoda, Darth Vader or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Magic_School_Bus_(TV_series)&quot;&gt;Miss Frizzle&lt;/a&gt;. ML can capture the personality of real people--imaging a course about Kurt Vonnegut taught by the author, government from Henry Kissinger or a course in quantum computing from your own personal Scott Aaronson. But most importantly you can have a tutor who looks and sounds like you, with your own language, gender, race and ethnicity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Somehow we&#39;ll have to find ways to include the social aspects such as working in groups, socializing, playing sports and living together. But that one-one-one teaching experience that most of us cannot afford&amp;nbsp; today will be cheaply available tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And what will this all mean for teachers, professors and universities? A good question for future blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Lance Fortnow&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Turing&#39;s Invisible Hand: 2023 SIGecom Test of Time Award — Call for Nominations</title>
    <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/2022/12/05/2023-sigecom-test-of-time-award-call-for-nominations/"/>
    <id>http://agtb.wordpress.com/?p=3548</id>
    <updated>2022-12-05T09:16:02+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;The SIGecom Test of Time Award recognizes the author or authors of an influential paper or series of papers published between ten and twenty-five years ago that has significantly impacted research or applications exemplifying the interplay of economics and computation.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The 2023 SIGecom Test of Time Award will be given for papers published no earlier than 1998 and no later than 2013. Nominations are due by&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;February 28th, 2023&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;(Anywhere on Earth), and must be made&amp;nbsp;together with the endorsement letters by submission using&amp;nbsp;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdm6Hk4uYDi45rvQxHj0dQasjyNMD3XBbS72SK7MPnypWTMmQ/viewform&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;this form&lt;/a&gt;. Any member of SIGecom may submit a nomination. Self-nomination is not allowed.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;More details regarding the nomination procedure can be found&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sigecom.org/award-tot-details.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; The list of winners from previous years can be found&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sigecom.org/award-tot.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;has-text-align-left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 2023 Test of Time Award Committee&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alvin Roth&lt;/strong&gt;, Stanford University&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moshe Tennenholtz&lt;/strong&gt;, The Technion&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Noam Nisan (chair)&lt;/strong&gt;, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Noam Nisan&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Turing's Invisible Hand</name>
      <uri>https://agtb.wordpress.com</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">CCI: jobs: Motwani Postdoctoral Fellowship at Stanford Computer Science (apply by December 15, 2022)</title>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/12/05/motwani-postdoctoral-fellowship-at-stanford-computer-science-apply-by-december-15-2022/"/>
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/12/05/motwani-postdoctoral-fellowship-at-stanford-computer-science-apply-by-december-15-2022/</id>
    <updated>2022-12-05T08:32:41+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;The theory group at Stanford invites applications for the Motwani postdoctoral fellowship in theoretical computer science. Information and application instructions below. Applications will be accepted until the positions are filled, but review of applicants will begin after Dec 15.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/23929&quot;&gt;https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/23929&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: theory.stanford@gmail.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>CCI: jobs</name>
      <uri>https://cstheory-jobs.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR22-176 |  The power of the Binary Value Principle | 

	Yaroslav Alekseev, 

	Edward Hirsch</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/176"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/176</id>
    <updated>2022-12-04T04:21:35+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    The (extended) Binary Value Principle (eBVP, the equation $\sum x_i 2^{i-1} = -k$ for $k &amp;gt; 0$
and in the presence of $x_i^2=x_i$) has received a lot of attention recently, several lower
bounds have been proved for it [Alekseev et al 20, Alekseev 21, Part and Tzameret 21]. 
Also it has been shown [Alekseev et al 20] that the 
probabilistically verifiable Ideal Proof System (IPS) [Grochow and Pitassi 18] together with eBVP
polynomially simulates a similar semialgebraic proof system. In this paper we consider
Polynomial Calculus with the algebraic version of Tseitin’s extension rule (Ext-PC). Contrary
to IPS, this is a Cook--Reckhow proof system. We show that in this context eBVP still allows
to simulate similar semialgebraic systems. We also prove that it allows to simulate the
Square Root Rule [Grigoriev and Hirsch 03], which is in sharp contrast with the result of [Alekseev 21] that shows
an exponential lower bound on the size of Ext-PC derivations of the Binary Value Principle
from its square. On the other hand, we demonstrate that eBVP probably does not help in
proving exponential lower bounds for Boolean formulas: we show that an Ext-PC (even with
the Square Root Rule) derivation of any unsatisfiable Boolean formula in CNF from eBVP
must be of exponential size.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR22-175 |  Derandomization Under Different Resource Constraints | 

	Samuel Epstein</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/175"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/175</id>
    <updated>2022-12-04T04:19:03+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    We provide another proof to the EL Theorem. We show the tradeoff between compressibility of codebooks and their communication capacity. A resource bounded version of the EL Theorem is proven. This is used to prove three instances of resource bounded derandomization.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR22-174 |  Noisy Radio Network Lower Bounds Via Noiseless Beeping Lower Bounds | 

	Raghuvansh Saxena, 

	Gillat Kol, 

	Klim Efremenko, 

	Dmitry Paramonov</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/174"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/174</id>
    <updated>2022-12-04T04:13:34+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    Much of today&amp;#39;s communication is carried out over large wireless systems with different input-output behaviors. In this work, we compare the power of central abstractions of wireless communication through the general notion of boolean symmetric $f$-channels: In every round of the $f$-channel, each of its $n$ parties decides to either broadcast or not, and the channel outputs $f(m)$, where $m$ is the number of broadcasting parties.

Our first result is that the well studied beeping channel, where $f$ is the threshold-$1$ function, is not stronger than any other $f$-channel. To this end, we design a protocol over the $f$-channel and prove that any protocol that simulates it over the beeping channel blows up the round complexity by a factor of $\Omega(\log n)$. Our lower bound technique may be of independent interest, as it essentially generalizes the popular fooling set technique by exploiting a &amp;quot;local&amp;quot; relaxation of combinatorial rectangles.

Curiously, while this result shows the limitations of a noiseless channel, namely, the beeping channel, we are able to use it to show the limitations of the noisy version of many other channels. This includes the extensively studied single-hop radio network model with collisions-as-silence (CAS), which is equivalent to the $f$-channel with $f(m)=1$ iff $m=1$.

In particular, our second and main result, obtained from the first, shows that converting CAS protocols to noise resilient ones may incur a large performance overhead, i.e., no constant rate interactive code exists. To this end, we design a CAS protocol and prove that any protocol that simulates it over the noisy CAS model with correlated stochastic noise, blows up the round complexity by a factor of $\Omega(\log n)$. We mention that the $\Omega(\log n)$ overhead in both our results is tight.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">TOC for Fairness: Our 2023 Postdoc Program is up</title>
    <link href="https://toc4fairness.org/our-2023-postdoc-program-is-up/"/>
    <id>https://toc4fairness.org/?p=2387</id>
    <updated>2022-12-03T19:20:43+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://toc4fairness.org/&quot; data-type=&quot;URL&quot; data-id=&quot;https://toc4fairness.org/&quot;&gt;Simons collaboration on the theory of algorithmic fairness&lt;/a&gt; is excited to announce &lt;a href=&quot;https://toc4fairness.org/postdoc-opportunities/&quot; data-type=&quot;URL&quot; data-id=&quot;https://toc4fairness.org/postdoc-opportunities/&quot;&gt;our new postdoc program&lt;/a&gt;. We are seeking strong candidates from a diverse set of academic backgrounds and personal experiences who want to work with one or more of the PIs on algorithmic fairness and responsible computing more broadly. We expect to be extending multiple offers.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Omer Reingold&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>TOC for Fairness</name>
      <uri>https://toc4fairness.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">CCI: jobs: Postdoc in combinatorial optimization at University of Copenhagen (apply by January 15, 2023)</title>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/12/03/postdoc-in-combinatorial-optimization-at-university-of-copenhagen-apply-by-january-15-2023/"/>
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/12/03/postdoc-in-combinatorial-optimization-at-university-of-copenhagen-apply-by-january-15-2023/</id>
    <updated>2022-12-03T11:49:30+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;The CS department at the University of Copenhagen invites applications for postdoc positions in combinatorial optimization. The application deadline is January 15. See &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jakobnordstrom.se/openings/Postdoc-UCPH-230115.html&quot;&gt;http://www.jakobnordstrom.se/openings/Postdoc-UCPH-230115.html&lt;/a&gt; for the full announcement with more information and instructions for how to apply. Informal enquiries are welcome and may be sent to jn@di.ku.dk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jakobnordstrom.se/openings/Postdoc-UCPH-230115.html&quot;&gt;http://www.jakobnordstrom.se/openings/Postdoc-UCPH-230115.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: jn@di.ku.dk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>CCI: jobs</name>
      <uri>https://cstheory-jobs.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">TCS+ Seminar Series: TCS+ “Test of Time” talk: Wednesday, December 7 — Ronitt Rubinfeld, MIT and Tel Aviv University</title>
    <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2022/12/03/tcs-test-of-time-talk-wednesday-december-7-ronitt-rubinfeld-mit-and-tel-aviv-university/"/>
    <id>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=658</id>
    <updated>2022-12-03T05:33:48+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, December 7th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 18:00 UTC). &lt;a href=&quot;https://people.csail.mit.edu/ronitt/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ronitt Rubinfeld&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from MIT and Tel Aviv University will give our very first &amp;#8220;Test of Time&amp;#8221; talk, titled &amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;A Comedy of Errors&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8221; (abstract below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to join us live by signing up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/next-tcs-talk&quot;&gt;the online form&lt;/a&gt;. Registration is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; required to attend the interactive talk, and the link will be posted on the website the day prior to the talk; however, by registering in the form, you will receive a reminder, along with the link. (The recorded talk will also be posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/past-talks&quot;&gt;on our website&lt;/a&gt; afterwards) As usual, for more information about the TCS+ online seminar series and the upcoming talks, or to &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/suggest-a-talk&quot;&gt;suggest&lt;/a&gt; a possible topic or speaker, please see &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/&quot;&gt;the website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract: In the late 1980s, a new model of &amp;#8220;Program Checking&amp;#8221; was put forth by Blum and Kannan in order to prevail over errors in programs. With that as a starting point, several lines of research developed &amp;#8212; including one that eventually morphed into the area of sublinear time algorithms. Along the way, errors were made and others were detected. We will recount a personal view of the arbitrary nature of this process and place it in historical context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The talk will be followed by an unrecorded &amp;#8220;Ask Me Anything&amp;#8221; (AMA) session.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By plustcs&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>TCS+ Seminar Series</name>
      <uri>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">CCI: jobs: Simons-Berkeley Research Fellowships at Simons Institute (apply by December 15, 2022)</title>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/12/03/simons-berkeley-research-fellowships-at-simons-institute-apply-by-december-15-2022/"/>
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/12/03/simons-berkeley-research-fellowships-at-simons-institute-apply-by-december-15-2022/</id>
    <updated>2022-12-03T02:40:31+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;[Deadline Reminder] The Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing invites applications for Simons-Berkeley Research Fellowships for the Summer 2023, Fall 2023, and Spring 2024 semesters. The deadline for receipt of applications is December 15, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://simons.berkeley.edu/simons-berkeley-research-fellowship-call-applications&quot;&gt;https://simons.berkeley.edu/simons-berkeley-research-fellowship-call-applications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: simonsvisitorservices@berkeley.edu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>CCI: jobs</name>
      <uri>https://cstheory-jobs.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Scott Aaronson: Google&amp;#8217;s Sycamore chip: no wormholes, no superfast classical simulation either</title>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6871"/>
    <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6871</id>
    <updated>2022-12-02T23:04:15+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;div class=&quot;wp-block-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;aligncenter size-large&quot;&gt;&lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://www.scottaaronson.com/sycamore.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;mark style=&quot;background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0)&quot; class=&quot;has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color&quot;&gt;Update (Dec. 6):&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;#8217;m having a blast at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ias.edu/sns/scientific-program-qubit-2022&quot;&gt;Workshop on Spacetime and Quantum Information&lt;/a&gt; at the Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton.  I&amp;#8217;m learning a huge amount from the talks and discussions here&amp;#8212;and also simply enjoying being back in Princeton, to see old friends and visit old haunts like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://palmersquare.com/directory/the-bent-spoon/&quot;&gt;Bent Spoon&lt;/a&gt;.  Tomorrow I&amp;#8217;ll speak about my &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.15601&quot;&gt;recent work with Jason Pollack&lt;/a&gt; on polynomial-time AdS bulk reconstruction.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;But there&amp;#8217;s one thing, relevant to this post, that I can&amp;#8217;t let pass without comment.  Tonight, David Nirenberg, Director of the IAS and a medieval historian, gave an after-dinner speech to our workshop, centered around how auspicious it was that the workshop was being held a mere week after the momentous announcement of &lt;em&gt;a holographic wormhole on a microchip (!!)&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8212;a feat that experts were calling the first-ever laboratory investigation of quantum gravity, and a new frontier for experimental physics itself.  Nirenberg asked whether, a century from now, people might look back on the wormhole achievement as today we look back on Eddington&amp;#8217;s 1919 eclipse observations providing the evidence for general relativity.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I confess: this was the first time I felt visceral anger, rather than mere bemusement, over this wormhole affair.  Before, I had implicitly assumed: no one was &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; hoodwinked by this.  No one &lt;em&gt;really, literally&lt;/em&gt; believed that this little 9-qubit simulation opened up a wormhole, or helped prove the holographic nature of the real universe, or anything like that.  I was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;To be clear, I don&amp;#8217;t blame Professor Nirenberg at all.  If &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; were a medieval historian, everything he said about the experiment&amp;#8217;s historic significance might strike me as perfectly valid inferences from what I&amp;#8217;d read in the press.  I don&amp;#8217;t blame the It from Qubit community&amp;#8212;most of which, I can report, was grinding its teeth and turning red in the face right alongside me.  I don&amp;#8217;t even blame most of the authors of the wormhole paper, such as Daniel Jafferis, who gave a perfectly sober, reasonable, technical talk at the workshop about how he and others managed to compress a simulation of a variant of the SYK model into a mere 9 qubits&amp;#8212;a talk that eschewed all claims of historic significance and of literal wormhole creation.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;#8217;s now clear to me that, between&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;(1) the It from Qubit community that likes to explore speculative ideas like holographic wormholes, and&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;(2) the lay news readers who are now under the impression that Google just did one of the greatest physics experiments of all time,&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; went terribly wrong&amp;#8212;something that risks damaging trust in the scientific process itself.  And I think it&amp;#8217;s worth reflecting on what we can do to prevent it from happening again.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;hr class=&quot;wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity&quot;/&gt;



&lt;p&gt;This is going to be one of the many &lt;em&gt;Shtetl-Optimized&lt;/em&gt; posts that I didn&amp;#8217;t feel like writing, but was given no choice but to write.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;News, social media, and my inbox have been abuzz with two claims about Google&amp;#8217;s Sycamore quantum processor, the one that now has 72 superconducting qubits.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The first claim is that Sycamore created a wormhole (!)&amp;#8212;a historic feat possible only with a quantum computer.  See for example the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2022/11/30/science/physics-wormhole-quantum-computer.html&quot;&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantamagazine.org/physicists-create-a-wormhole-using-a-quantum-computer-20221130/&quot;&gt;Quanta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arstechnica.com/science/2022/12/no-physicists-didnt-make-a-real-wormhole-what-they-did-was-still-pretty-cool/&quot;&gt;Ars Technica&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-03832-z&quot;&gt;Nature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (and of course, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-022-05424-3&quot;&gt;actual paper&lt;/a&gt;), as well as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/?p=13181&quot;&gt;Peter Woit&amp;#8217;s blog&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://chadorzel.substack.com/p/wormhole-to-2006&quot;&gt;Chad Orzel&amp;#8217;s blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The second claim is that Sycamore&amp;#8217;s pretensions to quantum supremacy have been refuted.  The latter claim is based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.03999&quot;&gt;this recent preprint&lt;/a&gt; by Dorit Aharonov, Xun Gao, Zeph Landau, Yunchao Liu, and Umesh Vazirani.  No one&amp;#8212;least of all me!&amp;#8212;doubts that these authors have proved a strong new technical result, solving a significant open problem in the theory of noisy random circuit sampling.  On the other hand, it might be less obvious how to interpret their result and put it in context.  See also a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zDnA1gu4QO0&quot;&gt;YouTube video&lt;/a&gt; of Yunchao speaking about the new result at this week&amp;#8217;s Simons Institute Quantum Colloquium, and of a panel discussion afterwards, where Yunchao, Umesh Vazirani, Adam Bouland, Sergio Boixo, and your humble blogger discuss what it means.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;On their face, the two claims about Sycamore might seem to be in tension.  After all, if Sycamore can&amp;#8217;t do anything beyond what a classical computer can do, then how exactly did it &lt;em&gt;bend the topology of spacetime&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I submit that neither claim is true.  On the one hand, Sycamore did not &amp;#8220;create a wormhole.&amp;#8221;  On the other hand, it remains pretty hard to simulate with a classical computer, as far as anyone knows.  To summarize, then, our knowledge of what Sycamore can and can&amp;#8217;t do remains much the same as last week or last month!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;hr class=&quot;wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity&quot;/&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s start with the wormhole thing.  I can&amp;#8217;t really improve over how I put it in Dennis Overbye&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;NYT&lt;/em&gt; piece:&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The most important thing I’d want New York Times readers to understand is this,” Scott Aaronson, a quantum computing expert at the University of Texas in Austin, wrote in an email. “If this experiment has brought a wormhole into actual physical existence, then a strong case could be made that you, too, bring a wormhole into actual physical existence every time you sketch one with pen and paper.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;



&lt;p&gt;More broadly, Overbye&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;NYT&lt;/em&gt; piece explains with admirable clarity what this experiment did and didn&amp;#8217;t do&amp;#8212;leaving only the question &amp;#8220;wait &amp;#8230; if that&amp;#8217;s all that&amp;#8217;s going on here, then why is it being written up in the &lt;em&gt;NYT&lt;/em&gt;??&amp;#8221;  This is a rare case where, in my opinion, the &lt;em&gt;NYT&lt;/em&gt; did a much better job than &lt;em&gt;Quanta&lt;/em&gt;, which unequivocally accepted and amplified the &amp;#8220;QC creates a wormhole&amp;#8221; framing.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Alright, but what&amp;#8217;s the actual basis for the &amp;#8220;QC creates a wormhole&amp;#8221; claim, for those who don&amp;#8217;t want to leave this blog to read about it?  Well, the authors used 9 of Sycamore&amp;#8217;s 72 qubits to do a crude simulation of something called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sachdev%E2%80%93Ye%E2%80%93Kitaev_model&quot;&gt;SYK (Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev) model&lt;/a&gt;.  SYK has become popular as a toy model for quantum gravity.  In particular, it has a holographic dual description, which can indeed involve a spacetime with one or more wormholes.  So, they ran a quantum circuit that crudely modelled the SYK dual of a scenario with information sent through a wormhole.  They then confirmed that the circuit did what it was supposed to do&amp;#8212;i.e., what they’d already classically calculated that it &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; do.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;So, the objection is obvious: if someone simulates a black hole on their classical computer, they don&amp;#8217;t say they thereby &amp;#8220;created a black hole.&amp;#8221;  Or if they do, journalists don&amp;#8217;t uncritically repeat the claim.  Why should the standards be different just because we&amp;#8217;re talking about a quantum computer rather than a classical one?&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Did we at least &lt;em&gt;learn anything new&lt;/em&gt; about SYK wormholes from the simulation?  Alas, not really, because 9 qubits take a mere 2&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;=512 complex numbers to specify their wavefunction, and are therefore trivial to simulate on a laptop.  There&amp;#8217;s some argument in the paper that, if the simulation were scaled up to (say) 100 qubits, then maybe we &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; learn something new about SYK.  Even then, however, we&amp;#8217;d mostly learn about certain corrections that arise &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; the simulation was being done with &amp;#8220;only&amp;#8221; n=100 qubits, rather than in the n→∞ limit where SYK is rigorously understood.  But while those corrections, arising when n is &amp;#8220;neither too large nor too small,&amp;#8221; would surely be interesting to specialists, they&amp;#8217;d have no obvious bearing on the prospects for creating real physical wormholes in our universe.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;And yet, this is not a sensationalistic misunderstanding invented by journalists.  Some prominent quantum gravity theorists themselves&amp;#8212;including some of my close friends and collaborators&amp;#8212;persist in talking about the simulated SYK wormhole as &amp;#8220;actually being&amp;#8221; a wormhole.  What are they thinking?&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Daniel Harlow explained the thinking to me as follows (he stresses that he&amp;#8217;s explaining it, not necessarily endorsing it).  If you had two entangled quantum computers, one on Earth and the other in the Andromeda galaxy, and if they were both simulating SYK, and if Alice on Earth and Bob in Andromeda both &lt;em&gt;uploaded their own brains into their respective quantum simulations&lt;/em&gt;, then it seems possible that the simulated Alice and Bob could have the experience of jumping into a wormhole and meeting each other in the middle.  Granted, they couldn&amp;#8217;t get a message back &lt;em&gt;out&lt;/em&gt; from the wormhole, at least not without &amp;#8220;going the long way,&amp;#8221; which could happen only at the speed of light&amp;#8212;so only simulated-Alice and simulated-Bob themselves could ever &lt;em&gt;test&lt;/em&gt; this prediction.  Nevertheless, &lt;em&gt;if true&lt;/em&gt;, I suppose some would treat it as grounds for regarding a quantum simulation of SYK as &amp;#8220;more real&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;more wormholey&amp;#8221; than a classical simulation.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Of course, this scenario depends on strong assumptions not merely about quantum gravity, but &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; about the metaphysics of consciousness!  And I&amp;#8217;d &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; prefer to call it a simulated wormhole for simulated people.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;For completeness, here&amp;#8217;s Harlow&amp;#8217;s passage from the &lt;em&gt;NYT&lt;/em&gt; article:&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel Harlow, a physicist at M.I.T. who was not involved in the experiment, noted that the experiment was based on a model of quantum gravity that was so simple, and unrealistic, that it could just as well have been studied using a pencil and paper.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;“So I’d say that this doesn’t teach us anything about quantum gravity that we didn’t already know,” Dr. Harlow wrote in an email. “On the other hand, I think it is exciting as a technical achievement, because if we can’t even do this (and until now we couldn’t), then simulating more interesting quantum gravity theories would CERTAINLY be off the table.” Developing computers big enough to do so might take 10 or 15 years, he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;



&lt;hr class=&quot;wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity&quot;/&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Alright, let&amp;#8217;s move on to the claim that quantum supremacy has been refuted.  What Aharonov et al. actually show in their &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.03999&quot;&gt;new work&lt;/a&gt;, building on &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.03176&quot;&gt;earlier work by Gao and Duan&lt;/a&gt;, is that Random Circuit Sampling, with a constant rate of noise per gate and no error-correction, can&amp;#8217;t provide a &lt;em&gt;scalable&lt;/em&gt; approach to quantum supremacy.  Or more precisely: as the number of qubits n goes to infinity, and assuming you&amp;#8217;re in the &amp;#8220;anti-concentration regime&amp;#8221; (which in practice probably means: the depth of your quantum circuit is at least ~log(n)), there&amp;#8217;s a classical algorithm to approximately sample the quantum circuit&amp;#8217;s output distribution in poly(n) time (albeit, not yet a practical algorithm).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s what&amp;#8217;s crucial to understand: this is &lt;em&gt;100% consistent&lt;/em&gt; with what those of us working on quantum supremacy had assumed since at least 2016!  We &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; that if you tried to scale Random Circuit Sampling to 200 or 500 or 1000 qubits, while you also increased the circuit depth proportionately, the signal-to-noise ratio would become exponentially small, meaning that your quantum speedup would disappear.  That&amp;#8217;s why, from the very beginning, we targeted the &amp;#8220;practical&amp;#8221; regime of 50-100 qubits: a regime where&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you can still see explicitly that you&amp;#8217;re exploiting a 2&lt;sup&gt;50&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;#8211; or 2&lt;sup&gt;100&lt;/sup&gt;-dimensional Hilbert space for computational advantage, thereby confirming one of the main predictions of quantum computing theory, but&lt;/li&gt;



&lt;li&gt;you &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; have a signal that (as it turned out) is large enough to see with heroic effort.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;



&lt;p&gt;To their credit, Aharonov et al. explain all this perfectly clearly in their abstract and introduction.  I&amp;#8217;m just worried that &lt;em&gt;others&lt;/em&gt; aren&amp;#8217;t reading their paper as carefully as they should be!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;So then, what&amp;#8217;s the new advance in the Aharonov et al. paper?  Well, there had been some hope that circuit depth ~log(n) might be a sweet spot, where an exponential quantum speedup might both exist &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; survive constant noise, even in the asymptotic limit of n→∞ qubits.  Nothing in Google&amp;#8217;s or USTC&amp;#8217;s actual Random Circuit Sampling experiments depended on that hope, but it would&amp;#8217;ve been nice if it were true.  What Aharonov et al. have now done is to kill that hope, using powerful techniques involving summing over Feynman paths in the Pauli basis.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Stepping back, what &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the current status of quantum supremacy based on Random Circuit Sampling?  I would say it&amp;#8217;s still standing, but more precariously than I&amp;#8217;d like&amp;#8212;underscoring the need for new and better quantum supremacy experiments.  In more detail, &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.03011&quot;&gt;Pan, Chen, and Zhang&lt;/a&gt; have shown how to simulate Google&amp;#8217;s 53-qubit Sycamore chip classically, using what I estimated to be 100-1000X the electricity cost of running the quantum computer itself (&lt;em&gt;including&lt;/em&gt; the dilution refrigerator!).  Approaching from the problem from a different angle, &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01657&quot;&gt;Gao et al.&lt;/a&gt; have given a polynomial-time classical algorithm for spoofing Google&amp;#8217;s Linear Cross-Entropy Benchmark (LXEB)&amp;#8212;&lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; their algorithm can currently achieve only about 10% of the excess in LXEB that Google&amp;#8217;s experiment found.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;So, though it&amp;#8217;s been under sustained attack from multiple directions these past few years, I&amp;#8217;d say that the flag of quantum supremacy yet waves.  The Extended Church-Turing Thesis is still on thin ice.  The wormhole is still open.  Wait &amp;#8230; &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8230; that&amp;#8217;s not what I meant to write&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;hr class=&quot;wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity&quot;/&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark style=&quot;background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0)&quot; class=&quot;has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/mark&gt;With this post, as with future science posts, &lt;em&gt;all off-topic comments will be ruthlessly left in moderation&lt;/em&gt;.  Yes, even if the comments &amp;#8220;create their own reality&amp;#8221; full of anger and disappointment that I talked about what I talked about, instead of what the commenter wanted me to talk about.  Even if merely &lt;em&gt;refuting&lt;/em&gt; the comments would require me to give in and talk about their preferred topics after all.  Please stop.  This is a wormholes-&amp;#8216;n-supremacy post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Scott&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Scott Aaronson</name>
      <uri>https://scottaaronson.blog</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR22-173 |  On Disperser/Lifting Properties of the Index and Inner-Product Functions | 

	Sajin Koroth, 

	Paul Beame</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/173"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/173</id>
    <updated>2022-12-02T22:55:23+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    Query-to-communication lifting theorems, which connect the query complexity of a Boolean function to the communication complexity of an associated `lifted&amp;#39; function obtained by composing the function with many copies of another function known as a gadget, have been instrumental in resolving many open questions in computational complexity. Several important complexity questions could be resolved if we could make substantial improvements in the input size required for lifting with the Index function, from its current near-linear size down to polylogarithmic in the number of inputs $N$ of the original function or, ideally, constant. The near-linear size bound was shown by Lovett, Meka, Mertz, Pitassi and Zhang using a recent breakthrough improvement on the Sunflower Lemma to show that a certain graph associated with the Index function of near-linear size is a disperser. They also stated a conjecture about the Index function that is essential for further improvements in the size required for lifting with Index using current techniques. In this paper we prove the following;
  1) The conjecture of Lovett et al. is false when the size of the Index gadget is $\log N-\omega(1)$.
  2) Also, the Inner-Product function, which satisfies the disperser property at size $O(\log N)$, does not have this property when its size is  $\log N-\omega(1)$.
  3) Nonetheless, using Index gadgets of size at least 4, we prove a lifting theorem for a restricted class of communication protocols in which one of the players is limited to sending parities of its inputs.
  4) Using the ideas from this lifting theorem, we derive a strong lifting theorem from decision tree size to parity decision tree size. We use this to derive a general lifting theorem in proof complexity from tree-resolution size to tree-like $Res(\oplus)$ refutation size, which yields many new exponential lower bounds on such proofs.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">ECCC Papers: TR22-172 |  Lifting to Parity Decision Trees Via Stifling | 

	Arkadev Chattopadhyay, 

	Nikhil Mande, 

	Swagato Sanyal, 

	Suhail Sherif</title>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/172"/>
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/172</id>
    <updated>2022-12-02T22:16:33+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    We show that the deterministic decision tree complexity of a (partial) function or relation $f$ lifts to the deterministic parity decision tree (PDT) size complexity of the composed function/relation $f \circ g$ as long as the gadget $g$ satisfies a property that we call stifling. We observe that several simple gadgets of constant size, like Indexing on 3 input bits, Inner Product on 4 input bits, Majority on 3 input bits and random functions, satisfy this property. It can be shown that existing randomized communication lifting theorems ([Göös, Pitassi, Watson. SICOMP&amp;#39;20], [Chattopadhyay et al. SICOMP&amp;#39;21]) imply PDT-size lifting. However there are two shortcomings of this approach: first they lift randomized decision tree complexity of $f$, which could be exponentially smaller than its deterministic counterpart when either $f$ is a partial function or even a total search problem. Second, the size of the gadgets in such lifting theorems are as large as logarithmic in the size of the input to $f$. Reducing the gadget size to a constant is an important open problem at the frontier of current research.

Our result shows that even a random constant-size gadget does enable lifting to PDT size. Further, it also yields the first systematic way of turning lower bounds on the width of tree-like resolution proofs of the unsatisfiability of constant-width CNF formulas to lower bounds on the size of tree-like proofs in the resolution with parity system, i.e., $\mathrm{Res}$($\oplus$), of the unsatisfiability of closely related constant-width CNF formulas.
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>ECCC Papers</name>
      <uri>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">Computational Complexity: How do we keep the community connected?</title>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/12/how-do-we-keep-community-connected.html"/>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-4202676814033172170</id>
    <updated>2022-12-01T16:37:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;A colleague said how they enjoyed watching the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/11/should-you-quit-twitter-and-texas.html&quot;&gt;collapse of Twitter&lt;/a&gt; under Elon Musk. But I use Twitter to keep connected to the CS community. In Twitter I hear not only new results but ones that excite particular people. I watch the debate between those who see ML as revolutionary and those who see ML as revolting. I see the issues that our community worries about and those that they celebrate. I follow people as they progress in their careers or outright change them. Mostly it just makes me feel part of an academic community that goes beyond my own institution.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A bit surprisingly, so far Twitter hasn&#39;t collapsed. But it could and I expect many of my followers and those I follow spend less time there. I set up a Mastodon account&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://fediscience.org/@fortnow&quot;&gt;@fortnow@fediscience.org&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;but not much happens over there, though feel free to tell me who I should be following. There are many other social networks but none that bring us as a field together.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Blog posts and their comments play a role but not like they used to. There&#39;s&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cstheory.stackexchange.com/&quot;&gt;CS Theory StackExchange&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;which has some good (and not so good) technical discussions but we don&#39;t really have conversations there.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;How about conferences now that researchers are (mostly) willing to attend in person? Since conferences in CS are the primary publication venue, we have too many meetings and many won&#39;t go, or at least won&#39;t go in person, if they don&#39;t have a paper in the conference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2008/07/games.html&quot;&gt;once again&lt;/a&gt;, I suggest a big theory conference we hold every four years that everyone who&#39;s anyone will make sure to attend. Hey, it works for the World Cup.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Lance Fortnow&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Computational Complexity</name>
      <uri>http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">CCI: jobs: Assistant, Associate, or Full Professor (Search 2) at University of California – San Diego (apply by January 1, 2023)</title>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/11/30/assistant-associate-or-full-professor-search-2-at-university-of-california-san-diego-apply-by-january-1-2023/"/>
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/11/30/assistant-associate-or-full-professor-search-2-at-university-of-california-san-diego-apply-by-january-1-2023/</id>
    <updated>2022-11-30T23:22:09+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;The UC San Diego Department of Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) invites applications for multiple tenure-track faculty positions at the Assistant Professor or tenured faculty positions at the Associate, or Full Professor rank. The department is looking for exceptional candidates in all areas of Computer Science and Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cse.ucsd.edu/administration/human-resources/recruitment/faculty-positions&quot;&gt;https://cse.ucsd.edu/administration/human-resources/recruitment/faculty-positions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: nherrera@eng.ucsd.edu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>CCI: jobs</name>
      <uri>https://cstheory-jobs.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">CCI: jobs: Assistant, Associate, or Full Professor (Search 1) at University of California – San Diego (apply by January 1, 2023)</title>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/11/30/assistant-associate-or-full-professor-search-1-at-university-of-california-san-diego-apply-by-january-1-2023/"/>
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/11/30/assistant-associate-or-full-professor-search-1-at-university-of-california-san-diego-apply-by-january-1-2023/</id>
    <updated>2022-11-30T23:20:48+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;p&gt;The UC San Diego Department of Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) invites applications for multiple tenure-track faculty positions at the Assistant Professor or tenured faculty positions at Associate, or Full Professor rank. The department is looking for exceptional candidates in all areas of Computer Science and Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cse.ucsd.edu/administration/human-resources/recruitment/faculty-positions&quot;&gt;https://cse.ucsd.edu/administration/human-resources/recruitment/faculty-positions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: nherrera@eng.ucsd.edu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>CCI: jobs</name>
      <uri>https://cstheory-jobs.org</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <title type="html" xml:lang="en">David Eppstein: Linkage</title>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/11/30/linkage.html"/>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/11/30/linkage</id>
    <updated>2022-11-30T15:47:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
    &lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://kylehovey.github.io/blog/automata-nebula&quot;&gt;Digital astronomy with cellular automata&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/109356657961629085&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=33578376&quot;&gt;via&lt;/a&gt;). No, this is not about using CA to study patterns in the sky (though that might be interesting); it is about using &lt;a href=&quot;https://umap-learn.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&quot;&gt;UMAP dimension-reduction techniques&lt;/a&gt; to create something like a Hertzsprung-Russell diagram for finding CA rules with complex behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/guanajuato/&quot;&gt;My photos from my recent visit to Guanajuato are now online&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/109357876852587696&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; Very pretty city, and good food, worth a visit. My recommendation from the locals for their favorite restaurant was Truco 7, where I had amazing chicken mole for much less than I would have expected. Off the main streets much of the city looks like the photo below: steep narrow alleys with very colorful buildings. Maybe not the best for accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/guanajuato/9-m.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Steep alley in Guanajuato, Mexico, lined with colorful buildings&quot; style=&quot;border-style:solid;border-color:black&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@ct_bergstrom@fediscience.org/109355406095574860&quot;&gt;Galactica can generate Wikipedia articles, supposedly&lt;/a&gt;, but actually writes total bullshit resembling a Wikipedia article but not resembling any real-world use of the title term. The example given by Carl T. Bergstrom is for “Brandolini’s law, the principle that bullshit takes another of magnitude less effort create than to clean up”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://leanprover-community.github.io/sphere-eversion/&quot;&gt;Formal proof of Smale’s sphere-inversion theorem&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@highergeometer/109354222002349360&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; showing that “Lean doesn’t do just algebra or abstract nonsense, but really serious geometric topology, too”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://b3s23life.blogspot.com/2022/11/in-conways-life-fifteen-gliders-can.html&quot;&gt;You can build anything you want in Conway’s Game of Life by colliding 15 gliders together&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@OscarCunningham/109375074140276198&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; Anything that you can build out of any larger number of gliders, that is.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.c82.net/math-instruments/&quot;&gt;The Construction &amp;amp; Principal Uses of Mathematical Instruments&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/109384275129127171&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=33592636&quot;&gt;via&lt;/a&gt;), a digital edition of a 1709 book by Nicolas Bion, as translated into English in 1758 by Edmund Stone. Site designed as an exercise by Nicholas Rougeux; see also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.c82.net/blog/?id=90&quot;&gt;Rougeux’s blog post about the site design&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@tao/109390971278692349&quot;&gt;Maths at internet speed&lt;/a&gt;. Terry Tao links to &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.09055&quot;&gt;Justin Gilmer’s breakthrough&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Union-closed_sets_conjecture&quot;&gt;union-closed sets conjecture&lt;/a&gt;, followed in quick succession by improvements by &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.11504&quot;&gt;Will Sawin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.11689&quot;&gt;Zachary Chase and Shachar Lovett&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.11731&quot;&gt;Ryan Alweiss, Brice Huang, and Mark Sellke&lt;/a&gt;. See also &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/11/17/amazing-justin-gilmer-gave-a-constant-lower-bound-for-the-union-closed-sets-conjecture/&quot;&gt;Gil Kalai’s blog post&lt;/a&gt;. In other news, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@tao&quot;&gt;Terry Tao is now on mathstodon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@oschene@mastodon.social&quot;&gt;The Chambered Nautilus&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;MLINK&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; Curved paperfolding model by oschene (Philip Chapman-Bell).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Minor terminological disagreement with some coauthors &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/109406394361043315&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/span&gt; let \(T\) be a single-source shortest path tree in an unweighted undirected graph. Can you call \(T\) a “BFS tree”? Or is that only for trees that could be generated by breadth-first search? E.g. consider shortest paths in \(K_{2,3}\) starting from the 3-vertex side. For breadth first search, two leaves from the 3-vertex side will share a parent. But there is a different shortest path tree where they have different parents. Is it a BFS tree?&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/2022/bfs-vs-shortest.svg&quot; alt=&quot;K_{2,3}, a BFS tree, and a shortest-path tree that cannot be generated by breadth-first search&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;max-width:600px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@johncarlosbaez/109398225812984155&quot;&gt;Extended thread on combinatorial species of linear orderings and permutations by John Baez&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;MLINK&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; I had the vague impression that a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Combinatorial_species&quot;&gt;combinatorial species&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Combinatorial_class&quot;&gt;combinatorial class&lt;/a&gt; were more or less the same thing: a ranked collection of combinatorial objects, equivalent when they have the same number of objects of each rank. But that’s not accurate. It describes classes, but not species, which have a more specific equivalence relation. In particular, the linear orderings and the permutations form the same combinatorial class (they are both counted by the factorials), but different combinatorial species.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/11/who-first-thought-of-notion-of.html&quot;&gt;Who first thought of the notion of Polynomial Time&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/109419856682356083&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;)?&lt;/span&gt;  As Gasarch points out, the usual answer of Cobham and Edmonds in 1965 is incorrect. The same distinction, between polynomial and super-polynomial algorithms, already appeared in a 1910 paper of Henry Cabourn Pocklington. In the comments, Martin Berger points to the even-earlier analysis of Euclidean GCD, for which a polynomial bound was known by 1841.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@Leahwrenn@mastodon.social/109394896886730411&quot;&gt;Leah Berman Williams posts a new mathematical sculpture&lt;/a&gt;: a tetrahedron with its faces symmetrically knotted into trefoils.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantamagazine.org/wei-ho-is-drawn-to-algebra-geometry-and-the-human-side-of-math-20221122&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Quanta&lt;/em&gt; profiles Wei Ho&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@QuantaMagazine@mstdn.social/109388303834501212&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; her research on elliptic curves, and her new post as director of the Women and Mathematics program at the Institute for Advanced Study.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not every curvy triangle is a Reuleaux triangle &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/109433756706982819&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; Even if you ascribe the greater width than height in the photo (from &lt;a href=&quot;https://scilogs.spektrum.de/hlf/maths-on-a-plate/&quot;&gt;a post by Katie Steckles at the Heidelberg Laureate Forum&lt;/a&gt;) to an angled perspective, and imagine it to be 3-way symmetric, this plate is too bulgy to be Reuleaux. Still a fun example to find at a mathematics facility, though.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/2022/HLF-plate.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of a post by Katie Steckles at the Heidelberg Laureate Forum, showing a dinner plate described by Steckles as being a Reuleaux triangle, overlaid with red circles outlining the actual shape of a Reuleaux triangle&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;max-width:600px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This has been a special edition of “Things that are not Reuleaux triangles”; for the most recent full episode, see “&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2022/06/18/shapes-triangular-pencils.html&quot;&gt;The shapes of triangular pencils&lt;/a&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By David Eppstein&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
      <uri>https://11011110.github.io/blog/</uri>
    </author>
  </entry>


</feed>
