<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Theory of Computing Report</title>
  <link></link>
  <language>en</language>
  <description></description>


<item>
  <title>Triplet Loss-less Center Loss Sampling Strategies in Facial Expression Recognition Scenarios</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.04108</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.04108</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rajoli_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hossein Rajoli&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lotfi_F/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Fatemeh Lotfi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Atyabi_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Adham Atyabi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Afghah_F/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Fatemeh Afghah&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Facial expressions convey massive information and play a crucial role in
emotional expression. Deep neural network (DNN) accompanied by deep metric
learning (DML) techniques boost the discriminative ability of the model in
facial expression recognition (FER) applications. DNN, equipped with only
classification loss functions such as Cross-Entropy cannot compact intra-class
feature variation or separate inter-class feature distance as well as when it
gets fortified by a DML supporting loss item. The triplet center loss (TCL)
function is applied on all dimensions of the sample&#39;s embedding in the
embedding space. In our work, we developed three strategies: fully-synthesized,
semi-synthesized, and prediction-based negative sample selection strategies. To
achieve better results, we introduce a selective attention module that provides
a combination of pixel-wise and element-wise attention coefficients using
high-semantic deep features of input samples. We evaluated the proposed method
on the RAF-DB, a highly imbalanced dataset. The experimental results reveal
significant improvements in comparison to the baseline for all three negative
sample selection strategies.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-09 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Optimal Sufficient Requirements on the Embedded Ising Problem in Polynomial Time</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.04162</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.04162</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Lobe_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Elisabeth Lobe&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Kaibel_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Volker Kaibel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the central applications for quantum annealers is to find the
solutions of Ising problems. Suitable Ising problems, however, need to be
formulated such that they, on the one hand, respect the specific restrictions
of the hardware and, on the other hand, represent the original problems which
shall actually be solved. We evaluate sufficient requirements on such an
embedded Ising problem analytically and transform them into a linear
optimization problem. With an objective function aiming to minimize the maximal
absolute problem parameter, the precision issues of the annealers are
addressed. Due to the redundancy of several constraints, we can show that the
formally exponentially large optimization problem can be reduced and finally
solved in polynomial time for the standard embedding setting where the embedded
vertices induce trees. This allows to formulate provably equivalent embedded
Ising problems in a practical setup.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-09 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>On the Computational Complexity of Ethics: Moral Tractability for Minds and Machines</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.04218</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.04218</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Stenseke_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jakob Stenseke&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why should moral philosophers, moral psychologists, and machine ethicists
care about computational complexity? Debates on whether artificial intelligence
(AI) can or should be used to solve problems in ethical domains have mainly
been driven by what AI can or cannot do in terms of human capacities. In this
paper, we tackle the problem from the other end by exploring what kind of moral
machines are possible based on what computational systems can or cannot do. To
do so, we analyze normative ethics through the lens of computational
complexity. First, we introduce computational complexity for the uninitiated
reader and discuss how the complexity of ethical problems can be framed within
Marr&#39;s three levels of analysis. We then study a range of ethical problems
based on consequentialism, deontology, and virtue ethics, with the aim of
elucidating the complexity associated with the problems themselves (e.g., due
to combinatorics, uncertainty, strategic dynamics), the computational methods
employed (e.g., probability, logic, learning), and the available resources
(e.g., time, knowledge, learning). The results indicate that most problems the
normative frameworks pose lead to tractability issues in every category
analyzed. Our investigation also provides several insights about the
computational nature of normative ethics, including the differences between
rule- and outcome-based moral strategies, and the implementation-variance with
regard to moral resources. We then discuss the consequences complexity results
have for the prospect of moral machines in virtue of the trade-off between
optimality and efficiency. Finally, we elucidate how computational complexity
can be used to inform both philosophical and cognitive-psychological research
on human morality by advancing the Moral Tractability Thesis (MTT).
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-09 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A generalization of the persistent Laplacian to simplicial maps</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03771</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03771</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Gulen_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Aziz Burak G&amp;#xfc;len&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Memoli_F/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Facundo M&amp;#xe9;moli&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Wan_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zhengchao Wan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Wang_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yusu Wang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The graph Laplacian is a fundamental object in the analysis of and
optimization on graphs. This operator can be extended to a simplicial complex
$K$ and therefore offers a way to perform ``signal processing&quot; on
$p$-(co)chains of $K$. Recently, the concept of persistent Laplacian was
proposed and studied for a pair of simplicial complexes $K\hookrightarrow L$
connected by an inclusion relation, further broadening the use of Laplace-based
operators.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we expand the scope of the persistent Laplacian by
generalizing it to a pair of simplicial complexes connected by a simplicial map
$f: K \to L$. Such simplicial map setting arises frequently, e.g., when
relating a coarsened simplicial representation with an original representation,
or the case when the two simplicial complexes are spanned by different point
sets i.e. cases in which it does not hold that $K\subset L$. However, the
simplicial map setting is more challenging than the inclusion setting since the
underlying algebraic structure is more complicated.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We present a natural generalization of the persistent Laplacian to the
simplicial setting. To shed insight on the structure behind it, as well as to
develop an algorithm to compute it, we exploit the relationship between the
persistent Laplacian and the Schur complement of a matrix. A critical step is
to view the Schur complement as a functorial way of restricting a self-adjoint
PSD operator to a given subspace. As a consequence, we prove that persistent
Betti numbers of a simplicial map can be recovered by persistent Laplacians. We
then propose an algorithm for finding the matrix representations of persistent
Laplacians which in turn yields a new algorithm for computing persistent Betti
numbers of a simplicial map. Finally, we study the persistent Laplacian on
simplicial towers under simplicial maps and establish monotonicity results for
their eigenvalues.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-09 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Geometry</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Storing a Trie with Compact and Predictable Space</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03690</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03690</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Dong_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yuxuan Dong&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper proposed a storing approach for trie structures, called Coordinate
Hash Trie. For a trie with $n$ nodes and an alphabet with size $m$, the
execution time of finding, inserting and deleting a child node, is $O(1)$ for
the average case, $O(m)$ for the worst case. The space used by this approach is
$O(n)$, unrelated to $m$. The constant of space consumption is predictable,
with no need for reallocation or resizing.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-09 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Cardinality-Constrained Continuous Knapsack Problem with Concave Piecewise-Linear Utilities</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03781</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03781</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Bai_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Miao Bai&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Cardonha_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Carlos Cardonha&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study an extension of the cardinality-constrained knapsack problem where
each item has a concave piecewise-linear utility structure. Our main
contributions are approximation algorithms for the problem and the
investigation of an online version in the random order model. For the offline
problem, we present a fully polynomial-time approximation scheme and show that
it can be cast as the maximization of a submodular function with cardinality
constraints; the latter result allows us to derive a greedy $(1 -
\frac{1}{e})$-approximation algorithm. For the online problem in the random
order model, we present a 6.027-competitive algorithm. Finally, we investigate
the empirical performance of the greedy and online algorithms in numerical
experiments.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-09 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Men Can&#39;t Always be Transformed into Mice: Decision Algorithms and Complexity for Sorting by Symmetric Reversals</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03797</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03797</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Tong_X/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Xin Tong&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Yu_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yixiao Yu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Fang_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ziyi Fang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Jiang_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Haitao Jiang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wang_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Lusheng Wang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zhu_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Binhai Zhu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zhu_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Daming Zhu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sorting a permutation by reversals is a famous problem in genome
rearrangements. Since 1997, quite some biological evidence were found that in
many genomes the reversed regions are usually flanked by a pair of inverted
repeats. This type of reversals are called symmetric reversals, which,
unfortunately, were largely ignored until recently. In this paper, we
investigate the problem of sorting by symmetric reversals, which requires a
series of symmetric reversals to transform one chromosome $A$ into the another
chromosome $B$. The decision problem of sorting by symmetric reversals is
referred to as {\em SSR} (when the input chromosomes $A$ and $B$ are given, we
use {\em SSR(A,B)}) and the corresponding optimization version (i.e., when the
answer for {\em SSR(A,B)} is yes, using the minimum number of symmetric
reversals to convert $A$ to $B$), is referred to as {\em SMSR(A,B)}. The main
results of this paper are summarized as follows, where the input is a pair of
chromosomes $A$ and $B$ with $n$ repeats. (1) We present an $O(n^2)$ time
algorithm to solve the decision problem {\em SSR(A,B)}, i.e., determine whether
a chromosome $A$ can be transformed into $B$ by a series of symmetric
reversals. (2) We design an $O(n^2)$ time algorithm for a special 2-balanced
case of {\em SMSR(A,B)}, where chromosomes $A$ and $B$ both have duplication
number 2 and every repeat appears twice in different orientations in $A$ and
$B$. (3) We show that SMSR is NP-hard even if the duplication number of the
input chromosomes are at most 2, hence showing that the above positive
optimization result is the best possible. As a by-product, we show that the
\emph{minimum Steiner tree} problem on \emph{circle graphs} is NP-hard,
settling the complexity status of a 38-year old open problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-09 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Approximately Optimal Core Shapes for Tensor Decompositions</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03886</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03886</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ghadiri_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mehrdad Ghadiri&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Fahrbach_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Matthew Fahrbach&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Fu_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Gang Fu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mirrokni_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vahab Mirrokni&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This work studies the combinatorial optimization problem of finding an
optimal core tensor shape, also called multilinear rank, for a size-constrained
Tucker decomposition. We give an algorithm with provable approximation
guarantees for its reconstruction error via connections to higher-order
singular values. Specifically, we introduce a novel Tucker packing problem,
which we prove is NP-hard, and give a polynomial-time approximation scheme
based on a reduction to the 2-dimensional knapsack problem with a matroid
constraint. We also generalize our techniques to tree tensor network
decompositions. We implement our algorithm using an integer programming solver,
and show that its solution quality is competitive with (and sometimes better
than) the greedy algorithm that uses the true Tucker decomposition loss at each
step, while also running up to 1000x faster.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-09 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Fully-Dynamic Approximate Decision Trees With Worst-Case Update Time Guarantees</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03994</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03994</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Bressan_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Marco Bressan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sozio_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mauro Sozio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We give the first algorithm that maintains an approximate decision tree over
an arbitrary sequence of insertions and deletions of labeled examples, with
strong guarantees on the worst-case running time per update request. For
instance, we show how to maintain a decision tree where every vertex has Gini
gain within an additive $\alpha$ of the optimum by performing
$O\Big(\frac{d\,(\log n)^4}{\alpha^3}\Big)$ elementary operations per update,
where $d$ is the number of features and $n$ the maximum size of the active set
(the net result of the update requests). We give similar bounds for the
information gain and the variance gain. In fact, all these bounds are
corollaries of a more general result, stated in terms of decision rules --
functions that, given a set $S$ of labeled examples, decide whether to split
$S$ or predict a label. Decision rules give a unified view of greedy decision
tree algorithms regardless of the example and label domains, and lead to a
general notion of $\epsilon$-approximate decision trees that, for natural
decision rules such as those used by ID3 or C4.5, implies the gain
approximation guarantees above. The heart of our work provides a deterministic
algorithm that, given any decision rule and any $\epsilon &amp;gt; 0$, maintains an
$\epsilon$-approximate tree using $O\!\left(\frac{d\, f(n)}{n}
\operatorname{poly}\frac{h}{\epsilon}\right)$ operations per update, where
$f(n)$ is the complexity of evaluating the rule over a set of $n$ examples and
$h$ is the maximum height of the maintained tree.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-09 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Adaptive Massively Parallel Connectivity in Optimal Space</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.04033</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.04033</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lacki_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jakub &amp;#x141;&amp;#x105;cki&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Latypov_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Rustam Latypov&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Maus_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yannic Maus&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Uitto_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jara Uitto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the problem of finding connected components in the Adaptive
Massively Parallel Computation (AMPC) model. We show that when we require the
total space to be linear in the size of the input graph the problem can be
solved in $O(\log^* n)$ rounds in forests (with high probability) and
$2^{O(\log^* n)}$ expected rounds in general graphs. This improves upon an
existing $O(\log \log_{m/n} n)$ round algorithm.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the case when the desired number of rounds is constant we show that both
problems can be solved using $\Theta(m + n \log^{(k)} n)$ total space in
expectation (in each round), where $k$ is an arbitrarily large constant and
$\log^{(k)}$ is the $k$-th iterate of the $\log_2$ function. This improves upon
existing algorithms requiring $\Omega(m + n \log n)$ total space.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-09 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Weighted Edit Distance Computation: Strings, Trees and Dyck</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.04229</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.04229</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Das_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Debarati Das&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gilbert_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jacob Gilbert&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hajiaghayi_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;MohammadTaghi Hajiaghayi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kociumaka_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tomasz Kociumaka&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Saha_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Barna Saha&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given two strings of length $n$ over alphabet $\Sigma$, and an upper bound
$k$ on their edit distance, the algorithm of Myers (Algorithmica&#39;86) and Landau
and Vishkin (JCSS&#39;88) computes the unweighted string edit distance in
$\mathcal{O}(n+k^2)$ time. Till date, it remains the fastest algorithm for
exact edit distance computation, and it is optimal under the Strong Exponential
Hypothesis (STOC&#39;15). Over the years, this result has inspired many
developments, including fast approximation algorithms for string edit distance
as well as similar $\tilde{\mathcal{O}}(n+$poly$(k))$-time algorithms for
generalizations to tree and Dyck edit distances. Surprisingly, all these
results hold only for unweighted instances.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While unweighted edit distance is theoretically fundamental, almost all
real-world applications require weighted edit distance, where different weights
are assigned to different edit operations and may vary with the characters
being edited. Given a weight function $w: \Sigma \cup \{\varepsilon \}\times
\Sigma \cup \{\varepsilon \} \rightarrow \mathbb{R}_{\ge 0}$ (such that
$w(a,a)=0$ and $w(a,b)\ge 1$ for all $a,b\in \Sigma \cup \{\varepsilon\}$ with
$a\ne b$), the goal is to find an alignment that minimizes the total weight of
edits. Except for the vanilla $\mathcal{O}(n^2)$-time dynamic-programming
algorithm and its almost trivial $\mathcal{O}(nk)$-time implementation, none of
the aforementioned developments on the unweighted edit distance apply to the
weighted variant. In this paper, we propose the first
$\mathcal{O}(n+$poly$(k))$-time algorithm that computes weighted string edit
distance exactly, thus bridging a fundamental gap between our understanding of
unweighted and weighted edit distance. We then generalize this result to
weighted tree and Dyck edit distances, which lead to a deterministic algorithm
that improves upon the previous work for unweighted tree edit distance.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-09 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>News for January 2023</title>
  <guid>https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1824</guid>
  <link>https://ptreview.sublinear.info/2023/02/news-for-january-2023/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;Welcome to the first batch of 2023. Looks like it&amp;#8217;s going to be a good year, with 5 property testing or related papers (that I could find) already: &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An efficient asymmetric removal lemma and its limitations&lt;/strong&gt;, by Lior Gishboliner, Asaf Shapira, and Yuval Wigderson (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.07693&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;). One of the jewels of graph property testing is the triangle removel lemma (and its many generalizations and variants), which relates the number of triangles in a dense graph to its distance from being triangle-free: namely, any graph \(\varepsilon\)-far from being triangle-free must have \(\delta(\varepsilon)n^3\) triangles, where the density \(\delta(\varepsilon)\) only depends on the distance (and not the size of the graph!). This immediately leads to constant-query testers (and even &amp;#8220;proximity-oblivious&amp;#8221; testers) for triangle-freness (and, more generally, pattern-freeness). Unfortunately, the dependence on \(\varepsilon\) is quite bad, essentially a tower-type function (and it is known no polynomial bound is possible). This work attempts to bypass this impossibility result by proving an asymmetric removal lemma, or the form &amp;#8220;any graph \(\varepsilon\)-far from being triangle-free must have \(\mathrm{poly}(\varepsilon)n^5\) 5-cycles&amp;#8221; (and generalizations beyond triangles). This seems like a very interesting direction, with potential applications to property testing, and (who knows!) efficient testers for many properties hithertho only known to be (practically) testable for constant \(\varepsilon\).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Related (more removal lemmata!), a different work on this topic:&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Minimum Degree Removal Lemma Thresholds&lt;/strong&gt;, by Lior Gishboliner, Zhihan Jin, and Benny Sudakov (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.13789&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;). As mentioned above, removal lemmata relate the distance \(\varepsilon\) from being \(H\)-free (for a given subgraph \(H\)) to the density \(\delta(\varepsilon)\) of occurrences of \(H\) in the graph. Sadly, it is known that this density will be superpolynomial (in the distance) unless \(H\) is bipartite… which, while technically still yielding testing algorithms (query complexity independent of the size of the graph!), yields very inefficient testers (very bad dependence on \(\varepsilon\)!). This paper studies one direction to bypass this sad state of affairs: under which additional assumption on the underlying graph (specifically, bounds on its minimum degree) can we obtain a polynomial bound on \(\delta(\varepsilon)\)? And a linear bound? The authors give a tight degree condition for \(\delta(\varepsilon)\) to be polynomial when \(H\) is an odd cycle, and their results for the linear-dependence case establishes a separation between the two. Put differently: obtaining polynomial-query testers via removal lemmas is possible for a strictly larger class of graphs than linear-query ones!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;And now, for something completely different: testing binary matrices!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Note on Property Testing of the Binary Rank&lt;/strong&gt;, by Nader H. Bshouty (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.04406&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;). The binary rank of a matrix \(M\in\{0,1\}^{n\times m}\) is the smallest \(d\) such that there exist \(A\in\{0,1\}^{n\times d}\) and \(B\in\{0,1\}^{d\times m}\) with \(M=AB\); this can also be seen as the minimal number of bipartite cliques needed to partition the edges of a bipartite graph represented by \(M\). One can also define the relaxed notion of \(s\)-binary rank, if one enforces that each edge of the bipartite graph is covered by at most \(s\) bipartite cliques. The property testing question is then to decide, given inputs \(s,d,\varepsilon\), if \(M\) has \(s\)-binary rank at most \(d\), or is \(\varepsilon\)-far from it. The main result of this note is to give one-sided testers (one adaptive, and one non-adaptive) for \(s\)-binary rank with query complexity \(\tilde{O}(2^d)\) (for constant \(s\)), improving on the previous algorithms by a factor \(2^d\).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Into the quantum realm!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Testing quantum satisfiability,&lt;/strong&gt; by Ashley Montanaro, Changpeng Shao, and Dominic Verdon (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.10699&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;). Classically, one can study the property version of \(k\)-SAT, which asks to decide whether a given instance is satisfiable or far from being so. And people (namely, Alon and Shapira, in 2003) did! Quantumly, one can define an analogue of \(k\)-SAT, &amp;#8220;quantum \(k\)-SAT&amp;#8221;: and people (namely, Bravyi, in 2011) did! But what about property testing of quantum \(k\)-SAT? Well, now, people (namely, the authors of this paper) just did! Showing (Corollary 1.10) that one can efficiently distinguish between (1) the quantum \(k\)-SAT is satisfiable, and (2) it is far from satisfiable by a product state. This, effectively, extends the result of Alon–Shapira&amp;#8217;03 to the quantum realm.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;And to conclude, a foray into reinforcement learning via distribution testing…&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lower Bounds for Learning in Revealing POMDPs&lt;/strong&gt;, by Fan Chen, Huan Wang, Caiming Xiong, Song Mei, and Yu Bai (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01333&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;). Alright, I&amp;#8217;m even more out of my depth than usual here, so I&amp;#8217;ll just copy (part of) the abstract, for fear I don&amp;#8217;t do justice to the authors&amp;#8217; work: &amp;#8220;This paper studies the fundamental limits of reinforcement learning (RL) in the challenging &lt;em&gt;partially observable&lt;/em&gt; setting. While it is well-established that learning in Partially Observable Markov Decision Processes (POMDPs) requires exponentially many samples in the worst case, a surge of recent work shows that polynomial sample complexities are achievable under the &lt;em&gt;revealing condition&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8212; A natural condition that requires the observables to reveal some information about the unobserved latent states. However, the fundamental limits for learning in revealing POMDPs are much less understood, with existing lower bounds being rather preliminary and having substantial gaps from the current best upper bounds. We establish strong PAC and regret lower bounds for learning in revealing POMDPs. […] &lt;strong&gt;Technically, our hard instance construction adapts techniques in distribution testing, which is new to the RL literature and may be of independent interest.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;#8221; (Emphasis mine)&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Clement Canonne&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-08 06:04:08 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Property Testing Review</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Label propagation on binomial random graphs</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03569</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03569</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Kiwi_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Marcos Kiwi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Lichev_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Lyuben Lichev&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Mitsche_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Dieter Mitsche&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Pralat_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Pawe&amp;#x142; Pra&amp;#x142;at&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study a variant of the widely popular, fast and often used ``family&#39;&#39; of
community detection procedures referred to as label propagation algorithms.
Initially, given a network, each vertex starts with a random label in the
interval $[0,1]$. Then, in each round of the algorithm, every vertex switches
its label to the majority label in its neighborhood (including its own label).
At the first round, ties are broken towards smaller labels, while at each of
the next rounds, ties are broken uniformly at random.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We investigate the performance of this algorithm on the binomial random graph
$\mathcal G(n,p)$. We show that for $np \ge n^{5/8+\varepsilon}$, the algorithm
terminates with a single label a.a.s. (which was previously known only for
$np\ge n^{3/4+\varepsilon}$). Moreover, we show that if $np\gg n^{2/3}$, a.a.s.
this label is the smallest one, whereas if $n^{5/8+\varepsilon}\le np\ll
n^{2/3}$, the surviving label is a.a.s. not the smallest one.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-08 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Solidarity Cover Problem</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03451</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03451</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rosenbluth_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Eran Rosenbluth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Various real-world problems consist of partitioning a set of locations into
disjoint subsets, each subset spread in a way that it covers the whole set with
a certain radius. Given a finite set S, a metric d, and a radius r, define a
subset (of S) S&#39; to be an r-cover if and only if forall s in S there exists s&#39;
in S&#39; such that d(s,s&#39;) is less or equal to r. We examine the problem of
determining whether there exist m disjoint r-covers, naming it the Solidarity
Cover Problem (SCP). We consider as well the related optimization problems of
maximizing the number of r-covers, referred to as the partition size, and
minimizing the radius. We analyze the relation between the SCP and a graph
problem known as the Domatic Number Problem (DNP), both hard problems in the
general case. We show that the SCP is hard already in the Euclidean 2D setting,
implying hardness of the DNP already in the unit-disc-graph setting. As far as
we know, the latter is a result yet to be shown. We use the tight approximation
bound of (1-o(1))/ln(n) for the DNP&#39;s general case, shown by U.Feige,
M.Halld&#39;orsson, G.Kortsarz, and A.Srinivasan (SIAM Journal on computing, 2002),
to deduce the same bound for partition-size approximation of the SCP in the
Euclidean space setting. We show an upper bound of 3 and lower bounds of 2 and
sqrt(2) for approximating the minimal radius in different settings of the SCP.
Lastly, in the Euclidean 2D setting we provide a general
bicriteria-approximation scheme which allows a range of possibilities for
trading the optimality of the radius in return for better approximation of the
partition size and vice versa. We demonstrate a usage of the scheme which
achieves an approximation of (1/16,2) for the partition size and radius
respectively.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-08 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>On the complexity of the approximate hypergraph homomorphism problem</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03456</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03456</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ciardo_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Lorenzo Ciardo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kozik_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Marcin Kozik&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Krokhin_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Andrei Krokhin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nakajima_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tamio-Vesa Nakajima&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zivny_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Stanislav &amp;#x17d;ivn&amp;#xfd;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Understanding the computational complexity of fragments of the Constraint
Satisfaction Problem (CSP) has been instrumental in the formulation of
Feder-Vardi&#39;s Dichotomy Conjecture and its positive resolution by Bulatov and
Zhuk. An approximation version of the CSP - known as the promise CSP - has
recently gained prominence as an exciting generalisation of the CSP that
captures many fundamental computational problems. In this work, we establish a
computational complexity dichotomy for a natural fragment of the promise CSP
consisting of homomorphism problems involving a class of 3-uniform hypergraphs.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-08 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Optimally Interpolating between Ex-Ante Fairness and Welfare</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03071</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03071</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hogsgaard_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mikael H&amp;#xf8;gsgaard&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Karras_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Panagiotis Karras&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ma_W/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Wenyue Ma&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rathi_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nidhi Rathi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Schwiegelshohn_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Chris Schwiegelshohn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the fundamental problem of allocating a set of resources among
individuals with varied preferences, the quality of an allocation relates to
the degree of fairness and the collective welfare achieved. Unfortunately, in
many resource-allocation settings, it is computationally hard to maximize
welfare while achieving fairness goals.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this work, we consider ex-ante notions of fairness; popular examples
include the \emph{randomized round-robin algorithm} and \emph{sortition
mechanism}. We propose a general framework to systematically study the
\emph{interpolation} between fairness and welfare goals in a multi-criteria
setting. We develop two efficient algorithms ($\varepsilon-Mix$ and
$Simple-Mix$) that achieve different trade-off guarantees with respect to
fairness and welfare. $\varepsilon-Mix$ achieves an optimal multi-criteria
approximation with respect to fairness and welfare, while $Simple-Mix$ achieves
optimality up to a constant factor with zero computational overhead beyond the
underlying \emph{welfare-maximizing mechanism} and the \emph{ex-ante fair
mechanism}. Our framework makes no assumptions on either of the two underlying
mechanisms, other than that the fair mechanism produces a distribution over the
set of all allocations. Indeed, if these mechanisms are themselves
approximation algorithms, our framework will retain the approximation factor,
guaranteeing sensitivity to the quality of the underlying mechanisms, while
being \emph{oblivious} to them. We also give an extensive experimental analysis
for the aforementioned ex-ante fair mechanisms on real data sets, confirming
our theoretical analysis.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-08 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Sparsification of Monotone $k$-Submodular Functions of Low Curvature</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03143</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03143</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kudla_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jannik Kudla&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zivny_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Stanislav &amp;#x17d;ivn&amp;#xfd;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pioneered by Benczur and Karger for cuts in graphs [STOC&#39;96], sparsification
is a fundamental topic with wide-ranging applications that has been studied,
e.g., for graphs and hypergraphs, in a combinatorial and a spectral setting,
and with additive and multiplicate error bounds. Rafiey and Yoshida recently
considered sparsification of decomposable submodular functions [AAAI&#39;22]. We
extend their work by presenting an efficient algorithm for a sparsifier for
monotone $k$-submodular functions of low curvature.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-08 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Calibrated Recommendations for Users with Decaying Attention</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03239</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03239</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kleinberg_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jon Kleinberg&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ryu_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Emily Ryu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Tardos_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;&amp;#xc9;va Tardos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recommendation systems capable of providing diverse sets of results are a
focus of increasing importance, with motivations ranging from fairness to
novelty and other aspects of optimizing user experience. One form of diversity
of recent interest is calibration, the notion that personalized recommendations
should reflect the full distribution of a user&#39;s interests, rather than a
single predominant category -- for instance, a user who mainly reads
entertainment news but also wants to keep up with news on the environment and
the economy would prefer to see a mixture of these genres, not solely
entertainment news. Existing work has formulated calibration as a subset
selection problem; this line of work observes that the formulation requires the
unrealistic assumption that all recommended items receive equal consideration
from the user, but leaves as an open question the more realistic setting in
which user attention decays as they move down the list of results.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we consider calibration with decaying user attention under two
different models. In both models, there is a set of underlying genres that
items can belong to. In the first setting, where items are represented by
fine-grained mixtures of genre percentages, we provide a
$(1-1/e)$-approximation algorithm by extending techniques for constrained
submodular optimization. In the second setting, where items are coarsely binned
into a single genre each, we surpass the $(1-1/e)$ barrier imposed by
submodular maximization and give a $2/3$-approximate greedy algorithm. Our work
thus addresses the problem of capturing ordering effects due to decaying
attention, allowing for the extension of near-optimal calibration from
recommendation sets to recommendation lists.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-08 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Two Parallel PageRank Algorithms via Improving Forward Push</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03245</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03245</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zhang_Q/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Qi Zhang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Tang_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Rongxia Tang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Yao_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zhengan Yao&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Liang_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jun Liang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Initially used to rank web pages, PageRank has now been applied in many
fields. With the growing scale of graph, accelerating PageRank computing is
urged and designing parallel algorithm is a feasible solution. In this paper,
two parallel PageRank algorithms IFP1 and IFP2 are proposed via improving the
state-of-the-art Personalized PageRank algorithm, i.e., Forward Push.
Theoretical analysis indicates that, IFP1 can take advantage of the DAG
structure of the graph, where the dangling vertices improves the convergence
rate and the unreferenced vertices decreases the computation amount. As an
improvement of IFP1, IFP2 pushes mass to the dangling vertices only once but
rather many times, and thus decreases the computation amount further.
Experiments on six data sets illustrate that both IFP1 and IFP2 outperform
Power method, where IFP2 with 38 parallelism can be at most 50 times as fast as
the Power method.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-08 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Engineering Shared-Memory Parallel Shuffling to Generate Random Permutations In-Place</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03317</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03317</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Penschuck_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Manuel Penschuck&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shuffling is the process of rearranging a sequence of elements into a random
order such that any permutation occurs with equal probability. It is an
important building block in a plethora of techniques used in virtually all
scientific areas. Consequently considerable work has been devoted to the design
and implementation of shuffling algorithms.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We engineer, -- to the best of our knowledge -- for the first time, a
practically fast, parallel shuffling algorithm with $\Oh{\sqrt{n}\log n}$
parallel depth that requires only poly-logarithmic auxiliary memory. Our
reference implementations in Rust are freely available, easy to include in
other projects, and can process large data sets approaching the size of the
system&#39;s memory. In an empirical evaluation, we compare our implementations
with a number of existing solutions on various computer architectures. Our
algorithms consistently achieve the highest through-put on all machines.
Further, we demonstrate that the runtime of our parallel algorithm is
comparable to the time that other algorithms may take to acquire the memory
from the operating system to copy the input.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-08 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>First-Order Model Checking on Structurally Sparse Graph Classes</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03527</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03527</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Dreier_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jan Dreier&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mahlmann_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nikolas M&amp;#xe4;hlmann&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Siebertz_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sebastian Siebertz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A class of graphs is structurally nowhere dense if it can be constructed from
a nowhere dense class by a first-order transduction. Structurally nowhere dense
classes vastly generalize nowhere dense classes and constitute important
examples of monadically stable classes. We show that the first-order model
checking problem is fixed-parameter tractable on every structurally nowhere
dense class of graphs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our result builds on a recently developed game-theoretic characterization of
monadically stable graph classes. As a second key ingredient of independent
interest, we provide a polynomial-time algorithm for approximating weak
neighborhood covers (on general graphs). We combine the two tools into a
recursive locality-based model checking algorithm. This algorithm is efficient
on every monadically stable graph class admitting flip-closed sparse weak
neighborhood covers, where flip-closure is a mild additional assumption.
Thereby, establishing efficient first-order model checking on monadically
stable classes is reduced to proving the existence of flip-closed sparse weak
neighborhood covers on these classes - a purely combinatorial problem. We
complete the picture by proving the existence of the desired covers for
structurally nowhere dense classes: we show that every structurally nowhere
dense class can be sparsified by contracting local sets of vertices, enabling
us to lift the existence of covers from sparse classes.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-08 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Tight algorithms for connectivity problems parameterized by clique-width</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03627</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03627</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hegerfeld_F/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Falko Hegerfeld&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kratsch_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Stefan Kratsch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The complexity of problems involving global constraints is usually much more
difficult to understand than the complexity of problems only involving local
constraints. A natural form of global constraints are connectivity constraints.
We study connectivity problems from a fine-grained parameterized perspective.
In a breakthrough, Cygan et al. (TALG 2022) first obtained algorithms with
single-exponential running time c^{tw} n^O(1) for connectivity problems
parameterized by treewidth by introducing the cut-and-count-technique.
Furthermore, the obtained bases c were shown to be optimal under the Strong
Exponential-Time Hypothesis (SETH).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, since only sparse graphs may admit small treewidth, we lack
knowledge of the fine-grained complexity of connectivity problems with respect
to dense structure. The most popular graph parameter to measure dense structure
is arguably clique-width, which intuitively measures how easily a graph can be
constructed by repeatedly adding bicliques. Bergougnoux and Kant\&#39;e (TCS 2019)
have shown, using the rank-based approach, that also parameterized by
clique-width many connectivity problems admit single-exponential algorithms.
Unfortunately, the obtained running times are far from optimal under SETH.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We show how to obtain optimal running times parameterized by clique-width for
two benchmark connectivity problems, namely Connected Vertex Cover and
Connected Dominating Set. These are the first tight results for connectivity
problems with respect to clique-width and these results are obtained by
developing new algorithms based on the cut-and-count-technique and novel lower
bound constructions. Precisely, we show that there exist one-sided error
Monte-Carlo algorithms that given a k-clique-expression solve Connected Vertex
Cover in time 6^k n^O(1), and Connected Dominating Set in time 5^k n^O(1). Both
results are shown to be tight under SETH.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-08 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Planted Bipartite Graph Detection</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03658</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03658</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rotenberg_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Asaf Rotenberg&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Huleihel_W/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Wasim Huleihel&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Shayevitz_O/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ofer Shayevitz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We consider the task of detecting a hidden bipartite subgraph in a given
random graph. Specifically, under the null hypothesis, the graph is a
realization of an Erd\H{o}s-R\&#39;{e}nyi random graph over $n$ vertices with edge
density $q$. Under the alternative, there exists a planted $k_{\mathsf{R}}
\times k_{\mathsf{L}}$ bipartite subgraph with edge density $p&amp;gt;q$. We derive
asymptotically tight upper and lower bounds for this detection problem in both
the dense regime, where $q,p = \Theta\left(1\right)$, and the sparse regime
where $q,p = \Theta\left(n^{-\alpha}\right), \alpha \in \left(0,2\right]$.
Moreover, we consider a variant of the above problem, where one can only
observe a relatively small part of the graph, by using at most $\mathsf{Q}$
edge queries. For this problem, we derive upper and lower bounds in both the
dense and sparse regimes.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-08 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Postdoc at Department of Computer Science, Stony Brook University (apply by April 8, 2023)</title>
  <guid>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/02/07/postdoc-at-department-of-computer-science-stony-brook-university-apply-by-april-8-2023/</guid>
  <link>https://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/02/07/postdoc-at-department-of-computer-science-stony-brook-university-apply-by-april-8-2023/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;The department of Computer Science at Stony Brook University is looking to hire a postdoc in quantum information science, including but not limited to complexity theory, property testing, algorithms, sensing, and program analysis, with an expected start date in May 2023 and a duration of 1+1 years. The postdocs will work closely with Prof Nengkun Yu and Prof Supartha Podder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://stonybrooku.taleo.net/careersection/2/jobdetail.ftl?job=2204491&amp;amp;tz=GMT-05%3A00&amp;amp;tzname=America%2FNew_York&quot;&gt;https://stonybrooku.taleo.net/careersection/2/jobdetail.ftl?job=2204491&amp;amp;tz=GMT-05%3A00&amp;amp;tzname=America%2FNew_York&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: nengkun.yu@cs.stonybrook.edu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-07 17:30:54 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>CCI: jobs</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>FOCS 2022 Program</title>
  <guid>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=21043</guid>
  <link>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/02/07/focs-2022-program/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;Alvy Ray Smith designed the distinctive cover art that was a notable feature of FOCS proceedings until FOCS ended the production of printed proceedings in 2010. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/02/07/focs-2022-program/ars/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-21047&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;21047&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/02/07/focs-2022-program/ars/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ars.jpeg?fit=225%2C225&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;225,225&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;ars&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ars.jpeg?fit=225%2C225&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ars.jpeg?fit=225%2C225&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ars.jpeg?resize=225%2C225&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;225&quot; height=&quot;225&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-full wp-image-21047&quot; srcset=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ars.jpeg?w=225&amp;amp;ssl=1 225w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ars.jpeg?resize=150%2C150&amp;amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ars.jpeg?resize=200%2C200&amp;amp;ssl=1 200w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/02/07/focs-2022-program/cover-2/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-21048&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;21048&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/02/07/focs-2022-program/cover-2/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/cover.jpg?fit=378%2C450&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;378,450&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;cover&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/cover.jpg?fit=252%2C300&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/cover.jpg?fit=378%2C450&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/cover.jpg?resize=378%2C450&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;378&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-full wp-image-21048&quot; srcset=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/cover.jpg?w=378&amp;amp;ssl=1 378w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/cover.jpg?resize=252%2C300&amp;amp;ssl=1 252w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 378px) 100vw, 378px&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FOCS was founded in 1960 as the Symposium on Switching Circuit Theory and Logical Design. The 1960 conference did not have a separate published proceedings but most of the papers were published in the second half of the proceedings of the 1961 conference. For the 7th instantiation of the conference in 1966, the name was changed to the Symposium on Switching and Automata Theory (SWAT). The greatly increased breadth of the conference led to a name change to its present one in 1975. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FOCS 2022&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes the FOCS 2023 is about to be out. But I was looking at the &amp;#8220;old&amp;#8221; ones and thought this might be useful. So here are the papers with pointers to online versions. We will do the same for the 2023 version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04551.pdf&quot;&gt;Shortest Paths without a Map, but with an Entropic Regularizer.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Sebastien Bubeck (Microsoft Research), Christian Coester (University of Sheffield), Yuval Rabani (Hebrew University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.02763&quot;&gt;Online List Labeling: Breaking the &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;log&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Barrier.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Michael A. Bender (Stony Brook University), Alex Conway (VMWare Research), Martin Farach-Colton (Rutgers University), Hanna Komlos (Rutgers University), William Kuszmaul (MIT), Nicole Wein (DIMACS).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.07175&quot;&gt;Simple Hard Instances for Low-Depth Algebraic Proofs.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Nashlen Govindasamy (Imperial College London), Tuomas Hakoniemi (Imperial College London), Iddo Tzameret (Imperial College London).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.05390&quot;&gt;Constant Approximation of Min-Distances in Near-Linear Time.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Shiri Chechik (Tel Aviv University), Tianyi Zhang (Tel Aviv University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.01761&quot;&gt;First Price Auction is &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;1 − 1/&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Efficient.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Yaonan Jin (Columbia University), Pinyan Lu (Shanghai University of Finance and Economics).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.05106&quot;&gt;Estimating the Longest Increasing Subsequence in Nearly Optimal Time.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Alexandr Andoni (Columbia University), Negev Shekel Nosatzki (Columbia University), Sandip Sinha (Columbia University), Clifford Stein (Columbia University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.01425&quot;&gt;Order Selection Prophet Inequality: From Threshold Optimization to Arrival Time Design.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Bo Peng (ITCS, Shanghai University of Finance and Economics), Zhihao Gavin Tang (ITCS, Shanghai University of Finance and Economics).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9996652&quot;&gt;Using invariant theory to fool polynomials.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Harm Derksen (Northeastern University), Emanuele Viola (Northeastern University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2111.13198.pdf&quot;&gt;The Implicit Graph Conjecture is False.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Hamed Hatami (McGill University), Pooya Hatami (Ohio State University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2201.05674&quot;&gt;Cut Query Algorithms with Star Contraction.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Yuval Efron (Columbia University), Danupon Nanongkai (University of Copenhagen &amp;amp; KTH), Sagnik Mukhopadhyay (University of Sheffield), Simon Apers (CNRS IRIF), Troy Lee (University of Technology Sydney), Pawel Gawrychowski (University of Wroc?aw).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.08688&quot;&gt;Improved Optimal Testing Results from Global Hypercontractivity.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Tali Kaufman (Bar Ilan University), Dor Minzer (MIT).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.06038&quot;&gt;A Hash Table Without Hash Functions, and How to Get the Most out of Your Random Bits.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
William Henry Kuszmaul (Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT)).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.06558&quot;&gt;Balanced Allocations: The Heavily Loaded Case with Deletions.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Nikhil Bansal (University of Michigan), William Kuszmaul (MIT).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.01550&quot;&gt;A Characterization of Multiclass Learnability.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Nataly Brukhim (Princeton University), Daniel Carmon (Technion), Irit Dinur (Weizmann), Shay Moran (Technion and Google), Amir Yehudayoff (Technion-IIT).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.07016&quot;&gt;Algorithms and Lower Bounds for Replacement Paths under Multiple Edge Failures.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Virginia Vassilevska Williams (Massachusetts Institute of Technology), Eyob Woldeghebriel (Massachusetts Institute of Technology), Yinzhan Xu (Massachusetts Institute of Technology).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.10959&quot;&gt;Derandomizing Directed Random Walks in Almost-Linear Time.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Rasmus Kyng (ETH Zurich, Department of Computer Science), Simon Meierhans (ETH Zurich, Department of Computer Science), Maximilian Probst Gutenberg (ETH Zurich, Department of Computer Science).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.07346&quot;&gt;Sparse random hypergraphs: Non-backtracking spectra and community detection.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ludovic Stephan (Ecole Polytechnique Federale de Lausanne), Yizhe Zhu (University of California, Irvine).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.04923&quot;&gt;Killing a Vortex.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Dimitrios Thilikos (LIRMM, Univ Montpellier, CNRS, Montpellier, France), Sebastian Wiederrecht (LIRMM, Univ Montpellier, CNRS, Montpellier, France).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.15627&quot;&gt;Low Treewidth Embeddings of Planar and Minor-Free Metrics.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Hung Le (University of Massachusetts), Arnold Filtser (Bar-Ilan University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.06168&quot;&gt;Cheeger Inequalities for Vertex Expansion and Reweighted Eigenvalues.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Tsz Chiu Kwok (Shanghai University of Finance and Economics), Lap Chi Lau (University of Waterloo), Kam Chuen Tung (University of Waterloo).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.01923&quot;&gt;Algorithms for the ferromagnetic Potts model on expanders.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Charlie Carlson (University of Colorado, Boulder), Ewan Davies (University of Colorado, Boulder), Nicolas Fraiman (University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill), Alexandra Kolla (University of Colorado, Boulder and University of California Santa Cruz), Aditya Potukuchi (University of Illinois at Chicago), Corrine Yap (Rutgers University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.02526&quot;&gt;Nearly Optimal Communication and Query Complexity of Bipartite Matching.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Joakim Blikstad (KTH Royal Institute of Technology), Jan van den Brand (Simons Institute and UC Berkeley), Yuval Efron (Columbia University USA), Sagnik Mukhopadhyay (University of Sheffield UK), Danupon Nanongkai (University of Copenhagen &amp;amp; KTH).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02550&quot;&gt;Continuous LWE is as Hard as LWE &amp;amp; Applications to Learning Gaussian Mixtures.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Aparna Gupte (MIT CSAIL), Neekon Vafa (MIT CSAIL), Vinod Vaikuntanathan (MIT CSAIL).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02063&quot;&gt;Verifiable Quantum Advantage without Structure.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Takashi Yamakawa (NTT Social Informatics Laboratories), Mark Zhandry (Princeton University and NTT Research).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9996896&quot;&gt;Separated borders: Exponential-gap fanin-hierarchy theorem for approximative depth-3 circuits.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Pranjal Dutta (Chennai Mathematical Institute), Nitin Saxena (Department of Computer Science &amp;amp; Engg., Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.13920&quot;&gt;Fitting Metrics and Ultrametrics with Minimum Disagreements.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Vincent Cohen-Addad (Google), Chenglin Fan (Sorbonne Universite, Paris, France), Euiwoong Lee (University of Michigan), Arnaud de Mesmay (CNRS, LIGM, Universite Gustave Eiffel).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.15667&quot;&gt;Algorithms and Barriers in the Symmetric Binary Perceptron Model.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
David Gamarnik (MIT), Eren Can Kizildag (MIT), Will Perkins (University of Illinois at Chicago), Changji Xu (Harvard).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.10887&quot;&gt;Differential Privacy from Locally Adjustable Graph Algorithms: k-Core Decomposition, Low Outdegree Ordering, and Densest Subgraphs.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Laxman Dhulipala (Google Research), Quanquan C. Liu (Northwestern University), Sofya Raskhodnikova (Boston University), Jessica Shi (Massahusetts Institute of Technology), Julian Shun (Massahusetts Institute of Technology), Shangdi Yu (Massachusetts Institute of Technology).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.ucla.edu/~pak/papers/SharpP11.pdf&quot;&gt;What is in &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;#&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and what is not?.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Christian Ikenmeyer (University of Liverpool), Igor Pak (University of California, Los Angeles).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.05093&quot;&gt;Sampling from the Sherrington-Kirkpatrick Gibbs measure via algorithmic stochastic localization.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ahmed El Alaoui (Cornell University), Andrea Montanari (Stanford University), Mark Sellke (Stanford University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.00213&quot;&gt;The Quantum and Classical Streaming Complexity of Quantum and Classical Max-Cut.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
John Kallaugher (Sandia National Laboratories), Ojas Parekh (Sandia National Laboratories).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.01665&quot;&gt;Linear Hashing with &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;ℓ&lt;sub&gt;∞&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; guarantees and two-sided Kakeya bounds.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Manik Dhar (Princeton University), Zeev Dvir (Princeton University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.03790&quot;&gt;High-Dimensional Geometric Streaming in Polynomial Space.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
David P. Woodruff (Carnegie Mellon University), Taisuke Yasuda (Carnegie Mellon University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.04888&quot;&gt;Active Linear Regression for &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;ℓ&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Norms and Beyond.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Cameron Musco (University of Massachusetts Amherst), Christopher Musco (New York University), David P. Woodruff (Carnegie Mellon University), Taisuke Yasuda (Carnegie Mellon University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.07847&quot;&gt;Tight Lipschitz Hardness for Optimizing Mean Field Spin Glasses.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Brice Huang (Massachusetts Institute of Technology), Mark Sellke (Stanford University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.10889&quot;&gt;Correlation Clustering with Sherali-Adams.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Vincent Cohen-Addad (Google Research), Euiwoong Lee (University of Michigan), Alantha Newman (Laboratoire G-SCOP (CNRS, Grenoble-INP)).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2101.08208&quot;&gt;Solving SDP Faster: A Robust IPM Framework and Efficient Implementation.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Baihe Huang (Peking University), Shunhua Jiang (Columbia University), Zhao Song (Adobe Research), Runzhou Tao (Columbia University), Ruizhe Zhang (The University of Texas at Austin).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.06974&quot;&gt;Planting Undetectable Backdoors in Machine Learning Models.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Shafi Goldwasser (UC Berkeley), Michael P. Kim (UC Berkeley), Vinod Vaikuntanathan (MIT), Or Zamir (IAS).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.05839&quot;&gt;Bounded depth proof for Tseitin formulas on the grid; revisited.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Johan Hastad (KTH Royal Institute of Technology), Kilian Risse (KTH Royal Institute of Technology).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01104&quot;&gt;Local Computation of Maximal Independent Set.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Mohsen Ghaffari (MIT).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.13648&quot;&gt;Survivable Network Design Revisited: Group-Connectivity.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Qingyun Chen (University of California, Merced), Bundit Laekhanukit (Shanghai University of Finance and Economics), Chao Liao (Huawei TCS Lab), Yuhao Zhang (Shanghai Jiao Tong University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.01873&quot;&gt;Induced Cycles and Paths Are Harder Than You Think.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Mina Dalirrooyfard (Massachusetts Institute of Technology), Virginia Vassilevska Williams (Massachusetts Institute of Technology).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9996753&quot;&gt;Binary Codes with Resilience Beyond 1/4 via Interaction.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Klim Efremenko (Ben-Gurion University), Gillat Kol (Princeton University), Raghuvansh Saxena (Microsoft Research), Zhijun Zhang (Princeton University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.03456&quot;&gt;Negative-Weight Single-Source Shortest Paths in Near-Linear Time.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Aaron Bernstein (Rutgers University), Danupon Nanongkai (University of Copenhagen), Christian Wulff-Nilsen (University of Copenhagen).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9996716&quot;&gt;Error Correcting Codes that Achieve BSC Capacity Against Channels that are Poly-Size Circuits.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ronen Shaltiel (University of Haifa), Jad Silbak (Tel Aviv University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.00122&quot;&gt;Polynomial-Time Power-Sum Decomposition of Polynomials.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Mitali Bafna (Harvard University), Jun-Ting Hsieh (Carnegie Mellon University), Pravesh Kothari (CMU), Jeff Xu (Carnegie Mellon University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/045/&quot;&gt;Relaxed Locally Decodable and Correctable Codes: Beyond Tensoring.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Gil Cohen (Tel Aviv University), Tal Yankovitz (Tel Aviv University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.04342&quot;&gt;Improved Lower Bounds for Submodular Function Minimization.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Deeparnab Chakrabarty (Dartmouth College), Andrei Graur (Stanford University), Haotian Jiang (University of Washington), Aaron Sidford (Stanford University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/048/&quot;&gt;On the Range Avoidance Problem for Circuits.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Hanlin Ren (University of Oxford), Rahul Santhanam (University of Oxford), Zhikun Wang (Xi’an Jiaotong University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.03930&quot;&gt;Near-Optimal Deterministic Vertex-Failure Connectivity Oracles.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Yaowei Long (University of Michigan), Thatchaphol Saranurak (University of Michigan).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9996620&quot;&gt;Solving the Hamilton Cycle problem fast on average.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Michael Anastos (Institute of Science and Technology Austria).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.11894&quot;&gt;Properly learning monotone functions via local correction.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Jane Lange (MIT), Ronitt Rubinfeld (MIT), Arsen Vasilyan (MIT).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.11725&quot;&gt;Punctured Low-Bias Codes Behave Like Random Linear Codes.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Venkatesan Guruswami (UC Berkeley), Jonathan Mosheiff (Ben-Gurion University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.07024&quot;&gt;Almost Ramanujan Expanders from Arbitrary Expanders via Operator Amplification.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Fernando Granha Jeronimo (Institute of Advanced Study), Tushant Mittal (University of Chicago), Sourya Roy (University of California, Riverside), Avi Wigderson (Institute for Advanced Study).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.01520&quot;&gt;Sampling Lovasz Local Lemma For General Constraint Satisfaction Solutions In Near-Linear Time.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Kun He (Chinese Academy of Sciences), Chunyang Wang (Nanjing University), Yitong Yin (Nanjing University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.03782&quot;&gt;Testing Positive Semidefiniteness Using Linear Measurements.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Deanna Needell (University of California Los Angeles), William Swartworth (University of California Los Angeles), David P Woodruff (CMU).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/108/&quot;&gt;Hardness Self-Amplification from Feasible Hard-Core Sets.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Shuichi Hirahara (National Institute of Informatics), Nobutaka Shimizu (Tokyo Institute of Technology).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.07524&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;O&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;+&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;-time Algorithm for Distance k Tree Edit Distance.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Debarati Das (Penn State University), Jacob Gilbert (University of Maryland), MohammadTaghi Hajiaghayi (University of Maryland), Tomasz Kociumaka (UC Berkeley), Barna Saha (University of California San Diego), Hamed Saleh (University of Maryland).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.03076&quot;&gt;Approximation Algorithms and Hardness for n-Pairs Shortest Paths and All-Nodes Shortest Cycles.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Mina Dalirooyfard (MIT), Ce Jin (MIT), Virginia Vassilevska Williams (MIT), Nicole Wein (DIMACS).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.01513&quot;&gt;Radical Sylvester-Gallai Theorem for Cubics.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Rafael Oliveira (University of Waterloo), Akash Kumar Sengupta (Columbia University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.11469&quot;&gt;Explicit Lower Bounds Against &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ω&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;-Rounds of Sum-of-Squares.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Max Hopkins (UCSD), Ting-Chun Lin (UCSD, Hong Hai Research Institute).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.10091&quot;&gt;Factorial Lower Bounds for (Almost) Random Order Streams.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ashish Chiplunkar (IIT Delhi), John Kallaugher (Sandia National Labs), Michael Kapralov (EPFL), Eric Price (The University of Texas at Austin).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.03427&quot;&gt;Binary Iterative Hard Thresholding Converges with Optimal Number of Measurements for 1-Bit Compressed Sensing.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Namiko Matsumoto (UC San Diego), Arya Mazumdar (UC San Diego).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.07771&quot;&gt;Optimal mixing for two-state anti-ferromagnetic spin systems.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Xiaoyu Chen (Nanjing University), Weiming Feng (University of Edinburgh), Yitong Yin (Nanjing University), Xinyuan Zhang (Nanjing University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.04318&quot;&gt;Determinant Maximization via Matroid Intersection Algorithms.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Adam Brown (Georgia Insittute of Technology), Aditi Laddha (Georgia Insittute of Technology), Madhusudhan Pittu (Carnegie Mellon University), Mohit Singh (Georgia Insittute of Technology), Prasad Tetali (Carnegie Mellon University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.04958&quot;&gt;Breaking the Cubic Barrier for All-Pairs Max-Flow: Gomory-Hu Tree in Nearly Quadratic Time.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Amir Abboud (Weizmann Institute of Science), Robert Krauthgamer (Weizmann Institute of Science), Jason Li (UC Berkeley), Debmalya Panigrahi (Duke University), Thatchaphol Saranurak (University of Michigan), Ohad Trabelsi (University of Michigan).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.04989&quot;&gt;Generalised entropy accumulation.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Tony Metger (ETH Zurich), Omar Fawzi (ENS Lyon), David Sutter (IBM Quantum, IBM Research Zurich), Renato Renner (ETH Zurich).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.04163&quot;&gt;Localization schemes: A framework for proving mixing bounds for Markov chains.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Yuansi Chen (Duke University), Ronen Eldan (Microsoft Research).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9996905&quot;&gt;A tight (non-combinatorial) conditional lower bound for Klee’s Measure Problem in 3D.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Marvin Kunnemann (TU Kaiserslautern).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.03361&quot;&gt;Fast Deterministic Fully Dynamic Distance Approximation.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Jan van den Brand (Simons Institute and UC Berkeley), Sebastian Forster (University of Salzburg), Yasamin Nazari (University of Salzburg).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.07729&quot;&gt;On Weighted Graph Sparsification by Linear Sketching.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Yu Chen (University of Pennsylvania), Sanjeev Khanna (University of Pennsylvania), Huan Li (University of Pennsylvania).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.03087&quot;&gt;Faster Pattern Matching under Edit Distance.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Panagiotis Charalampopoulos (Reichman University, Herzliya, Israel and Birkbeck, University of London), Tomasz Kociumaka (UC Berkeley and Max Planck Institute for Informatics, SIC, Germany), Philip Wellnitz (Max Planck Institute for Informatics, SIC, Germany).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/119/&quot;&gt;NP-Hardness of Learning Programs and Partial MCSP.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Shuichi Hirahara (National Institute of Informatics).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.00795&quot;&gt;An Approximate Generalization of the Okamura-Seymour Theorem.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Nikhil Kumar (Hasso Plattner Institute Potsdam).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.12706&quot;&gt;Gap Edit Distance via Non-Adaptive Queries: Simple and Optimal.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Elazar Goldenberg (The Academic College of Tel Aviv-Yafo), Tomasz Kociumaka (UC Berkeley), Robert Krauthgamer (Weizmann Institute of Science), Barna Saha (University of California San Diego).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.01078&quot;&gt;On Matrix Multiplication and Polynomial Identity Testing.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Robert Andrews (University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02095&quot;&gt;Streaming Facility Location in High Dimension via Geometric Hashing.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Artur Czumaj (University of Warwick), Shaofeng Jiang (Peking University), Robert Krauthgamer (Weizmann Institute of Science), Pavel Vesel? (Charles University), Mingwei Yang (Peking University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.10830&quot;&gt;Memory Bounds for Continual Learning.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Binghui Peng (Columbia), Christos Papadimitriou (Columbia University), Xi Chen (Columbia University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.08254&quot;&gt;Deterministic Low-Diameter Decompositions for Weighted Graphs and Distributed and Parallel Applications.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Michael Elkin (Ben-Gurion University of the Negev), Bernhard Haeupler (ETHZ &amp;amp; Carnegie Mellon University), Vaclav Rozho? (ETH Zurich), Christoph Grunau (ETH Zurich).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06920&quot;&gt;Having Hope in Hops: New Spanners, Preservers and Lower Bounds for Hopsets.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Shimon Kogan (Weizmann Institute), Merav Parter (Weizmann Institute).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.11152&quot;&gt;Strong XOR Lemma for Communication with Bounded Rounds.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Huacheng Yu (Princeton University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.13641&quot;&gt;Quantum Tanner codes.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Anthony Leverrier (Inria), Gilles Zemor (University of Bordeaux).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.04842&quot;&gt;Optimal learning of quantum Hamiltonians from high-temperature Gibbs states.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Jeongwan Haah (Microsoft Research), Robin Kothari (Microsoft), Ewin Tang (University of Washington).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.09951&quot;&gt;Motif Cut Sparsifiers.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Michael Kapralov (EPFL), Mikhail Makarov (EPFL), Sandeep Silwal (MIT), Christian Sohler (University of Cologne), Jakab Tardos (EPFL).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.00671&quot;&gt;Maximum Flow and Minimum-Cost Flow in Almost-Linear Time.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Li Chen (Georgia Tech), Rasmus Kyng (ETH Zurich), Yang P. Liu (Stanford University), Richard Peng (University of Waterloo), Maximilian Probst Gutenberg (ETH Zurich), Sushant Sachdeva (University of Toronto).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.11903&quot;&gt;Minimax Rates for Robust Community Detection.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Allen Liu (MIT), Ankur Moitra (Math &amp;amp; CSAIL, MIT).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://eprint.iacr.org/2021/1543.pdf&quot;&gt;Post-Quantum Zero Knowledge, Revisited (or: How to Do Quantum Rewinding Undetectably).&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Alex Lombardi (MIT), Fermi Ma (Simons Institute and UC Berkeley), Nicholas Spooner (University of Warwick).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.08810&quot;&gt;Interior point methods are not worse than Simplex.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Xavier Allamigeon (INRIA &amp;amp; Ecole Polytechnique), Daniel Dadush (CWI Amsterdam), Georg Loho (University of Twente), Bento Natura (London School of Economics and Political Science), Laszlo A. Vegh (London School of Economics and Political Science).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2105.10043&quot;&gt;A (Slightly) Improved Bound on the Integrality Gap of the Subtour LP for TSP.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Anna Karlin (University of Washington), Nathan Klein (University of Washington), Shayan Oveis Gharan (University of Washington).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.07155&quot;&gt;Tight Bounds for Quantum State Certification with Incoherent Measurements.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Sitan Chen (UC Berkeley), Brice Huang (MIT), Jerry Li (Microsoft Research), Allen Liu (MIT).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.00342&quot;&gt;Fast Multivariate Multipoint Evaluation Over All Finite Fields.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Vishwas Bhargava (Rutgers University), Sumanta Ghosh (Caltech), Zeyu Guo (UT Austin), Mrinal Kumar (IIT Bombay), Chris Umans (Caltech).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://eprint.iacr.org/2022/1236&quot;&gt;Rate-1 Non-Interactive Arguments for Batch-NP and Applications.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Lalita Devadas (MIT CSAIL), Rishab Goyal (MIT CSAIL), Yael Tauman Kalai (MIT and Microsoft Research), Vinod Vaikuntanathan (MIT CSAIL).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.02168&quot;&gt;Separations in Proof Complexity and TFNP.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Mika Goos (EPFL), Alexandros Hollender (University of Oxford), Siddhartha Jain (EPFL), Gilbert Maystre (EPFL), William Pires (McGill), Robert Robere (McGill), Ran Tao (McGill).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.12896&quot;&gt;Randomised Composition and Small-Bias Minimax.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Shalev Ben-David (University of Waterloo), Eric Blais (University of Waterloo), Mika Goos (EPFL), Gilbert Maystre (EPFL).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9996646&quot;&gt;Incrementally Verifiable Computation via Rate-1 Batch Arguments.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Omer Paneth (Tel Aviv University), Rafael Pass (Cornell Tech and Tel Aviv University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/097/&quot;&gt;Unstructured Hardness to Average-Case Randomness.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Lijie Chen (MIT), Ron Rothblum (Technion), Roei Tell (IAS + DIMACS).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.11832&quot;&gt;New Additive Spanner Lower Bounds by an Unlayered Obstacle Product.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Greg Bodwin (University of Michigan), Gary Hoppenworth (University of Michigan).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.01901&quot;&gt;The Power of Uniform Sampling for Coresets.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Vladimir Braverman (Johns Hopkins University), Vincent Cohen-Addad (Google Research, Switzerland), Shaofeng Jiang (Peking University), Robert Krauthgamer (Weizmann Institute of Science), Chris Schwiegelshohn (Aarhus University), Mads Bech Toftrup (Aarhus University), Xuan Wu (Johns Hopkins University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.purdue.edu/homes/hmaji/papers/BKMN22.pdf&quot;&gt;Geometry of Secure Two-party Computation.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Saugata Basu (Purdue University), Hamidreza Amini Khorasgani (Purdue University), Hemanta K. Maji (Purdue University), Hai H. Nguyen (Purdue University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02128&quot;&gt;Computing in Anonymous Dynamic Networks Is Linear.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Giuseppe Antonio Di Luna (Sapienza University of Rome), Giovanni Viglietta (Japan Advanced Institute of Science and Technology (JAIST)).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.13997&quot;&gt;Classical Verification of Quantum Computations in Linear Time.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Jiayu Zhang (California Institute of Technology).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.15149&quot;&gt;Pure-Circuit: Strong Inapproximability for PPAD.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Argyrios Deligkas (Royal Holloway, University of London), John Fearnley (University of Liverpool), Alexandros Hollender (University of Oxford), Themistoklis Melissourgos (University of Essex).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.10306&quot;&gt;Performance and limitations of the QAOA at constant levels on large sparse hypergraphs and spin glass models.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Joao Basso (Google), David Gamarnik (MIT), Song Mei (University of California, Berkeley), Leo Zhou (California Institute of Technology).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.09049&quot;&gt;Rounds vs Communication Tradeoffs for Maximal Independent Sets.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Sepehr Assadi (Rutgers University), Gillat Kol (Princeton University), Zhijun Zhang (Princeton University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.03710&quot;&gt;Almost 3-Approximate Correlation Clustering in Constant Rounds.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Soheil Behnezhad (Stanford University), Moses Charikar (Stanford University), Weiyun Ma (Stanford University), Li-Yang Tan (Stanford University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.03142&quot;&gt;Inapproximability of Positive Semidefinite Permanents and Quantum State Tomography.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Alexander Meiburg (UCSB).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.17207&quot;&gt;A Proof of the Kahn-Kalai Conjecture.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Huy Tuan Pham (Stanford University), Jinyoung Park (Stanford University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.13739&quot;&gt;Deterministic Small Vertex Connectivity in Almost Linear Time.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Thatchaphol Saranurak (University of Michigan), Sorrachai Yingchareonthawornchai (Aalto University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02570&quot;&gt;Optimal Sublinear Sampling of Spanning Trees and Determinantal Point Processes via Average-Case Entropic Independence.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Nima Anari (Stanford University), Yang P. Liu (Stanford University), Thuy-Duong Vuong (Stanford University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://eprint.iacr.org/2022/1430&quot;&gt;Indistinguishability Obfuscation via Mathematical Proofs of Equivalence.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Abhishek Jain (Johns Hopkins University), Zhengzhong Jin (Johns Hopkins University).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Problems&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this of any value? Should we do it for FOCS 2023?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By rjlipton&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-07 13:44:21 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Richard Lipton</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>After you are notified that an article is accepted...</title>
  <guid>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-6646652451610616557</guid>
  <link>https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2023/02/after-you-are-notified-that-article-is.html</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;After just one round of referees reports&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(they send me the reports, I made the corrections, they were happy) I got email saying my paper on proving the primes are infinite FROM Schur&#39;s theorem in Ramsey was ACCEPTED. Yeah! Now What?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1) The journal send me an email with a link GOOD FOR ONLY FIFTY DAYS to help me publicize the article. Here is the link:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-saferedirecturl=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://authors.elsevier.com/a/1gTyD,H-cWw6X&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1674683686602000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2aEyfN69fYfqlMmiFLM6l6&quot; fg_scanned=&quot;1&quot; href=&quot;https://authors.elsevier.com/a/1gTyD,H-cWw6X&quot; style=&quot;background-color: white; color: #007398; font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; font-size: 18px; text-align: -webkit-center;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://authors.elsevier.com/&lt;wbr&gt;&lt;/wbr&gt;a/1gTyD,H-cWw6X&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Will this really help? The article is already on arxiv. Also, I can blog about it, but how do non-bloggers publicize their work? Do they need to?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(ADDED LATER: A commenter wanted to know why I am publishing in an Elsevier journal. This was a memorial issue in honor of Bruce Landman, a combinatorist who died young.&amp;nbsp; I was invited to submit an article.)&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;QUESTION: Is this common practice? If so, what do you do with those links? Email them to all of your the people who should care about the article?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;2) I got some forms to fill out that asked how many offprints I wanted. While my readers can probably guess what that means, I will remind you: paper copies of the article. I filled out the form:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I want 0 of them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They still wanted to know the address to send the 0 copies to, so I gave that as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Does anyone actually get offprints anymore? That seems so 1990&#39;s. With everything on the web I tend to email people who want article pointers. In fact, that happens rarely - either nobody wants to read my articles (quite possible) or they find them on my website (quite possible).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1991 when I went up for tenure the dept wanted 15 copies of every article I wrote so they could send my letter writers (and others) all my stuff. Rumor is that the Governor of Maryland got a copy of every article I ever wrote. I hoped he was a fan of oracle constructions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1998 when I went up for full prof they did not do this, assuming that the letter writers could find what the needed on the web. I do wonder about that- it might have been a nice courtesy to send them stuff directly and that would be a use for offprints. Depends on if my letter writers prefer reading online or on paper. They could of course print out my papers, but again- as a courtesy perhaps we should have supplied the papers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;QUESTION: Do you order a non-zero number of offprints and if so why?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;3) The journal offered to have my article to be open access at their site for a price. I did not do this as, again, the article is already on arxiv.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;QUESTION: Is there a reason to have your article formally open-access given that its already on arixv?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;4) One of my co-authors on a different article asked me &lt;i&gt;When will it appear IN PRINT&lt;/i&gt;?&amp;nbsp; I can&#39;t imagine caring about that. Its already on arxiv and I doubt having it in a journal behind paywalls will increase its visibility AT ALL. The only reason to care about when it appears IN PRINT is so I can update my resume from TO APPEAR to the actual volume and number and year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;QUESTION: Aside from updating your resume do you care when an article that was accepted appears IN PRINT? And if so why?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By gasarch&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-07 01:56:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Reducing Nearest Neighbor Training Sets Optimally and Exactly</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.02132</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.02132</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rohrer_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Josiah Rohrer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Weber_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Simon Weber&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In nearest-neighbor classification, a training set $P$ of points in
$\mathbb{R}^d$ with given classification is used to classify every point in
$\mathbb{R}^d$: Every point gets the same classification as its nearest
neighbor in $P$. Recently, Eppstein [SOSA&#39;22] developed an algorithm to detect
the relevant training points, those points $p\in P$, such that $P$ and
$P\setminus\{p\}$ induce different classifications. We investigate the problem
of finding the minimum cardinality reduced training set $P&#39;\subseteq P$ such
that $P$ and $P&#39;$ induce the same classification. We show that the set of
relevant points is such a minimum cardinality reduced training set if $P$ is in
general position. Furthermore, we show that finding a minimum cardinality
reduced training set for possibly degenerate $P$ is in P for $d=1$, and
NP-complete for $d\geq 2$.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-07 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Geometry</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Robust Budget Pacing with a Single Sample</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.02006</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.02006</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Balseiro_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Santiago Balseiro&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kumar_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Rachitesh Kumar&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mirrokni_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vahab Mirrokni&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sivan_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Balasubramanian Sivan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wang_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Di Wang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major Internet advertising platforms offer budget pacing tools as a standard
service for advertisers to manage their ad campaigns. Given the inherent
non-stationarity in an advertiser&#39;s value and also competing advertisers&#39;
values over time, a commonly used approach is to learn a target expenditure
plan that specifies a target spend as a function of time, and then run a
controller that tracks this plan. This raises the question: how many historical
samples are required to learn a good expenditure plan? We study this question
by considering an advertiser repeatedly participating in $T$ second-price
auctions, where the tuple of her value and the highest competing bid is drawn
from an unknown time-varying distribution. The advertiser seeks to maximize her
total utility subject to her budget constraint. Prior work has shown the
sufficiency of $T\log T$ samples per distribution to achieve the optimal
$O(\sqrt{T})$-regret. We dramatically improve this state-of-the-art and show
that just one sample per distribution is enough to achieve the near-optimal
$\tilde O(\sqrt{T})$-regret, while still being robust to noise in the sampling
distributions.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-07 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Sketch-Flip-Merge: Mergeable Sketches for Private Distinct Counting</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.02056</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.02056</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hehir_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jonathan Hehir&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ting_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Daniel Ting&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Cormode_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Graham Cormode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Data sketching is a critical tool for distinct counting, enabling multisets
to be represented by compact summaries that admit fast cardinality estimates.
Because sketches may be merged to summarize multiset unions, they are a basic
building block in data warehouses. Although many practical sketches for
cardinality estimation exist, none provide privacy when merging. We propose the
first practical cardinality sketches that are simultaneously mergeable,
differentially private (DP), and have low empirical errors. These introduce a
novel randomized algorithm for performing logical operations on noisy bits, a
tight privacy analysis, and provably optimal estimation. Our sketches
dramatically outperform existing theoretical solutions in simulations and on
real-world data.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-07 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>An Effective and Differentially Private Protocol for Secure Distributed Cardinality Estimation</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.02158</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.02158</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wang_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Pinghui Wang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Yang_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Chengjin Yang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Xie_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Dongdong Xie&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zhao_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Junzhou Zhao&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Li_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hui Li&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Tao_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jing Tao&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Guan_X/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Xiaohong Guan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Counting the number of distinct elements distributed over multiple data
holders is a fundamental problem with many real-world applications ranging from
crowd counting to network monitoring. Although a number of space and
computational efficient sketch methods (e.g., the Flajolet-Martin sketch and
the HyperLogLog sketch) for cardinality estimation have been proposed to solve
the above problem, these sketch methods are insecure when considering privacy
concerns related to the use of each data holder&#39;s personal dataset. Despite a
recently proposed protocol that successfully implements the well-known
Flajolet-Martin (FM) sketch on a secret-sharing based multiparty computation
(MPC) framework for solving the problem of private distributed cardinality
estimation (PDCE), we observe that this MPC-FM protocol is not differentially
private. In addition, the MPC-FM protocol is computationally expensive, which
limits its applications to data holders with limited computation resources. To
address the above issues, in this paper we propose a novel protocol DP-DICE,
which is computationally efficient and differentially private for solving the
problem of PDCE. Experimental results show that our DP-DICE achieves orders of
magnitude speedup and reduces the estimation error by several times in
comparison with state-of-the-arts under the same security requirements.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-07 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Linear-time 2-strong connectivity orientations of mixed graphs and related problems</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.02215</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.02215</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Georgiadis_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Loukas Georgiadis&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kefallinos_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Dionysios Kefallinos&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kosinas_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Evangelos Kosinas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A mixed graph $G$ is a graph that consists of both undirected and directed
edges. An orientation of $G$ is formed by orienting all the undirected edges of
$G$, i.e., converting each undirected edge $\{u,v\}$ into a directed edge that
is either $(u,v)$ or $(v,u)$. The problem of finding an orientation of a mixed
graph that makes it strongly connected is well understood and can be solved in
linear time. Here we introduce the following orientation problem in mixed
graphs. Given a mixed graph $G$, we wish to compute its maximal sets of
vertices $C_1,C_2,\ldots,C_k$ with the property that by removing any edge $e$
from $G$ (directed or undirected), there is an orientation $R_i$ of
$G\setminus{e}$ such that all vertices in $C_i$ are strongly connected in
$R_i$. We discuss properties of those sets, and we show how to solve this
problem in linear time by reducing it to the computation of the $2$-edge
twinless strongly connected components of a directed graph. A directed graph
$G=(V,E)$ is twinless strongly connected if it contains a strongly connected
spanning subgraph without any pair of antiparallel (or twin) edges. The
twinless strongly connected components (TSCCs) of a directed graph $G$ are its
maximal twinless strongly connected subgraphs. A $2$-edge twinless strongly
connected component (2eTSCC) of $G$ is a maximal subset of vertices $C$ such
that any two vertices $u, v \in C$ are in the same twinless strongly connected
component of $G \setminus e$, for any edge $e$. These concepts have several
diverse applications, such as the design of road and telecommunication
networks, and the structural stability of buildings.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-07 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Maximal $k$-Edge-Connected Subgraphs in Weighted Graphs via Local Random Contraction</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.02290</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.02290</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nalam_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Chaitanya Nalam&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Saranurak_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Thatchaphol Saranurak&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The \emph{maximal $k$-edge-connected subgraphs} problem is a classical graph
clustering problem studied since the 70&#39;s. Surprisingly, no non-trivial
technique for this problem in weighted graphs is known: a very straightforward
recursive-mincut algorithm with $\Omega(mn)$ time has remained the fastest
algorithm until now. All previous progress gives a speed-up only when the graph
is unweighted, and $k$ is small enough (e.g.~Henzinger~et~al.~(ICALP&#39;15),
Chechik~et~al.~(SODA&#39;17), and Forster~et~al.~(SODA&#39;20)).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We give the first algorithm that breaks through the long-standing
$\tilde{O}(mn)$-time barrier in \emph{weighted undirected} graphs. More
specifically, we show a maximal $k$-edge-connected subgraphs algorithm that
takes only $\tilde{O}(m\cdot\min\{m^{3/4},n^{4/5}\})$ time. As an immediate
application, we can $(1+\epsilon)$-approximate the \emph{strength} of all edges
in undirected graphs in the same running time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our key technique is the first local cut algorithm with \emph{exact}
cut-value guarantees whose running time depends only on the output size. All
previous local cut algorithms either have running time depending on the cut
value of the output, which can be arbitrarily slow in weighted graphs or have
approximate cut guarantees.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-07 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Back From A Vacation</title>
  <guid>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=20989</guid>
  <link>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/02/06/back-from-a-vacation/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;I am just back from a multi-week vacation on the cruise ship the Voyager.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/02/06/back-from-a-vacation/ship/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-20993&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;20993&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/02/06/back-from-a-vacation/ship/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ship.jpg?fit=550%2C366&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;550,366&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;ship&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ship.jpg?fit=300%2C200&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ship.jpg?fit=550%2C366&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ship.jpg?resize=550%2C366&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;550&quot; height=&quot;366&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-full wp-image-20993&quot; srcset=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ship.jpg?w=550&amp;amp;ssl=1 550w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ship.jpg?resize=300%2C200&amp;amp;ssl=1 300w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My dear wife&amp;#8212;Kathryn Farley&amp;#8212;and I were on the trip together with&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/02/06/back-from-a-vacation/kf/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-20991&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;20991&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/02/06/back-from-a-vacation/kf/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/kf.jpg?fit=1200%2C1005&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1200,1005&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;kf&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/kf.jpg?fit=300%2C251&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/kf.jpg?fit=600%2C503&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/kf.jpg?resize=600%2C503&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;503&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-full wp-image-20991&quot; srcset=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/kf.jpg?w=1200&amp;amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/kf.jpg?resize=300%2C251&amp;amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/kf.jpg?resize=1024%2C858&amp;amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/kf.jpg?resize=768%2C643&amp;amp;ssl=1 768w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;her brother. It was wonderful. It was relaxing and terrific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H1&gt;Well Not Exactly&lt;/H1&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first got on the ship I had to reset my wifi connection on my laptop. Somehow I messed it up and it failed. I then tried to reconnect and the internet connection failed again and I could not reconnect it ever. Suggestions like: Open your Settings app and tap Network &amp;#038; internet or Connections. Depending on your device, these options may be different. Turn Wi-Fi off and mobile data on, and check if there&amp;#8217;s a difference. If not, turn mobile data off and Wi-Fi on and check again. never worked. Not ever. The rest of the cruise I gave up&amp;#8212;I was after all on a vacation. I decided I did not need the internet, email, or Google. I still enjoyed the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2The Problem More Exactly&lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this raised an interesting problem: How do we search the settings of a laptop and reset the state? Somehow the state of the laptop got messed up and then I could not get it reset to the correct state. Being on a ship made it harder to reconnect and actually made it impossible. I just got stuff working after being back at home in NYC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the technical problem that I faced. My laptop was in a correct state let&amp;#8217;s denote it as &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{S}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;. Then I messed it up somehow to the state &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%5E%7B%5Cbf+bad%7D%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{S^{&amp;#92;bf bad}}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;. Since I cleverly did not keep a clean state I did not know how to get back to the state &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{S}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;. The trouble with this problem was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The state I was in on the laptop did not work; the state was not one that allowed the laptop to do anything useful. Anything. For example it did not allow me to do Google searches. Thus I could not try to see how to get to a useful state.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did ask an &amp;#8220;expert&amp;#8221; that was on the ship for help. But he was an expert but not one who could help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt;The Problem Even More Exactly&lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine the laptop is in some state &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%5E%7B%5Cbf+bad%7D%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{S^{&amp;#92;bf bad}}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;. How do we try to find the correct state &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{S}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;? The interesting issue is that tools like Google are not available while you are in the wrong state. You can edit some part of the state but then when you try and use the laptop the state may still not work. You can then try another state, but it may stlll be broken. Good luck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt;Open Problems&lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How would you have attacked this problem? I gave up after a while. What would you have done?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By rjlipton&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-06 13:22:30 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Richard Lipton</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A Computational Separation Between Quantum No-cloning and No-teleportation</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01858</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01858</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Nehoran_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Barak Nehoran&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Zhandry_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mark Zhandry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two of the fundamental no-go theorems of quantum information are the
no-cloning theorem (that it is impossible to make copies of general quantum
states) and the no-teleportation theorem (the prohibition on sending quantum
states over classical channels without pre-shared entanglement). They are known
to be equivalent, in the sense that a collection of quantum states is clonable
if and only if it is teleportable. Our main result suggests that this is not
the case when computational efficiency is considered. We give a collection of
quantum states and oracles relative to which these states are efficiently
clonable but not efficiently teleportable. Given that the opposite scenario is
impossible (states that can be teleported can always trivially be cloned), this
gives the most complete oracle separation possible between these two important
no-go properties. In doing so, we introduce a related quantum no-go property,
reconstructibility, which refers to the ability to construct a quantum state
from a uniquely identifying classical description. We show the stronger result
of a collection of quantum states that are efficiently clonable but not
efficiently reconstructible. This novel no-go property only exists in relation
to computational efficiency, as it is trivial for unbounded computation. It
thus opens up the possibility of further computational no-go properties that
have not yet been studied because they do not exist outside the computational
context.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-06 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Complexity of Solo Chess with Unlimited Moves</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01405</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01405</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Brunner_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Josh Brunner&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chung_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Lily Chung&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Coulombe_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Michael Coulombe&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Demaine_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Erik D. Demaine&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gomez_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Timothy Gomez&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lynch_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jayson Lynch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analyze Solo Chess puzzles, where the input is an $n \times n$ board
containing some standard Chess pieces of the same color, and the goal is to
make a sequence of capture moves to reduce down to a single piece. Prior work
analyzes this puzzle for a single piece type when each piece is limited to make
at most two capture moves (as in the Solo Chess puzzles on chess.com). By
contrast, we study when each piece can make an unlimited number of capture
moves. We show that any single piece type can be solved in polynomial time in a
general model of piece types, while any two standard Chess piece types are
NP-complete. We also analyze the restriction (as on chess.com) that one piece
type is unique and must be the last surviving piece, showing that in this case
some pairs of piece types become tractable while others remain hard.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-06 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Optimal Heaviest Induced Ancestors</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01373</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01373</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Charalampopoulos_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Panagiotis Charalampopoulos&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Dudek_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Bart&amp;#x142;omiej Dudek&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gawrychowski_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Pawe&amp;#x142; Gawrychowski&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Pokorski_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Karol Pokorski&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We revisit the Heaviest Induced Ancestors (HIA) problem that was introduced
by Gagie, Gawrychowski, and Nekrich [CCCG 2013] and has a number of
applications in string algorithms. Let $T_1$ and $T_2$ be two rooted trees
whose nodes have weights that are increasing in all root-to-leaf paths, and
labels on the leaves, such that no two leaves of a tree have the same label. A
pair of nodes $(u, v)\in T_1 \times T_2$ is \emph{induced} if and only if there
is a label shared by leaf-descendants of $u$ and $v$. In an HIA query, given
nodes $x \in T_1$ and $y \in T_2$, the goal is to find an induced pair of nodes
$(u, v)$ of the maximum total weight such that $u$ is an ancestor of~$x$ and
$v$ is an ancestor of $y$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let $n$ be the upper bound on the sizes of the two trees. It is known that no
data structure of size $\tilde{\mathcal{O}}(n)$ can answer HIA queries in
$o(\log n / \log \log n)$ time [Charalampopoulos, Gawrychowski, Pokorski; ICALP
2020]. This (unconditional) lower bound is a $\operatorname{polyloglog} n$
factor away from the query time of the fastest $\tilde{\mathcal{O}}(n)$-size
data structure known to date for the HIA problem [Abedin, Hooshmand, Ganguly,
Thankachan; Algorithmica 2022]. In this work, we resolve the query-time
complexity of the HIA problem for the near-linear space regime by presenting a
data structure that can be built in $\tilde{\mathcal{O}}(n)$ time and answers
HIA queries in $\mathcal{O}(\log n/\log\log n)$ time. As a direct corollary, we
obtain an $\tilde{\mathcal{O}}(n)$-size data structure that maintains the LCS
of a static string and a dynamic string, both of length at most $n$, in time
optimal for this space regime.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main ingredients of our approach are fractional cascading and the
utilization of an $\mathcal{O}(\log n/ \log\log n)$-depth tree decomposition.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-06 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Group Fairness in Non-monotone Submodular Maximization</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01546</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01546</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Yuan_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jing Yuan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Tang_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Shaojie Tang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Maximizing a submodular function has a wide range of applications in machine
learning and data mining. One such application is data summarization whose goal
is to select a small set of representative and diverse data items from a large
dataset. However, data items might have sensitive attributes such as race or
gender, in this setting, it is important to design \emph{fairness-aware}
algorithms to mitigate potential algorithmic bias that may cause over- or
under- representation of particular groups. Motivated by that, we propose and
study the classic non-monotone submodular maximization problem subject to novel
group fairness constraints. Our goal is to select a set of items that maximizes
a non-monotone submodular function, while ensuring that the number of selected
items from each group is proportionate to its size, to the extent specified by
the decision maker. We develop the first constant-factor approximation
algorithms for this problem. We also extend the basic model to incorporate an
additional global size constraint on the total number of selected items.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-06 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Chaining of Maximal Exact Matches in Graphs</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01748</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01748</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rizzo_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nicola Rizzo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Caceres_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Manuel C&amp;#xe1;ceres&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Makinen_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Veli M&amp;#xe4;kinen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the problem of finding maximal exact matches (MEMs) between a query
string $Q$ and a labeled directed acyclic graph (DAG) $G=(V,E,\ell)$ and
subsequently co-linearly chaining these matches. We show that it suffices to
compute MEMs between node labels and $Q$ (node MEMs) to encode full MEMs. Node
MEMs can be computed in linear time and we show how to co-linearly chain them
to solve the Longest Common Subsequence (LCS) problem between $Q$ and $G$. Our
chaining algorithm is the first to consider a symmetric formulation of the
chaining problem in graphs and runs in $O(k^2|V| + |E| + kN\log N)$ time, where
$k$ is the width (minimum number of paths covering the nodes) of $G$, and $N$
is the number of node MEMs. We then consider the problem of finding MEMs when
the input graph is an indexable elastic founder graph (subclass of labeled DAGs
studied by Equi et al., Algorithmica 2022). For arbitrary input graphs, the
problem cannot be solved in truly sub-quadratic time under SETH (Equi et al.,
ICALP 2019). We show that we can report all MEMs between $Q$ and an indexable
elastic founder graph in time $O(nH^2 + m + M_\kappa)$, where $n$ is the total
length of node labels, $H$ is the maximum number of nodes in a block of the
graph, $m = |Q|$, and $M_\kappa$ is the number of MEMs of length at least
$\kappa$.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-06 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Online Ad Allocation with Predictions</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01827</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01827</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Spaeh_F/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Fabian Spaeh&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ene_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Alina Ene&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Display Ads and the generalized assignment problem are two well-studied
online packing problems with important applications in ad allocation and other
areas. In both problems, ad impressions arrive online and have to be allocated
immediately to budget-constrained advertisers. Worst-case algorithms that
achieve the ideal competitive ratio are known, but might act overly
conservative given the predictable and usually tame nature of real-world input.
Given this discrepancy, we develop an algorithm for both problems that
incorporate machine-learned predictions and can thus improve the performance
beyond the worst-case. Our algorithm is based on the work of Feldman et al.
(2009) and similar in nature to Mahdian et al. (2007) who were the first to
develop a learning-augmented algorithm for the related, but more structured Ad
Words problem. We use a novel analysis to show that our algorithm is able to
capitalize on a good prediction, while being robust against poor predictions.
We experimentally evaluate our algorithm on synthetic and real-world data on a
wide range of predictions. Our algorithm is consistently outperforming the
worst-case algorithm without predictions.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-06 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Qubit-Efficient Randomized Quantum Algorithms for Linear Algebra</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01873</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01873</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Wang_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Samson Wang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+McArdle_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sam McArdle&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Berta_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mario Berta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose a class of randomized quantum algorithms for the task of sampling
from matrix functions, without the use of quantum block encodings or any other
coherent oracle access to the matrix elements. As such, our use of qubits is
purely algorithmic, and no additional qubits are required for quantum data
structures. For $N\times N$ Hermitian matrices, the space cost is $\log(N)+1$
qubits and depending on the structure of the matrices, the gate complexity can
be comparable to state-of-the-art methods that use quantum data structures of
up to size $O(N^2)$, when considering equivalent end-to-end problems. Within
our framework, we present a quantum linear system solver that allows one to
sample properties of the solution vector, as well as an algorithm for sampling
properties of ground states of Hamiltonians. As a concrete application, we
combine these two sub-routines to present a scheme for calculating Green&#39;s
functions of quantum many-body systems.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-06 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Nathan Never strikes back</title>
  <guid>http://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?p=1163</guid>
  <link>https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2023/02/05/nathan-never-strikes-back/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amiga-germany-fanzine.de/produkt/amiga-germany-fanzine-5/&quot;&gt;Amiga Germany Fan’zine – #5&lt;/a&gt; features &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ccs.neu.edu/home/viola/#Nineties&quot;&gt;Nathan Never&lt;/a&gt;, 30 years after the game came out (the article is from some months ago, but I just found out).  You can read the article &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ccs.neu.edu/home/viola/pix/nathan-never-press&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;My first day of high school I was looking for a desk, and the one that was left was occupied by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.marcogenovesi.com/&quot;&gt;Marco Genovesi&lt;/a&gt; (also see &lt;a href=&quot;https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2016/12/10/black-viper/&quot;&gt;previous post about Black Viper&lt;/a&gt;, our other game together, also featured in article). We had both programmed a little the mythical C64.  I had written in basic a fighting game inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2016/08/05/hokuto-no-ken-and-growing-up-in-italy/&quot;&gt;Hokuto No Ken&lt;/a&gt;. It was hand-coded pixellated sprites doing flying martial arts kicks.  It was on a cassette &amp;#8212; I didn&amp;#8217;t have a floppy disk. I would love to see it again, but it seems lost forever. It was my first game, written sometime when I was between 10 and 12.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;If I think back at my schools, from elementary to high, I scream in horror.  There was &lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;/em&gt;.  No play-yard, no props, nothing.  Even the walls! How much does it cost to hang a world map? Instead they were solid color. We were 8-1 or something, every day, including Saturdays, in a room with solid color walls, solid color desks, and a blackboard, and that&amp;#8217;s it. Perhaps no wonder that I exercised my art and craft on what I had. I dismembered floppy disks, cassettes, speakers etc. and stuck them on the wall.  I scribbled all over my desk.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;At some point I got an Amiga 1000 (my trajectory was Spectrum 48K, Commodore 64, Amiga 1000). Naturally I wanted to program, but had &lt;em&gt;zero &lt;/em&gt;leads.  Unlike today, it was very hard to get started.  Interestingly, people more experienced than me had the same complaint, like &amp;#8220;when I was 13 myself good luck finding an assembler.&amp;#8221; Actually, I think things will continue to move in this direction. Even today, learning something isn&amp;#8217;t that easy, and one can imagine how in 20 years you&amp;#8217;ll have tutorials precisely tailored to &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; background, instead of having to zap through youtube to find the small step you&amp;#8217;re missing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;So for a while I was stuck fiddling with startup sequences and shell commands. I remember my parents puzzled at why I wasn&amp;#8217;t doing anything fancy like on the C64.&lt;br /&gt;&amp;#8220;You&amp;#8217;re still at &lt;em&gt;popcli&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8221; (a type of shell, known back then as CLI, command line interface) they told me once &amp;#8212;  I am cursed with good memory.&lt;br /&gt;My reply was &amp;#8220;You need a program to write a program.&amp;#8221; They looked puzzled. (And so was I, after all, I didn&amp;#8217;t need one on the C64.)&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;My turning point occurred when I did one of my stupid things. I was balancing myself on the top beam of a swing. Naturally, I fell, didn&amp;#8217;t land right, and injured my ankle. I was stuck in my room for a month, and one day Marco showed up and brought me the &lt;em&gt;Amiga hardware reference manual&lt;/em&gt;, a book we had overheard was critical.  I thanked him and I remember him saying: &amp;#8220;I am doing it for me.&amp;#8221;  This book became my bible. I thrashed the stupid C compilers, got an assembler, and started &amp;#8220;bashing metal&amp;#8221; and having &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Then there was the store. I don&amp;#8217;t remember how I ended up there. It sold games, so maybe I was just there to buy games.  But I never bought a new game &amp;#8212; only pirate &amp;#8212; so the explanation doesn&amp;#8217;t stand.  Anyway, we were there and the person there was a techno-musician who knew people who wanted to make a game on Nathan Never, a pretty high-profile graphic novel series in Italy.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;To this day I am shocked they didn&amp;#8217;t find anyone else, since as I said it&amp;#8217;s pretty high-profile. Maybe the programmer wanted too much money, or ditched them last moment and they needed the game fast. Who knows. I had just barely started programming on Amiga, but&amp;#8230; I know blitter, I know copper; I am obviously ready for a major project.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;So we signed the contract, and I insisted on some money upfront which I got. A few Ks. The development of the game was covered in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ccs.neu.edu/home/viola/pix/nathan-never-press/&quot;&gt;games magazines, &lt;/a&gt;which other people in our high school were devouring. They were shocked to find out the team was us! Waking around, we would pass by a store and find the box of the game on display.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;As part of my deal I managed to get an Amiga 3000 tower, a one-of-a-kind machine, which for a kid like me was a dream. Before that, I didn&amp;#8217;t have enough memory to play the game from the assembler with the graphics loaded, so when I tested it I would see dots instead of sprites.  Marco, who did the graphics, at the beginning didn&amp;#8217;t have a color monitor, and would pick colors from the hex code, quite cool.  I brought the 3000T to our vacation that summer, and instead of going to the sea (which I hated) I stayed indoor to program.  Naturally, I spent 50% (easily) of that time programming a script that would compile an animation through a landscape of fractal mountains. The final animation was quite cool.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I wish the game was more fun to play.  It isn&amp;#8217;t really my fault: no experience, no time, and crucially the people who imposed the game design on us were not players but exclusively concerned with showing the main character, whose frames occupy most of the memory. More than the game they cared about the graphic novel that came with it in the box.  Of all the people buzzing around the game, I was the only one who actually played computer games (I still do).  Still, of course, I could have improved the gameplay.  Instead, on an ultra-tight deadline, I decided to embark on a 3D &amp;#8220;escape from the tunnel&amp;#8221; last level, something they didn&amp;#8217;t ask for (they were happy with an animation, which would have cost me zero effort) and that probably almost noone has seen, since to get there you need to beat two grueling platform levels a puzzle level, with one life and no save state.  (The 3D level starts at 20:09 in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ccs.neu.edu/home/viola/movies/NathanNever.mp4&quot;&gt;this long play&lt;/a&gt;.) And this is what it means to be 14.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;On the bright side, however, perhaps the game has its unique charm, and today it can be played on a hard disk through the emulator, even though the game was not designed to be installed on a hard disk.  And this is great because playing the game from the disks is &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; painful, despite or in part because of a crazy color hack to make a 3D &amp;#8220;change disk&amp;#8221; message (another uncalled-for feature). And it&amp;#8217;s a good feeling that after 30+ years some people are still watching and playing the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Manu&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-05 16:17:22 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Emanuele Viola</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Artificial Intelligence Just Lost a Leader</title>
  <guid>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=20980</guid>
  <link>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/02/05/artificial-intelligence-just-lost-a-leader/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;
&lt;font color=&quot;#0044cc&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Plus a position-search announcement from NSF&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;font color=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Schank just passed away. Roger was a top leader of AI. I overlapped with him for my time at Yale. In 1974, he became a professor of computer science and psychology at Yale University. In 1981, Schank became Chairman of Computer Science at Yale and director of the Yale Artificial Intelligence Project. I was gone by then off to Berkeley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/02/05/artificial-intelligence-just-lost-a-leader/rs-2/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-20982&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;20982&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/02/05/artificial-intelligence-just-lost-a-leader/rs-2/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/rs.jpeg?fit=268%2C188&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;268,188&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;rs&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/rs.jpeg?fit=268%2C188&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/rs.jpeg?fit=268%2C188&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/rs.jpeg?resize=268%2C188&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;268&quot; height=&quot;188&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-full wp-image-20982&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Brockman &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edge.org/3rd_culture/schank/schank_index.html#:~:text=Roger%20Schank%20is%20a%20computer,to%20deconstruct%20the%20human%20mind.&quot;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt;: He is a computer scientist and cognitive psychologist who has worked in the AI field for twenty-five years. Like Marvin Minsky, he takes the strong AI view, but rather than trying to build an intelligent machine he wants to deconstruct the human mind. He wants to know, in particular, how natural language&amp;#8212; one&amp;#8217;s mother tongue &amp;#8212; is processed, how memory works, and how learning occurs. Schank thinks of the human mind as a learning device, and he thinks that it is being taught in the wrong way. He is something of a gadfly; he deplores the curriculum-based, drill-oriented methods in today&amp;#8217;s schools, and his most recent contributions have been in the area of education, looking at ways to use computers to enhance the learning process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roger&amp;#8217;s View&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger was a scary guy&amp;#8212;especially for junior theory faculty like me. I did get along with Roger and he did support me when I was up for tenure. But he was scary no matter what. Part of the issue was that Roger did not think much of any research that was not AI based. Theory was not a top issue in his view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beat Roger Out&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Yale once Schank walked into Alan Perlis&amp;#8217;s office and told Alan that he had thought about some post-doc position we had funding for. Schank began to explain to Perlis that he, Roger, had a couple of ideas of who he planned to hire to fill this position&amp;#8212;of course the position was his. Perlis waved him off and said,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lipton already has found a candidate and the position is gone.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was not there, so all this is second-hand from Perlis, but I can imagine that Roger was not pleased&amp;#8212;in his mind all resources of the department should have gone to build up the AI group. Roger was initially upset, but after this event he acted differently toward me. He treated me with more respect&amp;#8212;in general theory was not his type of research. I always thought that he respected someone who &amp;#8220;beat&amp;#8221; him at the resource game, since he was such a strong player. I probably should not do it again, but doing it once was cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Years later, after Roger had moved to Northwestern University, he tried hard to hire me. Perhaps I should have gone. Oh well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Problems&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to announce this from Dilma Da Silva:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/02/05/artificial-intelligence-just-lost-a-leader/dd-2/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-20983&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;20983&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/02/05/artificial-intelligence-just-lost-a-leader/dd-2/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/dd.jpeg?fit=299%2C168&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;299,168&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;dd&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/dd.jpeg?fit=299%2C168&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/dd.jpeg?fit=299%2C168&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/dd.jpeg?resize=299%2C168&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;299&quot; height=&quot;168&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-full wp-image-20983&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The Division Director, Computing and Communication Foundations (CCF) of NSF: NSF/CCF is looking for an IPA (rotator) Program Director (PD) for the Algorithm Foundation cluster. The job posting for the IPA PD position is available at here. My colleague Tracy Kimbrel and I will be happy to address any questions that potential applicants may have.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
[sourced Brockman quote, added subtitle for NSF announcement]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By rjlipton&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-05 15:03:39 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Richard Lipton</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>TR23-008 |  Limits of structures and Total NP Search Problems | 

	Ond?ej Ježil</title>
  <guid>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/008</guid>
  <link>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/008</link>
  <description>
    For a class of finite graphs, we define a limit object relative to some computationally restricted class of functions. The properties of the limit object then reflect how a computationally restricted viewer &amp;quot;sees&amp;quot; a generic instance from the class. The construction uses Krají?ek&amp;#39;s forcing with random variables [7]. We prove sufficient conditions for universal and existential sentences to be valid in the limit, provide several examples, and prove that such a limit object can then be expanded to a model of weak arithmetic. We then take the limit of all finite pointed paths to obtain a model of arithmetic where the problem OntoWeakPigeon is total but Leaf (the complete problem for $\textbf{PPA}$) is not. This can be viewed as a logical separation of the oracle classes of total NP search problems, which in our setting implies standard nonreducibility of Leaf to OntoWeakPigeon.
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-05 08:30:13 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>ECCC Papers</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Thursday, Feb 9th, 2023 — Amit Chakrabarti from Dartmouth College</title>
  <guid>http://dstheory.wordpress.com/?p=147</guid>
  <link>https://dstheory.wordpress.com/2023/02/04/thursday-feb-9th-2023-amit-chakrabarti-from-dartmouth-college/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;has-text-align-justify&quot;&gt;The next &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot; href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/dstheory/home&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Foundations of Data Science&lt;/a&gt; virtual talk series on recent advances in &lt;em&gt;adversarially robust streaming&lt;/em&gt; will take place on &lt;strong&gt;Thursday, February 9th&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;strong&gt;2:00 PM Pacific Time&lt;/strong&gt; (17:00 Eastern Time, 23:59 Central European Time, 22:00 UTC). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.dartmouth.edu/~ac&quot;&gt;Amit Chakrabarti&lt;/a&gt; from&lt;strong&gt; Dartmouth College&lt;/strong&gt; will talk about &lt;em&gt;“How to color your adversary&amp;#8217;s graph”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/dstheory&quot;&gt;Details of the talk (Zoom link) are available here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;has-text-align-justify&quot;&gt;An n-vertex graph with maximum degree D is (D+1)-colorable: an almost trivial combinatorial result, with an equally simple greedy algorithm to produce a (D+1)-coloring. However, given a stream of edges of such a graph, can we maintain a valid (D+1)-coloring as the edges arrive, while using not much more than O(n) space? What if the edges are chosen by an adversary who can look at our current coloring and add additional edges to try to confound us? This is the newly-popular setting of adversarially robust streaming algorithms and this talk is about the coloring problem in this setting.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;has-text-align-justify&quot;&gt;We obtain upper and lower bound results for this problem. In O(n polylog n) space, we can maintain an O(D^(5/2))-coloring of such an adversarial graph. On the other hand, every adversarially robust coloring algorithm under the same space limitation must spend Omega(D^2) colors. We in fact prove more general. results that trade off the space usage against the color budget.&amp;nbsp; One interesting by-product of our work is that in combination with the celebrated Assadi-Chen-Khanna algorithm (SODA 2019), it provides the first separation between randomized and deterministic algorithms for the (ordinary, non-robust) streaming graph coloring problem.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Based on joint works [C.-Ghosh-Stoeckl] and [Assadi-C.-Ghosh-Stoeckl].&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;The series is supported by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1934846&amp;amp;HistoricalAwards=false&quot;&gt;NSF HDR TRIPODS Grant 1934846&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By dstheory&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-04 19:49:34 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Foundation of Data Science - Virtual Talk Series</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Postdoc at IST Austria (apply by March 15, 2023)</title>
  <guid>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/02/03/postdoc-at-ist-austria-apply-by-march-15-2023/</guid>
  <link>https://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/02/03/postdoc-at-ist-austria-apply-by-march-15-2023/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;Postdoctorial positions at IST Austria are available funded by the ERC Advanced Grant &amp;#8220;Modern Dynamic Data Structures, led by Prof. Monika Henzinger&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://ist.ac.at/en/job/postdoc-research-group-monika-henzinger/&quot;&gt;https://ist.ac.at/en/job/postdoc-research-group-monika-henzinger/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: monika.henzinger@ista.ac.at&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-03 12:26:50 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>CCI: jobs</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>TR23-007 |  Extended Nullstellensatz proof systems | 

	Jan  Krajicek</title>
  <guid>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/007</guid>
  <link>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/007</link>
  <description>
    For a finite set $\cal F$ of polynomials over a fixed finite prime field of size  $p$ containing all polynomials $x^2 - x$, a Nullstellensatz proof of the unsolvability of the system
$$
	f = 0\ ,\ \mbox{ all } f \in {\cal F}
$$
is a linear combination $\sum_{f \in {\cal F}} \ h_f \cdot f$ that equals to $1$ in the ring of polynomials. The measure of complexity of such a proof is its degree: $\max_f deg(h_f f)$.

We study the problem to establish degree lower bounds for some {\em extended} NS proof systems: these systems prove the unsolvability of $\cal F$ by proving the unsolvability of a bigger set ${\cal F}\cup {\cal E}$, where set $\cal E$ may use more variables $r$ and contains polynomials $r^p - r$ for them, and satisfies the following soundness condition:
 
-- Any $0,1$-assignment ${\overline a}$ to variables ${\overline x}$ can be appended by an assignment ${\overline b}$ to variables $\overline r$ such that for all $g \in {\cal E}$ it holds that $g(\overline a, \overline b) = 0$.

We define a notion of pseudo-solutions of $\cal F$ and prove that the existence of pseudo-solutions with suitable parameters implies lower bounds for two extended NS proof systems ENS and UENS defined in Buss et al. (1996/97). Further we give a combinatorial example of $\cal F$ and candidate pseudo-solutions based on the pigeonhole principle.
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-03 08:33:12 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>ECCC Papers</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>This Game Is Not Going To Analyze Itself</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01145</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01145</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Adler_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Aviv Adler&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ani_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Joshua Ani&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chung_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Lily Chung&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Coulombe_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Michael Coulombe&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Demaine_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Erik D. Demaine&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Diomidov_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yevhenii Diomidov&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hendrickson_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Dylan Hendrickson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lynch_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jayson Lynch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analyze the puzzle video game This Game Is Not Going To Load Itself, where
the player routes data packets of three different colors from given sources to
given sinks of the correct color. Given the sources, sinks, and some previously
placed arrow tiles, we prove that the game is in Sigma_2^P; in NP for sources
of equal period; NP-complete for three colors and six equal-period sources with
player input; and even without player input, simulating the game is both NP-
and coNP-hard for two colors and many sources with different periods. On the
other hand, we characterize which locations for three data sinks admit a
perfect placement of arrow tiles that guarantee correct routing no matter the
placement of the data sources, effectively solving most instances of the game
as it is normally played.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-03 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Order-Preserving Squares in Strings</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.00724</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.00724</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gawrychowski_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Pawe&amp;#x142; Gawrychowski&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ghazawi_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Samah Ghazawi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Landau_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Gad M. Landau&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An order-preserving square in a string is a fragment of the form $uv$ where
$u\neq v$ and $u$ is order-isomorphic to $v$. We show that a string $w$ of
length $n$ over an alphabet of size $\sigma$ contains $\mathcal{O}(\sigma n)$
order-preserving squares that are distinct as words. This improves the upper
bound of $\mathcal{O}(\sigma^{2}n)$ by Kociumaka, Radoszewski, Rytter, and
Wale\&#39;n [TCS 2016]. Further, for every $\sigma$ and $n$ we exhibit a string
with $\Omega(\sigma n)$ order-preserving squares that are distinct as words,
thus establishing that our upper bound is asymptotically tight. Finally, we
design an $\mathcal{O}(\sigma n)$ time algorithm that outputs all
order-preserving squares that occur in a given string and are distinct as
words. By our lower bound, this is optimal in the worst case.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-03 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A Universal Technique for Machine-Certified Proofs of Linearizable Algorithms</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.00737</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.00737</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Jayanti_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Prasad Jayanti&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Jayanti_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Siddhartha Jayanti&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Yavuz_U/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ugur Y. Yavuz&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hernandez_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Lizzie Hernandez&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Linearizability has been the long standing gold standard for consistency in
concurrent data structures. However, proofs of linearizability can be long and
intricate, hard to produce, and extremely time consuming even to verify. In
this work, we address this issue by introducing simple $universal$, $sound$,
and $complete$ proof methods for producing machine-verifiable proofs of
linearizability and its close cousin, strong linearizability. Universality
means that our method works for any object type; soundness means that an
algorithm can be proved correct by our method only if it is linearizable (resp.
strong linearizable); and completeness means that any linearizable (resp.
strong linearizable) implementation can be proved so using our method. We
demonstrate the simplicity and power of our method by producing proofs of
linearizability for the Herlihy-Wing queue and Jayanti&#39;s single-scanner
snapshot, as well as a proof of strong linearizability of the Jayanti-Tarjan
union-find object. All three of these proofs are machine-verified by TLAPS (the
Temporal Logic of Actions Proof System).
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-03 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Constant RMR Recoverable Mutex under System-wide Crashes</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.00748</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.00748</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Jayanti_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Prasad Jayanti&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Jayanti_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Siddhartha Jayanti&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Joshi_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Anup Joshi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We design two Recoverable Mutual Exclusion (RME) locks for the system-wide
crash model. Our first algorithm requires only $O(1)$ space per process, and
achieves $O(1)$ worst-case RMR complexity in the CC model. Our second algorithm
enhances the first algorithm to achieve (the same) $O(1)$ space per process and
$O(1)$ worst-case RMR complexity in both the CC and DSM models. Furthermore,
both algorithms allow dynamically created threads of arbitrary names to join
the protocol and access the locks. To our knowledge, these are the only RME
locks to achieve worst-case $O(1)$ RMR complexity assuming nothing more than
standard hardware support. In light of Chan and Woelfel&#39;s $\Omega(\log n /
\log\log n)$ worst-case RMR lower bound for RME in the individual crash model,
our results show a separation between the system-wide crash and individual
crash models in worst-case RMR complexity in both the CC and DSM models.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-02-03 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
