<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Theory of Computing Report</title>
  <link></link>
  <language>en</language>
  <description></description>


<item>
  <title>postdoc positions in Algorithms and Complexity at Algorithms and Compleixty Group, IRIF, Paris, France (apply by November 1, 2022)</title>
  <guid>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/10/07/postdoc-positions-in-algorithms-and-complexity-at-algorithms-and-compleixty-group-irif-paris-france-apply-by-november-1-2022/</guid>
  <link>https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/10/07/postdoc-positions-in-algorithms-and-complexity-at-algorithms-and-compleixty-group-irif-paris-france-apply-by-november-1-2022/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;The Algorithms and Complexity group of IRIF ( &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.irif.fr/en/equipes/algocomp/index&quot;&gt;https://www.irif.fr/en/equipes/algocomp/index&lt;/a&gt; ), Paris, France, is seeking excellent candidates for one or more postdoctoral positions in classical and quantum computing, with a usual starting date of September-October 2023 (but possibly negotiable). Knowledge of French is not necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.irif.fr/en/postes/postdoc&quot;&gt;https://www.irif.fr/en/postes/postdoc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: adiro@irif.fr&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-07 08:36:39 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>CCI: jobs</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Transformers Implement First-Order Logic with Majority Quantifiers</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02671</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02671</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Merrill_W/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;William Merrill&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sabharwal_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ashish Sabharwal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Characterizing the implicit structure of the computation within neural
networks is a foundational problem in the area of deep learning
interpretability. Can their inner decision process be captured symbolically in
some familiar logic? We show that any transformer neural network can be
translated into an equivalent fixed-size first-order logic formula which may
also use majority quantifiers. The idea is to simulate transformers with highly
uniform threshold circuits and leverage known theoretical connections between
circuits and logic. Our findings also reveal the surprising fact that the
entire transformer computation can be reduced merely to the division of two
(large) integers. While our results are most pertinent for transformers, they
apply equally to a broader class of neural network architectures, namely those
with a fixed-depth uniform computation graph made up of standard neural net
components, which includes feedforward and convolutional networks.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-07 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>NLTS Hamiltonians from classical LTCs</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02999</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02999</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+He_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zhiyang He&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Nirkhe_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Chinmay Nirkhe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We provide a completely self-contained construction of a family of NLTS
Hamiltonians [Freedman and Hastings, 2014] based on ideas from [Anshu,
Breuckmann, and Nirkhe, 2022], [Cross, He, Natarajan, Szegedy, and Zhu, 2022]
and [Eldar and Harrow, 2017]. Crucially, it does not require optimal-parameter
quantum LDPC codes and can be built from simple classical LTCs such as the
repetition code on an expander graph. Furthermore, it removes the constant-rate
requirement from the construction of Anshu, Breuckmann, and Nirkhe.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-07 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Romeo and Juliet Meeting in Forest Like Regions</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02582</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02582</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Misra_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Neeldhara Misra&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mulpuri_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Manas Mulpuri&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Tale_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Prafullkumar Tale&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Viramgami_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Gaurav Viramgami&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The game of rendezvous with adversaries is a game on a graph played by two
players: Facilitator and Divider. Facilitator has two agents and Divider has a
team of $k \ge 1$ agents. While the initial positions of Facilitator&#39;s agents
are fixed, Divider gets to select the initial positions of his agents. Then,
they take turns to move their agents to adjacent vertices (or stay put) with
Facilitator&#39;s goal to bring both her agents at same vertex and Divider&#39;s goal
to prevent it. The computational question of interest is to determine if
Facilitator has a winning strategy against Divider with $k$ agents. Fomin,
Golovach, and Thilikos [WG, 2021] introduced this game and proved that it is
PSPACE-hard and co-W[2]-hard parameterized by the number of agents.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This hardness naturally motivates the structural parameterization of the
problem. The authors proved that it admits an FPT algorithm when parameterized
by the modular width and the number of allowed rounds. However, they left open
the complexity of the problem from the perspective of other structural
parameters. In particular, they explicitly asked whether the problem admits an
FPT or XP-algorithm with respect to the treewidth of the input graph. We answer
this question in the negative and show that Rendezvous is co-NP-hard even for
graphs of constant treewidth. Further, we show that the problem is co-W[1]-hard
when parameterized by the feedback vertex set number and the number of agents,
and is unlikely to admit a polynomial kernel when parameterized by the vertex
cover number and the number of agents. Complementing these hardness results, we
show that the Rendezvous is FPT when parameterized by both the vertex cover
number and the solution size. Finally, for graphs of treewidth at most two and
girds, we show that the problem can be solved in polynomial time.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-07 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>$(1-\epsilon)$-approximate fully dynamic densest subgraph: linear space and faster update time</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02611</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02611</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chekuri_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Chandra Chekuri&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Quanrud_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Kent Quanrud&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We consider the problem of maintaining a $(1-\epsilon)$-approximation to the
densest subgraph (DSG) in an undirected multigraph as it undergoes edge
insertions and deletions (the fully dynamic setting). Sawlani and Wang [SW20]
developed a data structure that, for any given $\epsilon &amp;gt; 0$, maintains a
$(1-\epsilon)$-approximation with $O(\log^4 n/\epsilon^6)$ worst-case update
time for edge operations, and $O(1)$ query time for reporting the density
value. Their data structure was the first to achieve near-optimal
approximation, and improved previous work that maintained a $(1/4 - \epsilon)$
approximation in amortized polylogarithmic update time [BHNT15]. In this paper
we develop a data structure for $(1-\epsilon)$-approximate DSG that improves
the one from [SW20] in two aspects. First, the data structure uses linear space
improving the space bound in [SW20] by a logarithmic factor. Second, the data
structure maintains a $(1-\epsilon)$-approximation in amortized $O(\log^2
n/\epsilon^4)$ time per update while simultaneously guaranteeing that the worst
case update time is $O(\log^3 n \log \log n/\epsilon^6)$. We believe that the
space and update time improvements are valuable for current large scale graph
data sets. The data structure extends in a natural fashion to hypergraphs and
yields improvements in space and update times over recent work [BBCG22] that
builds upon [SW20].
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-07 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Cooperative Coverage with a Leader and a Wingmate in Communication-Constrained Environments</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02628</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02628</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hari_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sai Krishna Kanth Hari&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rathinam_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sivakumar Rathinam&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Darbha_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Swaroop Darbha&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Casbeer_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;David W. Casbeer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We consider a mission framework in which two unmanned vehicles (UVs), a
leader and a wingmate, are required to provide cooperative coverage of an
environment while being within a short communication range. This framework
finds applications in underwater and/or military domains, where certain
constraints are imposed on communication by either the application or the
environment. An important objective of missions within this framework is to
minimize the total travel and communication costs of the leader-wingmate duo.
In this paper, we propose and formulate the problem of finding routes for the
UVs that minimize the sum of their travel and communication costs as a network
optimization problem of the form of a binary program (BP). The BP is
computationally expensive, with the time required to compute optimal solutions
increasing rapidly with the problem size. To address this challenge, here, we
propose two algorithms, an approximation algorithm and a heuristic algorithm,
to solve large-scale instances of the problem swiftly. We demonstrate the
effectiveness and the scalability of these algorithms through an analysis of
extensive numerical simulations performed over 500 instances, with the number
of targets in the instances ranging from 6 to 100.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-07 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>What Can We Compute in a Single Round of the Congested Clique?</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02638</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02638</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Robinson_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Peter Robinson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the computational power of one-round distributed algorithms in the
congested clique model. We show that any one-round algorithm that computes a
minimum spanning tree (MST) in the unicast congested clique must use a link
bandwidth of $\Omega(\log^3 n)$ bits in the worst case. This is the first round
complexity lower bound in the unicast congested clique for a problem where the
output size is small, i.e., $O(n\log n)$ bits. Our main technical contribution
is to investigate one-round algorithms in the broadcast congested clique and,
equivalently, the distributed graph sketching model where the nodes send their
message to a referee who computes the output. First, we present a tight lower
bound of $\Omega(n)$ bits for the message size of computing a breadth-first
search tree. Then, we prove that computing a $k$-edge connected spanning
subgraph ($k$-ECSS) requires messages of size at least $\Omega \left(
k\log^2(n/k) \right)$. We also show that verifying whether a given vertex
coloring forms a weak 2-coloring of the input graph requires messages of
$\Omega(n^{1/3}\log^{2/3}n)$ bits, and the same lower bound holds for verifying
whether a subset of nodes forms a maximal independent set or a minimal
dominating set. Interestingly, it turns out that the same class of lower bound
graphs for the distributed sketching model is versatile enough to yield a space
lower bound of $\Omega(n^2)$ bits for verifying symmetry breaking problems such
as weak $2$-coloring in the fully dynamic turnstile model, where the input
arrives as a stream of edges. We also (nearly) settle the space complexity of
the $k$-ECSS problem in the streaming model by extending the work of Kapralov
et al. (FOCS 2017): We prove a communication complexity lower bound for a
direct sum variant of the $\text{UR}_k^{\subset}$ problem and show that this
implies $\Omega(k\,n\log^2(n/k))$ bits of memory for computing a $k$-ECSS.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-07 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Orthogonal Non-negative Matrix Factorization: a Maximum-Entropy-Principle Approach</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02672</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02672</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Basiri_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Salar Basiri&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kapadia_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mustafa Kapadia&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Salapaka_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Srinivasa Salapaka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we introduce a new methodology to solve the orthogonal
non-negative matrix factorization (ONMF) problem, where the objective is to
approximate an input data matrix by the product of two non-negative matrices,
the features matrix and the mixing matrix, while one of them is orthogonal. We
show how the ONMF can be interpreted as a specific facility-location problem
(FLP), and adapt a maximum-entropy-principle based solution for FLP to the ONMF
problem. The proposed approach guarantees orthogonality of the features or the
mixing matrix, while ensuring that both of the matrix factors are non-negative.
Also, the features (mixing) matrix has exactly one non-zero element across each
row (column), providing the maximum sparsity of the orthogonal factor. This
enables a semantic interpretation of the underlying data matrix using
non-overlapping features. The experiments on synthetic data and a standard
microarray dataset demonstrate significant improvements in terms of sparsity
and orthogonality scores of features (mixing) matrices, while achieving
approximately the same or better (up to 3%) reconstruction errors.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-07 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Paging with Succinct Predictions</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02775</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02775</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Antoniadis_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Antonios Antoniadis&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Boyar_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Joan Boyar&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Elias_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Marek Eli&amp;#xe1;&amp;#x161;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Favrholdt_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Lene M. Favrholdt&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hoeksma_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ruben Hoeksma&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Larsen_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Kim S. Larsen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Polak_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Adam Polak&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Simon_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Bertrand Simon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Paging is a prototypical problem in the area of online algorithms. It has
also played a central role in the development of learning-augmented algorithms
-- a recent line of research that aims to ameliorate the shortcomings of
classical worst-case analysis by giving algorithms access to predictions. Such
predictions can typically be generated using a machine learning approach, but
they are inherently imperfect. Previous work on learning-augmented paging has
investigated predictions on (i) when the current page will be requested again
(reoccurrence predictions), (ii) the current state of the cache in an optimal
algorithm (state predictions), (iii) all requests until the current page gets
requested again, and (iv) the relative order in which pages are requested.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We study learning-augmented paging from the new perspective of requiring the
least possible amount of predicted information. More specifically, the
predictions obtained alongside each page request are limited to one bit only.
We consider two natural such setups: (i) discard predictions, in which the
predicted bit denotes whether or not it is ``safe&#39;&#39; to evict this page, and
(ii) phase predictions, where the bit denotes whether the current page will be
requested in the next phase (for an appropriate partitioning of the input into
phases). We develop algorithms for each of the two setups that satisfy all
three desirable properties of learning-augmented algorithms -- that is, they
are consistent, robust and smooth -- despite being limited to a one-bit
prediction per request. We also present lower bounds establishing that our
algorithms are essentially best possible.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-07 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Sequentially Swapping Tokens: Further on Graph Classes</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02835</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02835</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kiya_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hironori Kiya&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Okada_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yuto Okada&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ono_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hirotaka Ono&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Otachi_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yota Otachi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the following variant of the 15 puzzle. Given a graph and two token
placements on the vertices, we want to find a walk of the minimum length (if
any exists) such that the sequence of token swappings along the walk obtains
one of the given token placements from the other one. This problem was
introduced as Sequential Token Swapping by Yamanaka et al. [JGAA 2019], who
showed that the problem is intractable in general but polynomial-time solvable
for trees, complete graphs, and cycles. In this paper, we present a
polynomial-time algorithm for block-cactus graphs, which include all previously
known cases. We also present general tools for showing the hardness of problem
on restricted graph classes such as chordal graphs and chordal bipartite
graphs. We also show that the problem is hard on grids and king&#39;s graphs, which
are the graphs corresponding to the 15 puzzle and its variant with relaxed
moves.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-07 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Scalable Experimental Bounds for Entangled Quantum State Fidelities</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.03048</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.03048</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Aktar_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Shamminuj Aktar&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Bartschi_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Andreas B&amp;#xe4;rtschi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Badawy_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Abdel-Hameed A. Badawy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Eidenbenz_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Stephan Eidenbenz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Estimating the state preparation fidelity of highly entangled states on noisy
intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices is an important task for benchmarking
and application considerations. Unfortunately, exact fidelity measurements
quickly become prohibitively expensive, as they scale exponentially as O(3^N)
for N-qubit states, using full state tomography with measurements in all Pauli
bases combinations.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it is known [Somma et.al. 2006] that the complexity can be
drastically reduced when looking at fidelity lower bounds for states that
exhibit symmetries, such as Dicke States and GHZ States. For larger states,
these bounds have so far not been tight enough to provide reasonable
estimations on today&#39;s (2022) NISQ devices. In this work, for the first time
and more than 15 years after the theoretical introduction, we report meaningful
lower bounds for the state preparation fidelity of all Dicke States up to N=10
and all GHZ states up to N=20 on Quantinuum H1 ion-trap systems using efficient
implementations of recently proposed scalable circuits for these states.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, we give state preparation fidelity lower bounds of (i) 0.46 for
the Dicke State |D10,5&amp;gt; and (ii) 0.73 for the GHZ State |G20&amp;gt;. These match or
exceed exact fidelity records recently achieved on superconducting systems for
the much smaller states |D6,3&amp;gt; and |G5&amp;gt;, respectively. Furthermore, we provide
evidence that for large Dicke States |DN,N/2&amp;gt;, we can resort to a GHZ-based
approximate state preparation to achieve better fidelity.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-07 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Google Supremacy Experiment: Data, Information, Discussions, and Three Questions.</title>
  <guid>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=23316</guid>
  <link>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/10/07/the-google-supremacy-experiment-data-information-discussions-and-three-questions/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yosi Rinott, Tomer Shoham, and I&amp;nbsp; wrote a manuscript regarding our study of the Google 2019 supremacy experiment. This is still a draft and comments or corrections are most welcome. (The paper already incorporates a few comments by the Google team.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/10/cc22a15.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;Google’s 2019 “Quantum Supremacy” Claims: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;Data, Documentation, &amp;amp; Discussion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Gil Kalai, Yosef Rinott, and Tomer Shoham&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; In October 2019, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;Nature &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;published a paper describing an exper&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;imental work that took place at Google. The paper claims to demon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;strate quantum (computational) supremacy on a 53-qubit quantum &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;computer.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;Since September 2019 the authors have been involved in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;a long-term project to study various statistical aspects of the Google &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;experiment.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;In particular, we have been trying to gather the rele&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;vant data and information, to reconstruct and verify those parts of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;the Google 2019 supremacy experiments that are based on classical &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;computations (unless they require too heavy computation), and to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;put the data under statistical analysis. We have now (August 2022) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;concluded the part relating to the gathering of data and information &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;needed for our study of the 2019 Google experiment, and this docu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;ment describes the available data and information for the Google 2019 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;experiment and some of our results and plans.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The manuscript describes the stage of gathering data and information needed for our study and our analysis based on this data will be described separately. Statistical analysis of the Google experiment is already described in our Statistical Science paper&amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/sts836.pdf&quot;&gt;Statistical Aspects of the Quantum Supremacy Demonstration.&lt;/a&gt; (In this paper we mainly rely on data of 12-qubit and 14-qubit circuits.) Some preliminary statistical analysis is also given in Sections 6 and 7 of my paper&amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/laws-blog2.pdf&quot;&gt;The argument against quantum computers, the quantum laws of nature, and Google’s supremacy claims&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Quo Vadis&lt;/em&gt; random circuit sampling&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;Here are three concrete questions about &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;random circuit sampling of a quantum circuit&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;C&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;of the kind discussed in the Google &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;paper &lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;with&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;22 qubits and depth&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;14&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. These three questions refer, of course, to the ability of current &lt;span style=&quot;color:#0000ff;&quot;&gt;quantum computers&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; (it is quite easy to achieve them with classical simulations). &lt;br&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;1. Can humanity produce at present samples which are good approxima&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;tions of the Google noise model or any other specific noise model?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;2. Has humanity reached the ability to produce samples for quantum circuit &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;C&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; fidelity according to the &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;linear cross entropy&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;fidelity-estimator above 0.15?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;3. Has humanity reached the ability to predict, for a quantum circuit&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;C&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;with good accuracy, the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;linear cross entropy&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;fidelity estimator based on the fidelity &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;of the individual components of this circuit?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;The findings of our Statistical Science paper &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;indicate that the answer to the first ques&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;tion is negative. The Google supremacy paper itself and subsequent confirmations &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;present a strong case for a positive answer to the other two questions (even for larger circuits). However, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;there are remaining doubts and concerns that need to be carefully checked, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;and not enough replications to regard the answer as a solid yes.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to check a 20-qubit quantum computer?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.il/en/departments/general/iia-to-establish-israeli-quantum-computing-center-17-jul-2022&quot;&gt;It was announced&lt;/a&gt; recently that Israel is going to build a quantum computer. It is an interesting question to find a methodology to confirm that a 10-qubit, 20-qubit or 50-qubit quantum computer genuinely performs quantum computation or rather that the experimental data represents classical computation. In our Statistical Science paper we offered a certain blind experiment mechanism, but it still requires that classical simulation be much slower than quantum computing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the new paper we also propose a mechanism for letting other groups test calibration methods (which are crucial ingredients in such experiments) on the Sycamore QC or other NISQ computers. In our discussions, the Google team endorsed both these proposals for future experiments. (See Section 5 of the new manuscript.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Gil Kalai&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-06 21:26:21 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Gil Kalai</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Postdoc at IST Austria (apply by November 15, 2022)</title>
  <guid>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/10/06/postdoc-at-ist-austria-apply-by-november-15-2022/</guid>
  <link>https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/10/06/postdoc-at-ist-austria-apply-by-november-15-2022/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;We are looking for three outstanding, highly-motivated postdoctoral researchers interested in working on combinatorial algorithm, especially in dynamic settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://ist.ac.at/en/job/postdoc-research-group-monika-henzinger/&quot;&gt;https://ist.ac.at/en/job/postdoc-research-group-monika-henzinger/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: monika.henzinger@ist.ac.at&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-06 19:12:28 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>CCI: jobs</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Art and Technology</title>
  <guid>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-6131043346672536750</guid>
  <link>http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/10/art-and-technology.html</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;Last weekend I went to one of Chicago&#39;s jewels, the Art Institute, and saw the opening of a new exhibit by Berlin-based artist Josephine Pryde entitled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artic.edu/exhibitions/2932/the-vibrating-slab&quot;&gt;The Vibrating Slab&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;referring mainly to the phone that constantly tries to gain our attention. The exhibit used photographs and sculptures to tie smart phones to prehistoric rocks. No pictures here because ironically they didn&#39;t allow us to take photos with our &quot;slabs&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After I saw the Pryde exhibit I went to see the artist herself give a presentation. She related a story where she talked about going to the movies and seeing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1745960&quot;&gt;Top Gun: Maverick&lt;/a&gt;, not knowing it is a new release. Tom Cruise, who&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PJqbivkm0Ms&quot;&gt;controlled a computer with hand movements&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;in Minority Report, goes old-school in Maverick. Cruise and several young actors, through various plot contrivances, flew 20th century planes in a movie that could have taken place in the 90s. According to IMBD, at the insistence of Tom Cruise, minimal green screen and CGI aerial shots exist in the film, and even the close up cockpit shots were taken during real in-flight sequences. Old school indeed. Kind of the opposite of say the Disney series &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt8111088/&quot;&gt;The Mandalorian&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;filmed in a soundstage with everything generated by CGI.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pryde&#39;s exhibit looked at the interaction with technology as art. Upstairs from Pryde&#39;s exhibit was art from technology, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artic.edu/exhibitions/9705/david-hockney-the-arrival-of-spring-normandy-2020&quot;&gt;series of prints&lt;/a&gt; that David Hockney created on another slab, the iPad, in Normandy during the early days of the Covid pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table align=&quot;center&quot; cellpadding=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;tr-caption-container&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://artic-web.imgix.net/b8c0f3d0-2abc-4c17-9aba-629d8536e90d/IPD-2221.jpg?rect=0%2C0%2C3564%2C2490&amp;amp;auto=format%2Ccompress&amp;amp;q=80&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;crop=faces%2Cedges%2Centropy&amp;amp;w=1600&amp;amp;h=1118&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; data-original-height=&quot;559&quot; data-original-width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;280&quot; src=&quot;https://artic-web.imgix.net/b8c0f3d0-2abc-4c17-9aba-629d8536e90d/IPD-2221.jpg?rect=0%2C0%2C3564%2C2490&amp;amp;auto=format%2Ccompress&amp;amp;q=80&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;crop=faces%2Cedges%2Centropy&amp;amp;w=1600&amp;amp;h=1118&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;tr-caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;No. 340, 21st May 2020 - David Hockney&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the way from Pryde&#39;s exhibit to the lecture I passed through the Art Institute&#39;s impressionism collection and compared real Monets with the fake one I created with Dall-E. Monet manages to capture a detailed scene with broad brush strokes--if you zoom in the detail disappears. Dall-E can&#39;t quite pull that off.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table cellpadding=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;tr-caption-container&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artic.edu/iiif/2/d39b1026-7d8d-6e6a-738e-8a136b1a0033/full/843,/0/default.jpg&quot; style=&quot;clear: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; data-original-height=&quot;770&quot; data-original-width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;308&quot; src=&quot;https://www.artic.edu/iiif/2/d39b1026-7d8d-6e6a-738e-8a136b1a0033/full/843,/0/default.jpg&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;tr-caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artic.edu/artworks/14634/vetheuil&quot;&gt;Vétheuil&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;by Monet&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table align=&quot;center&quot; cellpadding=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;tr-caption-container&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjZ6-EWvauVOODiC3Q6NtPqk34MFd8yF-m0Pr8qms48vtunPrdnclEYpSdFnlm691u7vTf4qU7EkPCOSaY8NSmfxh6FYsgKUN5QWaAzirVQDaX_Y9kZarqcyCtUafapja3KIy3k6bUd9SrlL83yCOnayQgseDMD3xcCwfPzvb0kimeKIr8FDw/s1024/DALL%C2%B7E%202022-09-17%2014.00.36%20-%20Schloss%20Dagstuhl%20in%20the%20style%20of%20monet.png&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; data-original-height=&quot;1024&quot; data-original-width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;320&quot; src=&quot;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjZ6-EWvauVOODiC3Q6NtPqk34MFd8yF-m0Pr8qms48vtunPrdnclEYpSdFnlm691u7vTf4qU7EkPCOSaY8NSmfxh6FYsgKUN5QWaAzirVQDaX_Y9kZarqcyCtUafapja3KIy3k6bUd9SrlL83yCOnayQgseDMD3xcCwfPzvb0kimeKIr8FDw/w320-h320/DALL%C2%B7E%202022-09-17%2014.00.36%20-%20Schloss%20Dagstuhl%20in%20the%20style%20of%20monet.png&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;tr-caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Monet Dagsthul by Dall-E&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Lance Fortnow&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-06 13:40:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A Counterexample to a Directed KKL Inequality</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02035</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02035</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Dubroff_Q/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Quentin Dubroff&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Nadimpalli_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Shivam Nadimpalli&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Narayanan_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Bhargav Narayanan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We show that the natural directed analogues of the KKL theorem [KKL88] and
the Eldan--Gross inequality [EG20] from the analysis of Boolean functions fail
to hold. This is in contrast to several other isoperimetric inequalities on the
Boolean hypercube (such as the Poincare inequality, Margulis&#39;s inequality
[Mar74] and Talagrand&#39;s inequality [Tal93]) for which directed strengthenings
have recently been established.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-06 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>On Convexity in Split graphs: Complexity of Steiner tree and Domination</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02288</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02288</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mohanapriya_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;A Mohanapriya&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Renjith_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;P Renjith&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sadagopan_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;N Sadagopan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given a graph $G$ with a terminal set $R \subseteq V(G)$, the Steiner tree
problem (STREE) asks for a set $S\subseteq V(G) \setminus R$ such that the
graph induced on $S\cup R$ is connected. A split graph is a graph which can be
partitioned into a clique and an independent set. It is known that STREE is
NP-complete on split graphs \cite{white1985steiner}. To strengthen this result,
we introduce convex ordering on one of the partitions (clique or independent
set), and prove that STREE is polynomial-time solvable for tree-convex split
graphs with convexity on clique ($K$), whereas STREE is NP-complete on
tree-convex split graphs with convexity on independent set ($I$). We further
strengthen our NP-complete result by establishing a dichotomy which says that
for unary-tree-convex split graphs (path-convex split graphs), STREE is
polynomial-time solvable, and NP-complete for binary-tree-convex split graphs
(comb-convex split graphs). We also show that STREE is polynomial-time solvable
for triad-convex split graphs with convexity on $I$, and circular-convex split
graphs. Further, we show that STREE can be used as a framework for the
dominating set problem (DS) on split graphs, and hence the classical complexity
(P vs NPC) of STREE and DS is the same for all these subclasses of split
graphs. Furthermore, it is important to highlight that in
\cite{CHLEBIK20081264}, it is incorrectly claimed that the problem of finding a
minimum dominating set on split graphs cannot be approximated within
$(1-\epsilon)\ln |V(G)|$ in polynomial-time for any $\epsilon &amp;gt;0$ unless NP
$\subseteq$ DTIME $n^{O(\log \log n)}$. When the input is restricted to split
graphs, we show that the minimum dominating set problem has
$2-\frac{1}{|I|}$-approximation algorithm that runs in polynomial time.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-06 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Faster parameterized algorithms for modification problems to minor-closed classes</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02167</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02167</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Morelle_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Laure Morelle&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sau_I/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ignasi Sau&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Stamoulis_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Giannos Stamoulis&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Thilikos_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Dimitrios M. Thilikos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let ${\cal G}$ be a minor-closed graph class and let $G$ be an $n$-vertex
graph. We say that $G$ is a $k$-apex of ${\cal G}$ if $G$ contains a set $S$ of
at most $k$ vertices such that $G\setminus S$ belongs to ${\cal G}$. Our first
result is an algorithm that decides whether $G$ is a $k$-apex of ${\cal G}$ in
time $2^{{\sf poly}(k)}\cdot n^2$, where ${\sf poly}$ is a polynomial function
depending on ${\cal G}$. This algorithm improves the previous one, given by
Sau, Stamoulis, and Thilikos [ICALP 2020], whose running time was $2^{{\sf
poly}(k)}\cdot n^3$. The elimination distance of $G$ to ${\cal G}$, denoted by
${\sf ed}_{\cal G}(G)$, is the minimum number of rounds required to reduce each
connected component of $G$ to a graph in ${\cal G}$ by removing one vertex from
each connected component in each round. Bulian and Dawar [Algorithmica 2017]
provided an FPT-algorithm, with parameter $k$, to decide whether ${\sf
ed}_{\cal G}(G)\leq k$. However, its dependence on $k$ is not explicit. We
extend the techniques used in the first algorithm to decide whether ${\sf
ed}_{\cal G}(G)\leq k$ in time $2^{2^{2^{{\sf poly}(k)}}}\cdot n^2$. This is
the first algorithm for this problem with an explicit parametric dependence in
$k$. In the special case where ${\cal G}$ excludes some apex-graph as a minor,
we give two alternative algorithms, running in time $2^{2^{{\cal O}(k^2\log
k)}}\cdot n^2$ and $2^{{\sf poly}(k)}\cdot n^3$ respectively, where $c$ and
${\sf poly}$ depend on ${\cal G}$. As a stepping stone for these algorithms, we
provide an algorithm that decides whether ${\sf ed}_{\cal G}(G)\leq k$ in time
$2^{{\cal O}({\sf tw}\cdot k+{\sf tw}\log{\sf tw})}\cdot n$, where ${\sf tw}$
is the treewidth of $G$. Finally, we provide explicit upper bounds on the size
of the graphs in the minor-obstruction set of the class of graphs ${\cal
E}_k({\cal G})=\{G\mid{\sf ed}_{\cal G}(G)\leq k\}$.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-06 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Link Partitioning on Simplicial Complexes Using Higher-Order Laplacians</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01849</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01849</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wu_X/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Xinyi Wu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sarker_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Arnab Sarker&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Jadbabaie_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ali Jadbabaie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Link partitioning is a popular approach in network science used for
discovering overlapping communities by identifying clusters of strongly
connected links. Current link partitioning methods are specifically designed
for networks modelled by graphs representing pairwise relationships. Therefore,
these methods are incapable of utilizing higher-order information about group
interactions in network data which is increasingly available. Simplicial
complexes extend the dyadic model of graphs and can model polyadic
relationships which are ubiquitous and crucial in many complex social and
technological systems. In this paper, we introduce a link partitioning method
that leverages higher-order (i.e. triadic and higher) information in simplicial
complexes for better community detection. Our method utilizes a novel random
walk on links of simplicial complexes defined by the higher-order Laplacian--a
generalization of the graph Laplacian that incorporates polyadic relationships
of the network. We transform this random walk into a graph-based random walk on
a lifted line graph--a dual graph in which links are nodes while nodes and
higher-order connections are links--and optimize for the standard notion of
modularity. We show that our method is guaranteed to provide interpretable link
partitioning results under mild assumptions. We also offer new theoretical
results on the spectral properties of simplicial complexes by studying the
spectrum of the link random walk. Experiment results on real-world community
detection tasks show that our higher-order approach significantly outperforms
existing graph-based link partitioning methods.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-06 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Bicriteria Approximation Algorithms for Priority Matroid Median</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01888</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01888</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Bajpai_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tanvi Bajpai&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chekuri_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Chandra Chekuri&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fairness considerations have motivated new clustering problems and algorithms
in recent years. In this paper we consider the Priority Matroid Median problem
which generalizes the Priority $k$-Median problem that has recently been
studied. The input consists of a set of facilities $\mathcal{F}$ and a set of
clients $\mathcal{C}$ that lie in a metric space $(\mathcal{F} \cup
\mathcal{C},d)$, and a matroid $\mathcal{M}=(\mathcal{F},\mathcal{I})$ over the
facilities. In addition each client $j$ has a specified radius $r_j \ge 0$ and
each facility $i \in \mathcal{F}$ has an opening cost $f_i$. The goal is to
choose a subset $S \subseteq \mathcal{F}$ of facilities to minimize the
$\sum_{i \in \mathcal{F}} f_i + \sum_{j \in \mathcal{C}} d(j,S)$ subject to two
constraints: (i) $S$ is an independent set in $\mathcal{M}$ (that is $S \in
\mathcal{I}$) and (ii) for each client $j$, its distance to an open facility is
at most $r_j$ (that is, $d(j,S) \le r_j$). For this problem we describe the
first bicriteria $(c_1,c_2)$ approximations for fixed constants $c_1,c_2$: the
radius constraints of the clients are violated by at most a factor of $c_1$ and
the objective cost is at most $c_2$ times the optimum cost. We also improve the
previously known bicriteria approximation for the uniform radius setting ($r_j
:= L$ $\forall j \in \mathcal{C}$).
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-06 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The DAG Visit approach for Pebbling and I/O Lower Bounds</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01897</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01897</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Bilardi_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Gianfranco Bilardi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Stefani_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Lorenzo De Stefani&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduce the notion of an $r$-visit of a Directed Acyclic Graph DAG
$G=(V,E)$, a sequence of the vertices of the DAG complying with a given rule
$r$. A rule $r$ specifies for each vertex $v\in V$ a family of $r$-enabling
sets of (immediate) predecessors: before visiting $v$, at least one of its
enabling sets must have been visited. Special cases are the $r^{(top)}$-rule
(or, topological rule), for which the only enabling set is the set of all
predecessors and the $r^{(sin)}$-rule (or, singleton rule), for which the
enabling sets are the singletons containing exactly one predecessor. The
$r$-boundary complexity of a DAG $G$, $b_{r}\left(G\right)$, is the minimum
integer $b$ such that there is an $r$-visit where, at each stage, for at most
$b$ of the vertices yet to be visited an enabling set has already been visited.
By a reformulation of known results, it is shown that the boundary complexity
of a DAG $G$ is a lower bound to the pebbling number of the reverse DAG, $G^R$.
Several known pebbling lower bounds can be cast in terms of the
$r^{(sin)}$-boundary complexity.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A visit partition technique for I/O lower bounds, which generalizes the
$S$-partition I/O technique introduced by Hong and Kung in their classic paper
&quot;I/O complexity: The Red-Blue pebble game&quot;. The visit partition approach yields
tight I/O bounds for some DAGs for which the $S$-partition technique can only
yield an $\Omega(1)$ lower bound.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-06 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Rectangular Ruler Wrapping</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01954</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01954</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lyu_X/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Xing Lyu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gagie_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Travis Gagie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1985 Hopcroft, Joseph and Whitesides introduced the problem of folding a
carpenter&#39;s ruler with $n$ hinged segments of lengths $\ell_1, \ldots, \ell_n$
into an interval of a given length $k$. By {\em folding} we mean that each
hinge must be either straight or folded 180 degrees, with folded hinges
alternating between being folded clockwise and counterclockwise. They showed
this problem is NP-hard in the weak sense by a reduction from {\sc Partition},
gave a pseudo-polynomial-time algorithm for it, and gave an $O (n)$-time
2-approximation algorithm. Gagie, Saeidi and Sapucaia recently considered the
related problem of wrapping the ruler into the interval instead of folding it.
By {\em wrapping} we mean that all the folded hinges must be folded 180 degrees
clockwise. They gave an $O (n)$-time algorithm for this problem, based on the
$O (n \log n)$-time algorithm for {\sc Longest Increasing Subsequence} that
Fredman analyzed and attributed to Knuth, thus answering a question posed by
O&#39;Rourke during the open-problems session of CCCG &#39;21.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopcroft et al.\ and Gagie et al.\ assume the ruler&#39;s segments are lines and
its hinges are points, so a folded ruler has length but zero width. As anyone
who has ever folded something knows, however, making perfect 180-degree folds
is not always possible. In this paper we initiate the study of {\em
rectangular} ruler wrapping, for which all folded hinges are to be folded 90
degrees clockwise instead of 180 degrees and we want the wrapped ruler to fit
in a rectangle of height $h$ and width $w$. We give a quartic algorithm and
then an $O (n^2\,\mathrm{polylog} (n))$-time algorithm.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-06 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Internal Longest Palindrome Queries in Optimal Time</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02000</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02000</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mitani_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Kazuki Mitani&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mieno_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Takuya Mieno&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Seto_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Kazuhisa Seto&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Horiyama_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Takashi Horiyama&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Palindromes are strings that read the same forward and backward. Problems of
computing palindromic structures in strings have been studied for many years
with a motivation of their application to biology. The longest palindrome
problem is one of the most important and classical problems regarding
palindromic structures, that is, to compute the longest palindrome appearing in
a string $T$ of length $n$. The problem can be solved in $\mathcal{O}(n)$ time
by the famous algorithm of Manacher [Journal of the ACM, 1975]. In this paper,
we consider the problem in the internal model. The internal longest palindrome
query is, given a substring $T[i..j]$ of $T$ as a query, to compute the longest
palindrome appearing in $T[i.. j]$. The best known data structure for this
problem is the one proposed by Amir et al. [Algorithmica, 2020], which can
answer any query in $\mathcal{O}(\log n)$ time. In this paper, we propose a
linear-size data structure that can answer any internal longest palindrome
query in constant time. Also, given the input string $T$, our data structure
can be constructed in $\mathcal{O}(n)$ time.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-06 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Computing maximal generalized palindromes</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02067</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02067</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Funakoshi_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mitsuru Funakoshi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mieno_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Takuya Mieno&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nakashima_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yuto Nakashima&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Inenaga_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Shunsuke Inenaga&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Bannai_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hideo Bannai&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Takeda_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Masayuki Takeda&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Palindromes are popular and important objects in textual data processing,
bioinformatics, and combinatorics on words. Let $S = XaY$ be a string, where
$X$ and $Y$ are of the same length and $a$ is either a single character or the
empty string. Then, there exist two alternative definitions for palindromes:
$S$ is said to be a palindrome if: Reversal-based definition: $S$ is equal to
its reversal $S^R$; Symmetry-based definition: its left-arm $X$ is equal to the
reversal of its right-arm $Y^R$. It is clear that if the &quot;equality&quot; ($\approx$)
used in both definitions is exact character matching ($=$), then the two
definitions are the same. However, if we apply other string-equality criteria
$\approx$, including the complementary model for biological sequences, the
parameterized model [Baker, JCSS 1996], the order-preserving model [Kim et al.,
TCS 2014], the Cartesian-tree model [Park et al., TCS 2020], and the
palindromic-structure model [I et al., TCS 2013], then are the reversal-based
palindromes and the symmetry-based palindromes the same? To the best of our
knowledge, no previous work has considered or answered this natural question.
In this paper, we first provide answers to this question, and then present
efficient algorithms for computing all maximal generalized palindromes that
occur in a given string. After confirming that Gusfield&#39;s offline suffix-tree
based algorithm for computing maximal symmetry-based palindromes can be readily
extended to the aforementioned matching models, we show how to extend
Manacher&#39;s online algorithm for computing maximal reversal-based palindromes in
linear time for all the aforementioned matching models.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-06 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Tight Lower Bounds for Problems Parameterized by Rank-width</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02117</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02117</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Bergougnoux_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Benjamin Bergougnoux&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Korhonen_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tuukka Korhonen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nederlof_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jesper Nederlof&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We show that there is no $2^{o(k^2)} n^{O(1)}$ time algorithm for Independent
Set on $n$-vertex graphs with rank-width $k$, unless the Exponential Time
Hypothesis (ETH) fails. Our lower bound matches the $2^{O(k^2)} n^{O(1)}$ time
algorithm given by Bui-Xuan, Telle, and Vatshelle [Discret.~Appl.~Math., 2010]
and it answers the open question of Bergougnoux and Kant\&#39;{e} [SIAM J. Discret.
Math.,~2021]. We also show that the known $2^{O(k^2)} n^{O(1)}$ time algorithms
for Weighted Dominating Set, Maximum Induced Matching and Feedback Vertex Set
parameterized by rank-width $k$ are optimal assuming ETH. Our results are the
first tight ETH lower bounds parameterized by rank-width that do not follow
directly from lower bounds for $n$-vertex graphs.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-06 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Double-Ended Palindromic Trees: A Linear-Time Data Structure and Its Applications</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02292</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02292</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wang_Q/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Qisheng Wang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Yang_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ming Yang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zhu_X/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Xinrui Zhu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The palindromic tree (a.k.a. eertree) is a linear-size data structure that
provides access to all palindromic substrings of a string. In this paper, we
propose a generalized version of eertree, called double-ended eertree, which
supports linear-time online double-ended queue operations on the stored string.
At the heart of our construction, is a class of substrings, called surfaces, of
independent interest. Namely, surfaces are neither prefixes nor suffixes of any
other palindromic substrings and characterize the link structure of all
palindromic substrings in the eertree.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an application, we develop a framework for range queries involving
palindromes on strings, including counting distinct palindromic substrings, and
finding the longest palindromic substring, shortest unique palindromic
substring and shortest absent palindrome of any substring. In particular,
offline queries only use linear space. Apart from range queries, we enumerate
palindromic rich strings with a given word in linear time on the length of the
given word.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-06 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Power of Duality: Response Time Analysis meets Integer Programming</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02361</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02361</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Deppert_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Max A. Deppert&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Jansen_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Klaus Jansen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study a mutually enriching connection between response time analysis in
real-time systems and the mixing set problem. Thereby generalizing over known
results we present a new approach to the computation of response times in
fixed-priority uniprocessor real-time scheduling. We even allow that the tasks
are delayed by some period-constrained release jitter. By studying a dual
problem formulation of the decision problem as an integer linear program we
show that worst-case response times can be computed by algorithmically
exploiting a conditional reduction to an instance of the mixing set problem. In
the important case of harmonic periods our new technique admits a
near-quadratic algorithm to the exact computation of worst-case response times.
We show that generally, a smaller utilization leads to more efficient
algorithms even in fixed-priority scheduling. Our technique can be reversed to
solve the mixing set problem by computing worst-case response times to
associated real-time scheduling task systems. Finally, we also apply our
optimization technique to solve 4-block integer programs with simple objective
functions.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-06 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A Fourier Approach to Mixture Learning</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02415</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02415</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Qiao_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mingda Qiao&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Guruganesh_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Guru Guruganesh&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rawat_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ankit Singh Rawat&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Dubey_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Kumar Avinava Dubey&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zaheer_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Manzil Zaheer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We revisit the problem of learning mixtures of spherical Gaussians. Given
samples from mixture $\frac{1}{k}\sum_{j=1}^{k}\mathcal{N}(\mu_j, I_d)$, the
goal is to estimate the means $\mu_1, \mu_2, \ldots, \mu_k \in \mathbb{R}^d$ up
to a small error. The hardness of this learning problem can be measured by the
separation $\Delta$ defined as the minimum distance between all pairs of means.
Regev and Vijayaraghavan (2017) showed that with $\Delta = \Omega(\sqrt{\log
k})$ separation, the means can be learned using $\mathrm{poly}(k, d)$ samples,
whereas super-polynomially many samples are required if $\Delta = o(\sqrt{\log
k})$ and $d = \Omega(\log k)$. This leaves open the low-dimensional regime
where $d = o(\log k)$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this work, we give an algorithm that efficiently learns the means in $d =
O(\log k/\log\log k)$ dimensions under separation $d/\sqrt{\log k}$ (modulo
doubly logarithmic factors). This separation is strictly smaller than
$\sqrt{\log k}$, and is also shown to be necessary. Along with the results of
Regev and Vijayaraghavan (2017), our work almost pins down the critical
separation threshold at which efficient parameter learning becomes possible for
spherical Gaussian mixtures. More generally, our algorithm runs in time
$\mathrm{poly}(k)\cdot f(d, \Delta, \epsilon)$, and is thus fixed-parameter
tractable in parameters $d$, $\Delta$ and $\epsilon$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our approach is based on estimating the Fourier transform of the mixture at
carefully chosen frequencies, and both the algorithm and its analysis are
simple and elementary. Our positive results can be easily extended to learning
mixtures of non-Gaussian distributions, under a mild condition on the Fourier
spectrum of the distribution.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-06 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Assistant Teaching Professor at CSE at UC San Diego (apply by October 15, 2022)</title>
  <guid>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/10/05/assistant-teaching-professor-at-cse-at-uc-san-diego-apply-by-october-15-2022/</guid>
  <link>https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/10/05/assistant-teaching-professor-at-cse-at-uc-san-diego-apply-by-october-15-2022/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;The University of California San Diego Computer Science and Engineering Department seeks applications for an Assistant Teaching Professor. We seek candidates who have demonstrated that they are promising CSE educators&amp;amp; who are interested in a teaching-focused career. Applicants must have an expectation of completing a Ph.D. in computer science and/or CS education or a related area by July 1, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://apol-recruit.ucsd.edu/JPF03253&quot;&gt;https://apol-recruit.ucsd.edu/JPF03253&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: nherrera@eng.ucsd.edu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-05 22:46:11 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>CCI: jobs</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>TR22-138 |  Robustness for Space-Bounded Statistical Zero Knowledge | 

	Eric Allender, 

	Jacob Gray, 

	Saachi Mutreja, 

	Harsha Tirumala, 

	Pengxiang Wang</title>
  <guid>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/138</guid>
  <link>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/138</link>
  <description>
    We show that the space-bounded Statistical Zero Knowledge classes SZK_L and NISZK_L are surprisingly robust, in that the power of the verifier and simulator can be strengthened or weakened without affecting the resulting class.  Coupled with other recent characterizations of these classes, this can be viewed as lending support to the conjecture that these classes may coincide with the non-space-bounded classes SZK and NISZK, respectively.
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-05 18:48:31 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>ECCC Papers</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>TCS+ talk: Wednesday, October 12 — Venkatesan Guruswami, UC Berkeley</title>
  <guid>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=641</guid>
  <link>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2022/10/05/tcs-talk-wednesday-october-12-venkatesan-guruswami-uc-berkeley/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, October 12th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC). &lt;strong&gt;Venkatesan Guruswami&lt;/strong&gt; from UC Berkeley will speak about &amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;A near-cubic lower bound for 3-query locally decodable codes&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8221; (abstract below). &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to join us live by signing up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/next-tcs-talk&quot;&gt;the online form&lt;/a&gt;. Registration is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; required to attend the interactive talk, and the link will be posted on the website the day prior to the talk; however, by registering in the form, you will receive a reminder, along with the link. (The recorded talk will also be posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/past-talks&quot;&gt;on our website&lt;/a&gt; afterwards) As usual, for more information about the TCS+ online seminar series and the upcoming talks, or to &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/suggest-a-talk&quot;&gt;suggest&lt;/a&gt; a possible topic or speaker, please see &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/&quot;&gt;the website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract: Locally decodable codes (LDCs) allow for ultra-efficient recovery of any single message symbol by querying very few symbols of the associated codeword, even in the presence of a constant fraction of errors. In addition to their appeal for storage and cryptographic applications, locality as a concept drives many connections between coding theory and computational complexity.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;An outstanding challenge concerning LDCs is their optimal encoding length for a desired number q of queries. For q=2, it is known that exponential blow-up in encoding length is necessary (and the simple Hadamard code achieves this). For q &amp;gt; 2, however, there are significant gaps in our understanding. For instance, for 3-query LDCs, the best known constructions have sub-exponential encoding length, whereas the best known lower bound, that has stood for two decades, was only quadratic.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;In this talk, we will describe a near-cubic lower bound on the encoding length of 3-query LDCs. The approach is inspired by and borrows from recent advances in refuting semi-random instances of constraint satisfaction problems.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Joint work with Omar Alrabiah, Pravesh Kothari, and Peter Manohar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By plustcs&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-05 11:43:33 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>TCS+ Seminar Series</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Postdoc  at IIT Bombay (apply by November 1, 2022)</title>
  <guid>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/10/05/postdoc-at-iit-bombay-apply-by-november-1-2022/</guid>
  <link>https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/10/05/postdoc-at-iit-bombay-apply-by-november-1-2022/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;We have two postdoc positions in the broad area of Algorithms, Complexity, and Cryptography. More about our research group can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cse.iitb.ac.in/~theory/&quot;&gt;https://www.cse.iitb.ac.in/~theory/&lt;/a&gt;. The positions can be for up to two years. Besides a competitive salary, it comes with a travel support for international and national conferences. To apply one needs to submit a CV, a research statement and two references.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iitb.ac.in/en/careers/institute-post-doctoral-fellows-recruitment&quot;&gt;https://www.iitb.ac.in/en/careers/institute-post-doctoral-fellows-recruitment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: rgurjar@cse.iitb.ac.in&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-05 07:11:42 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>CCI: jobs</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Notions of Tensor Rank</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01183</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01183</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Juvekar_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mandar Juvekar&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nadjimzadah_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Arian Nadjimzadah&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tensors, or multi-linear forms, are important objects in a variety of areas
from analytics, to combinatorics, to computational complexity theory. Notions
of tensor rank aim to quantify the &quot;complexity&quot; of these forms, and are thus
also important. While there is one single definition of rank that completely
captures the complexity of matrices (and thus linear transformations), there is
no definitive analog for tensors. Rather, many notions of tensor rank have been
defined over the years, each with their own set of uses. In this paper we
survey the popular notions of tensor rank. We give a brief history of their
introduction, motivating their existence, and discuss some of their
applications in computer science. We also give proof sketches of recent results
by Lovett, and Cohen and Moshkovitz, which prove asymptotic equivalence between
three key notions of tensor rank over finite fields with at least three
elements.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>On the hull and interval numbers of oriented graphs</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01598</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01598</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Araujo_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;J. Araujo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Maia_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;A. K. Maia&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Medeiros_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;P. P. Medeiros&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Penso_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;L. Penso&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this work, for a given oriented graph $D$, we study its interval and hull
numbers, denoted by ${in}(D)$ and ${hn}(D)$, respectively, in the geodetic,
${P_3}$ and ${P_3^*}$ convexities. This last one, we believe to be formally
defined and first studied in this paper, although its undirected version is
well-known in the literature. Concerning bounds, for a strongly oriented graph
$D$, we prove that ${hn_g}(D)\leq m(D)-n(D)+2$ and that there is a strongly
oriented graph such that ${hn_g}(D) = m(D)-n(D)$. We also determine exact
values for the hull numbers in these three convexities for tournaments, which
imply polynomial-time algorithms to compute them. These results allows us to
deduce polynomial-time algorithms to compute ${hn_{P_3}}(D)$ when the
underlying graph of $D$ is split or cobipartite. Moreover, we provide a
meta-theorem by proving that if deciding whether ${in_g}(D)\leq k$ or
${hn_g}(D)\leq k$ is NP-hard or W[i]-hard parameterized by $k$, for some
$i\in\mathbb{Z_+^*}$, then the same holds even if the underlying graph of $D$
is bipartite. Next, we prove that deciding whether ${hn_{P_3}}(D)\leq k$ or
${hn_{P_3^*}}(D)\leq k$ is W[2]-hard parameterized by $k$, even if the
underlying graph of $D$ is bipartite; that deciding whether ${in_{P_3}}(D)\leq
k$ or ${in_{P_3^*}}(D)\leq k$ is NP-complete, even if $D$ has no directed
cycles and the underlying graph of $D$ is a chordal bipartite graph; and that
deciding whether ${in_{P_3}}(D)\leq k$ or ${in_{P_3^*}}(D)\leq k$ is W[2]-hard
parameterized by $k$, even if the underlying graph of $D$ is split. We also
argue that the interval and hull numbers in the oriented $P_3$ and $P_3^*$
convexities can be computed in polynomial time for graphs of bounded tree-width
by using Courcelle&#39;s theorem.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Quantum communication complexity of linear regression</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01601</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01601</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Montanaro_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ashley Montanaro&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Shao_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Changpeng Shao&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dequantized algorithms show that quantum computers do not have exponential
speedups for many linear algebra problems in terms of time and query
complexity. In this work, we show that quantum computers can have exponential
speedups in terms of communication complexity for some fundamental linear
algebra problems. We mainly focus on solving linear regression and Hamiltonian
simulation. In the quantum case, the task is to prepare the quantum state of
the result. To allow for a fair comparison, in the classical case the task is
to sample from the result. We investigate these two problems in two-party and
multiparty models, propose near-optimal quantum protocols and prove
quantum/classical lower bounds. In this process, we propose an efficient
quantum protocol for quantum singular value transformation, which is a powerful
technique for designing quantum algorithms. As a result, for many linear
algebra problems where quantum computers lose exponential speedups in terms of
time and query complexity, it is possible to have exponential speedups in terms
of communication complexity.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Complexity of Online Graph Games</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01694</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01694</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Fuchs_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Janosch Fuchs&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Grune_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Christoph Gr&amp;#xfc;ne&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Janssen_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tom Jan&amp;#xdf;en&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Online computation is a concept to model uncertainty where not all
information on a problem instance is known in advance. An online algorithm
receives requests which reveal the instance piecewise and has to respond with
irrevocable decisions. Often, an adversary is assumed that constructs the
instance knowing the deterministic behavior of the algorithm. From a game
theoretical point of view, the adversary and the online algorithm are players
in a two-player game. By applying this view on combinatorial graph problems,
especially on problems where the solution is a subset of the vertices, we
analyze their complexity. For this, we introduce a framework based on gadget
reductions from 3-Satisfiability and extend it to an online setting where the
graph is a priori known by a map. This is done by identifying a set of rules
for the reductions and providing schemes for gadgets. The extension of the
framework to the online setting enable reductions from TQBF. We provide example
reductions to the well-known problems Vertex Cover, Independent Set and
Dominating Set and prove that they are PSPACE-complete. Thus, this paper
establishes that the online version with a map of NP-complete graph problems
form a large class of PSPACE-complete problems.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>An Almost Singularly Optimal Asynchronous Distributed MST Algorithm</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01173</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01173</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Dufoulon_F/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Fabien Dufoulon&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kutten_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Shay Kutten&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Moses_W/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;William K. Moses Jr.&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Pandurangan_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Gopal Pandurangan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Peleg_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;David Peleg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A singularly (near) optimal distributed algorithm is one that is (near)
optimal in \emph{two} criteria, namely, its time and message complexities. For
\emph{synchronous} CONGEST networks, such algorithms are known for fundamental
distributed computing problems such as leader election [Kutten et al., JACM
2015] and Minimum Spanning Tree (MST) construction [Pandurangan et al., STOC
2017, Elkin, PODC 2017]. However, it is open whether a singularly (near)
optimal bound can be obtained for the MST construction problem in general
\emph{asynchronous} CONGEST networks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We present a randomized distributed MST algorithm that, with high
probability, computes an MST in \emph{asynchronous} CONGEST networks and takes
$\tilde{O}(D^{1+\epsilon} + \sqrt{n})$ time and $\tilde{O}(m)$ messages, where
$n$ is the number of nodes, $m$ the number of edges, $D$ is the diameter of the
network, and $\epsilon &amp;gt;0$ is an arbitrarily small constant (both time and
message bounds hold with high probability). Our algorithm is message optimal
(up to a polylog$(n)$ factor) and almost time optimal (except for a
$D^{\epsilon}$ factor). Our result answers an open question raised in Mashregi
and King [DISC 2019] by giving the first known asynchronous MST algorithm that
has sublinear time (for all $D = O(n^{1-\epsilon})$) and uses $\tilde{O}(m)$
messages. Using a result of Mashregi and King [DISC 2019], this also yields the
first asynchronous MST algorithm that is sublinear in both time and messages in
the $KT_1$ CONGEST model.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key tool in our algorithm is the construction of a low diameter rooted
spanning tree in asynchronous CONGEST that has depth
$\tilde{O}(D^{1+\epsilon})$ (for an arbitrarily small constant $\epsilon &amp;gt; 0$)
in $\tilde{O}(D^{1+\epsilon})$ time and $\tilde{O}(m)$ messages. To the best of
our knowledge, this is the first such construction that is almost singularly
optimal in the asynchronous setting.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Designing a parallel suffix sort</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01475</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01475</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chowdhury_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Kunal Chowdhury&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Suffix sort plays a critical role in various computational algorithms
including genomics as well as in frequently used day to day software
applications. The sorting algorithm becomes tricky when we have lot of repeated
characters in the string for a given radix. Various innovative implementations
are available in this area e.g., Manber Myers. We present here an analysis that
uses a concept around generalized polynomial factorization to sort these
suffixes. The initial generation of these substring specific polynomial can be
efficiently done using parallel threads and shared memory. The set of distinct
factors and their order are known beforehand, and this helps us to sort the
polynomials (equivalent of strings) accordingly.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Scheduling with Many Shared Resources</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01523</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01523</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Deppert_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Max A. Deppert&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Jansen_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Klaus Jansen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Maack_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Marten Maack&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Pukrop_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Simon Pukrop&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rau_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Malin Rau&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consider the many shared resource scheduling problem where jobs have to be
scheduled on identical parallel machines with the goal of minimizing the
makespan. However, each job needs exactly one additional shared resource in
order to be executed and hence prevents the execution of jobs that need the
same resource while being processed. Previously a $(2m/(m+1))$-approximation
was the best known result for this problem. Furthermore, a $6/5$-approximation
for the case with only two machines was known as well as a PTAS for the case
with a constant number of machines. We present a simple and fast
5/3-approximation and a much more involved but still reasonable
1.5-approximation. Furthermore, we provide a PTAS for the case with only a
constant number of machines, which is arguably simpler and faster than the
previously known one, as well as a PTAS with resource augmentation for the
general case. The approximation schemes make use of the N-fold integer
programming machinery, which has found more and more applications in the field
of scheduling recently. It is plausible that the latter results can be improved
and extended to more general cases. Lastly, we give a $5/4 - \varepsilon$
inapproximability result for the natural problem extension where each job may
need up to a constant number (in particular $3$) of different resources.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>SicHash -- Small Irregular Cuckoo Tables for Perfect Hashing</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01560</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01560</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lehmann_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hans-Peter Lehmann&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sanders_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Peter Sanders&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Walzer_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Stefan Walzer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Perfect Hash Function (PHF) is a hash function that has no collisions on a
given input set. PHFs can be used for space efficient storage of data in an
array, or for determining a compact representative of each object in the set.
In this paper, we present the PHF construction algorithm SicHash - Small
Irregular Cuckoo Tables for Perfect Hashing. At its core, SicHash uses a known
technique: It places objects in a cuckoo hash table and then stores the final
hash function choice of each object in a retrieval data structure. We combine
the idea with irregular cuckoo hashing, where each object has a different
number of hash functions. Additionally, we use many small tables that we
overload beyond their asymptotic maximum load factor. The most space efficient
competitors often use brute force methods to determine the PHFs. SicHash
provides a more direct construction algorithm that only rarely needs to
recompute parts. Our implementation improves the state of the art in terms of
space usage versus construction time for a wide range of configurations. At the
same time, it provides very fast queries.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Two more shorties</title>
  <guid>https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6739</guid>
  <link>https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6739</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;For anyone living under a rock with no access to nerd social media, Alain Aspect, John Clauser, and Anton Zeilinger have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/physics/2022/press-release/&quot;&gt;finally won the Nobel Prize in Physics&lt;/a&gt;, for their celebrated experiments that rubbed everyone&amp;#8217;s faces in the reality of quantum entanglement (including Bell inequality violation and quantum teleportation).  I don&amp;#8217;t personally know Aspect or Clauser, but Zeilinger &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; graciously hosted me and my wife Dana when we visited Vienna in 2012, even bringing us to the symphony (he knows the director and has front-row seats), and somehow making me feel more cultured rather than less.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;As usual, the recipe for winning the Nobel Prize in Physics is this:&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;(1) Do something where anyone who knows about it is like, “why haven’t they given the Nobel Prize in Physics for that yet?”&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;(2) Live long enough.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Huge congratulations to Aspect, Clauser, and Zeilinger!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;hr class=&quot;wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity&quot;/&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=elham+kashefi&quot;&gt;Elham Kashefi&lt;/a&gt;, my quantum complexity theory colleague and treasured friend for more than 20 years, brought to my attention a &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLScAHNMbbvT9rWujs0Q_lQqiYz0jnx__tSVa7CQZyu3b4t8DXg/viewform&quot;&gt;Statement of Solidarity with Students in Iran from the International Academic Community&lt;/a&gt;.  Of course I was happy to sign the statement, just like I was &lt;a href=&quot;https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=409&quot;&gt;back in 2009&lt;/a&gt; when brave Iranian students similarly risked their lives and freedom for women&amp;#8217;s rights and other Enlightenment values against the theocracy.  I urge you to sign the statement as well.  If enough &lt;em&gt;Shtetl-Optimized&lt;/em&gt; readers disapprove of their brutal repression, surely the mullahs will reconsider!  More seriously though: if any readers can recommend a charity that&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;actually making a difference&lt;/em&gt; in helping Iranians participate in the modern world, I&amp;#8217;d be happy to do another of my matching donation drives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Scott&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-04 16:36:13 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Scott Aaronson</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>PhD Position at University of Edinburgh (apply by October 31, 2022)</title>
  <guid>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/10/04/phd-position-at-university-of-edinburgh-apply-by-october-31-2022/</guid>
  <link>https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/10/04/phd-position-at-university-of-edinburgh-apply-by-october-31-2022/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;Applications are invited for a PhD position in Economics and Computation at the School of Informatics of the University of Edinburgh, to work with Aris Filos-Ratsikas on topics related to game theory, fair division, social choice theory and computational complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please use the supplied URL to apply. Feel free to contact Dr. Filos-Ratsikas directly for additional information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.findaphd.com/phds/project/phd-studentship-in-economics-and-computation/?p147391&quot;&gt;https://www.findaphd.com/phds/project/phd-studentship-in-economics-and-computation/?p147391&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: Aris.Filos-Ratsikas@ed.ac.uk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-04 14:08:37 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>CCI: jobs</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Is it okay for a paper or book to say `for more on this topic see Wikipedia Entry BLAH.</title>
  <guid>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-7262081120052063822</guid>
  <link>http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/10/is-it-okay-for-paper-or-book-to-say-for.html</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;One of the proofreaders for &lt;i&gt;Computational Intractability: A Guide to Algorithmic Lower Bounds&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(available&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hardness.mit.edu/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;made the following objection, which raises some questions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;I object to telling readers to see a Wikipedia Entry.&amp;nbsp; Wikipedia is marvelous, but it is unstable. I have been led astray by short-lived editorial changes made by trolls.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The proofreader is surely correct that&amp;nbsp; `See Wikipedia entry X&#39; should be minimized. And indeed, I have gone through all of the cases we had of such things and tried to minimize them. But there are times when there seems to be no way around it. Or maybe there is but I can&#39;t see it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;a) I want to refer to the set of problems that are (exists R)-complete. The ONLY list I know of is on Wikipedia&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Existential_theory_of_the_reals&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;b) I want to discuss the complexity of the video game braid. There is a nice Wikipedia page about the game braid&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Braid_(video_game)&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. There are some sites that have videos about the game, but not reallyan&amp;nbsp; explanations of it. I DID find a site that looks pretty good,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://strategywiki.org/wiki/Braid&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but is that site more stable than the Wikipedia entry? There did not seem to be an official site. (I had the same issue with&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/15_puzzle&quot;&gt; the 15-puzzle&lt;/a&gt; and some other puzzles that do not seem to have a natural official site).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;c) I want to refer the reader to a list of algorithms for discrete log. Wikipedia has a great site on this&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discrete_logarithm&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;Is there a good article that does the same? Is it behind paywalls?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I tend to thing that the&amp;nbsp; Wikipedia sites above are stable and accurate. It helps that they are not on controversial topics.&amp;nbsp; They should be fine. Articles that are behind paywalls are much worse. As for articles on authors websites- are they more or less stable than Wikipedia?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span face=&quot;Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif&quot; style=&quot;background-color: white; color: #222222; font-size: small;&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By gasarch&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-04 14:05:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Three Open Rank Tenure-Track Faculty Positions at University of Delaware (apply by November 15, 2022)</title>
  <guid>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/10/04/three-open-rank-tenure-track-faculty-positions-at-university-of-delaware-apply-by-november-15-2022/</guid>
  <link>https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/10/04/three-open-rank-tenure-track-faculty-positions-at-university-of-delaware-apply-by-november-15-2022/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;The Department of Computer and Information Sciences at University of Delaware invites applications for an open rank tenure-track positions. Although there is a particular interest in computational biology/bioinformatics/comp materials, candidates in theory will be considered. Candidates in theory/algorithms with possible applications in these areas are especially encouraged to apply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://careers.udel.edu/en-us/filter/?search-keyword=&amp;amp;brand=college%20of%20engineering&amp;amp;category=computer%20%26%20information%20sciences&amp;amp;job-mail-subscribe-privacy=agree&quot;&gt;https://careers.udel.edu/en-us/filter/?search-keyword=&amp;amp;brand=college%20of%20engineering&amp;amp;category=computer%20%26%20information%20sciences&amp;amp;job-mail-subscribe-privacy=agree&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: isafro@udel.edu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-04 04:00:21 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>CCI: jobs</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Faculty at University of Iowa (apply by January 1, 2023)</title>
  <guid>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/10/04/faculty-at-university-of-iowa-apply-by-january-1-2023/</guid>
  <link>https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/10/04/faculty-at-university-of-iowa-apply-by-january-1-2023/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;The University of Iowa Computer Science Department invites applications for multiple tenure- and instructional-track positions effective August 2023. Algorithmic foundations is one of the priority areas in this search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cs.uiowa.edu/jobs&quot;&gt;https://cs.uiowa.edu/jobs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: sriram-pemmaraju@uiowa.edu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-04 02:37:31 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>CCI: jobs</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Multi-Robot Motion Planning for Unit Discs with Revolving Areas</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.00123</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.00123</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Agarwal_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Pankaj K. Agarwal&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Geft_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tzvika Geft&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Halperin_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Dan Halperin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Taylor_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Erin Taylor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the problem of motion planning for a collection of $n$ labeled unit
disc robots in a polygonal environment. We assume that the robots have
\emph{revolving areas} around their start and final positions: that each start
and each final is contained in a radius $2$ disc lying in the free space, not
necessarily concentric with the start or final position, which is free from
other start or final positions. This assumption allows a \emph{weakly-monotone}
motion plan, in which robots move according to an ordering as follows: during
the turn of a robot $R$ in the ordering, it moves fully from its start to final
position, while other robots do not leave their revolving areas. As $R$ passes
through a revolving area, a robot $R&#39;$ that is inside this area may move within
the revolving area to avoid a collision. Notwithstanding the existence of a
motion plan, we show that minimizing the total traveled distance in this
setting, specifically even when the motion plan is restricted to be
weakly-monotone, is APX-hard, ruling out any polynomial-time
$(1+\epsilon)$-approximation algorithm.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the positive side, we present the first constant-factor approximation
algorithm for computing a feasible weakly-monotone motion plan. The total
distance traveled by the robots is within an $O(1)$ factor of that of the
optimal motion plan, which need not be weakly monotone. Our algorithm extends
to an online setting in which the polygonal environment is fixed but the
initial and final positions of robots are specified in an online manner.
Finally, we observe that the overhead in the overall cost that we add while
editing the paths to avoid robot-robot collision can vary significantly
depending on the ordering we chose. Finding the best ordering in this respect
is known to be NP-hard, and we provide a polynomial time $O(\log n \log \log
n)$-approximation algorithm for this problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-04 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Geometry</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Closed cap condition under the cap construction algorithm</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.00198</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.00198</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sandu_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mercedes Sandu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Weng_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Shuyi Weng&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zhang_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jade Zhang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every polygon $P$ can be companioned by a cap polygon $\hat P$ such that $P$
and $\hat P$ serve as two parts of the boundary surface of a polyhedron $V$.
Pairs of vertices on $P$ and $\hat P$ are identified successively to become
vertices of $V$. In this paper, we study the cap construction that asserts
equal angular defects at these pairings. We exhibit a linear relation that
arises from the cap construction algorithm, which in turn demonstrates an
abundance of polygons that satisfy the closed cap condition, that is, those
that can successfully undergo the cap construction process.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-04 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Geometry</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Local and global expansion in random geometric graphs</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.00158</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.00158</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Liu_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Siqi Liu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Mohanty_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sidhanth Mohanty&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Schramm_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tselil Schramm&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Yang_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Elizabeth Yang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consider a random geometric 2-dimensional simplicial complex $X$ sampled as
follows: first, sample $n$ vectors $\boldsymbol{u_1},\ldots,\boldsymbol{u_n}$
uniformly at random on $\mathbb{S}^{d-1}$; then, for each triple $i,j,k \in
[n]$, add $\{i,j,k\}$ and all of its subsets to $X$ if and only if
$\langle{\boldsymbol{u_i},\boldsymbol{u_j}}\rangle \ge \tau,
\langle{\boldsymbol{u_i},\boldsymbol{u_k}}\rangle \ge \tau$, and $\langle
\boldsymbol{u_j}, \boldsymbol{u_k}\rangle \ge \tau$. We prove that for every
$\varepsilon &amp;gt; 0$, there exists a choice of $d = \Theta(\log n)$ and $\tau =
\tau(\varepsilon,d)$ so that with high probability, $X$ is a high-dimensional
expander of average degree $n^\varepsilon$ in which each $1$-link has spectral
gap bounded away from $\frac{1}{2}$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To our knowledge, this is the first demonstration of a natural distribution
over $2$-dimensional expanders of arbitrarily small polynomial average degree
and spectral link expansion better than $\frac{1}{2}$. All previously known
constructions are algebraic. This distribution also furnishes an example of
simplicial complexes for which the trickle-down theorem is nearly tight.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En route, we prove general bounds on the spectral expansion of random induced
subgraphs of arbitrary vertex transitive graphs, which may be of independent
interest. For example, one consequence is an almost-sharp bound on the second
eigenvalue of random $n$-vertex geometric graphs on $\mathbb{S}^{d-1}$, which
was previously unknown for most $n,d$ pairs.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-04 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>An experimental study of algorithms for obtaining a singly connected subgraph</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.00243</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.00243</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zahloote_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ahmed Zahloote&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Saleh_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Al-hasan Saleh&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ghanem_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ayman Ghanem&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hasan_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hiba Hasan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Dreibaty_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Asem Dreibaty&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Abodaraa_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ali Abodaraa&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Suleiman_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nermeen Suleiman&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Naameh_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nour Naameh&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ibrahim_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ali Ibrahim&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+mahfoud_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zeinab mahfoud&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;\begin{abstract}
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\normalsize{\noindent A directed graph $G = (V,E)$ is singly connected if for
any two vertices $v,u \in V$, the directed graph $G$ contains at most one
simple path from $v$ to $u$. In this paper, we study different algorithms to
find a feasible but necessarily optimal solution to the following problem.
Given a directed acyclic graph $G=(V,E)$, find a subset $H \subseteq E$ of
minimum size such that the subgraph $(V,E \setminus H)$ is singly connected.
Moreover, we prove that this problem can be solved in polynomial time for a
special kind of directed graphs.}
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\end{abstract}
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-04 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>On The Relative Error of Random Fourier Features for Preserving Kernel Distance</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.00244</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.00244</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Cheng_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Kuan Cheng&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Jiang_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Shaofeng H.-C. Jiang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wei_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Luojian Wei&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wei_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zhide Wei&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The method of random Fourier features (RFF), proposed in a seminal paper by
Rahimi and Recht (NIPS&#39;07), is a powerful technique to find approximate
low-dimensional representations of points in (high-dimensional) kernel space,
for shift-invariant kernels. While RFF has been analyzed under various notions
of error guarantee, the ability to preserve the kernel distance with
\emph{relative} error is less understood. We show that for a significant range
of kernels, including the well-known Laplacian kernels, RFF cannot approximate
the kernel distance with small relative error using low dimensions. We
complement this by showing as long as the shift-invariant kernel is analytic,
RFF with $\mathrm{poly}(\epsilon^{-1} \log n)$ dimensions achieves
$\epsilon$-relative error for pairwise kernel distance of $n$ points, and the
dimension bound is improved to $\mathrm{poly}(\epsilon^{-1}\log k)$ for the
specific application of kernel $k$-means. Finally, going beyond RFF, we make
the first step towards data-oblivious dimension-reduction for general
shift-invariant kernels, and we obtain a similar $\mathrm{poly}(\epsilon^{-1}
\log n)$ dimension bound for Laplacian kernels. We also validate the
dimension-error tradeoff of our methods on simulated datasets, and they
demonstrate superior performance compared with other popular methods including
random-projection and Nystr\&quot;{o}m methods.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-04 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A Novel Parallel Triangle Counting Algorithm with Reduced Communication</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.00389</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2210.00389</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Bader_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;David A. Bader&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Li_F/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Fuhuan Li&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ganeshan_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Anya Ganeshan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gundogdu_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ahmet Gundogdu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lew_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jason Lew&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rodriguez_O/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Oliver Alvarado Rodriguez&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Du_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zhihui Du&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Counting and finding triangles in graphs is often used in real-world
analytics for characterizing the cohesiveness and identifying communities in
graphs. In this paper, we present novel sequential and parallel triangle
counting algorithms based on identifying horizontal-edges in a breadth-first
search (BFS) traversal of the graph. The BFS allows our algorithm to
drastically reduce the number of edges examined for set intersections. Our new
approach is the first communication-optimal parallel algorithm that
asymptotically reduces the communication on massive graphs such as from real
social networks and synthetic graphs from the Graph500 Benchmark. In our
estimate from massive-scale Graph500 graphs, our new algorithms reduces the
communication by 21x on a scale 36 and by 176x on a scale 42. Because
communication is known to be the dominant cost of parallel triangle counting,
our new parallel algorithm, to our knowledge, is now the fastest method for
counting triangles in large graphs.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-10-04 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
