<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Theory of Computing Report</title>
  <link></link>
  <language>en</language>
  <description></description>


<item>
  <title>Postdocs in Quantum Information Science at Stony Brook University (apply by August 31, 2023)</title>
  <guid>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/11/15/postdocs-in-quantum-information-science-at-stony-brook-university-apply-by-august-31-2023/</guid>
  <link>https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/11/15/postdocs-in-quantum-information-science-at-stony-brook-university-apply-by-august-31-2023/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;Two postdocs in quantum information science, including but not limited to complexity theory, property testing, algorithms, sensing, and program analysis, with an expected start date in May 2023 and a duration of 2+1 years are available. Applicants in these areas or potentially related fields are welcome to apply. The postdocs will work closely with Prof Nengkun Yu and Prof Supartha Podder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: cs.stonybrook.edu&lt;br /&gt;
Email: nengkun.yu@cs.stonybrook.edu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-15 21:29:58 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>CCI: jobs</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>TR22-156 |  Parameterized Inapproximability of the Minimum Distance Problem over all Fields and the Shortest Vector Problem in all $\ell_p$ Norms | 

	Huck Bennett, 

	Mahdi Cheraghchi, 

	Venkatesan Guruswami, 

	Joao Ribeiro</title>
  <guid>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/156</guid>
  <link>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/156</link>
  <description>
    We prove that the Minimum Distance Problem (MDP) on linear codes over any fixed finite field and parameterized by the input distance bound is W[1]-hard to approximate within any constant factor. We also prove analogous results for the parameterized Shortest Vector Problem (SVP) on integer lattices. Specifically, we prove that SVP in the $\ell_p$ norm is W[1]-hard to approximate within any constant factor for any fixed $p &amp;gt;1$ and W[1]-hard to approximate within a factor approaching $2$ for $p=1$.(We show hardness under randomized reductions in each case.)

These results answer the main questions left open (and explicitly posed) by Bhattacharyya, Bonnet, Egri, Ghoshal, Karthik C. S., Lin, Manurangsi, and Marx (Journal of the ACM, 2021) on the complexity of parameterized MDP and SVP. For MDP, they established similar hardness for binary linear codes and left the case of general fields open. For SVP in $\ell_p$ norms with $p &amp;gt; 1$, they showed inapproximability within some constant factor (depending on $p$) and left open showing such hardness for arbitrary constant factors. They also left open showing W[1]-hardness even of exact SVP in the $\ell_1$ norm.
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-15 19:01:27 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>ECCC Papers</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>TR22-155 |  Testing of Index-Invariant Properties in the Huge Object Model | 

	Sayantan Sen, 

	Sourav Chakraborty, 

	Eldar Fischer, 

	Arijit Ghosh, 

	Gopinath Mishra</title>
  <guid>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/155</guid>
  <link>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/155</link>
  <description>
    The study of distribution testing has become ubiquitous in the area of property testing, both for its theoretical appeal, as well as for its applications in other fields of Computer Science, and in various real-life statistical tasks.

The original distribution testing model relies on samples drawn independently from the distribution to be tested. However, when testing distributions over the $n$-dimensional Hamming cube $\left\{0,1\right\}^{n}$ for a large $n$, even reading a few samples is infeasible. To address this, Goldreich and Ron [ITCS 2022] have defined a model called the huge object model, in which the samples may only be queried in a few places.

In this work, we initiate a study of a general class of properties in the huge object model, those that are invariant under a permutation of the indices of the vectors in $\left\{0,1\right\}^{n}$, while still not being necessarily fully symmetric as per the definition used in traditional distribution testing.

We  prove that every index-invariant property satisfying a bounded VC-dimension restriction admits a property tester with a number of queries independent of $n$. To complement this result, we argue that satisfying only index-invariance or only a VC-dimension bound is insufficient to guarantee a tester whose query complexity is independent of $n$. Moreover, we prove that the dependency of sample and query complexities of our tester on the VC-dimension is essentially tight. As a second part of this work, we address the question of the number of queries required for non-adaptive testing. We show that it can be at most quadratic in the number of queries required for an adaptive tester in the case of index-invariant properties. This is in contrast with the tight (easily provable) exponential gap between adaptive and non-adaptive testers for general non-index-invariant properties. Finally, we provide an index-invariant property for which the quadratic gap between adaptive and non-adaptive query complexities for testing is almost tight.
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-15 18:43:10 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>ECCC Papers</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Post-doc at University of Cambridge (apply by December 19, 2022)</title>
  <guid>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/11/15/post-doc-at-university-of-cambridge-apply-by-december-19-2022/</guid>
  <link>https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/11/15/post-doc-at-university-of-cambridge-apply-by-december-19-2022/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;A post-doctoral research position is available to work with Prof. Anuj Dawar on a UKRI-funded (ERC advanced grant replacement) project exploring the limits of symmetric computation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jobs.cam.ac.uk/job/37949/&quot;&gt;https://www.jobs.cam.ac.uk/job/37949/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: anuj.dawar@cl.cam.ac.uk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-15 17:21:22 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>CCI: jobs</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Professor(s) / Associate Professor(s) / Assistant Professor(s) at The Chinese University of Hong Kong (apply by May 31, 2023)</title>
  <guid>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/11/15/professors-associate-professors-assistant-professors-at-the-chinese-university-of-hong-kong-apply-by-may-31-2023/</guid>
  <link>https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/11/15/professors-associate-professors-assistant-professors-at-the-chinese-university-of-hong-kong-apply-by-may-31-2023/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;Applications are invited for:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Department of Computer Science and Engineering&lt;br /&gt;
Professor(s) / Associate Professor(s) / Assistant Professor(s) (Ref: 220002PK) (Closing date: May 31, 2023)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) at the Chinese University of Hong Kong has multiple tenure-track faculty positions at all ranks to pursue new strategic research initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cuhk.taleo.net/careersection/cu_career_teach/jobdetail.ftl?job=220002PK&amp;amp;tz=GMT%2B08%3A00&amp;amp;tzname=Asia%2FHong_Kong&quot;&gt;https://cuhk.taleo.net/careersection/cu_career_teach/jobdetail.ftl?job=220002PK&amp;amp;tz=GMT%2B08%3A00&amp;amp;tzname=Asia%2FHong_Kong&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: dept@cse.cuhk.edu.hk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-15 08:43:36 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>CCI: jobs</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Who first thought of the notion of Polynomial Time?</title>
  <guid>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-2374034479146058976</guid>
  <link>http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/11/who-first-thought-of-notion-of.html</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;(Updated version of&amp;nbsp; &lt;i&gt;Computational Intractability: A Guide to Algorithmic Lower Bound&lt;/i&gt; by Demaine-Gasarch-Hajiaghayi is&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hardness.mit.edu/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Any question like &lt;i&gt;who first though of X &lt;/i&gt;is often hard to answer. I blogged about who first came up with the Fib numbers&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/search?q=Fib&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I&#39;ve heard rumors that IBM had search engines way before Google but could not figure out how to make money off of it. There are other examples.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I had learned that Cobham defined P in the paper &lt;i&gt;The intrinsic computational difficulty of functions&lt;/i&gt;, in 1965. It was The conference on Logic, Methodology, and Philosophy of Science. The paper is&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.toronto.edu/~sacook/homepage/cobham_intrinsic.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; Jack Edmonds had the notion of P in the paper &lt;i&gt;Paths, Trees, and Flowers&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://math.nist.gov/~JBernal/p_t_f.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;in 1965.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While it is true that Cobham defined P in that paper, and he might have been the first one to do so, was the notion somehow around earlier. I first thought the answer was no. Why?&amp;nbsp; Because if you look at Joe Kruskal&#39;s paper on MST&amp;nbsp; (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ams.org/journals/proc/1956-007-01/S0002-9939-1956-0078686-7/S0002-9939-1956-0078686-7.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) you don&#39;t see anything resembling time complexity. No O(E+Vlog V) or whatnot. So I thought that if the notion of&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;this algorithm runs in such-and-such time &lt;/i&gt;was not in the air, then certainly any notion of P could not have been.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hence I was surprised when I accidentally (more on that later) came across the following:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1910 (really, 1910)&amp;nbsp; H.C.Pocklington analyzed two algorithms for solving quadratic congruences and noticed that&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;one took time proportional to a power of the log of the modulus, where as&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;the other took time proportional to the modulus itself or its square root.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;THAT is the distinction between P and NOT-P.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The paper is titled &lt;i&gt;The determination of the exponent to which a number belongs, the practical solution of&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;certain congruences, and the law of quadratic reciprocity. &lt;/i&gt;It appeared in 1910, in the Proceedings of the Cambridge Philosophical&amp;nbsp; Society, Volume 16, pages 1-5. (I could not find it online. If you know of a place online for it, leave a comment.)&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;How did I come across this? And why had I NOT come across this in my roughly 40 years working in complexity theory?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I came across it while reading a blog of Scotts, &lt;i&gt;The Kolmogorov Option, &lt;/i&gt;see&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=3376&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;where Pocklington is mentioned in passing. I am surprised how arbitrary the set of things ones knows can be. I have put the Pocklington story in the Demaine-Gasarch-Hajiaghayi book&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hardness.mit.edu/&quot;&gt;Computational Intractability: A Guide to Algorithmic Lower Bounds&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;so that this knowledge gets to be better known.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By gasarch&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-15 04:18:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Faculty at University of Toronto (apply by January 9, 2023)</title>
  <guid>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/11/15/faculty-at-university-of-toronto-apply-by-january-9-2023/</guid>
  <link>https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/11/15/faculty-at-university-of-toronto-apply-by-january-9-2023/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;The Department of Computer Science at the University of Toronto invites applications for multiple positions. In addition to a number of positions open to all areas of computer science, both at the assistant and at the associate levels, we also have positions targeted to computer security and cryptography, as well as to machine learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.cs.toronto.edu/employment-opportunities&quot;&gt;https://web.cs.toronto.edu/employment-opportunities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: recruit@cs.toronto.edu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-15 03:18:06 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>CCI: jobs</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>On automorphism group of a possible short algorithm for multiplication of $3\times3$ matrices</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06485</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06485</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Burichenko_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vladimir Burichenko&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Studying algorithms admitting nontrivial symmetries is a prospective way of
constructing new short algorithms of matrix multiplication. The main result of
the article is that if there exists an algorithm of multiplicative length
$l\leq22$ for multuplication of $3\times3$ matrices then its automorphism group
is isomorphic to a subgroup of $S_l\times S_3$.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-15 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Stackelberg Game: responses to regular strategies</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06472</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06472</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Byrne_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Thomas Byrne&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the solution to the One-Round Voronoi Game in &lt;a href=&quot;/abs/2011.13275&quot;&gt;arXiv:2011.13275&lt;/a&gt;, we
naturally may want to consider similar games based upon the competitive
locating of points and subsequent dividing of territories. In order to appease
the tears of White (the first player) after they have potentially been tricked
into going first in a game of point-placement, an alternative game (or rather,
an extension of the Voronoi game) is the Stackelberg game where all is not lost
if Black (the second player) gains over half of the contested area. It turns
out that plenty of results can be transferred from One-Round Voronoi Game and
what remains to be explored for the Stackelberg game is how best White can
mitigate the damage of Black&#39;s placements. Since significant weaknesses in
certain arrangements were outlined in &lt;a href=&quot;/abs/2011.13275&quot;&gt;arXiv:2011.13275&lt;/a&gt;, we shall first consider
arrangements that still satisfy these results (namely, White plays a certain
grid arrangement) and then explore how Black can best exploit these positions.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-15 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Geometry</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Faster Walsh-Hadamard and Discrete Fourier Transforms From Matrix Non-Rigidity</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06459</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06459</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Alman_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Josh Alman&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rao_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Kevin Rao&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We give algorithms with lower arithmetic operation counts for both the
Walsh-Hadamard Transform (WHT) and the Discrete Fourier Transform (DFT) on
inputs of power-of-2 size $N$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the WHT, our new algorithm has an operation count of $\frac{23}{24}N \log
N + O(N)$. To our knowledge, this gives the first improvement on the $N \log N$
operation count of the simple, folklore Fast Walsh-Hadamard Transform
algorithm.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the DFT, our new FFT algorithm uses $\frac{15}{4}N \log N + O(N)$ real
arithmetic operations. Our leading constant $\frac{15}{4} = 3.75$ is the first
improvement in over 15 years; it improves on the prior best leading constant
$\frac{34}{9} = 3.777\ldots$ by Van Buskirk from 2004, which in turn improved
on the leading constant of $4$ from the split-radix algorithm of Yavne from
1968 and the leading constant of $5$ from the Cooley-Tukey algorithm from 1965.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our new WHT algorithm takes advantage of a recent line of work on the
non-rigidity of the WHT: we decompose the WHT matrix as the sum of a low-rank
matrix and a sparse matrix, and then analyze the structures of these matrices
to achieve a lower operation count. Our new DFT algorithm comes from a novel
reduction, showing that parts of the previous best FFT algorithms can be
replaced by calls to an algorithm for the WHT. Replacing the folklore WHT
algorithm with our new improved algorithm leads to our improved FFT.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-15 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>On maximal 3-edge-connected subgraphs of undirected graphs</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06521</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06521</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Georgiadis_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Loukas Georgiadis&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Italiano_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Giuseppe F. Italiano&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kosinas_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Evangelos Kosinas&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Pattanayak_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Debasish Pattanayak&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We show how to find and efficiently maintain maximal 3-edge-connected
subgraphs in undirected graphs. In particular, we provide the following
results. $(1)$ Two algorithms for the incremental maintenance of the maximal
$3$-edge-connected subgraphs. These algorithms allow for vertex and edge
insertions, interspersed with queries asking whether two vertices belong to the
same maximal $3$-edge-connected subgraph, and there is a trade-off between
their time- and space-complexity. Specifically, the first algorithm has
$O(m\alpha(m,n) + n^2\log^2 n)$ total running time and uses $O(n)$ space, where
$m$ is the number of edge insertions and queries, and $n$ is the total number
of vertices inserted starting from an empty graph. The second algorithm
performs the same operations in faster $O(m\alpha(m,n) + n^2\alpha(n,n))$ time
in total, using $O(n^2)$ space. $(2)$ A fully dynamic algorithm for maintaining
information about the maximal $k$-edge-connected subgraphs for fixed $k$. Our
update bounds are ${O}(n\sqrt{n}\,\log n)$ worst-case time for $k&amp;gt;4$ and
${O}(n\sqrt{n}\,)$ worst-case time for $k\in\{3,4\}$. In both cases, we achieve
constant time for maximal $k$-edge-connected subgraph queries. $(3)$ A
deterministic algorithm for computing the maximal $k$-edge-connected subgraphs,
for any fixed $k&amp;gt;2$, in $\widetilde{O}(m+n\sqrt{n}\,)$ time. This result
improves substantially on the previously best known deterministic bounds and
matches (modulo $\log$ factors) the expected time of the best randomized
algorithm for the same problem. $(4)$ A linear-time algorithm for computing a
spanning subgraph with $O(n\log n)$ edges that has the same maximal
$k$-edge-connected subgraphs as the original graph.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-15 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Multi-Epoch Matrix Factorization Mechanisms for Private Machine Learning</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06530</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06530</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Choquette_Choo_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Christopher A. Choquette-Choo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+McMahan_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;H. Brendan McMahan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rush_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Keith Rush&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Thakurta_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Abhradeep Thakurta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduce new differentially private (DP) mechanisms for gradient-based
machine learning (ML) training involving multiple passes (epochs) of a dataset,
substantially improving the achievable privacy-utility-computation tradeoffs.
Our key contribution is an extension of the online matrix factorization DP
mechanism to multiple participations, substantially generalizing the approach
of DMRST2022. We first give conditions under which it is possible to reduce the
problem with per-iteration vector contributions to the simpler one of scalar
contributions. Using this, we formulate the construction of optimal (in total
squared error at each iterate) matrix mechanisms for SGD variants as a convex
program. We propose an efficient optimization algorithm via a closed form
solution to the dual function.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While tractable, both solving the convex problem offline and computing the
necessary noise masks during training can become prohibitively expensive when
many training steps are necessary. To address this, we design a
Fourier-transform-based mechanism with significantly less computation and only
a minor utility decrease.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extensive empirical evaluation on two tasks: example-level DP for image
classification and user-level DP for language modeling, demonstrate substantial
improvements over the previous state-of-the-art. Though our primary application
is to ML, we note our main DP results are applicable to arbitrary linear
queries and hence may have much broader applicability.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-15 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Hypercubes and Hamiltonian Cycles of Display Sets of Rooted Phylogenetic Networks</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06549</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06549</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Docker_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Janosch D&amp;#xf6;cker&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Linz_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Simone Linz&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Semple_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Charles Semple&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the context of reconstructing phylogenetic networks from a collection of
phylogenetic trees, several characterisations and subsequently algorithms have
been established to reconstruct a phylogenetic network that collectively embeds
all trees in the input in some minimum way. For many instances however, the
resulting network also embeds additional phylogenetic trees that are not part
of the input. However, little is known about these inferred trees. In this
paper, we explore the relationships among all phylogenetic trees that are
embedded in a given phylogenetic network. First, we investigate some
combinatorial properties of the collection P of all rooted binary phylogenetic
trees that are embedded in a rooted binary phylogenetic network N. To this end,
we associated a particular graph G, which we call rSPR graph, with the elements
in P and show that, if |P|=2^k, where k is the number of vertices with
in-degree two in N, then G has a Hamiltonian cycle. Second, by exploiting rSPR
graphs and properties of hypercubes, we turn to the well-studied class of
rooted binary level-1 networks and give necessary and sufficient conditions for
when a set of rooted binary phylogenetic trees can be embedded in a level-1
network without inferring any additional trees. Lastly, we show how these
conditions translate into a polynomial-time algorithm to reconstruct such a
network if it exists.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-15 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Pareto-Optimal Learning-Augmented Algorithms for Online k-Search Problems</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06567</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06567</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lee_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Russell Lee&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sun_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Bo Sun&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lui_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;John C.S. Lui&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hajiesmaili_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mohammad Hajiesmaili&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper leverages machine learned predictions to design online algorithms
for the k-max and k-min search problems. Our algorithms can achieve
performances competitive with the offline algorithm in hindsight when the
predictions are accurate (i.e., consistency) and also provide worst-case
guarantees when the predictions are arbitrarily wrong (i.e., robustness).
Further, we show that our algorithms have attained the Pareto-optimal trade-off
between consistency and robustness, where no other algorithms for k-max or
k-min search can improve on the consistency for a given robustness. To
demonstrate the performance of our algorithms, we evaluate them in experiments
of buying and selling Bitcoin.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-15 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Approximation Algorithms for Drone Delivery Scheduling Problem</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06636</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06636</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Jana_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Saswata Jana&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mandal_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Partha Sarathi Mandal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The coordination among drones and ground vehicles for last-mile delivery has
gained significant interest in recent years. In this paper, we study
\textit{multiple drone delivery scheduling problem(MDSP) \cite{Betti_ICDCN22}
for last-mile delivery, where we have a set of drones with an identical battery
budget and a set of delivery locations, along with reward or profit for
delivery, cost and delivery time intervals. The objective of the MDSP is to
find a collection of conflict-free schedules for each drone such that the total
profit for delivery is maximum subject to the battery constraint of the drones.
Here we propose a fully polynomial time approximation scheme (FPTAS) for the
single drone delivery scheduling problem (SDSP) and a
$\frac{1}{4}$-approximation algorithm for MDSP with a constraint on the number
of drones.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-15 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Distributed and secure linear algebra -- Master Thesis</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06732</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06732</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mirault_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hugo Mirault&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cryptography is the discipline that allows securing of the exchange of
information. In this internship, we will focus on a certain branch of this
discipline, secure computation in a network. The main goal of this internship,
illustrated in this report, is to adapt a roster of protocols intended to do
linear algebra. We want to adapt them to do algebra for matrices with
polynomial coefficients. We then wish to make a complete analysis of the
different complexities of these protocols.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-15 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Near-Linear Sample Complexity for $L_p$ Polynomial Regression</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06790</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06790</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Meyer_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Raphael A. Meyer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Musco_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Cameron Musco&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Musco_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Christopher Musco&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Woodruff_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;David P. Woodruff&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zhou_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Samson Zhou&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study $L_p$ polynomial regression. Given query access to a function
$f:[-1,1] \rightarrow \mathbb{R}$, the goal is to find a degree $d$ polynomial
$\hat{q}$ such that, for a given parameter $\varepsilon &amp;gt; 0$, $$
\|\hat{q}-f\|_p\le (1+\varepsilon) \cdot \min_{q:\text{deg}(q)\le d}\|q-f\|_p.
$$ Here $\|\cdot\|_p$ is the $L_p$ norm, $\|g\|_p = (\int_{-1}^1 |g(t)|^p
dt)^{1/p}$. We show that querying $f$ at points randomly drawn from the
Chebyshev measure on $[-1,1]$ is a near-optimal strategy for polynomial
regression in all $L_p$ norms. In particular, to find $\hat q$, it suffices to
sample $O(d\, \frac{\text{polylog}\,d}{\text{poly}\,\varepsilon})$ points from
$[-1,1]$ with probabilities proportional to this measure. While the optimal
sample complexity for polynomial regression was well understood for $L_2$ and
$L_\infty$, our result is the first that achieves sample complexity linear in
$d$ and error $(1+\varepsilon)$ for other values of $p$ without any
assumptions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our result requires two main technical contributions. The first concerns
$p\leq 2$, for which we provide explicit bounds on the $L_p$ Lewis weight
function of the infinite linear operator underlying polynomial regression.
Using tools from the orthogonal polynomial literature, we show that this
function is bounded by the Chebyshev density. Our second key contribution is to
take advantage of the structure of polynomials to reduce the $p&amp;gt;2$ case to the
$p\leq 2$ case. By doing so, we obtain a better sample complexity than what is
possible for general $p$-norm linear regression problems, for which
$\Omega(d^{p/2})$ samples are required.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-15 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Deputy Director at DIMACS, Rutgers University (apply by January 6, 2023)</title>
  <guid>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/11/14/deputy-director-at-dimacs-rutgers-university-apply-by-january-6-2023/</guid>
  <link>https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/11/14/deputy-director-at-dimacs-rutgers-university-apply-by-january-6-2023/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;DIMACS, the Center for Discrete Mathematics and Theoretical Computer Science, based at Rutgers University in New Brunswick, New Jersey, USA, seeks a Deputy Director of the Center who would also serve as an Associate or Full Professor in computer science, mathematics, statistics, or another Rutgers department. Fostering diversity and inclusion is part of DIMACSâ€™s culture and mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://go.rutgers.edu/dimacsdeputy&quot;&gt;https://go.rutgers.edu/dimacsdeputy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: spassion@dimacs.rutgers.edu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-14 19:54:33 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>CCI: jobs</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A parameterized halting problem, $\Delta_0$ truth and the MRDP theorem</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06121</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06121</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chen_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yijia Chen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Muller_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Moritz M&amp;#xfc;ller&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Yokoyama_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Keita Yokoyama&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the parameterized complexity of the problem to decide whether a
given natural number $n$ satisfies a given $\Delta_0$-formula $\varphi(x)$; the
parameter is the size of $\varphi$. This parameterization focusses attention on
instances where $n$ is large compared to the size of $\varphi$. We show
unconditionally that this problem does not belong to the parameterized analogue
of $\mathsf{AC}^0$. From this we derive that certain natural upper bounds on
the complexity of our parameterized problem imply certain separations of
classical complexity classes. This connection is obtained via an analysis of a
parameterized halting problem. Some of these upper bounds follow assuming that
$I\Delta_0$ proves the MRDP theorem in a certain weak sense.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-14 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A Closer Cut: Computing Near-Optimal Lawn Mowing Tours</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05891</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05891</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Fekete_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;S&amp;#xe1;ndor P. Fekete&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Krupke_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Dominik Krupke&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Perk_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Michael Perk&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rieck_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Christian Rieck&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Scheffer_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Christian Scheffer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a given polygonal region $P$, the Lawn Mowing Problem (LMP) asks for a
shortest tour $T$ that gets within Euclidean distance 1 of every point in $P$;
this is equivalent to computing a shortest tour for a unit-disk cutter $C$ that
covers all of $P$. As a geometric optimization problem of natural practical and
theoretical importance, the LMP generalizes and combines several notoriously
difficult problems, including minimum covering by disks, the Traveling Salesman
Problem with neighborhoods (TSPN), and the Art Gallery Problem (AGP).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we conduct the first study of the Lawn Mowing Problem with a
focus on practical computation of near-optimal solutions. We provide new
theoretical insights: Optimal solutions are polygonal paths with a bounded
number of vertices, allowing a restriction to straight-line solutions; on the
other hand, there can be relatively simple instances for which optimal
solutions require a large class of irrational coordinates. On the practical
side, we present a primal-dual approach with provable convergence properties
based on solving a special case of the TSPN restricted to witness sets. In each
iteration, this establishes both a valid solution and a valid lower bound, and
thereby a bound on the remaining optimality gap. As we demonstrate in an
extensive computational study, this allows us to achieve provably optimal and
near-optimal solutions for a large spectrum of benchmark instances with up to
2000 vertices.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-14 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Geometry</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>What&#39;s the Situation with Intelligent Mesh Generation: A Survey and Perspectives</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06009</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06009</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Li_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zezeng Li&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Xu_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zebin Xu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Li_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ying Li&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gu_X/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Xianfeng Gu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lei_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Na Lei&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Intelligent mesh generation (IMG) refers to a technique to generate mesh by
machine learning, which is a relatively new and promising research field.
Within its short life span, IMG has greatly expanded the generalizability and
practicality of mesh generation techniques and brought many breakthroughs and
potential possibilities for mesh generation. However, there is a lack of
surveys focusing on IMG methods covering recent works. In this paper, we are
committed to a systematic and comprehensive survey describing the contemporary
IMG landscape. Focusing on 110 preliminary IMG methods, we conducted an
in-depth analysis and evaluation from multiple perspectives, including the core
technique and application scope of the algorithm, agent learning goals, data
types, targeting challenges, advantages and limitations. With the aim of
literature collection and classification based on content extraction, we
propose three different taxonomies from three views of key technique, output
mesh unit element, and applicable input data types. Finally, we highlight some
promising future research directions and challenges in IMG. To maximize the
convenience of readers, a project page of IMG is provided at
\url{https://github.com/xzb030/IMG_Survey}.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-14 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Geometry</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A New Conjecture on Hardness of Low-Degree 2-CSP&#39;s with Implications to Hardness of Densest $k$-Subgraph and Other Problems</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05906</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05906</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chuzhoy_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Julia Chuzhoy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Dalirrooyfard_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mina Dalirrooyfard&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Grinberg_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vadim Grinberg&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Tan_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zihan Tan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose a new conjecture on hardness of low-degree $2$-CSP&#39;s, and show
that new hardness of approximation results for Densest $k$-Subgraph and several
other problems, including a graph partitioning problem, and a variation of the
Graph Crossing Number problem, follow from this conjecture. The conjecture can
be viewed as occupying a middle ground between the $d$-to-$1$ conjecture, and
hardness results for $2$-CSP&#39;s that can be obtained via standard techniques,
such as Parallel Repetition combined with standard $2$-prover protocols for the
3SAT problem. We hope that this work will motivate further exploration of
hardness of $2$-CSP&#39;s in the regimes arising from the conjecture. We believe
that a positive resolution of the conjecture will provide a good starting point
for further hardness of approximation proofs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another contribution of our work is proving that the problems that we
consider are roughly equivalent from the approximation perspective. Some of
these problems arose in previous work, from which it appeared that they may be
related to each other. We formalize this relationship in this work.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-14 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Accelerating Irregular Applications via Efficient Synchronization and Data Access Techniques</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05908</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05908</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Giannoula_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Christina Giannoula&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Irregular applications comprise an increasingly important workload domain for
many fields, including bioinformatics, chemistry, physics, social sciences and
machine learning. Therefore, achieving high performance and energy efficiency
in the execution of emerging irregular applications is of vital importance.
This dissertation studies the root causes of inefficiency of irregular
applications in modern computing systems, and fundamentally addresses such
inefficiencies, by proposing low-overhead synchronization techniques among
parallel threads in cooperation with well-crafted data access policies.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We make four major contributions to accelerating irregular applications in
different contexts including CPU and Near-Data-Processing (NDP) (or
Processing-In-Memory (PIM)) systems. First, we design ColorTM, a novel parallel
graph coloring algorithm for CPU systems that trades off using synchronization
with lower data access costs. Second, we propose SmartPQ, an adaptive priority
queue that achieves high performance under all various contention scenarios in
Non-Uniform Memory Access CPU systems. Third, we introduce SynCron, the first
practical hardware synchronization mechanism tailored for NDP systems. Fourth,
we design SparseP, the first library for high-performance Sparse Matrix Vector
Multiplication on real PIM systems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate that the execution of irregular applications in CPU and
NDP/PIM architectures can be significantly accelerated by co-designing
lightweight synchronization approaches along with well-crafted data access
policies. This dissertation bridges the gap between processor-centric CPU
systems and memory-centric PIM systems in the critically-important area of
irregular applications. We hope that this dissertation inspires future work in
co-designing software algorithms with cutting-edge computing platforms to
significantly accelerate emerging irregular applications.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-14 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Fair Curing and Network Design in SIS Epidemic Processes</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06028</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06028</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Yi_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yuhao Yi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Shan_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Liren Shan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Pare_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Philip E. Par&amp;#xe9;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Johansson_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Karl H. Johansson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper studies efficient algorithms for dynamic curing policies and the
corresponding network design problems to guarantee the fast extinction of
epidemic spread in a susceptible-infected-susceptible (SIS) model. We consider
a Markov process-based SIS epidemic model. We call a curing policy fair if
demographic groups are cured with comparable speeds. We propose a fair curing
policy based on the curing policy of Drakopoulos et al. Since these
optimization problems are NP-hard, finding optimal policies is intractable for
large graphs. We provide approximation guarantees on both curing and fair
curing policies. Moreover, when the total infection rate is large, the original
curing policy includes a waiting period in which no measures are taken to
mitigate the spread until the rate slows down. To avoid the waiting period, we
study network design problems to reduce the total infection rate by deleting
edges or reducing the weight of edges. Then the curing processes become
continuous since the total infection rate is restricted by network design. We
provide algorithms with provable guarantees for the considered network design
problems. In summary, the proposed fair curing and network design algorithms
together provide an effective, fair, and computationally efficient approach
that mitigates SIS epidemic spread in networks.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-14 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A Faster Small Treewidth SDP Solver</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06033</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06033</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Gu_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yuzhou Gu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Song_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zhao Song&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Semidefinite programming is a fundamental tool in optimization and
theoretical computer science. It has been extensively used as a black-box for
solving many problems, such as embedding, complexity, learning, and
discrepancy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One natural setting of semidefinite programming is the small treewidth
setting. The best previous SDP solver under small treewidth setting is due to
Zhang-Lavaei &#39;18, which takes $n^{1.5} \tau^{6.5}$ time. In this work, we show
how to solve a semidefinite programming with $n \times n$ variables, $m$
constraints and $\tau$ treewidth in $n \tau^{2\omega+0.5}$ time, where $\omega
&amp;lt; 2.373$ denotes the exponent of matrix multiplication. We give the first SDP
solver that runs in time in linear in number of variables under this setting.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, we improve the running time that solves a linear programming
with tau treewidth from $n \tau^2$ (Dong-Lee-Ye &#39;21) to $n
\tau^{(\omega+1)/2}$.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-14 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>External-memory dictionaries with worst-case update cost</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06044</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06044</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Das_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Rathish Das&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Iacono_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;John Iacono&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nekrich_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yakov Nekrich&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The $B^{\epsilon}$-tree [Brodal and Fagerberg 2003] is a simple I/O-efficient
external-memory-model data structure that supports updates orders of magnitude
faster than B-tree with a query performance comparable to the B-tree: for any
positive constant $\epsilon&amp;lt;1$ insertions and deletions take
$O(\frac{1}{B^{1-\epsilon}}\log_{B}N)$ time (rather than $O(\log_BN)$ time for
the classic B-tree), queries take $O(\log_BN)$ time and range queries returning
$k$ items take $O(\log_BN+\frac{k}{B})$ time. Although the $B^{\epsilon}$-tree
has an optimal update/query tradeoff, the runtimes are amortized. Another
structure, the write-optimized skip list, introduced by Bender et al. [PODS
2017], has the same performance as the $B^{\epsilon}$-tree but with runtimes
that are randomized rather than amortized. In this paper, we present a variant
of the $B^{\epsilon}$-tree with deterministic worst-case running times that are
identical to the original&#39;s amortized running times.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-14 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Extended Formulations via Decision Diagrams</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06065</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06065</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kurokawa_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yuta Kurokawa&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mitsuboshi_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ryotaro Mitsuboshi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hamasaki_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Haruki Hamasaki&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hatano_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Kohei Hatano&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Takimoto_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Eiji Takimoto&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rahmanian_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Holakou Rahmanian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose a general algorithm of constructing an extended formulation for
any given set of linear constraints with integer coefficients. Our algorithm
consists of two phases: first construct a decision diagram $(V,E)$ that somehow
represents a given $m \times n$ constraint matrix, and then build an equivalent
set of $|E|$ linear constraints over $n+|V|$ variables. That is, the size of
the resultant extended formulation depends not explicitly on the number $m$ of
the original constraints, but on its decision diagram representation.
Therefore, we may significantly reduce the computation time for optimization
problems with integer constraint matrices by solving them under the extended
formulations, especially when we obtain concise decision diagram
representations for the matrices. We can apply our method to $1$-norm
regularized hard margin optimization over the binary instance space
$\{0,1\}^n$, which can be formulated as a linear programming problem with $m$
constraints with $\{-1,0,1\}$-valued coefficients over $n$ variables, where $m$
is the size of the given sample. Furthermore, introducing slack variables over
the edges of the decision diagram, we establish a variant formulation of soft
margin optimization. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our extended
formulations for integer programming and the $1$-norm regularized soft margin
optimization tasks over synthetic and real datasets.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-14 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A Dynamic MaxSAT-based Approach to Directed Feedback Vertex Sets</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06109</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06109</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kiesel_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Rafael Kiesel&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Schidler_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Andr&amp;#xe9; Schidler&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose a new approach to the Directed Feedback Vertex Set Problem
(DFVSP), where the input is a directed graph and the solution is a minimum set
of vertices whose removal makes the graph acyclic.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our approach, implemented in the solver DAGer, is based on two novel
contributions: Firstly, we add a wide range of data reductions that are
partially inspired by reductions for the similar vertex cover problem. For
this, we give a theoretical basis for lifting reductions from vertex cover to
DFVSP but also incorporate novel ideas into strictly more general and new DFVSP
reductions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we propose dynamically encoding DFVSP in propositional logic using
cycle propagation for improved performance. Cycle propagation builds on the
idea that already a limited number of the constraints in a propositional
encoding is usually sufficient for finding an optimal solution. Our algorithm,
therefore, starts with a small number of constraints and cycle propagation adds
additional constraints when necessary. We propose an efficient integration of
cycle propagation into the workflow of MaxSAT solvers, further improving the
performance of our algorithm.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our extensive experimental evaluation shows that DAGer significantly
outperforms the state-of-the-art solvers and that our data reductions alone
directly solve many of the instances.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-14 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Approximate Max-Flow Min-Multicut Theorem for Graphs of Bounded Treewidth</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06267</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06267</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Friedrich_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tobias Friedrich&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Issac_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Davis Issac&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kumar_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nikhil Kumar&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mallek_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nadym Mallek&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zeif_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ziena Zeif&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We prove an approximate max-multiflow min-multicut theorem for bounded
treewidth graphs. In particular, we show the following: Given a treewidth-$r$
graph, there exists a (fractional) multicommodity flow of value $f$, and a
multicut of capacity $c$ such that $ f \leq c \leq \mathcal{O}(\ln (r+1)) \cdot
f$. It is well known that the multiflow-multicut gap on an $r$-vertex (constant
degree) expander graph can be $\Omega(\ln r)$, and hence our result is tight up
to constant factors. Our proof is constructive, and we also obtain a polynomial
time $\mathcal{O}(\ln (r+1))$-approximation algorithm for the minimum multicut
problem on treewidth-$r$ graphs. Our algorithm proceeds by rounding the optimal
fractional solution to the natural linear programming relaxation of the
multicut problem. We introduce novel modifications to the well-known region
growing algorithm to facilitate the rounding while guaranteeing at most a
logarithmic factor loss in the treewidth.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-14 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Spectral Triadic Decompositions of Real-World Networks</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06352</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06352</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Basu_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sabyasachi Basu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Bera_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Suman Kalyan Bera&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Seshadhri_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;C. Seshadhri&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A fundamental problem in mathematics and network analysis is to find
conditions under which a graph can be partitioned into smaller pieces. The most
important tool for this partitioning is the Fiedler vector or discrete Cheeger
inequality. These results relate the graph spectrum (eigenvalues of the
normalized adjacency matrix) to the ability to break a graph into two pieces,
with few edge deletions. An entire subfield of mathematics, called spectral
graph theory, has emerged from these results. Yet these results do not say
anything about the rich community structure exhibited by real-world networks,
which typically have a significant fraction of edges contained in numerous
densely clustered blocks. Inspired by the properties of real-world networks, we
discover a new spectral condition that relates eigenvalue powers to a network
decomposition into densely clustered blocks. We call this the \emph{spectral
triadic decomposition}. Our relationship exactly predicts the existence of
community structure, as commonly seen in real networked data. Our proof
provides an efficient algorithm to produce the spectral triadic decomposition.
We observe on numerous social, coauthorship, and citation network datasets that
these decompositions have significant correlation with semantically meaningful
communities.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-14 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>\~Optimal Differentially Private Learning of Thresholds and Quasi-Concave Optimization</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06387</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06387</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Cohen_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Edith Cohen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lyu_X/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Xin Lyu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nelson_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jelani Nelson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sarlos_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tam&amp;#xe1;s Sarl&amp;#xf3;s&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Stemmer_U/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Uri Stemmer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The problem of learning threshold functions is a fundamental one in machine
learning. Classical learning theory implies sample complexity of $O(\xi^{-1}
\log(1/\beta))$ (for generalization error $\xi$ with confidence $1-\beta$). The
private version of the problem, however, is more challenging and in particular,
the sample complexity must depend on the size $|X|$ of the domain. Progress on
quantifying this dependence, via lower and upper bounds, was made in a line of
works over the past decade. In this paper, we finally close the gap for
approximate-DP and provide a nearly tight upper bound of $\tilde{O}(\log^*
|X|)$, which matches a lower bound by Alon et al (that applies even with
improper learning) and improves over a prior upper bound of $\tilde{O}((\log^*
|X|)^{1.5})$ by Kaplan et al. We also provide matching upper and lower bounds
of $\tilde{\Theta}(2^{\log^*|X|})$ for the additive error of private
quasi-concave optimization (a related and more general problem). Our
improvement is achieved via the novel Reorder-Slice-Compute paradigm for
private data analysis which we believe will have further applications.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-14 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Re-Analyze Gauss: Bounds for Private Matrix Approximation via Dyson Brownian Motion</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06418</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06418</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mangoubi_O/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Oren Mangoubi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Vishnoi_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nisheeth K. Vishnoi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given a symmetric matrix $M$ and a vector $\lambda$, we present new bounds on
the Frobenius-distance utility of the Gaussian mechanism for approximating $M$
by a matrix whose spectrum is $\lambda$, under
$(\varepsilon,\delta)$-differential privacy. Our bounds depend on both
$\lambda$ and the gaps in the eigenvalues of $M$, and hold whenever the top
$k+1$ eigenvalues of $M$ have sufficiently large gaps. When applied to the
problems of private rank-$k$ covariance matrix approximation and subspace
recovery, our bounds yield improvements over previous bounds. Our bounds are
obtained by viewing the addition of Gaussian noise as a continuous-time matrix
Brownian motion. This viewpoint allows us to track the evolution of eigenvalues
and eigenvectors of the matrix, which are governed by stochastic differential
equations discovered by Dyson. These equations allow us to bound the utility as
the square-root of a sum-of-squares of perturbations to the eigenvectors, as
opposed to a sum of perturbation bounds obtained via Davis-Kahan-type theorems.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-14 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>TR22-154 |  Spectral Expanding Expanders | 

	Gil Cohen, 

	Itay Cohen</title>
  <guid>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/154</guid>
  <link>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/154</link>
  <description>
    Dinitz, Schapira, and Valadarsky (Algorithmica 2017) introduced the intriguing notion of expanding expanders -- a family of expander graphs with the property that every two consecutive graphs in the family differ only on a small number of edges. Such a family allows one to add and remove vertices with only few edge updates, making them useful in dynamic settings such as for datacenter network topologies and for the design of distributed algorithms for self-healing expanders. Dinitz et al. constructed explicit expanding-expanders based on the Bilu-Linial construction of spectral expanders (Combinatorica 2006). The construction of expanding expanders, however, ends up being of edge expanders, thus, an open problem raised by Dinitz et al. is to construct spectral expanding expanders (SEE).

In this work, we resolve this question by constructing SEE with spectral expansion which, like the Bilu-Linial construction, is optimal up to a poly-logarithmic factor, and the number of edge updates is optimal up to a constant. We further give a simple proof for the existence of SEE that are close to Ramanujan up to a small additive term. As in the work of Dinitz et al., our construction is based on interpolating between a graph and its lift. However, to establish spectral expansion, we carefully weigh the interpolated graphs, dubbed partial lifts, in a way that enables us to conduct a delicate analysis of their spectrum. In particular, at a crucial point in the analysis, we consider the eigenvectors structure of the partial lifts.
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-13 18:30:56 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>ECCC Papers</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Report from LATIN</title>
  <guid>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/11/13/report-from-latin</guid>
  <link>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/11/13/report-from-latin.html</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;I just returned from the 15th &lt;a href=&quot;https://pakal.cs.cinvestav.mx/latin2022/&quot;&gt;Latin American Symposium on Theoretical Informatics (LATIN 2022)&lt;/a&gt;, held this year in Guanajuato, Mexico. LATIN is a regional conference that is only offered every two years, like WADS in Canada and SWAT in Scandinavia. I had a paper in the first one, in 1992, but this is only the second one Iâ€™ve attended, after &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/04/16/photos-from-latin.html&quot;&gt;2016 in Ensenada&lt;/a&gt;. This time, I was one of four invited speakers, speaking about reversible computing. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pubs/Epp-LATIN-22.pdf&quot;&gt;My talk slides are online&lt;/a&gt;, and I think that a talk video should be uploaded by the conference in a week or so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Guanajuato, the conference was held at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centro_de_Investigaci%C3%B3n_en_Matem%C3%A1ticas&quot;&gt;CIMAT, the Centro de InvestigaciÃ³n en MatemÃ¡ticas&lt;/a&gt;. This is a large center with a permanent research staff and frequent visitors, similar for instance to the Mathematical Sciences Research Institute in Berkeley, California. Wikipedia tells me that it also offers advanced mathematics courses and postdoctoral degrees. Itâ€™s set high on a hill over the town and has a crazy architecture, seemingly designed with a combination of the idea of what a space for mathematicians should look like, and the organic architecture of Guanajuato itself: staircases leading in every directions leading to narrow angular alleys or in some cases to nowhere, lots of repeated geometric shapes and patterns, and saturated with a coral red-orange color. I was inspired to use some of the conference break times to explore the center and take some photographs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto&quot;&gt;
&lt;tr style=&quot;text-align:center;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;padding:10px&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/cimat/1.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/cimat/1-s.jpg&quot; style=&quot;border-style:solid;border-color:black;&quot; width=&quot;288&quot; height=&quot;162&quot; alt=&quot;CIMAT&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;padding:10px&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/cimat/2.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/cimat/2-s.jpg&quot; style=&quot;border-style:solid;border-color:black;&quot; width=&quot;193&quot; height=&quot;256&quot; alt=&quot;CIMAT&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;padding:10px&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/cimat/3.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/cimat/3-s.jpg&quot; style=&quot;border-style:solid;border-color:black;&quot; width=&quot;193&quot; height=&quot;256&quot; alt=&quot;CIMAT&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr style=&quot;text-align:center;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;padding:10px&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/cimat/4.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/cimat/4-s.jpg&quot; style=&quot;border-style:solid;border-color:black;&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; height=&quot;199&quot; alt=&quot;CIMAT&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;padding:10px&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/cimat/5.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/cimat/5-s.jpg&quot; style=&quot;border-style:solid;border-color:black;&quot; width=&quot;193&quot; height=&quot;256&quot; alt=&quot;CIMAT&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;padding:10px&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/cimat/6.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/cimat/6-s.jpg&quot; style=&quot;border-style:solid;border-color:black;&quot; width=&quot;193&quot; height=&quot;256&quot; alt=&quot;CIMAT&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr style=&quot;text-align:center;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;padding:10px&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/cimat/7.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/cimat/7-s.jpg&quot; style=&quot;border-style:solid;border-color:black;&quot; width=&quot;193&quot; height=&quot;256&quot; alt=&quot;CIMAT&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;padding:10px&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/cimat/8.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/cimat/8-s.jpg&quot; style=&quot;border-style:solid;border-color:black;&quot; width=&quot;287&quot; height=&quot;162&quot; alt=&quot;CIMAT&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;padding:10px&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/cimat/9.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/cimat/9-s.jpg&quot; style=&quot;border-style:solid;border-color:black;&quot; width=&quot;193&quot; height=&quot;256&quot; alt=&quot;CIMAT&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference activities were all in a single session in a single conference room, and
the center is located some distance from downtown (maybe an hour by foot), with shuttles to our hotels provided only at the start and end of each day. I think this worked very well to bring all the participants together and helped make the conference a success. The topic of the conference is very broad and diverse (all of theoretical computer science) but I was pleasantly surprised how many times I went to a session whose topic I didnâ€™t think I cared much about and found a talk that was interesting to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-20624-5&quot;&gt;proceedings are already online&lt;/a&gt;, published through Springer LNCS, and the conference web site promises free access until the end of November. Besides mine, the invited talks included Jeff Ullman on abstraction in parsing formal languages, Merav Parter on the connections between graph connectivity and the ability of distributed algorithms to resist passive and active attackers, and Mauricio Osorio on the use of non-monotonic and paraconsistent logic to model the ability of human reasoners to work with inconsistent and changing beliefs. There was also an initial day of tutorial sessions that I missed, and a roundtable memorial discussion for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H%C3%A9ctor_Garc%C3%ADa-Molina&quot;&gt;HÃ©ctor GarcÃ­a-Molina&lt;/a&gt;, focused more on his mentorship than his research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contributed papers were organized by topic, both in the conference sessions and in the proceedings, but the order of topics differed between the sessions and the proceedings. Among the contributed talks, some that stood out to me (listed in proceedings order) were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â€œ&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-20624-5_3&quot;&gt;Median and hybrid median \(K\)-dimensional trees&lt;/a&gt;â€ by Amalia Duch, Conrado MartÃ­nez, MercÃ¨ Pons, and Salvadour Roura. If you are given a geometric point set all at once, you can construct a \(K\)-d tree by median bisection with strict rotation through the dimensions, giving provably fast time bounds for certain types of range trees. What if the points come to you incrementally, but in random order? It turns out that some choices of dimension to cut work better than strict rotation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â€œ&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-20624-5_6&quot;&gt;Near-optimal search time in \(\delta\)-optimal space&lt;/a&gt;â€, by Tomasz Kociumaka, Gonzalo Navarro, and Francisco Olivares. This is on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grammar-based_code&quot;&gt;grammar-based compression&lt;/a&gt; of text in such a way that the compressed text can be used as an index for fast substring lookups. It turns out that this can be done with compressed size roughly proportional to the â€œsubstring complexityâ€&lt;/p&gt;

\[\delta=\max_k\left\{\frac{d_k(S)}{k}\right\},\]

    &lt;p&gt;where \(d_k(S)\) is the number of distinct length-\(k\) substrings of a given string.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â€œ&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-20624-5_8&quot;&gt;Kleeâ€™s measure problem made oblivious&lt;/a&gt;â€, by Thore ThieÃŸen and Jan Vahrenhold. The main result is on the problem of computing the volume of the union of rectangles in the plane, or of hyperrectangles in higher dimensions. A known \(O(n\log n+n^{d/2})\) algorithm of Chan is made oblivious, meaning that its data access pattern depends only on \(n\) and not on the data. This allows the algorithm to be used in cloud computing in a privacy-preserving way. But beyond this specific computation, the paper presents a general approach that can be applied to many other geometric divide-and-conquer algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â€œ&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-20624-5_11&quot;&gt;Pathlength of outerplanar graphs&lt;/a&gt;â€, by Thomas Dissaux and Nicolas Nisse. This is a variant of the more well-known &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pathwidth&quot;&gt;pathwidth&lt;/a&gt; parameter in which one measures the maximum distance between vertices in a bag of a path-like tree-decomposition instead of the size of the bag. It can be computed exactly in outerplanar graphs but the runtime is impractically large, \(O(n^{11})\). The authors find a much faster algorithm that gets within additive error one.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â€œ&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-20624-5_14&quot;&gt;Obtaining approximately optimal and diverse solutions via dispersion&lt;/a&gt;â€, by Jie Gao, Mayank Goswami, C. S. Karthik, Meng-Tsung Tsai, Shih-Yu Tsai, and Hao-Tsung Yang. An example of the type of problem solved here is to find many low-weight spanning trees such that the sum of their Hamming distances (as sets of edges) is as large as possible. Curiously, the authors were unable to extend their results from spanning trees to TSP tours (without repetition, on metric complete graphs). The tree-doubling heuristic turns trees into tours but their diversity could be lost if you shortcut repeated vertices incautiously.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â€œ&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-20624-5_17&quot;&gt;Multidimensional Manhattan preferences&lt;/a&gt;â€, by Jiehua Chen, Martin NÃ¶llenburg, Sofia Simola, AnaÃ¯s Villedieu, and Markus Wallinger. Given voter preferences for candidates, when is it possible to embed both voters and candidates into a Manhattan metric space so that the preferences are ordered by distance?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â€œ&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-20624-5_21&quot;&gt;Binary completely reachable automata&lt;/a&gt;â€, by David Casas and Mikhail V. Volkov. This is on a generalization of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Synchronizing_word&quot;&gt;reset automata&lt;/a&gt; which, when started in an unknown state, can be taken to any single state by an well-chosen input sequence. Here, one instead wants to find a collection of sequences that take the set of all states to each other set of states. For two-symbol automata, the existence of such a collection can be determined in polynomial time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â€œ&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-20624-5_24&quot;&gt;Embedding arbitrary Boolean circuits into fungal automata&lt;/a&gt;â€, by Augusto Modanese and Thomas Worsch. This concerns the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abelian_sandpile_model&quot;&gt;abelian sandpile model&lt;/a&gt;, a cellular automaton in which each cell has a small number of grains of sand and when it has enough, â€œtopplesâ€, sending one grain to each neighbor. Is there any way to determine what happens more quickly than step-by-step simulation? In one dimension, yes, and in three dimensions, no, but 2d remains open. This paper proves \(\mathsf{P}\)-completeness for a variation in which toppling is done to the vertical neighbors and to the horizontal neighbors in alternating steps, rather than in both directions in each step.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â€œ&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-20624-5_32&quot;&gt;On the zombie number of various graph classes&lt;/a&gt;â€, by Jit Bose, Jean-Lou De Carufel, and Tom Shermer. This is on a variation of the pursuit-evasion game studied for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cop-win_graph&quot;&gt;cop-win graphs&lt;/a&gt;, where a set of cops pursue a robber along the edges of the graph, alternating moves in which the players can either move along one edge or stay put. A â€œzombieâ€ is a cop who always shambles towards the robber, rather than more cleverly moving away when that might be needed to corner the robber.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â€œ&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-20624-5_33&quot;&gt;Patterns in ordered (random) matchings&lt;/a&gt;â€, by Andrzej Dudek, JarosÅ‚aw Grytczuk, and Andrzej RuciÅ„ski. A typical result: in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chord_diagram_(mathematics)&quot;&gt;chord diagram&lt;/a&gt; with \(n\) chords, there must be a subset of \(\Omega(n^{1/3})\) of the chords that all nest, all cover disjoint arcs, or all cross. Can such a basic variation of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erd%C5%91s%E2%80%93Szekeres_theorem&quot;&gt;ErdÅ‘sâ€“Szekeres theorem&lt;/a&gt; really be new?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â€œ&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-20624-5_34&quot;&gt;Tree \(3\)-spanners on generalized prisms of graphs&lt;/a&gt;â€, by Renzo GÃ³mez, FlÃ¡vio Miyazawa, and Yoshiko Wakabayashi. A tree \(k\)-spanner is a spanning tree of a graph such that every graph edge can be replaced by a path of at most \(k\) edges in the tree. \(2\)-spanners are easy and \(k\)-spanners are hard for \(k\ge 4\) but the complexity of finding \(3\)-spanners has been open since 1995.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â€œ&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-20624-5_35&quot;&gt;A general approach to Ammann bars for aperiodic tilings&lt;/a&gt;â€, by Carole Porrier and Thomas Fernique. Two of the many constructions for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penrose_tiling&quot;&gt;Penrose tilings&lt;/a&gt; are the cut and project method, in which the tiling is formed from the square faces in a 2d tube through a 5d hypercube tiling, and the method of Ammann bars, in which the prototiles are decorated with line segments that must link up to form the lines of a line arrangement. So far the cut and project method has appeared to be much more fertile, leading to many other types of aperiodic tiling. The authors find a general method for showing that some of these other tilings also can be constructed using Ammann bars. &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.13973&quot;&gt;The arXiv version&lt;/a&gt; has more including a link to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/cporrier/Cyrenaic&quot;&gt;SAGE code for generating these tilings as svg images&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â€œ&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-20624-5_40&quot;&gt;Improved parallel algorithms for generalized Baumslag groups&lt;/a&gt;â€, by Caroline Mattes and Armin WeiÃŸ. One of the pluses of having such a broad conference is that it brings together people with highly varied research specialties and produces synergies between areas that might otherwise not connect. This paper has the same flavor, bringing together parallel computational complexity theory and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Combinatorial_group_theory&quot;&gt;combinatorial group theory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â€œ&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-20624-5_41&quot;&gt;Complexity results on untangling red-blue matchings&lt;/a&gt;â€, by Arun Kumar Das, Sandip Das, Guilherme da Fonseca, Yan Gerard, and Bastien Rivier. Suppose you have a red-blue matching between \(n\) red and \(n\) blue points in the plane, and you want to remove all crossings by re-matching pairs of crossing edges. How many of these flips does it take? There are many unsolved questions. The problem may seem a little artificial (because you can get to an uncrossing matching directly rather than by flipping) but the real motivation is to understand how to turn an approximate TSP tour with crossings into a shorter uncrossed TSP tour, where the use of flips seems more essential.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best paper award (named in memory of Alejandro LÃ³pez-Ortiz) was given to â€œ&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-20624-5_10&quot;&gt;Theoretical analysis of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; bisect&lt;/a&gt;â€ by Julien Courtiel, Paul Dorbec, and Romain Lecoq (who unfortunately could not present it). The conference also has a â€œtest of timeâ€ award, named for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imre_Simon&quot;&gt;Imre Simon&lt;/a&gt;, which went to â€œ&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-12200-2_16&quot;&gt;Optimal succinctness for range minimum queries&lt;/a&gt;â€ by Johannes Fischer from 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, a very successful conference, and one Iâ€™m very happy to have traveled to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/web/@11011110/109338576841926898&quot;&gt;Discuss on Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By David Eppstein&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-13 13:04:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>David Eppstein</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>TR22-153 |  Hardness against Linear Branching Programs and More | 

	Jyun-Jie Liao, 

	Eshan Chattopadhyay</title>
  <guid>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/153</guid>
  <link>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/153</link>
  <description>
    In a recent work, Gryaznov, PudlÃ¡k and Talebanfard (CCC &amp;#39;22) introduced a linear variant of read-once
branching programs, with motivations from circuit and proof complexity. Such a read-once linear branching program  is 
a  branching program  where each node is allowed  to make $\mathbb{F}_2$-linear queries,  and are read-once in the sense
that the queries on each path is linearly independent.  As their main result, they  constructed an explicit
function with average-case complexity $2^{n/3-o(n)}$ against a slightly restricted model, which they call
strongly read-once linear branching programs.  The main tool in their lower bound result is a new type of extractor,
called directional affine extractors, that they introduced.

Our main result is an explicit function with $2^{n-o(n)}$ average-case complexity against the strongly read-once
linear branching program model, which is almost optimal. This result is based on a new connection from this problem
to sumset extractors, which is a randomness extractor model introduced by Chattopadhyay and Li (STOC &amp;#39;16) as a
generalization of many other well-studied models including two-source extractors, affine extractors and small-space extractors.
 With this new connection, our lower bound naturally follows from a recent construction of sumset extractors
by Chattopadhyay and Liao (STOC &amp;#39;22). In addition, we show that directional affine extractors imply
 sumset extractors in a restricted setting. We observe that such restricted sumset sources are enough to derive lower bounds,  and obtain an arguably more modular proof of the lower bound by Gryaznov, PudlÃ¡k and Talebanfard.

We also initiate a study of pseudorandomness against linear branching programs. Our main result here
is a hitting set generator construction against regular linear branching programs with constant width. We derive this result
based on a connection to Kakeya sets over finite fields.
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-13 09:55:40 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>ECCC Papers</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>TR22-152 |  The Strength of Equality Oracles in Communication | 

	Toniann Pitassi, 

	Morgan Shirley, 

	Adi Shraibman</title>
  <guid>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/152</guid>
  <link>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/152</link>
  <description>
    It is well-known that randomized communication protocols are more powerful than deterministic protocols. In particular the Equality function requires $\Omega(n)$ deterministic communication complexity but has efficient randomized protocols. Previous work of Chattopadhyay, Lovett and Vinyals shows that randomized communication is strictly stronger than what can be solved by deterministic protocols equipped with an Equality oracle. Despite this separation, we are far from understanding the exact strength of Equality oracles in the context of communication complexity.
	
In this work we focus on nondeterminisic communication equipped with an Equality oracle, which is a subclass of Merlin-Arthur communication.  We show that this inclusion is strict by proving that the previously-studied Integer Inner Product function, which can be efficiently computed even with bounded-error randomness, cannot be computed using sublinear communication in the nondeterministic Equality model. To prove this we give a new matrix-theoretic characterization of the nondeterministic Equality model: specifically, there is a tight connection between this model and a covering number based on the blocky matrices of Hambardzumyan, Hatami, and Hatami, as well as a natural variant of the Gamma-2 factorization norm. Similar equivalences are shown for the unambiguous nondeterministic model with Equality oracles. A bonus result arises from these proofs: for the studied communication models, a single Equality oracle call suffices without loss of generality.
	
Our results allow us to prove a separation between deterministic and unambiguous nondeterminism in the presence of Equality oracles. This stands in contrast to the result of Yannakakis which shows that these models are polynomially-related without oracles. We suggest a number of intriguing open questions along this direction of inquiry, as well as others that arise from our work.
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-13 09:47:52 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>ECCC Papers</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Sam Bankman-Fried and the geometry of conscience</title>
  <guid>https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6797</guid>
  <link>https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6797</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;Several readers have asked me for updated thoughts on AI safety, now that I&amp;#8217;m 5 months into my &lt;a href=&quot;https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6484&quot;&gt;year at OpenAI&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8212;and I promise, I&amp;#8217;ll share them soon!  The thing is, until last week I&amp;#8217;d entertained the idea of writing up some of those thoughts for an essay competition run by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ftxfuturefund.org/&quot;&gt;FTX Future Fund&lt;/a&gt;, which (I was vaguely aware) was founded by the cryptocurrency billionaire &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sam_Bankman-Fried&quot;&gt;Sam Bankman-Fried&lt;/a&gt;, henceforth SBF.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Alas, unless you&amp;#8217;ve been tucked away on some Caribbean island&amp;#8212;or perhaps, &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; if you have been&amp;#8212;you&amp;#8217;ll know that the FTX Future Fund has ceased to exist.  In the course of 2-3 days last week, SBF&amp;#8217;s estimated net worth went from ~$15 billion to a negative number, possibly the fastest evaporation of such a vast personal fortune in all human history.  Notably, SBF had promised to give virtually all of it away to various worthy causes, including mitigating existential risk and helping Democrats win elections, and the worldwide &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Effective_altruism&quot;&gt;Effective Altruist&lt;/a&gt; community had largely reoriented itself around that pledge.  That&amp;#8217;s all now up in smoke.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve never met SBF, although he was a physics undergraduate at MIT while I taught CS there.  What little I knew of SBF before this week, came mostly from reading Gideon Lewis-Kraus&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2022/08/15/the-reluctant-prophet-of-effective-altruism&quot;&gt;excellent &lt;em&gt;New Yorker&lt;/em&gt; article&lt;/a&gt; about Effective Altruism this summer.  The details of what happened at FTX are at once hopelessly complicated and&amp;#8212;it would appear&amp;#8212;damningly simple, involving the misuse of billions of dollars&amp;#8217; worth of customer deposits to place risky bets that failed.  SBF has, in any case, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mobile.twitter.com/SBF_FTX/status/1590709166515310593&quot;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt; that he &amp;#8220;fucked up and should have done better.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#8217;d think none of this would directly impact me, since SBF and I inhabit such different worlds.  He ran a crypto empire from the Bahamas, sharing a group house with other twentysomething executives who often dated each other.  I teach at a large state university and try to raise two kids.  He made his first fortune by arbitraging bitcoin between Asia and the West.  I own, I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt;, a couple bitcoins that someone gave me in 2016, but have no idea how to access them anymore.  His hair is large and curly; mine is neither.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Even so, I&amp;#8217;ve found myself obsessively following this story because I know that, in a broader sense, I &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be called to account for it.  SBF and I both grew up as nerdy kids in middle-class Jewish American families, and both had transformative experiences as teenagers at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mathcamp.org/&quot;&gt;Canada/USA Mathcamp&lt;/a&gt;.  He and I know many of the same people.  We&amp;#8217;ve both been attracted to the idea of small groups of idealistic STEM nerds using their skills to help save the world from climate change, pandemics, and fascism.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Aha, the sneerers will sneer!  Hasn&amp;#8217;t the entire concept of &amp;#8220;STEM nerds saving the world&amp;#8221; now been utterly discredited, revealed to be just a front for cynical grifters and Ponzi schemers?  So if I&amp;#8217;m &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; a STEM nerd who&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; dreamed of helping to save the world, then don&amp;#8217;t I stand condemned too?&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m writing this post because, if the Greek tragedy of SBF is going to be invoked as a cautionary tale in nerd circles forevermore&amp;#8212;which it will be&amp;#8212;then I think it&amp;#8217;s crucial that we tell the &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; cautionary tale.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s like, imagine the Apollo 11 moon mission had &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; succeeded, but because of a tiny crack in an oxygen tank, it instead exploded in lunar orbit, killing all three of the astronauts.  Imagine that the crack formed partly because, in order to hide a budget overrun, Wernher von Braun had secretly substituted a cheaper material, while telling almost none of his underlings.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;There are many excellent lessons that one could draw from such a tragedy, having to do with, for example, the construction of oxygen tanks, the procedures for inspecting them, Wernher von Braun as an individual, or NASA safety culture.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;But there would also be &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; lessons to &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; draw.  These include: &amp;#8220;The entire enterprise of sending humans to the moon was obviously doomed from the start.&amp;#8221;  &amp;#8220;Fate will always punish human hubris.â€  &amp;#8220;All the engineers&amp;#8217; supposed quantitative expertise proved to be worthless.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;From everything I&amp;#8217;ve read, SBF&amp;#8217;s mission to earn billions, then spend it saving the world, seems something like this imagined Apollo mission.  Yes, the failure was total and catastrophic, and claimed innocent victims.  Yes, while bad luck played a role, so did, shall we say, &lt;em&gt;fateful decisions with a moral dimension&lt;/em&gt;.  If it&amp;#8217;s true that, as alleged, FTX raided its customers&amp;#8217; deposits to prop up the risky bets of its sister organization Alameda Research, multiple countries&amp;#8217; legal systems will surely be sorting out the consequences for years.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;To my mind, though, it&amp;#8217;s important not to minimize the gravity of the fateful decision by conflating it with everything that preceded it.  I confess to taking this sort of conflation extremely personally.  For eight years now, the rap against me, advanced by thousands (!) on social media, has been: &lt;em&gt;sure, while by all accounts Aaronson is kind and respectful to women, he seems like exactly the sort of nerdy guy who, still bitter and frustrated over high school, could&amp;#8217;ve chosen instead to sexually harass women and hinder their scientific careers.&lt;/em&gt;  In other words, I stand condemned by part of the world, not for the choices I made, but for choices I &lt;em&gt;didn&amp;#8217;t&lt;/em&gt; make that are considered &amp;#8220;too close to me&amp;#8221; in the geometry of conscience.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;And I don&amp;#8217;t consent to that.  I don&amp;#8217;t wish to be held accountable for the misdeeds of my doppelgÃ¤ngers in parallel universes.  Therefore, I resolve not to judge anyone else by their parallel-universe doppelgÃ¤ngers either.  If SBF indeed gambled away his customers&amp;#8217; deposits and lied about it, then I condemn him for it utterly, but I refuse to condemn his hypothetical doppelgÃ¤nger who didn&amp;#8217;t do those things.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Granted, there are those who think &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; cryptocurrency is a Ponzi scheme and a scam, and that for that reason alone, it should&amp;#8217;ve been obvious from the start that crypto-related plans could only end in catastrophe.  The &amp;#8220;Ponzi scheme&amp;#8221; theory of cryptocurrency has, we ought to concede, a substantial case in its favor&amp;#8212;though I&amp;#8217;d rather opine about the matter in (say) 2030 than now.  Like many technologies that spend years as quasi-scams until they aren&amp;#8217;t, maybe blockchains &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; find some compelling everyday use-cases, besides the well-known ones like drug-dealing, ransomware, and financing rogue states.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Even if cryptocurrency remains just a modern-day tulip bulb or Beanie Baby, though, it seems morally hard to distinguish a cryptocurrency trader from the millions who deal in options, bonds, and all manner of other speculative assets.  And a traditional investor who made billions on successful gambles, or arbitrage, or creating liquidity, then gave virtually all of it away to effective charities, would seem, on net, &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; ahead of most of us morally.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;To be sure, I never pursued the &amp;#8220;Earning to Give&amp;#8221; path myself, though certainly the concept occurred to me as a teenager, before it had a name.  Partly I decided against it because I seem to lack a certain brazenness, or maybe just willingness to follow up on tedious details, needed to win in business.  Partly, though, I decided against trying to get rich because I&amp;#8217;m selfish (!).  I prioritized doing fascinating quantum computing research, starting a family, teaching, blogging, and other stuff I liked over devoting every waking hour to &lt;em&gt;possibly&lt;/em&gt; earning a fortune only to give it all to charity, and &lt;em&gt;more likely&lt;/em&gt; being a failure even at that.  All told, I don&amp;#8217;t regret my scholarly pathâ€”especially not now!â€”but I&amp;#8217;m also not going to encase it in some halo of obvious moral superiority.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;If I could go back in time and give SBF advice&amp;#8212;or if, let&amp;#8217;s say, he&amp;#8217;d come to me at MIT for advice back in 2013&amp;#8212;what could I have told him?  I surely wouldn&amp;#8217;t talk about cryptocurrency, about which I knew and know little.  I might try to carve out some space for deontological ethics against pure utilitarianism, but I might also consider that a lost cause with this particular undergrad.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;On reflection, maybe I&amp;#8217;d just try to convince SBF to weight money logarithmically when calculating expected utility (as in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kelly_criterion&quot;&gt;Kelly criterion&lt;/a&gt;), to forsake the linear weighting that SBF &lt;a href=&quot;https://mobile.twitter.com/SBF_FTX/status/1337250686870831107&quot;&gt;explicitly advocated&lt;/a&gt; and that he seems to have put into practice in his crypto ventures.  Or if not logarithmic weighing, Iâ€™d try to sell him on &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; concave utility function&amp;#8212;something that makes, let&amp;#8217;s say, a mere $1 billion in hand seem better than $15 billion that has a 50% probability of vanishing and leaving you, your customers, your employees, and the entire Effective Altruism community with less than nothing.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;At any rate, I&amp;#8217;d try to impress on him, as I do on anyone reading now, that the choice between linear and concave utilities, between risk-neutrality and risk-aversion, is not bloodless or technical&amp;#8212;that it&amp;#8217;s essential to make a choice that&amp;#8217;s not only in reflective equilibrium with your highest values, but that you&amp;#8217;ll still consider to be such regardless of which possible universe you end up in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Scott&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-13 08:55:25 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Scott Aaronson</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Two faculty positions in Computer Science at Reykjavik University</title>
  <guid>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-8722244999293992142</guid>
  <link>http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2022/11/two-faculty-positions-in-computer.html</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;My department has advertised two full-time, permanent faculty positions at any rank . Theoretical Computer Science is not the department&#39;s highest priority in hiring at this moment in time, but it is mentioned as one of the areas of interest, alongside Artificial Intelligence, Cybersecurity, Data Science  and Machine Learning, and Software Engineering. Do consider applying if you are theoretically minded, your work has, or has the potential to have, impact on any of those fields, and you&#39;d like to join our academic family and relocate to Iceland.&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;The call is below and at &lt;a data-saferedirecturl=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://jobs.50skills.com/ru/en/16728&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1668373530238000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3F1MIlXxSDx6MsnyzyA6y_&quot; href=&quot;https://jobs.50skills.com/ru/en/16728&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://jobs.50skills.com/ru/&lt;wbr&gt;&lt;/wbr&gt;en/16728&lt;/a&gt;, where the application form can be found. &lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Two faculty positions in Computer Science at Reykjavik University&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The  Department of Computer Science at Reykjavik University invites  applications for two full-time, permanent faculty positions at any rank  in the fields of Artificial Intelligence, Cybersecurity, Data Science  and Machine Learning, Software Engineering, and Theoretical Computer  Science. For one of the positions, we will give preferential treatment  to excellent applicants in Software Engineering, broadly construed.  However, the primary evaluation criterion is scientific quality.  Outstanding candidates in other areas of Computer Science are encouraged  to apply as well. See &lt;a data-saferedirecturl=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://jobs.50skills.com/ru/en/16728&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1668373530238000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3F1MIlXxSDx6MsnyzyA6y_&quot; href=&quot;https://jobs.50skills.com/ru/en/16728&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://jobs.50skills.com/ru/&lt;wbr&gt;&lt;/wbr&gt;en/16728&lt;/a&gt; for the link to the application form. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We  are looking for energetic, highly qualified academics with a proven  international research record and excellent potential in their field of  study. We particularly welcome applications from researchers who have a  strong network of research collaborators, can strengthen internal  collaborations within the department, have the proclivity to improve  their academic environment and its culture, and have the drive and  potential to flourish in our environment. The Department of Computer  Science at Reykjavik University is characterised by a flat hierarchical  structure and every faculty member is expected to act like a principal  investigator regardless of their level of employment. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;Apart  from developing their research career, the successful applicants will  play a full part in the teaching and administrative activities of the  department, teaching courses and supervising students at both graduate  and undergraduate level. Applicants with a demonstrated history of  excellence in teaching are preferred.&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;Salary and rank are  commensurate with experience. Successful applicants receive a relocation  budget, some seed research funding in the first two years of their  employment and support for one PhD student. Among other benefits,  Reykjavik University offers its research staff the option to take  research semesters (sabbaticals) every three years of satisfactory  teaching and research activity and provides some additional financial  support during those semesters. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;The positions are open until  filled, with intended starting date in August 2023. Later starting dates  can be negotiated, but preference will be given to candidates who can  take up their position in August 2023. The deadline for applications is  January 27, 2023. The review of the applications will begin in late  January 2023 and will continue until the positions are filled.&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;A  PhD in Computer Science or a related field is required. Applications  should be submitted through the universityâ€™s online application  submission system and should include the following documents:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;a cover letter specifying whether the candidate is applying for appointment as an assistant, associate, or full professor,&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;a CV with a full list of publications,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;links to three to five major publications,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;a research statement,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;a teaching statement,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;supporting material regarding excellence in teaching, if available, and&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;any other relevant information the applicant wishes to supply.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;Please arrange to have three letters of recommendation sent directly to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:mannaudur@ru.is&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;mannaudur@ru.is&lt;/a&gt; (subject â€œFaculty Positions in CSâ€) with a copy to Professor Luca Aceto (&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:luca@ru.is&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;luca@ru.is&lt;/a&gt;),  Chair of the Department of Computer Science. Informal communication and  discussions on any aspect related to the positions are encouraged, and  interested candidates are welcome to contact the chair of the search  committee, Associate Professor MarÃ­a Ã“skarsdÃ³ttir (&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:mariaoskars@ru.is&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;mariaoskars@ru.is&lt;/a&gt;), for further information.&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Department of Computer Science at Reykjavik University&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;The  Department of Computer Science at Reykjavik University is research  intensive and carries out research-based teaching in all its degree  programmes. It offers undergraduate and graduate programs in Computer  Science and Software Engineering, a combined undergraduate program in  Discrete Mathematics and Computer Science, two graduate programs in Data  Science and one in Artificial Intelligence and Language Technology.  From the autumn semester 2023, the department will also offer an MSc in  Digital Health. At the time of writing, it is home to 26 faculty  members, seven of whom are women, five postdoctoral researchers, and 32  PhD students representing altogether over 20 different countries. In  2022, the department had 740 students registered for its BSc and MSc  programmes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The department provides an excellent working  environment in which a motivated academic can have an impact at all  levels and has a career-development framework that encourages and  supports independence in academic endeavours. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The department is  home to several research centres producing high-quality collaborative  research in areas such as artificial intelligence, data science,  financial technology, information systems, language technology, software  systems, and theoretical computer science, among others; for more  information on those research centres, see &lt;a data-saferedirecturl=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://en.ru.is/research/&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1668373530238000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1dhd6eiTNSdkpnHHP99VVJ&quot; href=&quot;https://en.ru.is/research/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://en.ru.is/research/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;For further information about the Department of Computer Science at Reykjavik University and its activities, see &lt;a data-saferedirecturl=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=http://en.ru.is/scs/&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1668373530238000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1F5qGgvr6kc1XXrqr_r0Qp&quot; href=&quot;http://en.ru.is/scs/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://en.ru.is/scs/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;ReykjavÃ­k University&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;On  the Times Higher Education rankings for 2023, Reykjavik University is  ranked among the 350 best universities world-wide, first among Icelandic  universities, and 18th among Nordic ones. Moreover, it was ranked 12th  amongst the best small universities in the Times Higher Education  rankings 2022, when it was in first place along with eight other  universities for the average number of citations per faculty and 53rd  amongst all universities established fewer than 50 years ago. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Iceland&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Iceland  is well known for breathtaking natural beauty, with volcanoes, hot  springs, lava fields and glaciers offering a dramatic landscape. It  consistently ranks as one of the best places in the world to live. It  offers a high quality of life, is one of the safest places in the world,  with high gender equality, and strong healthcare and social-support  systems. It was in second position in the 2021 UN World Happiness  Report, which correlates with various life factors. Reykjavik is a  vibrant and cosmopolitan city, which provides an ideal environment for  combining cultural and family activities with an active lifestyle. &lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Luca Aceto&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-12 22:14:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Luca Aceto</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>TR22-151 |  Low-depth arithmetic circuit lower bounds via shifted partials | 

	Prashanth Amireddy, 

	Ankit Garg, 

	Neeraj Kayal, 

	Chandan Saha, 

	Bhargav Thankey</title>
  <guid>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/151</guid>
  <link>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/151</link>
  <description>
    We prove super-polynomial lower bounds for low-depth arithmetic circuits using the shifted partials measure [Gupta-Kamath-Kayal-Saptharishi, CCC 2013], [Kayal, ECCC 2012] and the affine projections of partials measure [Garg-Kayal-Saha, FOCS 2020], [Kayal-Nair-Saha, STACS 2016]. The recent breakthrough work of Limaye, Srinivasan and Tavenas [FOCS 2021] proved these lower bounds by proving lower bounds for low-depth set-multilinear circuits. An interesting aspect of our proof is that it does not require conversion of a circuit to a set-multilinear circuit, nor does it involve a random restriction. We are able to upper bound the measures for homogeneous formulas directly, without going via set-multilinearity. Our lower bounds hold for the iterated matrix multiplication as well as the Nisan-Wigderson design polynomials. We also define a subclass of homogeneous formulas which we call unique parse tree (UPT) formulas, and prove superpolynomial lower bounds for these. This generalizes the superpolynomial lower bounds for regular formulas in [Kayal-Saha-Saptharishi, STOC 2014], [Fournier-Limaye-Malod-Srinivasan, STOC 2014].
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-12 20:49:02 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>ECCC Papers</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Faculty at University of Wisconsin-Madison (apply by December 15, 2022)</title>
  <guid>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/11/12/faculty-at-university-of-wisconsin-madison-apply-by-december-15-2022/</guid>
  <link>https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/11/12/faculty-at-university-of-wisconsin-madison-apply-by-december-15-2022/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;The Department of Computer Sciences at UW Madison invites highly qualified candidates in all areas of computer science, especially machine learning, programming languages and software engineering, robotics, quantum computing, security and privacy, and theory to apply to positions at the assistant, associate, and full professor levels that will begin in August 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.wisc.edu/people/faculty-staff-recruitment/&quot;&gt;https://www.cs.wisc.edu/people/faculty-staff-recruitment/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: ilias@cs.wisc.edu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-12 19:19:48 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>CCI: jobs</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>TR22-150 |  Near-Optimal Derandomization of Medium-Width Branching Programs | 

	Aaron (Louie) Putterman, 

	Edward Pyne</title>
  <guid>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/150</guid>
  <link>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/150</link>
  <description>
    We give a deterministic white-box algorithm to estimate the expectation of a read-once branching program of length $n$ and width $w$ in space 
    $$\tilde{O}\left(\log n+\sqrt{\log n}\cdot\log w\right).$$
    In particular, we obtain an almost optimal space $\tilde{O}(\log n)$ derandomization of programs up to width $w=2^{\sqrt{\log n}}$.
    Previously, the best known space complexity for this problem was 
    $$O\left(\min\{\log n\cdot \log w,\log^{3/2}n+\sqrt{\log n}\cdot \log w\}\right)$$
    via the classic algorithms of Savitch (JCSS 1970) and Saks and Zhou (JCSS 1999), which only achieve space $\tilde{O}(\log n)$ for $w=poly\log(n)$.
    
    We prove this result by showing that a variant of the Saks-Zhou algorithm developed by Cohen, Doron, and Sberlo (ECCC 2022) still works without executing one of the steps in the algorithm, the so-called random shift step. This allows us to extend their algorithm from computing the $n$th power of a $w\times w$ stochastic matrix to multiplying $n$ distinct $w\times w$ stochastic matrices with no degradation in space consumption.
    In the regime where $w\geq n$, we also show that our approach can achieve parameters matching those of the original Saks-Zhou algorithm (with no loglog factors). Finally, we show that for $w\leq 2^{\sqrt{\log n}}$, an algorithm even simpler than our algorithm and that of Saks and Zhou achieves space $O(\log^{3/2} n)$.
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-11 22:15:04 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>ECCC Papers</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>TR22-149 |  Approximating Iterated Multiplication of Stochastic Matrices in Small Space | 

	Gil Cohen, 

	Ori Sberlo, 

	Amnon Ta-Shma, 

	Dean Doron</title>
  <guid>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/149</guid>
  <link>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/149</link>
  <description>
    Matrix powering, and more generally iterated matrix multiplication, is a fundamental linear algebraic primitive with myriad applications in computer science. Of particular interest is the problem&amp;#39;s space complexity as it constitutes the main route towards resolving the $\mathbf{BPL}$ vs. $\mathbf{L}$ problem. The seminal work by Saks and Zhou (FOCS 1995) gives a deterministic algorithm for approximating the product of $n$ stochastic matrices of dimension $w \times w$ in space $O(\log^{3/2}n + \sqrt{\log n} \cdot \log w)$. The first improvement upon Saks-Zhou was achieved by Hoza (RANDOM 2021) who gave a logarithmic improvement in the $n = \mathrm{poly}(w)$ regime, attaining $O(\frac1{\sqrt{\log\log n}} \cdot \log^{3/2}n)$ space.

We give the first polynomial improvement over Saks-Zhou. Our algorithm achieves space complexity of
$$
\widetilde{O}\left(\log n + \sqrt{\log n}\cdot \log w\right).
$$
In particular, in the regime $\log n &amp;gt; \log^2 w$, our algorithm runs in nearly-optimal $\widetilde{O}(\log n)$ space, improving upon the previous best $O(\log^{3/2}n)$.

To obtain our result for the special case of matrix powering, we harness recent machinery from time- and space-bounded Laplacian solvers to the Saks-Zhou framework and devise an intricate precision-alternating recursive scheme. This enables us to bypass the bottleneck of paying $\log n$-space per recursion level. The general case of iterated matrix multiplication poses several additional challenges, the substantial of which is handled by devising an improved shift and truncate mechanism. The new mechanism is made possible by a novel use of the Richardson iteration.
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-11 22:14:49 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>ECCC Papers</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>TR22-148 |  Efficient resilient functions | 

	Emanuele Viola, 

	Raghu Meka, 

	Peter Ivanov</title>
  <guid>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/148</guid>
  <link>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/148</link>
  <description>
    An $n$-bit boolean function is resilient to coalitions of size $q$
if no fixed set of $q$ bits is likely to influence the value of the
function when the other $n-q$ bits are chosen uniformly at random,
even though the function is nearly balanced. We construct explicit
functions resilient to coalitions of size $q=n/(\log n)^{O(\log\log n)}=n^{1-o(1)}$
computable by linear-size circuits and linear-time algorithms. We
also obtain a tight size-depth tradeoff for computing such resilient
functions.

Constructions such as ours were not available even non-explicitly.
It was known that functions resilient to coalitions of size $q=n^{0.63...}$
can be computed by linear-size circuits \cite{Ben-OrLi85}, and functions
resilient to coalitions of size $q=\Theta(n/\log^{2}n)$ can be computed
by quadratic-size circuits \cite{AL93}.

One component of our proofs is a new composition theorem for resilient
functions.
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-11 13:56:41 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>ECCC Papers</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Average-Case Complexity of Tensor Decomposition for Low-Degree Polynomials</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05274</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05274</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wein_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Alexander S. Wein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Suppose we are given an $n$-dimensional order-3 symmetric tensor $T \in
(\mathbb{R}^n)^{\otimes 3}$ that is the sum of $r$ random rank-1 terms. The
problem of recovering the rank-1 components is possible in principle when $r
\lesssim n^2$ but polynomial-time algorithms are only known in the regime $r
\ll n^{3/2}$. Similar &quot;statistical-computational gaps&quot; occur in many
high-dimensional inference tasks, and in recent years there has been a flurry
of work on explaining the apparent computational hardness in these problems by
proving lower bounds against restricted (yet powerful) models of computation
such as statistical queries (SQ), sum-of-squares (SoS), and low-degree
polynomials (LDP). However, no such prior work exists for tensor decomposition,
largely because its hardness does not appear to be explained by a &quot;planted
versus null&quot; testing problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We consider a model for random order-3 tensor decomposition where one
component is slightly larger in norm than the rest (to break symmetry), and the
components are drawn uniformly from the hypercube. We resolve the computational
complexity in the LDP model: $O(\log n)$-degree polynomial functions of the
tensor entries can accurately estimate the largest component when $r \ll
n^{3/2}$ but fail to do so when $r \gg n^{3/2}$. This provides rigorous
evidence suggesting that the best known algorithms for tensor decomposition
cannot be improved, at least by known approaches. A natural extension of the
result holds for tensors of any fixed order $k \ge 3$, in which case the LDP
threshold is $r \sim n^{k/2}$.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-11 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Parameterized Complexity of Weighted Local Hamiltonian Problems and the Quantum Exponential Time Hypothesis</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05325</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05325</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Bremner_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Michael J. Bremner&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ji_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zhengfeng Ji&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Li_X/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Xingjian Li&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mathieson_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Luke Mathieson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Morales_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mauro E.S. Morales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study a parameterized version of the local Hamiltonian problem, called the
weighted local Hamiltonian problem, where the relevant quantum states are
superpositions of computational basis states of Hamming weight $k$. The Hamming
weight constraint can have a physical interpretation as a constraint on the
number of excitations allowed or particle number in a system. We prove that
this problem is in QW[1], the first level of the quantum weft hierarchy and
that it is hard for QM[1], the quantum analogue of M[1]. Our results show that
this problem cannot be fixed-parameter quantum tractable (FPQT) unless certain
natural quantum analogue of the exponential time hypothesis (ETH) is false.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-11 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Description Graphs, Matrix-Power Stabilizations and Graph Isomorphism in Polynomial Time</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05637</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05637</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Xue_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Rui Xue&lt;/a&gt; (State Key Laboratory of Information Security, Institute of Information Engineering, CAS)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is confirmed in this work that the graph isomorphism can be tested in
polynomial time, which resolves a longstanding problem in the theory of
computation. The contributions are in three phases as follows.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. A description graph $\tilde{A}$ to a given graph $A$ is introduced so that
labels to vertices and edges of $\tilde{A}$ indicate the identical or different
amounts of walks of any sort in any length between vertices in $A$. Three
processes are then developed to obtain description graphs. They reveal
relations among matrix power, spectral decomposition and adjoint matrices,
which is of independent interest.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. We show that the stabilization of description graphs can be implemented
via matrix-power stabilization, a new approach to distinguish vertices and
edges to graphs. The approach is proven to be equivalent in the partition of
vertices to Weisfeiler-Lehman (WL for short) process. The specific
Square-and-Substitution (SaS) process is more succinct than WL process.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vertex partitions to our stable graphs are proven to be \emph{strongly}
equitable partitions, which is important in the proofs of our main conclusion.
Some properties on stable graphs are also explored.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. A class of graphs named binding graphs is proposed and proven to be
graph-isomorphism complete. The vertex partition to the stable graph of a
binding graph is the automorphism partition, which allows us to confirm
graph-isomorphism problem is in complexity class $\mathtt{P}$. Since the
binding graph to a graph is so simple in construction, our approach can be
readily applied in practice.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-11 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Complexity of Chess Domination Problems</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05651</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05651</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Langlois_Remillard_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Alexis Langlois-R&amp;#xe9;millard&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Mussig_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Christoph M&amp;#xfc;&amp;#xdf;ig&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Roldan_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;&amp;#xc9;rika R&amp;#xf3;ldan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study different domination problems of attacking and non-attacking rooks
and queens on polyominoes and polycubes of all dimensions. Our main result
proves that the problem is NP-complete for non-attacking queens on polyominoes
and for non-attacking rooks on three-dimensional polycubes. We also analyze
these problems on the set of convex polyominoes, for which we conjecture and
give some evidence that these domination problems restricted to this subset of
polyominoes might be NP-complete for both, queens and rooks. We have also
computed new values for classical queen domination problems on chessboards
(square polyominoes). For our computations, we have translated the problem into
an integer linear programming instance. Finally, using this computational
implementation and the game engine Godot, we have developed a video game of
minimal domination of queens and rooks on randomly generated polyominoes.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-11 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Geometry</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Certified Numerical Real Root Isolation of Zero-dimensional Multivariate Real Nonlinear Systems</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05266</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05266</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Cheng_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jin-San Cheng&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wen_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Junyi Wen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using the local geometrical properties of a given zero-dimensional square
multivariate nonlinear system inside a box, we provide a simple but effective
and new criterion for the uniqueness and the existence of a real simple zero of
the system inside the box. Based on the result, we design an algorithm based on
subdivision and interval arithmetics to isolate all the real zeros of a general
real nonlinear system inside a given box. Our method is complete for systems
with only finite isolated simple real zeros inside a box. A termination
precision is given for general zero-dimensional systems. Multiple zeros of the
system are output in bounded boxes. A variety of benchmarks show the
effectivity and efficiency of our implementation (in C++). It works for
polynomial systems with Bezout bound more than 100 million. It also works for
non-polynomial nonlinear systems. We also discuss the limitations of our
method.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-11 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Geometry</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Filtration-Domination in Bifiltered Graphs</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05574</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05574</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Alonso_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;&amp;#xc1;ngel Javier Alonso&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kerber_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Michael Kerber&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Pritam_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Siddharth Pritam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bifiltered graphs are a versatile tool for modelling relations between data
points across multiple grades of a two-dimensional scale. They are especially
popular in topological data analysis, where the homological properties of the
induced clique complexes are studied. To reduce the large size of these clique
complexes, we identify filtration-dominated edges of the graph, whose removal
preserves the relevant topological properties. We give two algorithms to detect
filtration-dominated edges in a bifiltered graph and analyze their complexity.
These two algorithms work directly on the bifiltered graph, without first
extracting the clique complexes, which are generally much bigger. We present
extensive experimental evaluation which shows that in most cases, more than 90%
of the edges can be removed. In turn, we demonstrate that this often leads to a
substantial speedup, and reduction in the memory usage, of the computational
pipeline of multiparameter topological data analysis.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-11 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Geometry</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Finding Triangles and Other Small Subgraphs in Geometric Intersection Graphs</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05345</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05345</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chan_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Timothy M. Chan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We consider problems related to finding short cycles, small cliques, small
independent sets, and small subgraphs in geometric intersection graphs. We
obtain a plethora of new results. For example:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* For the intersection graph of $n$ line segments in the plane, we give
algorithms to find a 3-cycle in $O(n^{1.408})$ time, a size-3 independent set
in $O(n^{1.652})$ time, a 4-clique in near-$O(n^{24/13})$ time, and a
$k$-clique (or any $k$-vertex induced subgraph) in $O(n^{0.565k+O(1)})$ time
for any constant $k$; we can also compute the girth in near-$O(n^{3/2})$ time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* For the intersection graph of $n$ axis-aligned boxes in a constant
dimension $d$, we give algorithms to find a 3-cycle in $O(n^{1.408})$ time for
any $d$, a 4-clique (or any 4-vertex induced subgraph) in $O(n^{1.715})$ time
for any $d$, a size-4 independent set in near-$O(n^{3/2})$ time for any $d$, a
size-5 independent set in near-$O(n^{4/3})$ time for $d=2$, and a $k$-clique
(or any $k$-vertex induced subgraph) in $O(n^{0.429k+O(1)})$ time for any $d$
and any constant $k$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* For the intersection graph of $n$ fat objects in any constant dimension
$d$, we give an algorithm to find any $k$-vertex (non-induced) subgraph in
$O(n\log n)$ time for any constant $k$, generalizing a result by Kaplan, Klost,
Mulzer, Roddity, Seiferth, and Sharir (1999) for 3-cycles in 2D disk graphs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A variety of techniques is used, including geometric range searching,
biclique covers, &quot;high-low&quot; tricks, graph degeneracy and separators, and
shifted quadtrees. We also prove a near-$\Omega(n^{4/3})$ conditional lower
bound for finding a size-4 independent set for boxes.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2022-11-11 01:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
