<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Theory of Computing Report</title>
  <link></link>
  <language>en</language>
  <description></description>


<item>
  <title>The Planted $k$-SUM Problem: Algorithms, Lower Bounds, Hardness Amplification, and Cryptography</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01787</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01787</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Saga_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sagnik Saga&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Schwartzbach_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nikolaj I. Schwartzbach&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Vasudevan_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Prashant Nalini Vasudevan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the average-case $k$-SUM problem, given $r$ integers chosen uniformly at
random from $\{0,\ldots,M-1\}$, the objective is to find a set of $k$ numbers
that sum to $0$ modulo $M$ (this set is called a solution). In the related
$k$-XOR problem, given $k$ uniformly random Boolean vectors of length
$\log{M}$, the objective is to find a set of $k$ of them whose bitwise-XOR is
the all-zero vector. Both of these problems have widespread applications in the
study of fine-grained complexity and cryptanalysis.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feasibility and complexity of these problems depends on the relative
values of $k$, $r$, and $M$. The dense regime of $M \leq r^k$, where solutions
exist with high probability, is quite well-understood and we have several
non-trivial algorithms and hardness conjectures here. Much less is known about
the sparse regime of $M\gg r^k$, where solutions are unlikely to exist. The
best answers we have for many fundamental questions here are limited to
whatever carries over from the dense or worst-case settings.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We study the planted $k$-SUM and $k$-XOR problems in the sparse regime. In
these problems, a random solution is planted in a randomly generated instance
and has to be recovered. As $M$ increases past $r^k$, these planted solutions
tend to be the only solutions with increasing probability, potentially becoming
easier to find. We show several results about the complexity and applications
of these problems.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Quantum Public-Key Encryption with Tamper-Resilient Public Keys from One-Way Functions</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01800</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01800</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Kitagawa_F/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Fuyuki Kitagawa&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Morimae_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tomoyuki Morimae&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Nishimaki_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ryo Nishimaki&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/quant-ph/1/au:+Yamakawa_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Takashi Yamakawa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We construct quantum public-key encryption from one-way functions. In our
construction, public keys are quantum, but ciphertexts are classical. Quantum
public-key encryption from one-way functions (or weaker primitives such as
pseudorandom function-like states) are also proposed in some recent works
[Morimae-Yamakawa, eprint:2022/1336; Coladangelo, eprint:2023/282;
Grilo-Sattath-Vu, eprint:2023/345; Barooti-Malavolta-Walter, eprint:2023/306].
However, they have a huge drawback: they are secure only when quantum public
keys can be transmitted to the sender (who runs the encryption algorithm)
without being tampered with by the adversary, which seems to require
unsatisfactory physical setup assumptions such as secure quantum channels. Our
construction is free from such a drawback: it guarantees the secrecy of the
encrypted messages even if we assume only unauthenticated quantum channels.
Thus, the encryption is done with adversarially tampered quantum public keys.
Our construction based only on one-way functions is the first quantum
public-key encryption that achieves the goal of classical public-key
encryption, namely, to establish secure communication over insecure channels.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Minimizing Running Buffers for Tabletop Object Rearrangement: Complexity, Fast Algorithms, and Applications</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01764</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01764</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gao_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Kai Gao&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Feng_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Si Wei Feng&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Huang_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Baichuan Huang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Yu_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jingjin Yu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For rearranging objects on tabletops with overhand grasps, temporarily
relocating objects to some buffer space may be necessary. This raises the
natural question of how many simultaneous storage spaces, or &quot;running buffers&quot;,
are required so that certain classes of tabletop rearrangement problems are
feasible. In this work, we examine the problem for both labeled and unlabeled
settings. On the structural side, we observe that finding the minimum number of
running buffers (MRB) can be carried out on a dependency graph abstracted from
a problem instance, and show that computing MRB is NP-hard. We then prove that
under both labeled and unlabeled settings, even for uniform cylindrical
objects, the number of required running buffers may grow unbounded as the
number of objects to be rearranged increases. We further show that the bound
for the unlabeled case is tight. On the algorithmic side, we develop effective
exact algorithms for finding MRB for both labeled and unlabeled tabletop
rearrangement problems, scalable to over a hundred objects under very high
object density. More importantly, our algorithms also compute a sequence
witnessing the computed MRB that can be used for solving object rearrangement
tasks. Employing these algorithms, empirical evaluations reveal that random
labeled and unlabeled instances, which more closely mimics real-world setups,
generally have fairly small MRBs. Using real robot experiments, we demonstrate
that the running buffer abstraction leads to state-of-the-art solutions for
in-place rearrangement of many objects in tight, bounded workspace.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Geometry</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A statistical framework for analyzing shape in a time series of random geometric objects</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01984</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01984</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Delft_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Anne van Delft&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Blumberg_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Andrew J. Blumberg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduce a new framework to analyze shape descriptors that capture the
geometric features of an ensemble of point clouds. At the core of our approach
is the point of view that the data arises as sampled recordings from a metric
space-valued stochastic process, possibly of nonstationary nature, thereby
integrating geometric data analysis into the realm of functional time series
analysis. We focus on the descriptors coming from topological data analysis.
Our framework allows for natural incorporation of spatial-temporal dynamics,
heterogeneous sampling, and the study of convergence rates. Further, we derive
complete invariants for classes of metric space-valued stochastic processes in
the spirit of Gromov, and relate these invariants to so-called ball volume
processes. Under mild dependence conditions, a weak invariance principle in
$D([0,1]\times [0,\mathscr{R}])$ is established for sequential empirical
versions of the latter, assuming the probabilistic structure possibly changes
over time. Finally, we use this result to introduce novel test statistics for
topological change, which are distribution free in the limit under the
hypothesis of stationarity.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Geometry</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Distribution Testing Under the Parity Trace</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01374</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01374</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Pinto_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Renato Ferreira Pinto Jr.&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Harms_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nathaniel Harms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Distribution testing is a fundamental statistical task with many
applications, but we are interested in a variety of problems where systematic
mislabelings of the sample prevent us from applying the existing theory. To
apply distribution testing to these problems, we introduce distribution testing
under the parity trace, where the algorithm receives an ordered sample $S$ that
reveals only the least significant bit of each element. This abstraction
reveals connections between the following three problems of interest, allowing
new upper and lower bounds:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. In distribution testing with a confused collector, the collector of the
sample may be incapable of distinguishing between nearby elements of a domain
(e.g. a machine learning classifier). We prove bounds for distribution testing
with a confused collector on domains structured as a cycle or a path.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. Recent work on the fundamental testing vs. learning question established
tight lower bounds on distribution-free sample-based property testing by
reduction from distribution testing, but the tightness is limited to symmetric
properties. The parity trace allows a broader family of equivalences to
non-symmetric properties, while recovering and strengthening many of the
previous results with a different technique.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. We give the first results for property testing in the well-studied trace
reconstruction model, where the goal is to test whether an unknown string $x$
satisfies some property or is far from satisfying that property, given only
independent random traces of $x$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our main technical result is a tight bound of $\widetilde
\Theta\left((n/\epsilon)^{4/5} + \sqrt n/\epsilon^2\right)$ for testing
uniformity of distributions over $[n]$ under the parity trace, leading also to
results for the problems above.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Tight Space Lower Bound for Pseudo-Deterministic Approximate Counting</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01438</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01438</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Grossman_O/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ofer Grossman&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gupta_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Meghal Gupta&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sellke_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mark Sellke&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We investigate one of the most basic problems in streaming algorithms:
approximating the number of elements in the stream. In 1978, Morris famously
gave a randomized algorithm achieving a constant-factor approximation error for
streams of length at most N in space $O(\log \log N)$. We investigate the
pseudo-deterministic complexity of the problem and prove a tight $\Omega(\log
N)$ lower bound, thus resolving a problem of
Goldwasser-Grossman-Mohanty-Woodruff.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A greedy approach for increased vehicle utilization in ridesharing networks</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01225</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01225</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Makhdomi_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Aqsa Ashraf Makhdomi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Gillani_I/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Iqra Altaf Gillani&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In recent years, ridesharing platforms have become a prominent mode of
transportation for the residents of urban areas. As a fundamental problem,
route recommendation for these platforms is vital for their sustenance. The
works done in this direction have recommended routes with higher passenger
demand. Despite the existing works, statistics have suggested that these
services cause increased greenhouse emissions compared to private vehicles as
they roam around in search of riders. This analysis provides finer details
regarding the functionality of ridesharing systems and it reveals that in the
face of their boom, they have not utilized the vehicle capacity efficiently. We
propose to overcome the above limitations and recommend routes that will fetch
multiple passengers simultaneously which will result in increased vehicle
utilization and thereby decrease the effect of these systems on the
environment. As route recommendation is NP-hard, we propose a k-hop-based
sliding window approximation algorithm that reduces the search space from
entire road network to a window. We further demonstrate that maximizing
expected demand is submodular and greedy algorithms can be used to optimize our
objective function within a window. We evaluate our proposed model on
real-world datasets and experimental results demonstrate superior performance
by our proposed model.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Randomly Punctured Reed-Solomon Codes Achieve the List Decoding Capacity over Polynomial-Size Alphabets</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01403</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01403</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Guo_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zeyu Guo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zhang_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zihan Zhang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper shows that, with high probability, randomly punctured Reed-Solomon
codes over fields of polynomial size achieve the list decoding capacity. More
specifically, we prove that for any $\epsilon&amp;gt;0$ and $R\in (0,1)$, with high
probability, randomly punctured Reed-Solomon codes of block length $n$ and rate
$R$ are $\left(1-R-\epsilon, O({1}/{\epsilon})\right)$ list decodable over
alphabets of size at least $2^{\mathrm{poly}(1/\epsilon)}n^2$. This extends the
recent breakthrough of Brakensiek, Gopi, and Makam (STOC 2023) that randomly
punctured Reed-Solomon codes over fields of exponential size attain the
generalized Singleton bound of Shangguan and Tamo (STOC 2020).
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A $d^{1/2+o(1)}$ Monotonicity Tester for Boolean Functions on $d$-Dimensional Hypergrids</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01416</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01416</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Black_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hadley Black&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chakrabarty_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Deeparnab Chakrabarty&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Seshadhri_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;C. Seshadhri&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Monotonicity testing of Boolean functions on the hypergrid, $f:[n]^d \to
\{0,1\}$, is a classic topic in property testing. Determining the non-adaptive
complexity of this problem is an important open question. For arbitrary $n$,
[Black-Chakrabarty-Seshadhri, SODA 2020] describe a tester with query
complexity $\widetilde{O}(\varepsilon^{-4/3}d^{5/6})$. This complexity is
independent of $n$, but has a suboptimal dependence on $d$. Recently,
[Braverman-Khot-Kindler-Minzer, ITCS 2023] and [Black-Chakrabarty-Seshadhri,
STOC 2023] describe $\widetilde{O}(\varepsilon^{-2} n^3\sqrt{d})$ and
$\widetilde{O}(\varepsilon^{-2} n\sqrt{d})$-query testers, respectively. These
testers have an almost optimal dependence on $d$, but a suboptimal polynomial
dependence on $n$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we describe a non-adaptive, one-sided monotonicity tester with
query complexity $O(\varepsilon^{-2} d^{1/2 + o(1)})$, independent of $n$. Up
to the $d^{o(1)}$-factors, our result resolves the non-adaptive complexity of
monotonicity testing for Boolean functions on hypergrids. The independence of
$n$ yields a non-adaptive, one-sided $O(\varepsilon^{-2} d^{1/2 + o(1)})$-query
monotonicity tester for Boolean functions $f:\mathbb{R}^d \to \{0,1\}$
associated with an arbitrary product measure.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Minimum Cost Flow in the CONGEST Model</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01600</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01600</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Vos_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tijn de Vos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We consider the CONGEST model on a network with $n$ nodes, $m$ edges,
diameter $D$, and integer costs and capacities bounded by $\text{poly} n$. In
this paper, we show how to find an exact solution to the minimum cost flow
problem in $n^{1/2+o(1)}(\sqrt{n}+D)$ rounds, improving the state of the art
algorithm with running time $m^{3/7+o(1)}(\sqrt nD^{1/4}+D)$ [Forster et al.
FOCS 2021], which only holds for the special case of unit capacity graphs. For
certain graphs, we achieve even better results. In particular, for planar
graphs, expander graphs, $n^{o(1)}$-genus graphs, $n^{o(1)}$-treewidth graphs,
and excluded-minor graphs our algorithm takes $n^{1/2+o(1)}D$ rounds. We obtain
this result by combining recent results on Laplacian solvers in the CONGEST
model [Forster et al. FOCS 2021, Anagnostides et al. DISC 2022] with a CONGEST
implementation of the LP solver of Lee and Sidford [FOCS 2014], and finally
show that we can round the approximate solution to an exact solution. Our
algorithm solves certain linear programs, that generalize minimum cost flow, up
to additive error $\epsilon$ in $n^{1/2+o(1)}(\sqrt{n}+D)\log^3 (1/\epsilon)$
rounds.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Algorithms for the Generalized Poset Sorting Problem</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01623</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01623</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Jiang_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Shaofeng H.-C. Jiang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wang_W/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Wenqian Wang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zhang_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yubo Zhang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zhang_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yuhao Zhang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We consider a generalized poset sorting problem (GPS), in which we are given
a query graph $G = (V, E)$ and an unknown poset $\mathcal{P}(V, \prec)$ that is
defined on the same vertex set $V$, and the goal is to make as few queries as
possible to edges in $G$ in order to fully recover $\mathcal{P}$, where each
query $(u, v)$ returns the relation between $u, v$, i.e., $u \prec v$, $v \prec
u$ or $u \not \sim v$. This generalizes both the poset sorting problem [Faigle
et al., SICOMP 88] and the generalized sorting problem [Huang et al., FOCS 11].
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We give algorithms with $\tilde{O}(n\cdot \mathrm{poly}(k))$ query complexity
when $G$ is a complete bipartite graph or $G$ is stochastic under the \ER
model, where $k$ is the \emph{width} of the poset, and these generalize
[Daskalakis et al., SICOMP 11] which only studies complete graph $G$. Both
results are based on a unified framework that reduces the poset sorting to
partitioning the vertices with respect to a given pivot element, which may be
of independent interest.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our study of GPS also leads to a new $\tilde{O}(n^{1 - 1 / (2W)})$
competitive ratio for the so-called weighted generalized sorting problem where
$W$ is the number of distinct weights in the query graph. This problem was
considered as an open question in [Charikar et al., JCSS 02], and our result
makes important progress as it yields the first nontrivial $\tilde{O}(n)$ ratio
for general weighted query graphs (and better ratio if $W$ is bounded). We
obtain this via an $\tilde{O}(nk + n^{1.5})$ query complexity algorithm for the
case where every edge in $G$ is guaranteed to be comparable in the poset, which
generalizes the state-of-the-art $\tilde{O}(n^{1.5})$ bound for generalized
sorting [Huang et al., FOCS 11].
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Dynamic treewidth</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01744</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01744</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Korhonen_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tuukka Korhonen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Majewski_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Konrad Majewski&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nadara_W/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Wojciech Nadara&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Pilipczuk_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Micha&amp;#x142; Pilipczuk&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Sokolowski_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Marek Soko&amp;#x142;owski&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present a data structure that for a dynamic graph $G$ that is updated by
edge insertions and deletions, maintains a tree decomposition of $G$ of width
at most $6k+5$ under the promise that the treewidth of $G$ never grows above
$k$. The amortized update time is ${\cal O}_k(2^{\sqrt{\log n}\log\log n})$,
where $n$ is the vertex count of $G$ and the ${\cal O}_k(\cdot)$ notation hides
factors depending on $k$. In addition, we also obtain the dynamic variant of
Courcelle&#39;s Theorem: for any fixed property $\varphi$ expressible in the
$\mathsf{CMSO}_2$ logic, the data structure can maintain whether $G$ satisfies
$\varphi$ within the same time complexity bounds. To a large extent, this
answers a question posed by Bodlaender [WG 1993].
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Mixing predictions for online metric algorithms</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01781</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01781</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Antoniadis_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Antonios Antoniadis&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Coester_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Christian Coester&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Elias_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Marek Eli&amp;#xe1;&amp;#x161;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Polak_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Adam Polak&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Simon_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Bertrand Simon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A major technique in learning-augmented online algorithms is combining
multiple algorithms or predictors. Since the performance of each predictor may
vary over time, it is desirable to use not the single best predictor as a
benchmark, but rather a dynamic combination which follows different predictors
at different times. We design algorithms that combine predictions and are
competitive against such dynamic combinations for a wide class of online
problems, namely, metrical task systems. Against the best (in hindsight)
unconstrained combination of $\ell$ predictors, we obtain a competitive ratio
of $O(\ell^2)$, and show that this is best possible. However, for a benchmark
with slightly constrained number of switches between different predictors, we
can get a $(1+\epsilon)$-competitive algorithm. Moreover, our algorithms can be
adapted to access predictors in a bandit-like fashion, querying only one
predictor at a time. An unexpected implication of one of our lower bounds is a
new structural insight about covering formulations for the $k$-server problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>VC Set Systems in Minor-free (Di)Graphs and Applications</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01790</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01790</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Le_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hung Le&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wulff_Nilsen_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Christian Wulff-Nilsen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A recent line of work on VC set systems in minor-free (undirected) graphs,
starting from Li and Parter, who constructed a new VC set system for planar
graphs, has given surprising algorithmic results. In this work, we initialize a
more systematic study of VC set systems for minor-free graphs and their
applications in both undirected graphs and directed graphs (a.k.a digraphs).
More precisely:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- We propose a new variant of Li-Parter set system for undirected graphs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- We extend our set system to $K_h$-minor-free digraphs and show that its VC
dimension is $O(h^2)$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- We show that the system of directed balls in minor-free digraphs has VC
dimension at most $h-1$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- On the negative side, we show that VC set system constructed from shortest
path trees of planar digraphs does not have a bounded VC dimension.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The highlight of our work is the results for digraphs, as we are not aware of
known algorithmic work on constructing and exploiting VC set systems for
digraphs.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Connected and Autonomous Vehicle Scheduling Problems: Some Models and Algorithms</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01806</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01806</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Gafarov_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Evgeny R. Gafarov&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Werner_F/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Frank Werner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we consider scheduling problems that arise in connected and
autonomous vehicle systems. For four variants of such problems, mathematical
models and solution algorithms are presented. In particular, three polynomial
algorithms and a branch and bound algorithms are developed.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Chasing Positive Bodies</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01889</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01889</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Bhattacharya_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sayan Bhattacharya&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Buchbinder_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Niv Buchbinder&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Levin_R/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Roie Levin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Saranurak_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Thatchaphol Saranurak&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the problem of chasing positive bodies in $\ell_1$: given a sequence
of bodies $K_{t}=\{x^{t}\in\mathbb{R}_{+}^{n}\mid C^{t}x^{t}\geq
1,P^{t}x^{t}\leq 1\}$ revealed online, where $C^{t}$ and $P^{t}$ are
nonnegative matrices, the goal is to (approximately) maintain a point $x_t \in
K_t$ such that $\sum_t \|x_t - x_{t-1}\|_1$ is minimized. This captures the
fully-dynamic low-recourse variant of any problem that can be expressed as a
mixed packing-covering linear program and thus also the fractional version of
many central problems in dynamic algorithms such as set cover, load balancing,
hyperedge orientation, minimum spanning tree, and matching.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We give an $O(\log d)$-competitive algorithm for this problem, where $d$ is
the maximum row sparsity of any matrix $C^t$. This bypasses and improves
exponentially over the lower bound of $\sqrt{n}$ known for general convex
bodies. Our algorithm is based on iterated information projections, and, in
contrast to general convex body chasing algorithms, is entirely memoryless.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also show how to round our solution dynamically to obtain the first fully
dynamic algorithms with competitive recourse for all the stated problems above;
i.e. their recourse is less than the recourse of every other algorithm on every
update sequence, up to polylogarithmic factors. This is a significantly
stronger notion than the notion of absolute recourse in the dynamic algorithms
literature.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Strong spatial mixing for colorings on trees and its algorithmic applications</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01954</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01954</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chen_Z/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Zongchen Chen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Liu_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Kuikui Liu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Mani_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nitya Mani&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Moitra_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Ankur Moitra&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strong spatial mixing (SSM) is an important quantitative notion of
correlation decay for Gibbs distributions arising in statistical physics,
probability theory, and theoretical computer science. A longstanding conjecture
is that the uniform distribution on proper $q$-colorings on a $\Delta$-regular
tree exhibits SSM whenever $q \ge \Delta+1$. Moreover, it is widely believed
that as long as SSM holds on bounded-degree trees with $q$ colors, one would
obtain an efficient sampler for $q$-colorings on all bounded-degree graphs via
simple Markov chain algorithms. It is surprising that such a basic question is
still open, even on trees, but then again it also highlights how much we still
have to learn about random colorings. In this paper, we show the following:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(1) For any $\Delta \ge 3$, SSM holds for random $q$-colorings on trees of
maximum degree $\Delta$ whenever $q \ge \Delta + 3$. Thus we almost fully
resolve the aforementioned conjecture. Our result substantially improves upon
the previously best bound which requires $q \ge 1.59\Delta+\gamma^*$ for an
absolute constant $\gamma^* &amp;gt; 0$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(2) For any $\Delta\ge 3$ and girth $g = \Omega_\Delta(1)$, we establish
optimal mixing of the Glauber dynamics for $q$-colorings on graphs of maximum
degree $\Delta$ and girth $g$ whenever $q \ge \Delta+3$. Our approach is based
on a new general reduction from spectral independence on large-girth graphs to
SSM on trees that is of independent interest.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the same techniques, we also prove near-optimal bounds on weak spatial
mixing (WSM), a closely-related notion to SSM, for the antiferromagnetic Potts
model on trees.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Online Time-Windows TSP with Predictions</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01958</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01958</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chawla_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Shuchi Chawla&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Christou_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Dimitris Christou&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the Time-Windows TSP (TW-TSP) we are given requests at different locations
on a network; each request is endowed with a reward and an interval of time;
the goal is to find a tour that visits as much reward as possible during the
corresponding time window. For the online version of this problem, where each
request is revealed at the start of its time window, no finite competitive
ratio can be obtained. We consider a version of the problem where the algorithm
is presented with predictions of where and when the online requests will
appear, without any knowledge of the quality of this side information.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vehicle routing problems such as the TW-TSP can be very sensitive to errors
or changes in the input due to the hard time-window constraints, and it is
unclear whether imperfect predictions can be used to obtain a finite
competitive ratio. We show that good performance can be achieved by explicitly
building slack into the solution. Our main result is an online algorithm that
achieves a competitive ratio logarithmic in the diameter of the underlying
network, matching the performance of the best offline algorithm to within
factors that depend on the quality of the provided predictions. The competitive
ratio degrades smoothly as a function of the quality and we show that this
dependence is tight within constant factors.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-05 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Neil Jones (1941-2023)</title>
  <guid>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-4674935859497045234</guid>
  <link>https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2023/04/neil-jones-1941-2023.html</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgvZYTofhc2zPgPq7_2CuI3JUbXlbSvpWL3xla-H8c4gpWz_wXGCjQQLGt3sNl3XP0E5PZ4qIzpnwddhMX1FzqbzTnicWf_oROVBk6TEzBq7novIBCrqlQ1-qj_KNB0LqJGeM6TXNGzx8yoFR4UyDOqme79mlKdSRpbGJrA0G-L_1m8nJF-1w/s885/Neil_D._Jones.jpg&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;clear: right; float: right; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; data-original-height=&quot;885&quot; data-original-width=&quot;657&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgvZYTofhc2zPgPq7_2CuI3JUbXlbSvpWL3xla-H8c4gpWz_wXGCjQQLGt3sNl3XP0E5PZ4qIzpnwddhMX1FzqbzTnicWf_oROVBk6TEzBq7novIBCrqlQ1-qj_KNB0LqJGeM6TXNGzx8yoFR4UyDOqme79mlKdSRpbGJrA0G-L_1m8nJF-1w/w149-h200/Neil_D._Jones.jpg&quot; width=&quot;149&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;i&gt;Eric Allender graciously agreed to write this remembrance of Neil Jones.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neil_D._Jones&quot;&gt;Neil Jones&lt;/a&gt; passed away on March 27.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neil&#39;s work had a profound impact on the field of computational complexity theory, although he was primarily known for his work in other areas of computer science.&amp;nbsp; For example, his 1998 ACM Fellow citation is &quot;For outstanding contributions to semantics-directed compilation, especially partial evaluation, and to the theory of computation, formal models and their practical realization.&quot;&amp;nbsp; Note that there&#39;s no mention of &quot;complexity&quot; (except as it is bundled together with &quot;theory of computation&quot; -- and Jones also published in the area of computability theory).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So what were some ways that Neil influenced the development of computational complexity theory?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1972, in the 4th STOC conference, Neil &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1145/800152.804909&quot;&gt;collaborated&lt;/a&gt; with Alan Selman, to show that a notion that logicians had been studying since the 1950&#39;s coincided exactly with a natural complexity class.&amp;nbsp; More specifically, given a logical formula F, the &quot;spectrum&quot; of F is the set of numbers {n : F has a finite model of size n}.&amp;nbsp; What kinds of sets can be the spectrum of a first-order formula?&amp;nbsp; Is this class of sets closed under complement?&amp;nbsp; These were some of the questions that logicians had struggled with.&amp;nbsp; Jones and Selman gave a precise characterization, as NE (nondeterministic exponential time).&amp;nbsp; Thus the complement of every spectrum is a spectrum if and only if NE=coNE.&amp;nbsp; As D. Sivakumar points out in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:7047571379897921536?commentUrn=urn%3Ali%3Acomment%3A%28activity%3A7047571379897921536%2C7048828674200006656%29&amp;amp;replyUrn=urn%3Ali%3Acomment%3A%28activity%3A7047571379897921536%2C7048876431841378304%29&quot;&gt;LinkedIn comment&lt;/a&gt; on Neil&#39;s death: &quot;The following year, Fagin proved that generalized spectra coincide with NP, and descriptive complexity theory was born.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, a lot of other things were happening in the late 60&#39;s and early 70&#39;s:&amp;nbsp; Savitch proved Savitch&#39;s Theorem.&amp;nbsp; The first NP-completeness results appeared.&amp;nbsp; It appears that several people were trying to build on Savitch&#39;s theorem, to show that everything in P can be done in log&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; space, and this motivated Steve Cook to define a problem (&quot;Path Systems&quot;) and show (1) certain algorithms for Path Systems could not be implemented in small space, and (2) Path Systems has a small-space algorithm iff everything in P does.&amp;nbsp; This result of Cook&#39;s was similar in flavor to a theorem of Savitch, showing that a problem he called &quot;Threadable Mazes&quot; was in L if and only if NL=L.&amp;nbsp; Although these notions were clearly in the air, Jones (and -- simultaneously -- Meyer &amp;amp; Stockmeyer) were the first to explicitly formalize the notion of logspace reducibility (including closure under composition), and to notice that the NP-completeness results of Cook and Karp held also under logspace reducibility.&amp;nbsp; And Jones was the first one to go ahead and develop the general theory of logspace reducibility and the theory of completeness for subclasses of P (first for P itself (with Laaser), and later for NL (with Laaser and Lien)).&amp;nbsp; I think that this is when people started to get the idea that completeness was not a special property that only a few problems shared.&amp;nbsp; Rather: Nearly EVERY natural computational problem was likely to be complete for some reasonable complexity class.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notably, Jones also recognized that logspace was overkill, when considering reductions.&amp;nbsp; He also wanted to have a really restricted notion of reducibility, so that one could talk meaningfully about problems being complete for L.&amp;nbsp; To this end, he &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/S0022-0000(75)80050-X&quot;&gt;defined&lt;/a&gt; &quot;log-rudimentary&quot; reducibility.&amp;nbsp; This was quite natural for him, since he had work previously on Smullyan&#39;s &quot;Rudimentary Relations&quot;.&amp;nbsp; But log-rudimentary reductions never really caught on.&amp;nbsp; Instead, after Furst, Saxe, and Sipser kickstarted the study of AC&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; circuits, a notion of AC&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; reducibility was developed by Chandra, Stockmeyer, and Vishkin in the mid-1980&#39;s, which turned out to be very useful in classifying problems as being complete in various subclasses of P.&amp;nbsp; Much later, in 1991, I published a &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/0020-0190(91)90015-A&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; with Vivek Gore, showing that Neil&#39;s log-rudimentary reductions are precisely the same thing as uniform AC&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; reducibility.&amp;nbsp; Thus Neil Jones had the insight to define and study a notion that would not become mainstream for another decade, and which still provides the best tool for classifying the complexity of natural problems in subclasses of P.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I only had the pleasure of meeting Neil once, during a visit to Copenhagen in 2004, although we would occasionally exchange some e-mail about topics in complexity.&amp;nbsp; It is interesting to note that the most &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2008.02932&quot;&gt;recent paper&lt;/a&gt; on Neil&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://dblp.org/pid/j/NeilDJones.html&quot;&gt;DBLP page&lt;/a&gt; deals with complexity classes.&amp;nbsp; I haven&#39;t spent much time looking at the paper, but I do see that the authors define a complexity class that lies between NL and P.&amp;nbsp; It might be interesting to see if this class coincides with SAC&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; (also known as LogCFL).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I thank Lance and Bill for encouraging me to write a few lines about Neil&#39;s importance to the field.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Lance Fortnow&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-04 19:05:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The communication complexity of functions with large outputs</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.00391</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.00391</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Fontes_L/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Lila Fontes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Laplante_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sophie Laplante&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lauriere_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mathieu Lauriere&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Nolin_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Alexandre Nolin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the two-party communication complexity of functions with large
outputs, and show that the communication complexity can greatly vary depending
on what output model is considered. We study a variety of output models,
ranging from the open model, in which an external observer can compute the
outcome, to the XOR model, in which the outcome of the protocol should be the
bitwise XOR of the players&#39; local outputs. This model is inspired by XOR games,
which are widely studied two-player quantum games. We focus on the question of
error-reduction in these new output models. For functions of output size k,
applying standard error reduction techniques in the XOR model would introduce
an additional cost linear in k. We show that no dependency on k is necessary.
Similarly, standard randomness removal techniques, incur a multiplicative cost
of $2^k$ in the XOR model. We show how to reduce this factor to O(k). In
addition, we prove analogous error reduction and randomness removal results in
the other models, separate all models from each other, and show that some
natural problems, including Set Intersection and Find the First Difference,
separate the models when the Hamming weights of their inputs is bounded.
Finally, we show how to use the rank lower bound technique for our weak output
models.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-04 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Gallai-like characterization of strong cocomparability graphs</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.00430</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.00430</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Huang_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jing Huang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strong cocomparability graphs are the reflexive graphs whose adjacency matrix
can be rearranged by a simultaneous row and column permutation to avoid the
submatrix with rows $01, 10$. Strong cocomparability graphs form a subclass of
cocomparability graphs (i.e., the complements of comparability graphs) and can
be recognized in polynomial time. In his seminal paper, Gallai characterized
cocomparability graphs in terms of a forbidden structure called asteroids.
Gallai proved that cocomparability graphs are precisely those reflexive graphs
which do not contain asteroids.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we give a characterization of strong cocomparability graphs
which is analogous to Gallai&#39;s characterization for cocomparability graphs. We
prove that strong cocomparability graphs are precisely those reflexive graphs
which do not contain weak edge-asteroids (a weaker version of asteroids). Our
characterization also leads to a polynomial time recognition algorithm for
strong cocomparability graphs.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-04 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Almost Linear Constant-Factor Sketching for $\ell_1$ and Logistic Regression</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.00051</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.00051</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Munteanu_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Alexander Munteanu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Omlor_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Simon Omlor&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Woodruff_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;David Woodruff&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We improve upon previous oblivious sketching and turnstile streaming results
for $\ell_1$ and logistic regression, giving a much smaller sketching dimension
achieving $O(1)$-approximation and yielding an efficient optimization problem
in the sketch space. Namely, we achieve for any constant $c&amp;gt;0$ a sketching
dimension of $\tilde{O}(d^{1+c})$ for $\ell_1$ regression and $\tilde{O}(\mu
d^{1+c})$ for logistic regression, where $\mu$ is a standard measure that
captures the complexity of compressing the data. For $\ell_1$-regression our
sketching dimension is near-linear and improves previous work which either
required $\Omega(\log d)$-approximation with this sketching dimension, or
required a larger $\operatorname{poly}(d)$ number of rows. Similarly, for
logistic regression previous work had worse $\operatorname{poly}(\mu d)$
factors in its sketching dimension. We also give a tradeoff that yields a
$1+\varepsilon$ approximation in input sparsity time by increasing the total
size to $(d\log(n)/\varepsilon)^{O(1/\varepsilon)}$ for $\ell_1$ and to $(\mu
d\log(n)/\varepsilon)^{O(1/\varepsilon)}$ for logistic regression. Finally, we
show that our sketch can be extended to approximate a regularized version of
logistic regression where the data-dependent regularizer corresponds to the
variance of the individual logistic losses.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-04 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Mini-batch $k$-means terminates within $O(d/\epsilon)$ iterations</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.00419</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2304.00419</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Schwartzman_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Gregory Schwartzman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We answer the question: &quot;Does local progress (on batches) imply global
progress (on the entire dataset) for mini-batch $k$-means?&quot;. Specifically, we
consider mini-batch $k$-means which terminates only when the improvement in the
quality of the clustering on the sampled batch is below some threshold.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although at first glance it appears that this algorithm might execute
forever, we answer the above question in the affirmative and show that if the
batch is of size $\tilde{\Omega}((d/\epsilon)^2)$, it must terminate within
$O(d/\epsilon)$ iterations with high probability, where $d$ is the dimension of
the input, and $\epsilon$ is a threshold parameter for termination. This is
true regardless of how the centers are initialized. When the algorithm is
initialized with the $k$-means++ initialization scheme, it achieves an
approximation ratio of $O(\log k)$ (the same as the full-batch version).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we show the applicability of our results to the mini-batch $k$-means
algorithm implemented in the scikit-learn (sklearn) python library.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-04 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Alef Corner: Deep Learning 2020, 2030, 2040</title>
  <guid>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=24111</guid>
  <link>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/04/03/alef-corner-deep-learning-2020-2030-2040/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;24112&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/img-20230228-wa0000/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0000.jpg&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1000,1000&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;IMG-20230228-WA0000&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0000.jpg?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0000.jpg?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-24112&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0000.jpg?w=640&quot; alt=&quot;IMG-20230228-WA0000&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0000.jpg?w=640 640w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0000.jpg?w=150 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0000.jpg?w=300 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0000.jpg?w=768 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0000.jpg 1000w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px&quot;   /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000&quot;&gt;Deep learning 2020&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;24113&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/04/03/alef-corner-deep-learning-2020-2030-2040/img-20230228-wa0002/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0002.jpg&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1000,1000&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;IMG-20230228-WA0002&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0002.jpg?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0002.jpg?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-24113&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0002.jpg?w=640&quot; alt=&quot;IMG-20230228-WA0002&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0002.jpg?w=640 640w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0002.jpg?w=150 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0002.jpg?w=300 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0002.jpg?w=768 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0002.jpg 1000w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px&quot;   /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000&quot;&gt;Deep learning 2030&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;24115&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/04/03/alef-corner-deep-learning-2020-2030-2040/img-20230228-wa0001/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0001.jpg&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1000,1000&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;IMG-20230228-WA0001&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0001.jpg?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0001.jpg?w=640&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-24115&quot; src=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0001.jpg?w=640&quot; alt=&quot;IMG-20230228-WA0001&quot; srcset=&quot;https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0001.jpg?w=640 640w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0001.jpg?w=150 150w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0001.jpg?w=300 300w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0001.jpg?w=768 768w, https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/img-20230228-wa0001.jpg 1000w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px&quot;   /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000&quot;&gt;Deep learning 2040&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Gil Kalai&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-03 20:36:02 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Gil Kalai</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>TR23-042 |  On small-depth Frege proofs for PHP | 

	Johan Hstad</title>
  <guid>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/042</guid>
  <link>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/042</link>
  <description>
    We study Frege proofs for the one-to-one graph Pigeon Hole Principle
defined on the $n\times n$ grid where $n$ is odd.
We are interested in the case where each formula
in the proof is a depth $d$ formula in the basis given by
$\land$, $\lor$, and $\neg$.  We prove that in this situation the
proof needs to be of size exponential in $n^{\Omega (1/d)}$.
If we restrict the size of each line in the proof to be of
size $M$ then the number of lines needed is exponential
in $n/(\log M)^{O(d)}$.   The main technical component of
the proofs is to design a new family of random restrictions
and to prove the appropriate switching lemmas.
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-03 11:46:42 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>ECCC Papers</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>TheoretiCS: Status update</title>
  <guid>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-3407399653899165687</guid>
  <link>http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2023/04/theoretics-status-update.html</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Thomas Schwentick, Meena Mahajan and Pascal Weil (Chair, Secretary and Treasurer of the TheoretiCS Foundation, respectively) sent me the following information on &lt;a href=&quot;https://theoretics.episciences.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TheoretiCS&lt;/a&gt;, which I am happy to share with our community with their permission. I encourage everyone to support the journal by submitting their best work to it!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TheoretiCS was officially launched in 
December 2021 and we wish to present you with the current status of the 
project. You can find more precise information on the journal&#39;s site, &lt;a data-saferedirecturl=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=http://theoretics-journal.org&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1680603853854000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0Ae4R2w9GxS1LLNOrTxwv2&quot; href=&quot;http://theoretics-journal.org&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;theoretics-journal.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The first papers were submitted right away in December 2021, and some 
were published in 2022: &lt;a href=&quot;https://theoretics.episciences.org/volume/view/id/691&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Volume 1&lt;/a&gt; (2022) has two papers. &lt;a href=&quot;https://theoretics.episciences.org/volume/view/id/692&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Volume 2&lt;/a&gt; (2023) 
already has five published papers, more are very near acceptance and 
there is a healthy list of papers under review, with more papers 
submitted every month.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Our intention was to have a journal that covers the whole of Theoretical
 Computer Science, and this is reflected in the list of published 
papers. We also wanted to have an open-access journal (it operates under
 the so-called diamond open access paradigm, which means that no charges
 are levied to read it, nor to publish in it), and one that involves the
 theoretical computer science community as much as possible. This was 
done by first establishing an Advisory Board, where the majority of the 
members are representatives of many of the most prominent conferences of
 the domain. The Advisory Board selected a pair of remarkable 
Editors-in-Chief (Javier Esparza, TU Mnchen, and Uri Zwick, Tel-Aviv 
University) and then worked with the EiCs to assemble a prestigious 
Editorial Board. The Advisory Board continues to meet regularly, with 
the EiCs, to help steer the journal.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
We also wanted to innovate in the reviewing process, streamlining it 
without compromising in any way the quality of the papers  as we are 
aiming to become one of the very top journals in the field. The 
Editorial Board has a so-called Phase 1 process which typically lasts 
between 2 and 3 months, which determines whether the paper is of the 
caliber expected for the journal (quality of the results and quality of 
the exposition, relatively wide interest), under the assumption that the
 proofs are correct. When this Phase 1 concludes positively, Phase 2 
starts, with the objective of verifying the proofs and, possibly, making
 constructive suggestions to the authors as to how to better present 
their results. The result, we hope, is a higher quality for the papers 
published, and also a shorter response time for most of the papers which
 will end up being rejected. As of early 2023, on average, a decision 
for Phase 1 was reached 64 days after submission, within the three-month
 commitment the Editorial Board made. 85% of the papers got a Phase 1 
decision within 94 days.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
TheoretiCS remains a work in progress, though we now have something to 
show for our efforts. The long-term success of the journal will however 
continue to depend on the support of the scientific community it wants 
to serve. Your support is precious in this context, and we hope you will
 spread the word and encourage people around you to submit their best 
papers to TheoretiCS.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
With best regards,&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Thomas Schwentick, Meena Mahajan and Pascal Weil,&lt;br /&gt;
respectively Chair, Secretary and Treasurer of the TheoretiCS Foundation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Luca Aceto&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-03 10:33:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Luca Aceto</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Many Qualities of a New Directly Accessible Compression Scheme</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.18063</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.18063</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Cantone_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Domenico Cantone&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Faro_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Simone Faro&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present a new variable-length computation-friendly encoding scheme, named
SFDC (Succinct Format with Direct aCcesibility), that supports direct and fast
accessibility to any element of the compressed sequence and achieves
compression ratios often higher than those offered by other solutions in the
literature. The SFDC scheme provides a flexible and simple representation
geared towards either practical efficiency or compression ratios, as required.
For a text of length $n$ over an alphabet of size $\sigma$ and a fixed
parameter $\lambda$, the access time of the proposed encoding is proportional
to the length of the character&#39;s code-word, plus an expected
$\mathcal{O}((F_{\sigma - \lambda + 3} - 3)/F_{\sigma+1})$ overhead, where
$F_j$ is the $j$-th number of the Fibonacci sequence. In the overall it uses
$N+\mathcal{O}\big(n \left(\lambda - (F_{\sigma+3}-3)/F_{\sigma+1}\big) \right)
= N + \mathcal{O}(n)$ bits, where $N$ is the length of the encoded string.
Experimental results show that the performance of our scheme is, in some
respects, comparable with the performance of DACs and Wavelet Tees, which are
among of the most efficient schemes. In addition our scheme is configured as a
\emph{computation-friendly compression} scheme, as it counts several features
that make it very effective in text processing tasks. In the string matching
problem, that we take as a case study, we experimentally prove that the new
scheme enables results that are up to 29 times faster than standard
string-matching techniques on plain texts.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-03 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Shipper collaboration matching: fast enumeration of triangular transports with high cooperation effects</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.18222</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.18222</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Kira_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Akifumi Kira&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Terajima_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nobuo Terajima&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Watanabe_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Yasuhiko Watanabe&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Yamamoto_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hirotaka Yamamoto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The logistics industry in Japan is facing a severe shortage of labor.
Therefore, there is an increasing need for joint transportation allowing large
amounts of cargo to be transported using fewer trucks. In recent years, the use
of artificial intelligence and other new technologies has gained wide attention
for improving matching efficiency. However, it is difficult to develop a system
that can instantly respond to requests because browsing through enormous
combinations of two transport lanes is time consuming. In this study, we focus
on a form of joint transportation called triangular transportation and
enumerate the combinations with high cooperation effects. The proposed
algorithm makes good use of hidden inequalities, such as the distance axiom, to
narrow down the search range without sacrificing accuracy. Numerical
experiments show that the proposed algorithm is thousands of times faster than
simple brute force. With this technology as the core engine, we developed a
joint transportation matching system. The system has already been in use by
over 150 companies as of October 2022, and was featured in a collection of
logistics digital transformation cases published by Japan&#39;s Ministry of Land,
Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-03 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>TR23-041 |  The communication complexity of functions with large outputs | 

	Sophie Laplante, 

	Mathieu Lauriere, 

	Lila Fontes, 

	Alexandre Nolin</title>
  <guid>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/041</guid>
  <link>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2023/041</link>
  <description>
    We study the two-party communication complexity of functions with large outputs, and show that the communication complexity can greatly vary depending on what output model is considered. We study a variety of output models, ranging from the open model, in which an external observer can compute the outcome, to the XOR model, in which the outcome of the protocol should be the bitwise XOR of the players local outputs. This model is inspired by XOR games, which are widely studied two-player quantum games.
We focus on the question of error-reduction in these new output models. For functions of output size k, applying standard error reduction techniques in the XOR model would introduce an additional cost linear in k. We show that no dependency on k is necessary. Similarly, standard randomness removal techniques, incur a multiplicative cost of 2k in the XOR model. We show how to reduce this factor to O(k).
In addition, we prove analogous error reduction and randomness removal results in the other models, separate all models from each other, and show that some natural problems  including Set Intersection and Find the First Difference  separate the models when the Hamming weights of their inputs is bounded. Finally, we show how to use the rank lower bound technique for our weak output models.
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-01 22:18:55 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>ECCC Papers</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Quips are what Ive got</title>
  <guid>https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=7188</guid>
  <link>https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=7188</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;In the comments on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=7174&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8212;the one about the open letter calling for a six-month pause on AI scaling&amp;#8212;a commenter named Hans Holander berates me over and over, as have others before him, for my failure to see that GPT is just a hoax and scam with no true intelligence.  Below is my reply: probably one of the most revealing things Ive ever written (which is saying something).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;hr class=&quot;wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity&quot;/&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The great irony here is that &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; youre rightand youre obviously 3000% confident that youre rightthen by my lights, there is no reason whatsoever to pause the scaling of Large Language Models, as your fellow LLM skeptics have urged.  If LLMs are mere &amp;#8220;stochastic parrots,&amp;#8221; and if further scaling will do nothing to alleviate their parroticity, then thered seem to be little danger that they&amp;#8217;ll ever form grounded plans to take over the world, or even help evil people form such plans. And soon it will be clear to everyone that LLMs are just a gigantic boondoggle that dont help them solve their problems, and the entire direction will be abandoned. All a six-month pause would accomplish would be to delay this much-needed reckoning.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;More broadly, though, do you see the problem with just following your conscience in this subject? Theres no way to operationalize follow your conscience, except do the thing that will make the highest moral authorities that you recognize not be disappointed in you, not consider you a coward or a monster or a failure. But what if theres no agreement among the highest moral authorities that you recognize, or the people who set themselves up as the moral authorities? What if people will call you a coward or a monster or a failure, will even do so right in your comment section, &lt;em&gt;regardless&lt;/em&gt; of what you choose?&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;This, of course, is hardly the first time in my life Ive been in this situation, condemned for X and equally condemned for not(X).  Ive never known how to navigate it.  When presented with diametrically opposed views about morality or the future of civilization, all confidently held by people who I consider smart and grounded, I can switch back and forth between the perspectives like with the Necker cube or the duck-rabbit.  But I dont have any confident worldview of my own.  What I have are mostly quips, and jokes, and metaphors, and realizing when one thing contradicts a different thing, and lectures (many people do seem to like my lectures) where I lay out all the different considerations, and sometimes I also have neat little technical observations that occasionally even get dignified with the name of theorems and published in papers.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;A quarter-century ago, though I remember like yesterday, I was an undergrad at Cornell, and belonged to a scholarship house called Telluride, where house-members had responsibilities for upkeep and governance and whatnot and would write periodic reviews of each other&amp;#8217;s performance.  And I once got a scathing performance review, which took me to task for shirking my housework, and bringing my problem sets to the house meetings.  (These were meetings where the great issues of the day were debated&amp;#8212;like whether or not to allocate $50 for fixing a light, and how guilty to feel over hiring maintenance workers and thereby participating in capitalist exploitation.)  And then there was this: &amp;#8220;Scott&amp;#8217;s contributions to house meetings are often limited to clever quips that, while amusing, do not advance the meeting agenda at all.&amp;#8221;  &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Im not like Eliezer Yudkowsky, nor am I even like the anti-Eliezer people. I dont, in the end, have any belief system at all with which to decide questions of a global or even cosmic magnitude, like whether the progress of AI should be paused or not. Mostly all Ive got are the quips and the jokes, and the trying to do right on the smaller questions.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;hr class=&quot;wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity&quot;/&gt;



&lt;p&gt;And anyone who doesnt like this post can consider it an April Fools (hey, Eliezer &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/j9Q8bRmwCgXRYAgcJ/miri-announces-new-death-with-dignity-strategy&quot;&gt;did the same&lt;/a&gt; last year!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Scott&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-01 21:11:47 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Scott Aaronson</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>postdoc at Institute of Mathematics, Czech Academy of Sciences (apply by April 30, 2023)</title>
  <guid>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/04/01/postdoc-at-institute-of-mathematics-czech-academy-of-sciences-apply-by-april-30-2023/</guid>
  <link>https://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/04/01/postdoc-at-institute-of-mathematics-czech-academy-of-sciences-apply-by-april-30-2023/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;(Extended deadline) The Institute of Mathematics of the Czech Academy of Sciences is seeking a researcher for the project Logic and unsatisfiability. Applications are invited from candidates who have completed their PhD within the last 5 years (or will have completed it before the time of hiring), and who have a strong background in proof complexity or bounded arithmetic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.math.cas.cz/recrutements/postes.php&quot;&gt;http://www.math.cas.cz/recrutements/postes.php&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: thapen@math.cas.cz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-01 19:25:48 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>CCI: jobs</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Who&#39;s on April First</title>
  <guid>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-691726575962306125</guid>
  <link>https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2023/04/whos-on-april-first.html</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgUtAqIYgEqirBv-z2YRBAEYrFBAawDGs1NjdMsbwYKeoNs_ma5zlR9yyRD5ifxav8zQt3FhOBV8_xLQjScraH3UoscL-RS-nmYPpzQvEuZW9frJXlc1txBOpoTsGz5lUtJ1dAmArOvA2dagN1l-J5Uda-v959LDoBiidDWUZCQQVSsc7LUoA/s1024/baseball.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; data-original-height=&quot;769&quot; data-original-width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;240&quot; src=&quot;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgUtAqIYgEqirBv-z2YRBAEYrFBAawDGs1NjdMsbwYKeoNs_ma5zlR9yyRD5ifxav8zQt3FhOBV8_xLQjScraH3UoscL-RS-nmYPpzQvEuZW9frJXlc1txBOpoTsGz5lUtJ1dAmArOvA2dagN1l-J5Uda-v959LDoBiidDWUZCQQVSsc7LUoA/w320-h240/baseball.jpg&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Carlos May waving to the crowd on April 1, 1972&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Instead of the usual April Fools Day post, I present one of the best April Fools Day stunts ever. Heres the text from an old Parade Magazine clipping I dug up recently that was published on April 1, 1985.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to innovative and wacky ideas in baseball, Bill Veeck was a true legend. As a team owner and promoter, Veeck was known for his creative approach to the sport, from planting ivy on the walls at Wrigley Field&amp;nbsp;to his famous &quot;exploding scoreboard&quot; at Comiskey Park. But did you know about the time Veeck pulled off an unforgettable April Fools&#39; stunt by having the 1972 Chicago White Sox wear the names from the classic &quot;Who&#39;s on First?&quot; sketch?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was April 1, 1972, and the Chicago White Sox were getting ready to play a game that would go down in history. Bill Veeck had decided to pay homage to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/sShMA85pv8M&quot;&gt;iconic comedy routine&lt;/a&gt; by Bud Abbott and Lou Costello, considered by many the greatest comedy sketch ever performed. For those unfamiliar with the sketch, it revolves around a series of misunderstandings based on the names of the players on a fictional baseball team. The names sound like common phrases, leading to a hilariously confusing conversation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Veeck&#39;s version of the stunt, the White Sox players would take the field with the names of the &quot;Who&#39;s on First?&quot; team on the back of their jerseys. The players, initially skeptical of the idea, eventually embraced the spirit of April Fools&#39; Day and played along.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the game commenced, fans were treated to a scene straight out of the Abbott and Costello routine. Instead of their usual names, the players&#39; jerseys featured names like &quot;Who,&quot; &quot;What,&quot; &quot;I Don&#39;t Know,&quot; &quot;Why,&quot; &quot;Because,&quot; &quot;Tomorrow,&quot; and &quot;Today.&quot; Here was the starting lineup:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;Who - First Base: Dick Allen&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;What - Second Base: Mike Andrews&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;I Don&#39;t Know - Third Base: Bill Melton&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Why - Left Field: Carlos May&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Because - Center Field: Ken Berry&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Abbott - Right Field: Jay Johnstone&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;I Don&#39;t Care - Shortstop: Luis Aparicio&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Today - Catcher: Ed Herrmann&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Tomorrow - Pitcher: Wilbur Wood&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;div&gt;The right fielder is never named in the sketch. Pat Kelly pinch hit for Johnstone in the 6th wearing Costello.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The confusion was not only limited to the fans in the stadium. The opposing team and the umpires struggled to keep track of the game, often leading to comical misunderstandings on the field. For instance, the umpire might have shouted, &quot;Who&#39;s out!&quot; only to be met with the response, &quot;No, Who&#39;s on first!&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Though some traditional baseball fans were initially taken aback by the stunt, the majority embraced the humor, making the game one of the most memorable in White Sox history. It was a testament to Veeck&#39;s genius that he could seamlessly blend comedy with the sport he loved.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &quot;Who&#39;s on First?&quot; game became a cherished part of baseball lore and added to the legend of Bill Veeck. It demonstrated his willingness to think outside the box, engage fans, and remind everyone that, at its core, baseball should be a source of fun and entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 1972 Chicago White Sox &quot;Who&#39;s on First?&quot; April Fools&#39; Day game captured the spirit of Bill Veeck&#39;s inventive approach to baseball. As we celebrate April Fools&#39; Day this year, let&#39;s remember the time when the White Sox took the field with the most confusing lineup in baseball history and showed us all that, sometimes, laughter truly is the best medicine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Lance Fortnow&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-01 14:04:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>What is the difference between PBFT, Tendermint, HotStuff, and HotStuff-2?</title>
  <guid>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2023-04-01-hotstuff-2/</guid>
  <link>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2023-04-01-hotstuff-2/</link>
  <description>
    We recently published our work HotStuff-2 on eprint, introducing a two-phase HotStuff variant which simultaneously achieves $O(n^2)$ worst-case communication, optimistically linear communication, a two-phase commit regime within a view, and optimistic responsiveness in partially-synchronous BFT. The main takeaway is that two phases are enough for BFT after all. In this...
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-01 05:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Decentralized Thoughts</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The ChatGPT Conundrum</title>
  <guid>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=21383</guid>
  <link>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/04/01/the-chatgpt-conundrum/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;
&lt;font color=&quot;#0044cc&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;High absolute, low relative Kolmogorov complexity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;font color=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;image alignright&quot;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/04/01/the-chatgpt-conundrum/chatgptfool/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-21385&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;21385&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/04/01/the-chatgpt-conundrum/chatgptfool/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/ChatGPTFool.jpg?fit=755%2C474&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;755,474&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;KWRegan&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;ChatGPTFool&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/ChatGPTFool.jpg?fit=300%2C188&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/ChatGPTFool.jpg?fit=600%2C377&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/ChatGPTFool.jpg?resize=189%2C118&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;189&quot; height=&quot;118&quot; class=&quot;alignnone wp-image-21385&quot; srcset=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/ChatGPTFool.jpg?w=755&amp;amp;ssl=1 755w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/ChatGPTFool.jpg?resize=300%2C188&amp;amp;ssl=1 300w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 189px) 100vw, 189px&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;caption alignright&quot;&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;-2&quot;&gt;4/1 prank &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.abplive.com/technology/chatgpt/april-fools-day-prank-chatgpt-suggest-fake-cake-upside-down-room-tricks-ideas-1592331&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
[Editors&amp;#8217; Note: Our usual blog format has the first paragraph lead with a human subject, but that does not apply here. &amp;#8212;RJL and KWR]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today, on this delightful April 1st, we bring you an intriguing revelation about the now-famous AI model, ChatGPT, which has gained notoriety for its ability to generate human-like text. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As many of you know, ChatGPT has been a hot topic in the computational world, but today we reveal a surprising truth: ChatGPT demonstrates high absolute Kolmogorov complexity but low relative Kolmogorov complexity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This breakthrough insight, which we&amp;#8217;ll call the &amp;#8220;ChatGPT Conundrum,&amp;#8221; has profound implications for complexity theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; KC &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Recall that the Kolmogorov complexity of a string is the shortest program (in some fixed programming language) that outputs the string. The absolute Kolmogorov complexity is concerned with the shortest program that produces a given string, while the relative complexity is the shortest program that produces the string, given another string as input.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our investigation began when we received an anonymous tip from a ChatGPT researcher who goes by the pseudonym &amp;#8220;Alan Turing Jr.&amp;#8221; They shared with us an unpublished manuscript detailing the intricate inner workings of the ChatGPT model. This document&amp;#8212;code-named &amp;#8220;The GPT-4 Enigma&amp;#8221;&amp;#8212;revealed that ChatGPT&amp;#8217;s design is incredibly complex, leading to high absolute Kolmogorov complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
However, what truly piqued our interest was the revelation that ChatGPT&amp;#8217;s output exhibits low relative Kolmogorov complexity when compared to any input. This means that, given an input string, there is a short program that generates ChatGPT&amp;#8217;s output using the input as a starting point. This may seem counterintuitive, as the AI produces incredibly human-like text, but it turns out that the model leverages its vast knowledge of the internet to create this illusion of complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; A New Class &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
This discovery led us to formulate a new complexity class, dubbed &amp;#8220;CHP&amp;#8221; (ChatGPT&amp;#8217;s Humble Paradox), which captures the unusual behavior of the ChatGPT Conundrum. As one would expect, CHP lies somewhere between P and NP, but it turns out it is also incomparable to both! This perplexing result has left the complexity theory community in a state of bewilderment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On a lighter note, we have heard rumors that a secret society of computer scientists is working on an even more advanced AI model, GPT-5. They hope to harness the ChatGPT Conundrum to create an AI that can solve NP-complete problems in polynomial time! If they succeed, we might finally have an answer to the age-old P vs. NP question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; Open Problems &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Of course, we must remind you that today is April Fool&amp;#8217;s Day. Could this tale be an elaborate hoax? Or is it a genuine breakthrough that will reshape our understanding of complexity theory? We leave it up to you, dear reader, to decide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Happy April Fool&amp;#8217;s Day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By RJLipton+KWRegan&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-04-01 04:02:56 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Richard Lipton</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Linkage with two breakthroughs</title>
  <guid>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2023/03/31/linkage-two-breakthroughs</guid>
  <link>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2023/03/31/linkage-two-breakthroughs.html</link>
  <description>
    &lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.09521&quot;&gt;An exponential improvement for diagonal Ramsey&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@tao/110034365802889269&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; The number of vertices needed to force either a &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;\(k\)-vertex&lt;/span&gt; clique or independent set is now down to \((4-\varepsilon)^k\) for a &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;small \(\varepsilon\).&lt;/span&gt; New preprint by Sahasrabudhe, Morris, Griffiths and Campos.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@joshmillard@mastodon.social/110039351524948885&quot;&gt;Josh Millard asks&lt;/a&gt;: where did &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polite_number&quot;&gt;polite numbers&lt;/a&gt; get their name? (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.metafilter.com/198606/Number-encyclopedia#8374632&quot;&gt;See also MF&lt;/a&gt;.) The answer may be in a 1988 issue of The Open Universitys &lt;em&gt;Sesame&lt;/em&gt; magazine, but it appears to be offline-only.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dehn_invariant&quot;&gt;Dehn invariant&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/110048576562617907&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; a value in an infinite-dimensional tensor space, determined from a polyhedron, that controls which other polyhedra it can be cut apart and reassembled into. Space-filling polyhedra must have Dehn invariant zero. For flexible polyhedra, the Dehn invariant stays constant as they flex. Now another Wikipedia Good Article.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Barriers and pathways to complexity lower bounds: &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/OTepzduYono&quot;&gt;relativization and algebrization&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/c8mCopOw_MI&quot;&gt;natural proofs&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/ylb0-YPFadw&quot;&gt;new stuff&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@rrwilliams@mastodon.social/109979448872186191&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; Three one-hour lectures from a virtual seminar by Ryan Williams.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boingboing.net/2023/03/20/stock-photo-sites-abuse-of-public-domain-images-countered-with-better-scans-and-a-0-price-tag.html&quot;&gt;Cory Doctorows new hobby is finding high-priced stock image copies of public-domain art, seeking out the originals, cleaning up the scans, and making them freely available at Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/110056699960584261&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.10798&quot;&gt;An aperiodic monotile&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@csk/110058807978537887&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; The long-sought solution to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Einstein_problem&quot;&gt;einstein problem&lt;/a&gt; by Smith, Myers, Kaplan, and Goodman-Strauss. There is a lot more that could be linked here; see &lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/03/31/a-new-tiling/&quot;&gt;Gdels Lost Letter&lt;/a&gt; for a pretty good roundup.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sad news for combinatorics: &lt;a href=&quot;https://mta.hu/mta_hirei/elhunyt-t-sos-vera-matematikus-az-mta-rendes-tagja-112809&quot;&gt;Vera Ss has died&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/110068824474268728&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; In Hungarian, but mostly readable through automatic translation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@divbyzero/110027300747816292&quot;&gt;The lost origin of the Lady on the Lake puzzle&lt;/a&gt;, in which someone on a boat at the center of a circular lake must escape someone on land who can move four times as fast as the boat. Maybe from Cambridge? Maybe from Malaysia? Maybe from papers by Guy or OBeirne?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/17-animal_inheritance_puzzle&quot;&gt;New Wikipedia article on a widely circulating recreational mathematics puzzle: how to divide 17 camels among three sons who are to get 1/2, 1/3, and 1/9 of the estate respectively&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/110080282730310183&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; It was repeatedly published in the late 19th and early 20th century, often given a vaguely oriental origin. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.4169%2Fmathhorizons.21.1.8&quot;&gt;Stockmeyer in 2013&lt;/a&gt; gives the earliest of these as 1873 London. But &lt;a href=&quot;https://ageron.users.lmno.cnrs.fr/17chameaux.pdf&quot;&gt;Ageron, also 2013&lt;/a&gt;, while agreeing that it is not from medieval Islamic mathematics, found it earlier, in the 18th-century work of an Iranian mullah. What could be the missing link? I think I have found one: James Phillips Fletcher recounts the story in his 1850 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/notesfromnineve00fletgoog/page/n213&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes from Nineveh: And Travels in Mesopotamia, Assyria and Syria&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and it was immediately &lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalcommons.colby.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1168&amp;amp;context=eastern_mail&quot;&gt;taken up by newspaper puzzle columnists&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After spending too much time recently fighting unsuccessfully with editorialmanager to set up yet another account on yet another subdomain of editorialmanager.com for the sole purpose of sending one referee report to an editor, and eventually giving up and looking up the editors email address instead, I am strongly tempted to boycott all refereeing requests that require me to set up even more editorialmanager accounts &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/110085946880291332&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; It should not take this much effort to do what is essentially volunteer work for a for-profit company. They have enough money that they can pay for some usability engineers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The hills around here are currently carpeted with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Encelia_californica&quot;&gt;California coast sunflowers&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/110092662654423131&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/sunflowers/&quot;&gt;A couple more shots&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/sunflowers/1-m.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;California coast sunflowers in the UC Irvine Ecological Preserve, among other coastal sage scrub including a cholla and patches of prickly pear&quot; style=&quot;border-style:solid;border-color:black&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://themarkup.org/organ-failure/2023/03/21/poorer-states-suffer-under-new-organ-donation-rules-as-livers-go-to-waste&quot;&gt;New organ donation rules favor coastal states at the expense of the south and midwest, and lead to more unused organs&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@craignewmark@mastodon.social/110062778645378443&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; The goal of the rule change was to fix problems where equally sick patients were prioritized unequally depending on where they live, but it has led to other problems in the place of that one.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2023/03/the-sigact-book-review-column-list-of.html&quot;&gt;SIGACT wants these books reviewed&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/110104133282428045&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; Former &lt;em&gt;SIGACT News&lt;/em&gt; book review editor Bill Gasarch and current editor Nick Tran post a list of 16 books they need reviews for. Beyond the fame and glory of publishing a book review, if youre in the US you can get a physical copy of the book mailed to you. (Maybe also for elsewhere but that depends on the publisher.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/fast-growing-open-access-journals-stripped-coveted-impact-factors&quot;&gt;Fast-growing open-access journals stripped of coveted impact factors&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/110108688282920362&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:MDPI&quot;&gt;via&lt;/a&gt;). Web of Science is de-listing some 50 journals, including at least 19 from Hindawi and at least 2 from MDPI, likely in part because of these journals many dubiously-curated and dubiously-on-topic special issues. A consultant quoted in the article says My expectation is that this initial delisting  is only the tip of the iceberg.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.babelstone.co.uk/Blog/2007/04/numbers-that-dont-add-up-tibetan-half.html&quot;&gt;Numbers that dont add up: Tibetan half digits&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@christianp/110106352612670334&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{M}\)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; Theyre encoded in the Unicode standards, but with one example (from a postage stamp), do we know what theyre supposed to mean?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By David Eppstein&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-03-31 22:46:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>David Eppstein</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Using Theory to Design Better Interactions with Visualized Data</title>
  <guid>https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/?p=894</guid>
  <link>https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/2023/03/using-theory-to-design-better-interactions-with-visualized-data/</link>
  <description>
    by Jessica Hullman (Senior Law and Society Fellow (Fall 2022), Simons Institute)  Theories of sequential decision-making have been around for decades but continue to flourish. The Simons Institutes Fall 2022 program on Data-Driven Decision Processes provided an excellent overview &amp;#8230; &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/2023/03/using-theory-to-design-better-interactions-with-visualized-data/&quot;&gt;Continue reading &lt;span class=&quot;meta-nav&quot;&gt;&amp;#8594;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Simons Institute Editor&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-03-31 07:01:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Simons Institute Blog</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A New Tiling</title>
  <guid>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=21355</guid>
  <link>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/03/31/a-new-tiling/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;
&lt;font color=&quot;#0044cc&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;With a flip and some twists&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;font color=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Roger Penrose has been floored. And perhaps re-floored. Here he is standing on the floor of the Mitchell Institute of Texas A&amp;#038;M, which features one of the famous aperiodic &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penrose_tiling&quot;&gt;tilings&lt;/a&gt; he discovered in the 1970s. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table style=&quot;margin:auto;&quot;&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/03/31/a-new-tiling/rp-2/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-21357&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;21357&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/03/31/a-new-tiling/rp-2/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/rp.jpg?fit=440%2C518&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;440,518&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;rp&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/rp.jpg?fit=255%2C300&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/rp.jpg?fit=440%2C518&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/rp.jpg?resize=330%2C390&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;330&quot; height=&quot;390&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter wp-image-21357&quot; srcset=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/rp.jpg?w=440&amp;amp;ssl=1 440w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/rp.jpg?resize=255%2C300&amp;amp;ssl=1 255w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 330px) 100vw, 330px&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;caption alignright&quot;&gt;&lt;FONT size=&quot;-2&quot;&gt;Wikipedia &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penrose_tiling&quot;&gt;src&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Aperiodic means that the set of two &lt;a href=&quot;https://tilings.math.uni-bielefeld.de/substitution/penrose-rhomb/&quot;&gt;rhombus&lt;/a&gt; tiles (with notches making them align only in certain ways) can cover the entire plane but only without any globally repeating pattern. Simple tilings, of the kind we covered &lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2017/07/16/kitchen-tile-catalog-complete/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, make a finite pattern that can be translated to cover the infinite plane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Penrose discovered another aperiodic tiling with only two pieces: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mathworld.wolfram.com/PenroseTiles.html&quot;&gt;kite&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.r-bloggers.com/2019/06/kites-and-darts-the-penrose-tiling/&quot;&gt;dart&lt;/a&gt; (again with forced markings). But for over 50 years it was open whether there is a single connected tile that can cover the whole plane but only aperiodically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Oxford&amp;#8217;s new Mathematical Institute&amp;#8212;Roger&amp;#8217;s home base&amp;#8212;has a courtyard paved with another of his tilings.  Now there is a new pattern to use for flooring:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/03/31/a-new-tiling/pattern/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-21358&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;21358&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/03/31/a-new-tiling/pattern/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/pattern.jpg?fit=1440%2C810&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1440,810&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;pattern&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/pattern.jpg?fit=300%2C169&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/pattern.jpg?fit=600%2C338&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/pattern.jpg?resize=550%2C310&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;550&quot; height=&quot;310&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter wp-image-21358&quot; srcset=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/pattern.jpg?w=1440&amp;amp;ssl=1 1440w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/pattern.jpg?resize=300%2C169&amp;amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/pattern.jpg?resize=1024%2C576&amp;amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/pattern.jpg?resize=768%2C432&amp;amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/pattern.jpg?resize=1200%2C675&amp;amp;ssl=1 1200w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; The New Pattern and Its Twists &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The single tile and its surprising properties were discovered by David Smith, Joseph Samuel Myers, Craig Kaplan, and Chaim Goodman-Strauss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table style=&quot;margin:auto;&quot;&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/03/31/a-new-tiling/tilers4/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-21359&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;21359&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/03/31/a-new-tiling/tilers4/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Tilers4.png?fit=369%2C403&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;369,403&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;Tilers4&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Tilers4.png?fit=275%2C300&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Tilers4.png?fit=369%2C403&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Tilers4.png?resize=246%2C268&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;246&quot; height=&quot;268&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter wp-image-21359&quot; srcset=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Tilers4.png?w=369&amp;amp;ssl=1 369w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Tilers4.png?resize=275%2C300&amp;amp;ssl=1 275w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 246px) 100vw, 246px&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;caption alignright&quot;&gt;&lt;FONT size=&quot;-2&quot;&gt;Composite crop from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AlexKontorovich/status/1640047202763522049&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.egmo.org/people/person144/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gathering4gardner.org/chaim-goodman-strauss/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://cs.uwaterloo.ca/~csk/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/FONT&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The introduction to their recently-posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.10798&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; has a nifty sentence that foreshadows why neither the discovery nor the proof of its correctness were easy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; Can one tile embody enough complexity to forcibly disrupt periodic order at all scales? &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
They have answered this question &lt;em&gt;yes&lt;/em&gt;, though with one asterisk: their asymmetric tile needs to call on its mirror twin&amp;#8212;obtained by flipping it over&amp;#8212;to complete the tilings. Whereas, the tiles in Penrose&amp;#8217;s pairs each have mirror symmetry and so work solely by translations. Penrose&amp;#8217;s rhombus tiles are also convex, whereas the 13-sided &amp;#8220;hat&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;shirt&amp;#8221; shape&amp;#8212;as with Penrose&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;dart&amp;#8221; shape&amp;#8212;is not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencenews.org/article/mathematicians-discovered-einstein-tile&quot;&gt;several&lt;/a&gt; popular-science &lt;a href=&quot;https://phys.org/news/2023-03-geometric-tiled.html&quot;&gt;articles&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://cp4space.hatsya.com/2023/03/21/aperiodic-monotile/&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://aperiodical.com/2023/03/an-aperiodic-monotile-exists/&quot;&gt;posts&lt;/a&gt;, in turn &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2023/03/25/an-aperiodic-monotile/&quot;&gt;linked&lt;/a&gt; by Gil Kalai, the New York Times &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2023/03/28/science/mathematics-tiling-einstein.html&quot;&gt;covered&lt;/a&gt; this in Tuesday&amp;#8217;s science section. The story by &lt;a href=&quot;https://siobhanroberts.com/&quot;&gt;Siobhan Roberts&lt;/a&gt; quoted &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/~senechal/&quot;&gt;Marjorie Senechal&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8212;who was recently editor of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.springer.com/journal/283&quot;&gt;Mathematical Intelligencer&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt; &amp;#8220;Mathematicians had been searching for such a shape for half a century. It wasn&amp;#8217;t even clear that such a thing could exist.&amp;#8221; &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
This applies whether or not one insists on convexity or translation without flips. In fact, the tile is composed of eight hexagonal slices, also referred to as &amp;#8220;kites&amp;#8221; but thinner than Penrose&amp;#8217;s, in a way that forms an asymmetric sub-region of a simple repeating tiling of those regions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table style=&quot;margin:auto;&quot;&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/03/31/a-new-tiling/monotile3/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-21360&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;21360&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/03/31/a-new-tiling/monotile3/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/monotile3.png?fit=768%2C768&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;768,768&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;monotile3&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/monotile3.png?fit=300%2C300&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/monotile3.png?fit=600%2C600&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/monotile3.png?resize=256%2C256&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;256&quot; height=&quot;256&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter wp-image-21360&quot; srcset=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/monotile3.png?w=768&amp;amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/monotile3.png?resize=300%2C300&amp;amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/monotile3.png?resize=150%2C150&amp;amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/monotile3.png?resize=400%2C400&amp;amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/monotile3.png?resize=200%2C200&amp;amp;ssl=1 200w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 256px) 100vw, 256px&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;caption alignright&quot;&gt;&lt;FONT size=&quot;-2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cp4space.hatsya.com/2023/03/21/aperiodic-monotile/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt; crediting Tilman Piesk&lt;/FONT&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This does not constitute a proof that the tile can cover the whole plane, let alone that it must do so aperiodically. Penrose is quoted in the NYT article as saying he finds the proofs in the new paper &amp;#8220;very complicated.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One further fact that both augments and aids the task of proving is that all tilings composed of hats can be continuously deformed keeping identical shapes that still tautly cover the plane. One direction of twisting terminates in a chevron pattern and the other in a &amp;#8220;comet&amp;#8221; composed of a hexagon plus diamond. The chevron and comet &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; tile repeatedly but here they do not&amp;#8212;meanwhile the authors prove that &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; shape in-between can only tile aperiodically. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cs_kaplan/status/1639269752194342912&quot;&gt;animation&lt;/a&gt; created by Kaplan is also in the NYT article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; The Proofs &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The proofs in the paper need to accomplish two goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Show that the tile (and its flip) can cover the entire plane&amp;#8212;no holes or gaps or dead-ends. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Show that no such covering can be periodic.
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Both tasks are hard, but among several proofs of the latter there is a nifty trick. The former works by an argument that rings of the hat tiles have a logical &amp;#8220;metastructure&amp;#8221; that enables them to scale up while preserving the ability to mesh with the next-inner and next-outer ring. Because the scale expands, this does not constitute a finite period. Also providing slack is the further-proved fact that the hat tile can cover the plane in &lt;em&gt;uncountably&lt;/em&gt; many ways, no two isomorphic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some visuals for the proofs of both points are summarized in a seven-part &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AlexKontorovich/status/1640047202763522049&quot;&gt;telling&lt;/a&gt; on twitter by Alex Kontorovich of Rutgers, which is based on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FkZPMf73qYc&quot;&gt;presentation&lt;/a&gt; given by the authors at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@MuseumOfMathematics&quot;&gt;National Museum of Mathematics&lt;/a&gt;, with which Goodman-Strauss is affiliated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The latter point is given multiple proofs in the paper. One of them, also summarized by Kontorovich from the presentation, has a nifty trick: Suppose the hat gave a periodic tiling. That tiling would admit the continuous twisting action, under which periodicity would be preserved. In particular, the chevron and comet tilings at the endpoints would be periodic after all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table style=&quot;margin:auto;&quot;&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/03/31/a-new-tiling/gridargument/&quot; rel=&quot;attachment wp-att-21362&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;21362&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2023/03/31/a-new-tiling/gridargument/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/GridArgument.png?fit=1099%2C260&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1099,260&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;1&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;GridArgument&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-image-caption=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/GridArgument.png?fit=300%2C71&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/GridArgument.png?fit=600%2C142&amp;amp;ssl=1&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/GridArgument.png?resize=600%2C145&amp;#038;ssl=1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;145&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter wp-image-21362&quot; data-recalc-dims=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;caption alignright&quot;&gt;&lt;FONT size=&quot;-2&quot;&gt;Kontorovich &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AlexKontorovich/status/1640047218802450432&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What the authors call &amp;#8220;a new kind of geometric incommensurability argument&amp;#8221; then comes into play. It ultimately reaches the conclusion that the simple triangular lattice would have equal-area regions under scalings that differ by a factor of &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csqrt%7B2%7D%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;sqrt{2}}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;, a contradiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The paper also gives a long separate proof of forced aperiodicity by means that are more analogous to proofs with other tile sets, but here it needs computer-assisted enumeration and verification of many cases. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; Logic and Complexity Impact? &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The subject of tilings has a long history growing out of art and esthetics, but vital connections to biology, crystallography, and logic were discovered more recently. The logical connection ties in the other two and was elevated by Hao Wang&amp;#8217;s famous &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wang_tile&quot;&gt;proofs&lt;/a&gt; that certain tiling problems&amp;#8212;and questions of periodicity&amp;#8212;are undecidable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just a few months ago, the online magazine &lt;em&gt;Quanta&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantamagazine.org/nasty-geometry-breaks-decades-old-tiling-conjecture-20221215/&quot;&gt;covered&lt;/a&gt; recent work by Rachel Greenfield and Terance Tao showing that in certain high dimensions &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{d}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;, there are single tiles that cover the space&amp;#8212;using only orientation-preserving translations&amp;#8212;but only aperiodically. Moreover, those tiles conform to the integer grid &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BZ%7D%5Ed%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;mathbb{Z}^d}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;&amp;#8212;that is, they are gluings of unit hypercubes. Siddhartha Bhattacharya &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1602.05738&quot;&gt;proved&lt;/a&gt; in 2020 that such a result was impossible in &lt;img decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BZ%7D%5E2%7D&amp;#038;bg=ffffff&amp;#038;fg=000000&amp;#038;s=0&amp;#038;c=20201002&quot; alt=&quot;{&amp;#92;mathbb{Z}^2}&quot; class=&quot;latex&quot; /&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.07902&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; by Greenfield and Tao is titled, &amp;#8220;Undecidable translational tilings with only two tiles, or one nonabelian tile,&amp;#8221; while the second &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.08451.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; is, &amp;#8220;A counterexample to the periodic tiling conjecture&amp;#8221; with the above result. This supplements and offsets the geenral result that when all translational tilings must be periodic, whether such a tiling is possible for a given set of tiles becomes decidable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We wonder what the impact of the new result will be on these connections, and how far the nexus of logic and combinatorics will reach down into computational complexity theory. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;H2&gt; Open Problems &lt;/H2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
In-between the new discovery using a tile and its flip and the impossibility results for translation-only tilings are questions when rotations in the plane but not flips are allowed. Are those questions still wide open? Look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.mathed.page/2020/12/29/tiling-and-transformations/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for lots on this issue in general. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And partly in jest we ask: will Oxford&amp;#8217;s Mathematical Institute&amp;#8212;or maybe better, &lt;a href=&quot;https://momath.org/&quot;&gt;MoMath&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8212;put in a new floor with the new tiling?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[fixed usage of &amp;#8220;kites&amp;#8221;, noted Penrose tiles need notches/markings to force aperiodicity]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By RJLipton+KWRegan&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-03-31 05:16:36 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Richard Lipton</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>TCS+ talk: Wednesday, April 5  Yael Kalai, MSR New England</title>
  <guid>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=677</guid>
  <link>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2023/03/30/tcs-talk-wednesday-april-5-yael-kalai-msr-new-england/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, April 5th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC). &lt;strong&gt;Yael Kalai&lt;/strong&gt; from MSR New England will speak about &amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;Efficient Verification of Computation on Untrusted Platforms&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8221; (abstract below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to join us live by signing up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/next-tcs-talk&quot;&gt;the online form&lt;/a&gt;. Registration is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; required to attend the interactive talk, and the link will be posted on the website the day prior to the talk; however, by registering in the form, you will receive a reminder, along with the link. (The recorded talk will also be posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/past-talks&quot;&gt;on our website&lt;/a&gt; afterwards) As usual, for more information about the TCS+ online seminar series and the upcoming talks, or to &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/suggest-a-talk&quot;&gt;suggest&lt;/a&gt; a possible topic or speaker, please see &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/&quot;&gt;the website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abstract: Efficient verification of computation is fundamental to computer science and is at the heart of the P vs. NP question. Recently it has had growing practical significance, especially with the increasing popularity of blockchain technologies and cloud computing. In this talk, I will present schemes for verifying the correctness of a computation. I will discuss their impact on quantum complexity, hardness of approximation, and the complexity of Nash equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By plustcs&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-03-31 02:47:42 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>TCS+ Seminar Series</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Online Learning and Disambiguations of Partial Concept Classes</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17578</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17578</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Cheung_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Tsun-Ming Cheung&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hatami_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Hamed Hatami&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hatami_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Pooya Hatami&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hosseini_K/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Kaave Hosseini&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a recent article, Alon, Hanneke, Holzman, and Moran (FOCS &#39;21) introduced
a unifying framework to study the learnability of classes of partial concepts.
One of the central questions studied in their work is whether the learnability
of a partial concept class is always inherited from the learnability of some
``extension&#39;&#39; of it to a total concept class.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They showed this is not the case for PAC learning but left the problem open
for the stronger notion of online learnability.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We resolve this problem by constructing a class of partial concepts that is
online learnable, but no extension of it to a class of total concepts is online
learnable (or even PAC learnable).
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-03-31 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Complexity</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>On the complexity of embedding in graph products</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17028</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17028</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Biedl_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Therese Biedl&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Eppstein_D/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;David Eppstein&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ueckerdt_T/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Torsten Ueckerdt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Graph embedding, especially as a subgraph of a grid, is an old topic in VLSI
design and graph drawing. In this paper, we investigate related questions
concerning the complexity of embedding a graph $G$ in a host graph that is the
strong product of a path $P$ with a graph $H$ that satisfies some properties,
such as having small treewidth, pathwidth or tree depth. We show that this is
NP-hard, even under numerous restrictions on both $G$ and $H$. In particular,
computing the row pathwidth and the row treedepth is NP-hard even for a tree of
small pathwidth, while computing the row treewidth is NP-hard even for
series-parallel graphs.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-03-31 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Computational Geometry</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Training Neural Networks is NP-Hard in Fixed Dimension</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17045</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17045</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Froese_V/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Vincent Froese&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hertrich_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Christoph Hertrich&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the parameterized complexity of training two-layer neural networks
with respect to the dimension of the input data and the number of hidden
neurons, considering ReLU and linear threshold activation functions. Albeit the
computational complexity of these problems has been studied numerous times in
recent years, several questions are still open. We answer questions by Arora et
al. [ICLR &#39;18] and Khalife and Basu [IPCO &#39;22] showing that both problems are
NP-hard for two dimensions, which excludes any polynomial-time algorithm for
constant dimension. We also answer a question by Froese et al. [JAIR &#39;22]
proving W[1]-hardness for four ReLUs (or two linear threshold neurons) with
zero training error. Finally, in the ReLU case, we show fixed-parameter
tractability for the combined parameter number of dimensions and number of
ReLUs if the network is assumed to compute a convex map. Our results settle the
complexity status regarding these parameters almost completely.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-03-31 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Sum-of-Squares Lower Bounds for Densest $k$-Subgraph</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17506</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17506</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Jones_C/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Chris Jones&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Potechin_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Aaron Potechin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Rajendran_G/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Goutham Rajendran&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Xu_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jeff Xu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given a graph and an integer $k$, Densest $k$-Subgraph is the algorithmic
task of finding the subgraph on $k$ vertices with the maximum number of edges.
This is a fundamental problem that has been subject to intense study for
decades, with applications spanning a wide variety of fields. The
state-of-the-art algorithm is an $O(n^{1/4 + \epsilon})$-factor approximation
(for any $\epsilon &amp;gt; 0$) due to Bhaskara et al. [STOC &#39;10]. Moreover, the
so-called log-density framework predicts that this is optimal, i.e. it is
impossible for an efficient algorithm to achieve an $O(n^{1/4 -
\epsilon})$-factor approximation. In the average case, Densest $k$-Subgraph is
a prototypical noisy inference task which is conjectured to exhibit a
statistical-computational gap.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this work, we provide the strongest evidence yet of hardness for Densest
$k$-Subgraph by showing matching lower bounds against the powerful
Sum-of-Squares (SoS) algorithm, a meta-algorithm based on convex programming
that achieves state-of-art algorithmic guarantees for many optimization and
inference problems. For $k \leq n^{\frac{1}{2}}$, we obtain a degree
$n^{\delta}$ SoS lower bound for the hard regime as predicted by the
log-density framework.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To show this, we utilize the modern framework for proving SoS lower bounds on
average-case problems pioneered by Barak et al. [FOCS &#39;16]. A key issue is that
small denser-than-average subgraphs in the input will greatly affect the value
of the candidate pseudoexpectation operator around the subgraph. To handle this
challenge, we devise a novel matrix factorization scheme based on the positive
minimum vertex separator. We then prove an intersection tradeoff lemma to show
that the error terms when using this separator are indeed small.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-03-31 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A Subquadratic Time Algorithm for the Weighted $k$-Center Problem on Cactus Graphs</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17204</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17204</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Bhattacharya_B/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Binay Bhattacharya&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Das_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Sandip Das&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Dev_S/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Subhadeep Ranjan Dev&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The weighted $k$-center problem in graphs is a classical facility location
problem where we place $k$ centers on the graph, which minimize the maximum
weighted distance of a vertex to its nearest center. We study this problem when
the underlying graph is a cactus with $n$ vertices and present an $O(n \log^2
n)$ time algorithm for the same. This time complexity improves upon the
$O(n^2)$ time algorithm by Ben-Moshe et al. [TCS 2007], which is the current
state-of-the-art.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-03-31 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Capacity-Preserving Subgraphs of Directed Flow Networks</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17274</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17274</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Chimani_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Markus Chimani&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Ilsen_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Max Ilsen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduce and discuss the Minimum Capacity-Preserving Subgraph (MCPS)
problem: given a directed graph and a retention ratio $\alpha \in (0,1)$, find
the smallest subgraph that, for each pair of vertices $(u,v)$, preserves at
least a fraction $\alpha$ of a maximum $u$-$v$-flow&#39;s value. This problem
originates from the practical setting of reducing the power consumption in a
computer network: it models turning off as many links as possible while
retaining the ability to transmit at least $\alpha$ times the traffic compared
to the original network.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First we prove that MCPS is NP-hard already on directed acyclic graphs
(DAGs). Our reduction also shows that a closely related problem (which only
considers the arguably most complicated core of the problem in the objective
function) is NP-hard to approximate within a sublogarithmic factor already on
DAGs. In terms of positive results, we present a simple linear time algorithm
that solves MCPS optimally on directed series-parallel graphs (DSPs). Further,
we introduce the family of laminar series-parallel graphs (LSPs), a
generalization of DSPs that also includes cyclic and very dense graphs. Not
only are we able to solve MCPS on LSPs in quadratic time, but our approach also
yields straightforward quadratic time algorithms for several related problems
such as Minimum Equivalent Digraph and Directed Hamiltonian Cycle on LSPs.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-03-31 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Advice Complexity bounds for Online Delayed F-Node-, H-Node- and H-Edge-Deletion Problems</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17346</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17346</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Berndt_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Niklas Berndt&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lotze_H/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Henri Lotze&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let F be a fixed finite obstruction set of graphs and G be a graph revealed
in an online fashion, node by node. The online Delayed F-Node-Deletion Problem
(F-Edge-Deletion Problem}) is to keep G free of every H in F by deleting nodes
(edges) until no induced subgraph isomorphic to any graph in F can be found in
G. The task is to keep the number of deletions minimal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advice complexity is a model in which an online algorithm has access to a
binary tape of infinite length, on which an oracle can encode information to
increase the performance of the algorithm. We are interested in the minimum
number of advice bits that are necessary and sufficient to solve a deletion
problem optimally.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this work, we first give essentially tight bounds on the advice complexity
of the Delayed F-Node-Deletion Problem and F-Edge-Deletion Problem where F
consists of a single, arbitrary graph H. We then show that the gadget used to
prove these results can be utilized to give tight bounds in the case of node
deletions if F consists of either only disconnected graphs or only connected
graphs. Finally, we show that the number of advice bits that is necessary and
sufficient to solve the general Delayed F-Node-Deletion Problem is heavily
dependent on the obstruction set F. To this end, we provide sets for which this
number is either constant, logarithmic or linear in the optimal number of
deletions.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-03-31 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Online Pause and Resume Problem: Optimal Algorithms and An Application to Carbon-Aware Load Shifting</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17551</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17551</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Lechowicz_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Adam Lechowicz&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Christianson_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Nicolas Christianson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Zuo_J/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Jinhang Zuo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Bashir_N/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Noman Bashir&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Hajiesmaili_M/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Mohammad Hajiesmaili&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Wierman_A/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Adam Wierman&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/cs/1/au:+Shenoy_P/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Prashant Shenoy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduce and study the online pause and resume problem. In this problem,
a player attempts to find the $k$ lowest (alternatively, highest) prices in a
sequence of fixed length $T$, which is revealed sequentially. At each time
step, the player is presented with a price and decides whether to accept or
reject it. The player incurs a switching cost whenever their decision changes
in consecutive time steps, i.e., whenever they pause or resume purchasing. This
online problem is motivated by the goal of carbon-aware load shifting, where a
workload may be paused during periods of high carbon intensity and resumed
during periods of low carbon intensity and incurs a cost when saving or
restoring its state. It has strong connections to existing problems studied in
the literature on online optimization, though it introduces unique technical
challenges that prevent the direct application of existing algorithms.
Extending prior work on threshold-based algorithms, we introduce
double-threshold algorithms for both the minimization and maximization variants
of this problem. We further show that the competitive ratios achieved by these
algorithms are the best achievable by any deterministic online algorithm.
Finally, we empirically validate our proposed algorithm through case studies on
the application of carbon-aware load shifting using real carbon trace data and
existing baseline algorithms.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-03-31 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Pseudorandom Linear Codes are List Decodable to Capacity</title>
  <guid>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17554</guid>
  <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17554</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p class=&quot;arxiv-authors&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Aaron/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Aaron&lt;/a&gt; (Louie) &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Putterman/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Putterman&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Pyne_E/0/1/0/all/0/1&quot;&gt;Edward Pyne&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduce a novel family of expander-based error correcting codes. These
codes can be sampled with randomness linear in the block-length, and achieve
list-decoding capacity (among other local properties). Our expander-based codes
can be made starting from any family of sufficiently low-bias codes, and as a
consequence, we give the first construction of a family of algebraic codes that
can be sampled with linear randomness and achieve list-decoding capacity. We
achieve this by introducing the notion of a pseudorandom puncturing of a code,
where we select $n$ indices of a base code $C\subset \mathbb{F}_q^m$ via an
expander random walk on a graph on $[m]$. Concretely, whereas a random linear
code (i.e. a truly random puncturing of the Hadamard code) requires $O(n^2)$
random bits to sample, we sample a pseudorandom linear code with $O(n)$ random
bits. We show that pseudorandom puncturings satisfy several desirable
properties exhibited by truly random puncturings. In particular, we extend a
result of (Guruswami Mosheiff FOCS 2022) and show that a pseudorandom
puncturing of a small-bias code satisfies the same local properties as a random
linear code with high probability. As a further application of our techniques,
we also show that pseudorandom puncturings of Reed Solomon codes are
list-recoverable beyond the Johnson bound, extending a result of (Lund
Potukuchi RANDOM 2020). We do this by instead analyzing properties of codes
with large distance, and show that pseudorandom puncturings still work well in
this regime.
&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-03-31 00:30:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Tenure Track Faculty at Iowa State University (apply by April 4, 2023)</title>
  <guid>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/03/30/tenure-track-faculty-at-iowa-state-university-apply-by-april-4-2023/</guid>
  <link>https://cstheory-jobs.org/2023/03/30/tenure-track-faculty-at-iowa-state-university-apply-by-april-4-2023/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;Iowa State University is seeking tenure track faculty in Theoretical Computer Science (broadly defined).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cra.org/job/iowa-state-university-tenure-track-faculty-positions-in-computer-science/&quot;&gt;https://cra.org/job/iowa-state-university-tenure-track-faculty-positions-in-computer-science/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Email: pavan@iastate.edu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By shacharlovett&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-03-30 18:09:58 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>CCI: jobs</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Logic engines and product graphs</title>
  <guid>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2023/03/30/logic-engines-product</guid>
  <link>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2023/03/30/logic-engines-product.html</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;The graph product structure theorem of Dujmovi et al.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:duj&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:duj&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; states that every planar graph can be represented as a subgraph of a special kind of graph product: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strong_product_of_graphs&quot;&gt;strong product&lt;/a&gt; of a &lt;a href=&quot;Path graph&quot;&gt;path graph&lt;/a&gt; and a graph of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treewidth&quot;&gt;bounded treewidth&lt;/a&gt;. Like other graph products, the strong product \(G\boxtimes H\) of two graphs \(G\) and \(H\) has a vertex for each pair of a vertex in \(G\) and a vertex in \(H\). You can move in the strong product by moving along an edge in one of the factors and staying put in the other (like the Cartesian product) but also by moving along an edge in each factor (like the tensor product). So, for instance, the graph of king moves on a chessboard is a strong product of two paths, one representing the sequence of rows along which the king can move and the other representing the sequence of columns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/2019/kings-graph.svg&quot; alt=&quot;The king&#39;s graph&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terminology later introduced by Bose et al.,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:bos&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:bos&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the graph product structure theorem states that planar graphs have bounded row treewidth. Here, having row treewidth \(w\) is the same as being a subgraph of a strong product of a path with a graph of treewidth \(w\). You can define the same sort of concept row X-width for any other graph width parameter, meaning the same thing: having row X-width \(w\) means being a subgraph of a strong product of a graph of X-width \(w\). Since the announcement of the graph product structure theorem, this area has quickly expanded in interest, with many papers studying the relations between these row parameters, the decompositions of beyond-planar graphs, and other kinds of product decompositions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there has not been as much work so far on the computational complexity of row treewidth and related parameters. Treewidth is NP-hard in general, but for any fixed \(k\), testing whether a graph has treewidth \(k\) takes only linear time.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:bod&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:bod&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Can this sort of fixed-parameter tractable algorithm be found for row treewidth and other analogous parameters? The answer turns out to be no. My new preprint, On the complexity of embedding in graph products, with Therese Biedl and Torsten Ueckerdt (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17028&quot;&gt;arXiv:2303.17028&lt;/a&gt;) provides NP-completeness proofs showing that even the smallest nontrivial parameter values are difficult to test, even on very simple graphs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The starting point for several of our proofs is a result that has been known for much longer: it is hard to tell whether a given graph is a subgraph of the integer grid. It remains hard even when the given graph is a tree.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:bc&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:bc&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The proof uses a technique later called the logic engine,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:ew&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:ew&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in which one makes a graph with pieces that, in any grid embedding, must remain rigid, with flexible connections to the other pieces. The illustration below shows an example that could be used in a proof of the known result that embedding planar graphs as subgraphs of a grid is NP-complete. It is constructed from a not-all-equal satisfiability problem, whose variables are translated into the blue arms of the figure. Each arm can flip vertically, across the central horizontal spine, giving its variable two states, true or false. The green flags, each suspended from a vertical path attached to an arm, can flip to the left or to the right. Each row of flags is confined by the surrounding yellow frame, in such a way that the flags can only fit into their row if at least one arm is missing a flag on that row. When a variable belongs to a clause, its flag is removed from the clauses row of the construction, providing a gap that will allow all the flags to fit on that row.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/2023/logic-engine.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Logic engine graph constructed by a reduction from not-all-equal satisfiability to planar grid embedding. In order for the blue variable arms and green term flags to all fit within the yellow frame, each row of the grid must have at least one missing flag.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grids are Cartesian products of a path with a path, but the products involved in row treewidth and row pathwidth are a bit more complicated, both because they use the strong product in place of the Cartesian product, and because one of the factors is not a path. The simplest case for row treewidth is width one, embedding into a strong product of a path and a tree. Testing whether such an embedding exists is trivial for trees (just use the product of the tree itself with a one-vertex path). But as we prove, it is hard for the next simplest case, when the graph to be embedded has treewidth two. Our proof again uses the logic engine. However, compared to the figure above, more care is needed in the construction to ensure that parts of the logic engine cannot avoid bumping into each other by twisting in ways that would be impossible for Cartesian products but possible in strong products, or by escaping into another branch of the factor graph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testing whether the row pathwidth one turns out to be hard even for trees. Because the graphs of pathwidth one are just the caterpillars, this means testing whether the given tree can be embedded into a strong product of a path with a caterpillar. It would be possible to prove this again using the logic engine, but we dont. Instead, we use the known result that its hard to embed trees into grids. We find a way to transform trees into larger trees so that grid embedding of the smaller tree becomes equivalent to path-caterpillar-product embedding of the expanded tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also prove that row treedepth, defined in the same way, is hard, even to test whether a tree has row treedepth one. This is the same as asking whether the given tree can be represented as a subgraph of a product of a path with a star. For this problem, the logic engine doesnt work. Path-star products are too narrow for its components to fit into them. Instead, we use a different hardness reduction based on bin packing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even accurately approximating the row treewidth is hard, at least if you believe that approximating treewidth itself is hard. The hardness of approximation of treewidth has not been proven rigorously, but instead rests on an unproven assumption, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Small_set_expansion_hypothesis&quot;&gt;small set expansion hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;, a variant of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unique_games_conjecture&quot;&gt;unique games conjecture&lt;/a&gt;. But if this assumption is true, then it is impossible to approximate treewidth to within any constant factor. If you add a universal vertex to a graph, you dont change its treewidth much, but you force its row treewidth to be within a constant factor of its treewidth, because it prevents you from using path factors that are longer than two edges. So, under this assumption, it is also impossible to approximate row treewidth to within any constant factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:duj&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Vida Dujmovi, Gwenal Joret, Piotr Micek, Pat Morin, Torsten Ueckerdt, and David R. Wood (2020), Planar graphs have bounded queue-number, &lt;em&gt;JACM&lt;/em&gt; 67 (4): Art. 22, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1145/3385731&quot;&gt;doi:10.1145/3385731&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.04791&quot;&gt;arXiv:1904.04791&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:duj&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:bos&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Prosenjit Bose, Vida Dujmovi, Mehrnoosh Javarsineh, Pat Morin, David R. Wood (2022), Separating layered treewidth and row treewidth, &lt;em&gt;DMTCS&lt;/em&gt; 24 (1): Art. 18, &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2105.01230&quot;&gt;arXiv:2105.01230&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:bos&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:bod&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hans L. Bodlaender (1996), A linear time algorithm for finding tree-decompositions of small treewidth, &lt;em&gt;SICOMP&lt;/em&gt; 25 (6): 13051317, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1137/S0097539793251219&quot;&gt;doi:10.1137/S0097539793251219&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:bod&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:bc&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Sandeep Bhatt and Stavros Cosmadakis (1987), The complexity of minimizing wire lengths in VLSI layouts, &lt;em&gt;IPL&lt;/em&gt; 25 (4): 263267, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/0020-0190(87)90173-6&quot;&gt;doi:10.1016/0020-0190(87)90173-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:bc&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:ew&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Peter Eades and Sue Whitesides (1996), The logic engine and the realization problem for nearest neighbor graphs, &lt;em&gt;TCS&lt;/em&gt; 169 (1): 2327, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/S0304-3975(97)84223-5&quot;&gt;doi:10.1016/S0304-3975(97)84223-5&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:ew&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/110115277230448668&quot;&gt;Discuss on Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By David Eppstein&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-03-30 16:46:00 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>David Eppstein</author>
</item>

<item>
  <title>TCS for all travel grants and speaker nominations (guest post by Elena Grigorescu)</title>
  <guid>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=8588</guid>
  <link>https://windowsontheory.org/2023/03/30/tcs-for-all-travel-grants-and-speaker-nominations-guest-post-by-elena-grigorescu/</link>
  <description>
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TCS for All (previously TCS Women) Spotlight Workshop at STOC 2023/Theory Fest: Travel grants and call for speaker nominations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;You are cordially invited to our TCS for All Spotlight Workshop! The workshop will be held&amp;nbsp;on Thursday, June 22nd, 2023 (2-4pm), in Orlando, Florida, USA, as part of the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://acm-stoc.org/stoc2022/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;54th&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://acm-stoc.org/stoc2023/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;Symposium&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://acm-stoc.org/stoc2022/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;on Theory of Computing (STOC)&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;and TheoryFest! The workshop is open to all.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;We are happy to announce that our annual inspirational talk will be given by Professor Dana Randall!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;More information about the workshop is available here:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sigact.org/tcsforall/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;https://sigact.org/tcsforall/&lt;/a&gt;. In particular, we would like to highlight the TCS for All Travel Scholarships (deadline&amp;nbsp;May 7th) and a call for nominations for Rising Stars talks at the workshop (deadline&amp;nbsp;May 7th).&amp;nbsp; More information on those are below.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Hope to see you in Orlando!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;TCS for All Travel Scholarship:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;TCS for All Travel Scholarships are intended for researchers at the beginning of their career. This scholarship is being made available for minorities in TCS, and anyone who identifies as such is welcome to apply; this scholarship is open to both US and international students. Preference will be given to students at the beginning of their studies. If we have sufficient funding, we will give awards to more senior students and possibly even postdocs.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;To apply, you will need to fill out the following form by&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;May 7th, 2023&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;(11:59 pm PDT) in which you provide basic information about yourself, an estimate of your expenses, and a brief statement:&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://forms.gle/btayQhoATxEkGoV18&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;Apply for a travel grant here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;In addition, you will need to have your advisor (or department head or other faculty mentor if you do not yet have an advisor) send a letter of support to&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:tcswomen@gmail.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;tcswomen@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;by&amp;nbsp;May 7th. Your advisors letter should also describe the availability of other travel funds.&amp;nbsp; Note for advisors: Specifics about alternative funding are very helpful.&amp;nbsp; Statements like funding is tight are not very helpful. This letter should be sent with subject line support letter for [your name]. This is very important. Your application is not complete without this letter.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Late applications (after&amp;nbsp;May 7th) will not be accepted. You will be notified about your status by&amp;nbsp;May 15th, which is prior to the STOC early registration deadline and hotel cut-off deadline.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Notes: Receipts will be required for all travel awards, and reimbursements will be made after the conference. Food or visa expenses will not be reimbursed.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nominations for Rising Star talks:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;We invite nomination for speakers in our Rising Star talks at the TCS for All Spotlight Workshop at STOC 2023. To be eligible, your nominee has to be a senior PhD student with expected graduation no later than August 2024,&amp;nbsp;or&amp;nbsp;a postdoc in theoretical computer science (all topics represented at STOC are welcome), an underrepresented minority, and not a speaker at a previous TCS Women Spotlight Workshop.&amp;nbsp; Preference will be given to speakers who are currently on the job market for postdoctoral/faculty positions, or who expect to be on the job market in Fall 2023.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;You can make your nomination by filling this form by&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;May 7th&lt;/strong&gt;:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://forms.gle/jCMXsTmZ4DZ8r5xJA&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;https://forms.gle/jCMXsTmZ4DZ8r5xJA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;By Boaz Barak&lt;/p&gt;
  </description>
  <pubDate>2023-03-30 13:10:38 UTC</pubDate>
  <author>Windows on Theory</author>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
